   <div type="book" osisID="1Kgs">
    <milestone type="pb" n="379"/>
    <chapter osisID="1Kgs.1" sID="1Kgs.1"/>
       <p>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.1" osisID="1Kgs.1.1"/> King David was an old man, well advanced in years, and although they covered him
           with the bed-clothes he could not keep himself warm. <verse eID="1Kgs.1.1"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.2" osisID="1Kgs.1.2"/> So his attendants said to the king, <q>Let some young girl be sought for my lord
           the king; let her wait upon the king and take care of him; let her lie in your bosom, that my lord the king may get
           warmth.</q> <verse eID="1Kgs.1.2"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.3" osisID="1Kgs.1.3"/> All over Israel they sought for a beautiful maiden, and found Abishag of Shunem,
           whom they brought to the king; <verse eID="1Kgs.1.3"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.4" osisID="1Kgs.1.4"/> she was most beautiful, and she took care of the king and attended to him. But
            the king had no intercourse with her. <verse eID="1Kgs.1.4"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.5" osisID="1Kgs.1.5"/> Now Adonijah the son of Haggith prided himself that he was to be king; he set up
            chariots and cavalry of his own, with fifty men to run in front. <verse eID="1Kgs.1.5"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.6" osisID="1Kgs.1.6"/> (Adonijah had been born next to Absalom. His father had never checked him all
            his life, by asking what he meant by his conduct. Also, he was a very handsome fellow.) <verse eID="1Kgs.1.6"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.7" osisID="1Kgs.1.7"/> He negotiated with Joab the son of Zeruiah and with Abiathar the priest, both of
            whom adhered to him and gave him their support, <verse eID="1Kgs.1.7"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.8" osisID="1Kgs.1.8"/> although Zadok the priest, Benaiah the son of Jehoiada, Nathan the prophet,
            Shimei, Rei, and David’s veterans, did not side with Adonijah. <verse eID="1Kgs.1.8"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.9" osisID="1Kgs.1.9"/> He then sacrificed sheep, oxen, and fatted cattle at the Serpent’s Stone beside
            Fuller’s Spring, inviting all his brothers, the king’s sons, and all the royal officials from Judah, <verse eID="1Kgs.1.9"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.10" osisID="1Kgs.1.10"/> but not Nathan the prophet, nor Benaiah, nor the veterans nor his brother
            Solomon. <verse eID="1Kgs.1.10"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.11" osisID="1Kgs.1.11"/> So Nathan went to Solomon's mother Bathsheba and said to her, <q>Have you not
            heard that Adonijah the son of Haggith has become king, without the knowledge of David our lord? <verse eID="1Kgs.1.11"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.12" osisID="1Kgs.1.12"/> Come now, let me advise you how to save your own life and the life of your son
            Solomon. <verse eID="1Kgs.1.12"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.13" osisID="1Kgs.1.13"/> Go at once to king David and ask him, <q>My lord, O king, did you not swear to
            your humble servant that Solomon my son should reign after you and sit upon your throne? Why, then, doesAdonijah
            reign?</q> <verse eID="1Kgs.1.13"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.14" osisID="1Kgs.1.14"/> While you are talking to the king, I will come in behind you and confirm what
            you say.</q> <verse eID="1Kgs.1.14"/>
       </p>
     <p>
         <verse sID="1Kgs.1.15" osisID="1Kgs.1.15"/> Bathsheba went to the king in his chamber. (The king was a very old man, and
          Abishag of Shunem attended to him.) <verse eID="1Kgs.1.15"/>
         <verse sID="1Kgs.1.16" osisID="1Kgs.1.16"/> Bathsheba bowed and did homage to the king, and the king asked what she desired. <verse eID="1Kgs.1.16"/>
         <verse sID="1Kgs.1.17" osisID="1Kgs.1.17"/> <q>My lord,</q> she replied, <q>you swore by the Eternal your God to your humble
          servant that her son Solomon was to reign after you and sit upon your throne. <verse eID="1Kgs.1.17"/>
         <verse sID="1Kgs.1.18" osisID="1Kgs.1.18"/> And here is Adonijah reigning, though you know nothing of it, my lord king! <verse eID="1Kgs.1.18"/>
         <verse sID="1Kgs.1.19" osisID="1Kgs.1.19"/> He has sacrificed oxen, fatted cattle, and sheep, plenty of them, and he has
          invited all the king’s sons, along with Abiathar the priest and Joab the commander-in-chief, but not your servant Solomon. <verse eID="1Kgs.1.19"/>
         <verse sID="1Kgs.1.20" osisID="1Kgs.1.20"/> Now, my lord king, all Israel looks to you to decide for them who is to succeed to
          the throne of my lord king. <verse eID="1Kgs.1.20"/>
         <verse sID="1Kgs.1.21" osisID="1Kgs.1.21"/> Otherwise the result will be that, when my lord king sleeps with his fathers, I
          and my son Solomon will have to suffer.</q> <verse eID="1Kgs.1.21"/>
         <verse sID="1Kgs.1.22" osisID="1Kgs.1.22"/> Just as she was
          <milestone type="pb" n="380"/>
          talking to the king, in came the prophet Nathan. <verse eID="1Kgs.1.22"/>
         <verse sID="1Kgs.1.23" osisID="1Kgs.1.23"/> The king was told that the prophet Nathan was present, and as he entered the
          king’s presence he bowed before the king, face to the ground. <verse eID="1Kgs.1.23"/>
         <verse sID="1Kgs.1.24" osisID="1Kgs.1.24"/> <q>My lord, O king,</q> said Nathan, <q>have you given orders that Adonijah is to
          reign after you and sit upon your throne? <verse eID="1Kgs.1.24"/>
         <verse sID="1Kgs.1.25" osisID="1Kgs.1.25"/> For he has gone down to-day and sacrificed oxen, sheep, and fatted cattle, plenty
          of them, inviting all the king’s sons, with Joab the commander-in-chief and Abiathar the priest. There they are, eating and
          drinking and shouting, <q>Long live king Adonijah!</q> <verse eID="1Kgs.1.25"/>
         <verse sID="1Kgs.1.26" osisID="1Kgs.1.26"/> But I, your humble servant, I and Zadok the priest and Benaiah the son of Jehoiada
          and your son Solomon have not been invited. <verse eID="1Kgs.1.26"/>
         <verse sID="1Kgs.1.27" osisID="1Kgs.1.27"/> If this is by order of my lord king, then you have not let your servants know who
          is to succeed to the throne of my lord king.</q> <verse eID="1Kgs.1.27"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.28" osisID="1Kgs.1.28"/> King David then ordered Bathsheba to be recalled. She came in and stood before
            the king, <verse eID="1Kgs.1.28"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.29" osisID="1Kgs.1.29"/> and the king swore, <q>By the life of the Eternal who has rescued my life from
            every strait, <verse eID="1Kgs.1.29"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.30" osisID="1Kgs.1.30"/> as I swore to you by the Eternal, the God of Israel, that your son Solomon
            should reign after me and succeed to my throne, so will I do this very day.</q> <verse eID="1Kgs.1.30"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.31" osisID="1Kgs.1.31"/> Bathsheba bowed her face to the ground and did homage to the king; <q>May my
            lord king David live for ever!</q> she cried. <verse eID="1Kgs.1.31"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.32" osisID="1Kgs.1.32"/> Then king David had Zadok the priest, Nathan the prophet, and Benaiah the son
            of Jehoiada summoned to his presence. When they appeared before the king, <verse eID="1Kgs.1.32"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.33" osisID="1Kgs.1.33"/> the king said to them, <q>Take your lord’s personal troops, mount my son
            Solomon upon my own mule, and convey him to Gihon; <verse eID="1Kgs.1.33"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.34" osisID="1Kgs.1.34"/> there let him be anointed king over Israel by Zadok the priest and Nathan the
            prophet; blow a trumpet blast and proclaim, <q>Long live king Solomon!</q> <verse eID="1Kgs.1.34"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.35" osisID="1Kgs.1.35"/> Then march up behind him, as he returns to seat himself on my throne, for he is
            to succeed me, and I appoint him supreme head of Israel and Judah.</q> <verse eID="1Kgs.1.35"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.36" osisID="1Kgs.1.36"/> <q>So be it,</q> said Benaiah the son of Jehoiada to the king. <q>May the
            Eternal confirm this order of my lord king! <verse eID="1Kgs.1.36"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.37" osisID="1Kgs.1.37"/> As the Eternal has been with my lord king, so may he be with Solomon, making his
            throne even greater than the throne of my lord king David!</q> <verse eID="1Kgs.1.37"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.38" osisID="1Kgs.1.38"/> Then Zadok the priest, Nathan the prophet, Benaiah the son of Jehoiada, and the
            foreign body-guard marched down; they mounted Solomon upon king David's mule and conveyed him to Gihon, <verse eID="1Kgs.1.38"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.39" osisID="1Kgs.1.39"/> where Zadok the priest took the vial of oil from the sacred Tent and anointed
            Solomon; a trumpet blast was blown, and the troops all shouted, <q>Long live king Solomon!</q> <verse eID="1Kgs.1.39"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.40" osisID="1Kgs.1.40"/> The troops all marched up behind him, dancing and cheering in their delight, so
            loudly that the earth seemed to be splitting with their noise. <verse eID="1Kgs.1.40"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.41" osisID="1Kgs.1.41"/> Adonijah and his guests all heard it, as they were finishing their feast.
            Hearing the sound of the trumpet, Joab said, <q>What does this uproar in city mean?</q> <verse eID="1Kgs.1.41"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.42" osisID="1Kgs.1.42"/> Just as he was speaking, in came Jonathan the son of Abiathar the priest.
            <q>Come along,</q> said Adonijah, <q>you are an honest fellow, you bring good news.</q> <verse eID="1Kgs.1.42"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.43" osisID="1Kgs.1.43"/> Jonathan answered Adonijah, “But our lord king David has made Solomon
           <milestone type="pb" n="381"/>
            king! <verse eID="1Kgs.1.43"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.44" osisID="1Kgs.1.44"/> The king sent Zadok the priest, Nathan the prophet, Benaiah the son of
            Jehoiada, and the foreign body-guard along with him; they mounted him on the king’s mule; <verse eID="1Kgs.1.44"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.45" osisID="1Kgs.1.45"/> Zadok the priest and Nathan the prophet anointed him king at Gihon; and they
            have come back rejoicing till the city resounds. That is the noise you heard! <verse eID="1Kgs.1.45"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.46" osisID="1Kgs.1.46"/> Solomon is seated on the throne of the realm, <verse eID="1Kgs.1.46"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.47" osisID="1Kgs.1.47"/> and the royal troops have gone to congratulate our lord king David, shouting,
            <q>God make Solomon's fame greater even than your fame, and his throne greater even than your throne! The king bowed on
                his couch. <verse eID="1Kgs.1.47"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.48" osisID="1Kgs.1.48"/> The king also said, <q>Blessed be the Eternal, the God of Israel, who has
            actually allowed me this day to see a son of mine sitting on my throne!</q></q> <verse eID="1Kgs.1.48"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.49" osisID="1Kgs.1.49"/> The guests of Adonijah were all terrified; every man of them got up and went
            home. <verse eID="1Kgs.1.49"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.50" osisID="1Kgs.1.50"/> Adonijah himself, in terror of Solomon, got up and ran to catch hold of the
            knobs of the altar. <verse eID="1Kgs.1.50"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.51" osisID="1Kgs.1.51"/> Solomon was told, <q>Adonijah is terrified of king Solomon; he has caught hold
            of the knobs of the altar, crying, <q>Let king Solomon first of all swear to me that he will not have his servant
            murdered!</q></q> <verse eID="1Kgs.1.51"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.52" osisID="1Kgs.1.52"/> Solomon said, <q>If he proves himself an honest man, not a hair of him shall
            fall to the ground; but if he is convicted of crime, then die he must.</q> <verse eID="1Kgs.1.52"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.53" osisID="1Kgs.1.53"/> Then king Solomon sent and had him taken from the altar; he came and did homage
            to king Solomon, and Solomon bade him go home. <verse eID="1Kgs.1.53"/>
       </p>
      <chapter eID="1Kgs.1"/>
      <chapter osisID="1Kgs.2" sID="1Kgs.2"/>
       <p>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.2.1" osisID="1Kgs.2.1"/>When David's time to die was near, he gave this charge to his son Solomon. <verse eID="1Kgs.2.1"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.2.2" osisID="1Kgs.2.2"/> <q>I am going the way of all the earth; be strong then, show yourself a man, <verse eID="1Kgs.2.2"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.2.3" osisID="1Kgs.2.3"/> and do your duty to the Eternal your God, by living his fife, by following his
            rules and orders and regulations and directions, as written in the law of Moses, so that, whatever you do and wherever you
            turn, you may have success, <verse eID="1Kgs.2.3"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.2.4" osisID="1Kgs.2.4"/> that the Eternal may fulfil his promise to me that if my children are careful
            how they live, living loyally under his eye with all their mind and all their soul, I shall never lack a man upon the
            throne of Israel. <verse eID="1Kgs.2.4"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.2.5" osisID="1Kgs.2.5"/> Again, you know what Joab the son of Zeruiah did to me, how he treated the two
            commanders of Israel, Abner the son of Ner and Amasa the son of Jether, how he murdered them, taking vengeance during peace
            for blood shed during war, staining the very girdle round his waist and the shoes on his feet with innocent blood. <verse eID="1Kgs.2.5"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.2.6" osisID="1Kgs.2.6"/> Choose your own time, but never let his grey head go to the grave in peace. <verse eID="1Kgs.2.6"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.2.7" osisID="1Kgs.2.7"/> Be kind to the family of Barzillai the Gileadite, and let them be among the guests
            at your table, for they fed me when I fled from your brother Absalom. <verse eID="1Kgs.2.7"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.2.8" osisID="1Kgs.2.8"/> You have also with you Shimei the Benjamite, the son of Gera, from Bahurim.
            Bitterly did he curse me on the day when I made my way to Mahanaim; but when he came to meet me at the Jordan I swore to
            him by the Eternal that I would not put him to death. <verse eID="1Kgs.2.8"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.2.9" osisID="1Kgs.2.9"/> Do not you let him go unpunished; you have your wits about you, you know what to
            do with him, to bring down his grey head to death with blood.</q><verse eID="1Kgs.2.9"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.2.10" osisID="1Kgs.2.10"/> Then David slept with his fathers and was buried in
            <milestone type="pb" n="382"/> David’s burg. <verse eID="1Kgs.2.10"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.2.11" osisID="1Kgs.2.11"/> For forty years David had reigned over Israel, seven years at Hebron and
            thirty-three years in Jerusalem. <verse eID="1Kgs.2.11"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.2.12" osisID="1Kgs.2.12"/> Solomon sat on the throne of his father David, and his kingdom was firmly
            established. <verse eID="1Kgs.2.12"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.2.13" osisID="1Kgs.2.13"/> Adonijah the son of Haggith then went to Bathsheba the mother of Solomon and
            bowed before her. <q>Do you come as a friend?</q> she asked. <q>Yes,</q> he answered, <verse eID="1Kgs.2.13"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.2.14" osisID="1Kgs.2.14"/> adding, <q>I have something to say to you.</q> <q>Say it,</q>  she said; <verse eID="1Kgs.2.14"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.2.15" osisID="1Kgs.2.15"/> so he went on, <q>You know the kingdom was mine, all Israel fully expected me to be
            king; however, the kingdom has passed from me to my brother, for it was his by the will of the Eternal. <verse eID="1Kgs.2.15"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.2.16" osisID="1Kgs.2.16"/>Now I am asking you one favour: do not refuse me.</q> <q>Go on,</q> she said. <verse eID="1Kgs.2.16"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.2.17" osisID="1Kgs.2.17"/> So he continued, <q>Pray ask king Solomon (he will not refuse you) to let me
            have Abishag of Shunem as my wife.</q> <verse eID="1Kgs.2.17"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.2.18" osisID="1Kgs.2.18"/><q>Very well,</q> said Bathsheba, <q>I will speak for you to the king.</q> <verse eID="1Kgs.2.18"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.2.19" osisID="1Kgs.2.19"/> So Bathsheba went to speak to king Solomon on behalf of Adonijah. The king rose
            to meet her and kissed her; then, seating himself on his throne, he had a chair placed for the king’s mother, who seated
            herself at his right hand. <verse eID="1Kgs.2.19"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.2.20" osisID="1Kgs.2.20"/> <q>I have a small favour to ask from you,</q> she said; <q>do not refuse me.</q>
            <q>Ask it, my mother,</q> said the king, <q>I will not refuse you.</q> <verse eID="1Kgs.2.20"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.2.21" osisID="1Kgs.2.21"/> So she said, <q>Let Abishag of Shunem be given to your brother Adonijah in
            marriage.</q> <verse eID="1Kgs.2.21"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.2.22" osisID="1Kgs.2.22"/> <q>Abishag of Shunem for Adonijah?</q> answered king Solomon. <q>Why do you
            ask that? Ask the kingdom for him as well!--he is my older brother and he has Abiathar the priest and Joab the son of
            Zerulah on his side!</q> <verse eID="1Kgs.2.22"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.2.23" osisID="1Kgs.2.23"/> And king Solomon swore by the Eternal, <q>God kill me and worse, if this plea of
            Adonijah does not cost him his life! <verse eID="1Kgs.2.23"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.2.24" osisID="1Kgs.2.24"/> By the life of the Eternal who has established me and set me on the throne of
            my father David and given me a family as he promised, Adonijah shall die this very day!</q> <verse eID="1Kgs.2.24"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.2.25" osisID="1Kgs.2.25"/> So king Solomon sent and had Adonijah killed by Benaiah the son of Jehoiada,
            who struck him down. <verse eID="1Kgs.2.25"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.2.26" osisID="1Kgs.2.26"/> The king said to Abiathar the priest, <q>Away with you to your estate at
            Anathoth! You deserve to die this day, but I will not put you to death, since you carried the ark of the Eternal before
            my father David and shared all the hard­ships of my father.</q> <verse eID="1Kgs.2.26"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.2.27" osisID="1Kgs.2.27"/> (This expulsion of Abiathar from the priesthood of the Eternal by Solomon was
            in fulfilment of what the Eternal had predicted about the household of Eli at Shilo.) <verse eID="1Kgs.2.27"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.2.28" osisID="1Kgs.2.28"/> When	the	news of	this reached Joab,	who had	supported Adonijah although he
            had not supported Absalom, Joab fled to the Eternal's Tent and caught hold of the knobs of the altar. <verse eID="1Kgs.2.28"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.2.29" osisID="1Kgs.2.29"/> When Solomon was told that Joab had fled to the Eternal's Tent and was at the
            altar there, Solomon sent to ask Joab why he had fled to the altar. <q>Because I was afraid of you,</q> Joab replied,
            <q>I fled to the Eternal.</q> Then Solomon sent Benaiah the son of Jehoiada to strike him down. <verse eID="1Kgs.2.29"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.2.30" osisID="1Kgs.2.30"/> Benaiah went to the Eternal's Tent and gave him the king's order to come away.
            <q>No,</q> said Joab, <q>I will die here.</q> When Benaiah took back his message to the king, telling him what Joab had
            <milestone type="pb" n="383"/>
            said in reply to him, <verse eID="1Kgs.2.30"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.2.31" osisID="1Kgs.2.31"/> the king said, <q>Take him at his word; strike him down and have him buried--so
            freeing me and my father's house from the guilt of the blood shed wantonly by Joab. <verse eID="1Kgs.2.31"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.2.32" osisID="1Kgs.2.32"/> The Eternal will make his murders fall on his own head, for he struck down two
            men higher and better than himself, Abner the son of Ner, commander of Israel, and Amasa the son of Jether, commander of
            Judah, murdering them without the knowledge of my father David. <verse eID="1Kgs.2.32"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.2.33" osisID="1Kgs.2.33"/> So shall the guilt of their murder come back upon the head of Joab and his
            descendants to all time. To David and his descendants, to his dynasty and throne, may there be peace from the Eternal for
            all time!</q> <verse eID="1Kgs.2.33"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.2.34" osisID="1Kgs.2.34"/> Then Benaiah the son of Jehoiada went and struck him down, killing him; he was
            buried at his own house in the open country of Judah, <verse eID="1Kgs.2.34"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.2.35" osisID="1Kgs.2.35"/> and the king put Benaiah the son of Jehoiada into his post as
            commander-in-chief, putting Zadok the priest in place of Abiathar. <verse eID="1Kgs.2.35"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.2.36" osisID="1Kgs.2.36"/> Then the king sent and summoned Shimei. <q>Build yourself a house in
            Jerusalem,</q> he said, <q>and live there; never leave it in any direction. <verse eID="1Kgs.2.36"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.2.37" osisID="1Kgs.2.37"/> The day you leave it and cross the Kidron-ravine, you die--be sure of that!
            Your blood be on your own head!</q> <verse eID="1Kgs.2.37"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.2.38" osisID="1Kgs.2.38"/> <q>Very good,</q> said Shimei to the king, <q>as my lord the king orders, so
            will your servant do.</q> For a long time Shimei did remain inside Jerusalem. <verse eID="1Kgs.2.38"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.2.39" osisID="1Kgs.2.39"/> But three years later two slaves of Shimei ran away to Achish son of Maakah,
            king of Gath, and when Shimei was told that his slaves were at Gath <verse eID="1Kgs.2.39"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.2.40" osisID="1Kgs.2.40"/> he saddled his ass and rode to Achish at Gath in search of his slaves. From
            Gath Shimei brought his slaves back. <verse eID="1Kgs.2.40"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.2.41" osisID="1Kgs.2.41"/> But when Solomon was informed that Shimei had returned to Jerusalem from a
            visit to Gath, <verse eID="1Kgs.2.41"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.2.42" osisID="1Kgs.2.42"/> the king sent for Shimei and asked him, <q>Did I not make you swear by the
            Eternal, did I not warn you, to be sure of this, that on the day you left and went anywhere outside you were to die?
            Did you not say to me, <q>Very good, I obey?</q> <verse eID="1Kgs.2.42"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.2.43" osisID="1Kgs.2.43"/> Why have you not kept your oath to the Eternal and the orders I enjoined upon
            you?</q> <verse eID="1Kgs.2.43"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.2.44" osisID="1Kgs.2.44"/> The king added, <q>Well does your own heart know all the evil you did to my
            father David. The Eternal returns that evil on your own head! <verse eID="1Kgs.2.44"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.2.45" osisID="1Kgs.2.45"/> But king Solomon shall be blessed and David's throne established before the
            Eternal for all time.</q> <verse eID="1Kgs.2.45"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.2.46" osisID="1Kgs.2.46"/> Then, by order of the king, Benaiah went and struck down Shimei dead. <verse eID="1Kgs.2.46"/>
       </p>
       <chapter eID="1Kgs.2"/>
       <chapter osisID="1Kgs.4" sID="1Kgs.4"/>
       <p>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.4.21" osisID="1Kgs.4.21"/> Now Solomon had complete control of the kingdom. <verse eID="1Kgs.4.21"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.4.20" osisID="1Kgs.4.20"/> Judah and Israel were as numerous as the sand on the seashore; they ate and
            drank and enjoyed themselves. <verse eID="1Kgs.4.20"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.4.25" osisID="1Kgs.4.25"/> Judah and Israel were safe, every man living under his own vine and under his
            own fig-tree, from Dan to Beersheba, all the days of Solomon; <verse eID="1Kgs.4.25"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.4.24" osisID="1Kgs.4.24"/> for he ruled all west of the Euphrates, from Thapsakus to Gaza, over all the
            kings west of the Euphrates, and he enjoyed peace on every side. <verse eID="1Kgs.4.24"/>
       </p>
      <chapter eID="1Kgs.4"/>
      <chapter osisID="1Kgs.3" sID="1Kgs.3"/>
       <p>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.3.3" osisID="1Kgs.3.3"/>Now Solomon loved the o Eternal, living by the rules laid down by his father David;
            only, he sacrificed and burned incense at the shrines. <verse eID="1Kgs.3.3"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.3.2" osisID="1Kgs.3.2"/> [[The people also sacrificed at the shrines, because no temple had yet been built
            in honour of the Eternal.]] <verse eID="1Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.3.4" osisID="1Kgs.3.4"/> One day the king went to sacrifice
            <milestone type="pb" n="384"/> at Gibeon, as that was the chief shrine; a thousand victims Solomon used to sacrifice on the
           altar there. <verse eID="1Kgs.3.4"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.3.5" osisID="1Kgs.3.5"/> The Eternal appeared to Solomon in a dream by night at Gibeon; God said to him,
            <q>Ask what I am to give you.</q> <verse eID="1Kgs.3.5"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.3.6" osisID="1Kgs.3.6"/> Solomon answered, <q>Thou hast proved thyself most generous to thy servant David
            my father, as he lived before thee a loyal and honest life with upright mind, and thou hast reserved this great boon for
            him, a son to sit upon his throne this day. <verse eID="1Kgs.3.6"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.3.7" osisID="1Kgs.3.7"/> And now, O Eternal my God, thou hast made thy servant king instead of David my
            father; and I am a mere child, I know not how to go about my business. <verse eID="1Kgs.3.7"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.3.8" osisID="1Kgs.3.8"/> Thy servant is surrounded by thine own chosen people, a vast host, too great to be
            numbered or counted. <verse eID="1Kgs.3.8"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.3.9" osisID="1Kgs.3.9"/> So grant thy servant a thoughtful mind for governing thy people, that I may
            distinguish right and wrong. For who can bear the weight of this government?</q> <verse eID="1Kgs.3.9"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.3.10" osisID="1Kgs.3.10"/> It pleased the Eternal that Solomon had asked this,<verse eID="1Kgs.3.10"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.3.11" osisID="1Kgs.3.11"/> God said to him, <q>Because you have asked this, because you have asked neither
            long fife for yourself nor wealth for yourself nor death to your enemies, but insight and justice, <verse eID="1Kgs.3.11"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.3.12" osisID="1Kgs.3.12"/> I now do as you have asked; I hereby give you a wise, thoughtful mind, so that
            never afterwards shall your equal rise, as never has your equal lived. <verse eID="1Kgs.3.12"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.3.13" osisID="1Kgs.3.13"/> Also, I give you what you did not ask, both wealth and honour, so that no king
            shall ever be your equal. <verse eID="1Kgs.3.13"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.3.14" osisID="1Kgs.3.14"/> And if you will live my life, keeping my rules and orders, as did your father
            David, I will give you a long life.</q> <verse eID="1Kgs.3.14"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.3.15" osisID="1Kgs.3.15"/> Then Solomon woke; it was a dream! He went to Jerusalem, where he stood in
            front of the ark of the Eternal's compact, sacrificing burnt-offerings and recompense-offerings, and feasting all his
            officers. <verse eID="1Kgs.3.15"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.3.16" osisID="1Kgs.3.16"/> Two harlots then came to the king and stood before him. <verse eID="1Kgs.3.16"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.3.17" osisID="1Kgs.3.17"/> One woman said, <q>O my lord, this woman and I live in the same house. I bore a
            child in the house beside her, <verse eID="1Kgs.3.17"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.3.18" osisID="1Kgs.3.18"/> and three days later she bore a child also; we were together, there was no one
            else in the house, only we two by ourselves. <verse eID="1Kgs.3.18"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.3.19" osisID="1Kgs.3.19"/> During the night her child died, for she overlaid it. <verse eID="1Kgs.3.19"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.3.20" osisID="1Kgs.3.20"/> So she got up at midnight and took away my child, while your humble servant was
            asleep; she laid the child in her bosom and put her dead child in my bosom. <verse eID="1Kgs.3.20"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.3.21" osisID="1Kgs.3.21"/> When I rose in the morning to suckle my child, there it lay dead! But as I
            looked at it carefully in the morning-light, it was not my son whom I had borne.</q> <verse eID="1Kgs.3.21"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.3.22" osisID="1Kgs.3.22"/> The other woman said, <q>No, the living child belongs to me, the dead is
            yours!</q> The first woman retorted, <q>No, the dead child belongs to you, the living child is mine!</q> So they wrangled
            before the king. <verse eID="1Kgs.3.22"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.3.23" osisID="1Kgs.3.23"/> The king mused: <q>One says, <q>This living son is mine, the dead belongs to
            you</q>; the other says, <q>No, the dead son is yours, mine is the living one.</q></q> <verse eID="1Kgs.3.23"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.3.24" osisID="1Kgs.3.24"/> Then said the king, <q>Fetch me a sword.</q> A sword was brought in. <verse eID="1Kgs.3.24"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.3.25" osisID="1Kgs.3.25"/> The king then gave his orders, <q>Cut the living child in two, and give half
            to the one, half to the other.</q> <verse eID="1Kgs.3.25"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.3.26" osisID="1Kgs.3.26"/> At this the mother of the living child, whose heart yearned for her boy, cried
            to the king, <q>O my lord, give her the living child, never lull it!</q> The other woman said, <q>No, divide
            <milestone type="pb" n="385"/>
            it; neither of us shall have it.</q>
           <verse eID="1Kgs.3.26"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.3.27" osisID="1Kgs.3.27"/> The king replied, <q>Give yonder woman the living child, instead of killing
            it; she is its mother!</q> <verse eID="1Kgs.3.27"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.3.28" osisID="1Kgs.3.28"/> All Israel heard of this decision of the king, and they stood in awe of the
           king, seeing that he had God's own wisdom for doing justice. <verse eID="1Kgs.3.28"/>
       </p>
       <chapter eID="1Kgs.3"/>
       <chapter osisID="1Kgs.4" sID="1Kgs.4"/>
       <p>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.4.1" osisID="1Kgs.4.1"/> King Solomon reigned over all Israel. <verse eID="1Kgs.4.1"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.4.2" osisID="1Kgs.4.2"/> His ministers of state were: Azariah the son of Zadok as priest, <verse eID="1Kgs.4.2"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.4.3" osisID="1Kgs.4.3"/> Elihoreph and Ahijah the sons of Shisha as secretaries, Jehoshaphat
            the son of Ahilud as chancellor, <verse eID="1Kgs.4.3"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.4.4" osisID="1Kgs.4.4"/> and Benaiah the son of Jehoiada as commander-in-chief [[Zadok and
            Abiathar were priests.]] <verse eID="1Kgs.4.4"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.4.5" osisID="1Kgs.4.5"/> Azariah the son of Nathan was head of the prefects, Zabud the son
            of Nathan was the king’s adviser, <verse eID="1Kgs.4.5"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.4.6" osisID="1Kgs.4.6"/> Ahishar was prefect of the palace, and Adoniram the son of Abda was
            in charge of the labour levy. <verse eID="1Kgs.4.6"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.4.7" osisID="1Kgs.4.7"/> Solomon had twelve prefects over all Israel, who provided the food
            for the king and his household, each man having to supply food for one month a year; <verse eID="1Kgs.4.7"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.4.8" osisID="1Kgs.4.8"/> their names were Ben-hur (over the highlands of Ephraim),<verse eID="1Kgs.4.8"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.4.9" osisID="1Kgs.4.9"/> Bendeker (over Makaz, Shaalbim, Beth-shemesh, and Elonbeth-hanan), <verse eID="1Kgs.4.9"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.4.10" osisID="1Kgs.4.10"/> Ben-hesed (over Arubboth, besides Soko and all the land of Hepher), <verse eID="1Kgs.4.10"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.4.11" osisID="1Kgs.4.11"/> Ben-abinadab (over all the uplands of Dor) who was married to
            Solomon's daughter Taphath, <verse eID="1Kgs.4.11"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.4.12" osisID="1Kgs.4.12"/>Baana the son of Ahilud (over Taanak, Megiddo, and the whole of
            Beth-shean next Zarethan below Jezreel, from Beth-shean to Abel-meholah as far as the other side of Jokmeam), <verse eID="1Kgs.4.12"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.4.13" osisID="1Kgs.4.13"/> Ben-geber (over Ramoth-gilead, with the tent-villages in Gilead
            belonging to Jair the son of Manasseh, and the region of Argob in Bashan, containing sixty large towns
            walled and bolted with bronze), <verse eID="1Kgs.4.13"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.4.14" osisID="1Kgs.4.14"/> Ahinadab the son of Iddo (over Mahanaim), <verse eID="1Kgs.4.14"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.4.15" osisID="1Kgs.4.15"/> Ahimaaz (over Naphtali) who was married to Solomon's daughter
            Basemath, <verse eID="1Kgs.4.15"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.4.16" osisID="1Kgs.4.16"/> Baana the son of Hushai (over Asher and Aloth), <verse eID="1Kgs.4.16"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.4.17" osisID="1Kgs.4.17"/> Jehoshaphat the son of Paruali (over Issachar), <verse eID="1Kgs.4.17"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.4.18" osisID="1Kgs.4.18"/> Shimei the son of Ela (over Benjamin), <verse eID="1Kgs.4.18"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.4.19" osisID="1Kgs.4.19"/> and Geber the son of Uri (over the land of Gad, the country of
            Sihon king of the Amorites and of Og king of Bashan). All these prefects were Under a single chief. <verse eID="1Kgs.4.19"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.4.27" osisID="1Kgs.4.27"/> They provided the food for king Solomon and for all guests
            admitted to king Solomon's table, each taking a month. They saw that nothing was wanting. <verse eID="1Kgs.4.27"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.4.28" osisID="1Kgs.4.28"/> Also they each brought, as they were bound, barley and straw for
            the horses and coursers, wherever the cavalry were stationed. <verse eID="1Kgs.4.28"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.4.22" osisID="1Kgs.4.22"/> Solomon's provision for a single day was three hundred and thirty
            bushels of fine flour, six hundred and sixty bushels of meal, <verse eID="1Kgs.4.22"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.4.23" osisID="1Kgs.4.23"/> ten fatted oxen, twenty meadow-fed oxen, and a hundred sheep,
            besides harts, gazelles, roebucks, and guinea-fowl. <verse eID="1Kgs.4.23"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.4.29" osisID="1Kgs.4.29"/> Now God gave Solomon wisdom and ample insight and breadth of mind
            like the broad sea-sands; <verse eID="1Kgs.4.29"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.4.30" osisID="1Kgs.4.30"/> Solomon's wisdom surpassed the wisdom of all Arabs in the east
            and all Egypt, <verse eID="1Kgs.4.30"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.4.31" osisID="1Kgs.4.31"/> for he was wiser than any man, wiser even than Ethan the Ezrahite,
            and Heman, Kalkol, and Darda, the sons of Mahol; his fame reached to all the nations around. <verse eID="1Kgs.4.31"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.4.32" osisID="1Kgs.4.32"/> He composed three thousand aphorisms, and his songs numbered one
            thousand and five. <verse eID="1Kgs.4.32"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.4.33" osisID="1Kgs.4.33"/>He could talk about any plant, from a cedar in Lebanon to a hyssop
            in the wall; he could also talk of animals, birds,
           <milestone type="pb" n="386"/> reptiles, and fish.
           <verse eID="1Kgs.4.33"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.4.34" osisID="1Kgs.4.34"/> People came from every nation, deputed by all the kings in the
            world, who had heard of Solomon’s wisdom, in order to listen to his wisdom. <verse eID="1Kgs.4.34"/>
       </p>
      <chapter eID="1Kgs.4"/>
       <chapter osisID="1Kgs.3" sID="1Kgs.3"/>
       <p>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.3.1" osisID="1Kgs.3.1"/> Solomon became the son-in-law of the Pharaoh, king of Egypt; he
            married the Pha­raoh's daughter and took her to David's burg till he had finished building his own palace
            and the Eternal's temple and the wall round Jerusalem. <verse eID="1Kgs.3.1"/>
       </p>
       <chapter eID="1Kgs.3"/>
       <chapter osisID="1Kgs.9" sID="1Kgs.9"/>
       <p>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.9.16" osisID="1Kgs.9.16"/> The Pha­raoh, king of Egypt, marched north, captured Gezer and
            burnt it, killing the Canaanites who lived in the town; then he presented it as a dowry to his daughter,
            Solomon's wife. <verse eID="1Kgs.9.16"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.9.17" osisID="1Kgs.9.17"/>Solo­mon rebuilt Gezer. <verse eID="1Kgs.9.17"/>
       </p>
       <chapter eID="1Kgs.9"/>
      <chapter osisID="1Kgs.5" sID="1Kgs.5"/>
       <p>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.5.1" osisID="1Kgs.5.1"/> When Hiram king of Tyre heard that it was Solomon who had been
            consecrated king instead of his father, he sent his officers to Solomon; for Hiram had always been friendly
            to David. <verse eID="1Kgs.5.1"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.5.2" osisID="1Kgs.5.2"/> Then Solomon sent this message to Hiram:
           <verse eID="1Kgs.5.2"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.5.3" osisID="1Kgs.5.3"/> <q>You know how my father David could not build a temple in honour
            of the Eternal his God, until the Eternal had crushed under him the warlike foes who surrounded him. <verse eID="1Kgs.5.3"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.5.4" osisID="1Kgs.5.4"/> The Eternal my God has now given me rest on every side; I have
            neither foe nor misfortune, <verse eID="1Kgs.5.4"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.5.5" osisID="1Kgs.5.5"/> and I propose to build a temple in honour of the Eternal, my God,
            as the Eternal told my father David that <q>your son, whom I place on your throne, shall build the temple in
            my honour.</q> <verse eID="1Kgs.5.5"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.5.6" osisID="1Kgs.5.6"/> Now give orders that cedars be felled for me on Lebanon; my
            servants will join your servants, and I will pay you any wage you fix for your servants; for you know we
            have no one fit to fell timber like the Phoenicians.</q> <verse eID="1Kgs.5.6"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.5.7" osisID="1Kgs.5.7"/> When Hiram heard what Solomon said, he was overjoyed. <q>Blessed be
            the Eternal the God of Israel this day,</q> he cried, <q>for granting David a wise son to rule this great
            people!</q> <verse eID="1Kgs.5.7"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.5.8" osisID="1Kgs.5.8"/> Hiram sent this message to Solomon: <q>I have heard your message;
            I will do all you desire in the matter of cedars and firs; <verse eID="1Kgs.5.8"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.5.9" osisID="1Kgs.5.9"/> my servants shall bring the timber down from Lebanon to the sea,
            and I will make the logs into floats to reach any spot you decide upon; then I will have them broken up for
            you to take away. You will meet my wishes by providing the food for my servants.</q><verse eID="1Kgs.5.9"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.5.10" osisID="1Kgs.5.10"/> So Hiram gave Solomon all the cedar and fir-wood that he desired, <verse eID="1Kgs.5.10"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.5.11" osisID="1Kgs.5.11"/>while Solomon gave Hiram two hundred and twenty thousand bushels
            of wheat and a hundred and eighty gallons of beaten oil as food for his servants--such was Solomon's annual
            gift to Hiram.
           <verse eID="1Kgs.5.11"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.5.12" osisID="1Kgs.5.12"/> Solomon and Hiram were at peace; the two men made an alliance
            with each other. <verse eID="1Kgs.5.12"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.5.13" osisID="1Kgs.5.13"/> Solomon raised a labour-force from all Israel, a levy of thirty
            thousand men, <verse eID="1Kgs.5.13"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.5.14" osisID="1Kgs.5.14"/> whom he sent to Lebanon in relays, ten thousand a month; one
            month they were at Lebanon and two months at home. Adoniram was in charge of this forced levy. <verse eID="1Kgs.5.14"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.5.15" osisID="1Kgs.5.15"/> Solomon also had seventy thousand carriers and eighty thousand
            stone-masons in the hills, <verse eID="1Kgs.5.15"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.5.16" osisID="1Kgs.5.16"/> as well as three thousand three hundred foremen, who controlled
            the workmen. <verse eID="1Kgs.5.16"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.5.17" osisID="1Kgs.5.17"/>By order of the king, they quarried huge, expensive blocks of
            stone, to have the foundation of the temple laid with dressed stone. <verse eID="1Kgs.5.17"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.5.18" osisID="1Kgs.5.18"/> Solomon's builders and Hiram's builders dressed the stones and
           ran grooved edges round them, besides
           <milestone type="pb" n="387"/>
           preparing the timber and the stones for building the temple.<verse eID="1Kgs.5.18"/>
       </p>
       <chapter eID="1Kgs.5"/>
       <chapter osisID="1Kgs.6" sID="1Kgs.6"/>
       <p>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.6.1" osisID="1Kgs.6.1"/> [[It was in the four hundred and eightieth year after the
            Israelites left Egypt, in the fourth year of Solomon's reign, and in the second month of that year, the
            month Ziv, that he began to build the temple of the Eternal.]] <verse eID="1Kgs.6.1"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.6.2" osisID="1Kgs.6.2"/> The temple which king Solomon built for the Eternal was ninety feet
            long, thirty feet broad, and forty-five feet high. <verse eID="1Kgs.6.2"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.6.3" osisID="1Kgs.6.3"/> The porch before the nave was thirty feet long, corresponding to
            the breadth of the temple, and fifteen feet wide.
           <verse eID="1Kgs.6.3"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.6.4" osisID="1Kgs.6.4"/> He made windows with gratings for the temple, and built wings round
            the wall of the temple, round both the nave and the inner shrine; <verse eID="1Kgs.6.4"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.6.5-1Kgs.6.6" osisID="1Kgs.6.5 1Kgs.6.6" n="5-6"/> he put side-rooms all round, the lower
            row of them about seven and a half feet wide, the middle row nine feet wide, and the top row about ten and a
            half feet wide--allowing space all round the outside wall so that the ends of the planks upholding the rows
            need not pierce the walls of the temple. <verse eID="1Kgs.6.5-1Kgs.6.6"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.6.7" osisID="1Kgs.6.7"/> [[The temple was built throughout of stones roughly dressed at the
            quarry; not a sound of hammer, chisel, or any iron tool was ever heard during the building of the temple.]] <verse eID="1Kgs.6.7"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.6.8" osisID="1Kgs.6.8"/> The entrance into the lower side-rooms was on the south side of the
            temple; you climbed to the middle row, and from the middle row to the top row, through trap-doors. <verse eID="1Kgs.6.8"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.6.10" osisID="1Kgs.6.10"/> Thus did he build the temple and finish it, roofing it over with
            cedar. <verse eID="1Kgs.6.10"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.6.9" osisID="1Kgs.6.9"/> Each row of side-rooms built against the temple was about seven and
            a half feet high, and they rested on cedar planks against the temple. <verse eID="1Kgs.6.9"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.6.15" osisID="1Kgs.6.15"/> The walls inside he lined with cedar planks, overlaying the
            interior from the floor to the rafters of the ceiling with wood, and covering the floor itself with fir. <verse eID="1Kgs.6.15"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.6.16" osisID="1Kgs.6.16"/> At the far end of the temple he built off a space of thirty feet
            as an inner shrine, the most sacred interior; <verse eID="1Kgs.6.16"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.6.17" osisID="1Kgs.6.17"/> the nave or hall in front of it was sixty feet long, <verse eID="1Kgs.6.17"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.6.20" osisID="1Kgs.6.20"/> but the inner shrine was thirty feet square. <verse eID="1Kgs.6.20"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.6.21" osisID="1Kgs.6.21"/> In front of the inner shrine he made an altar of cedar; <verse eID="1Kgs.6.21"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.6.23" osisID="1Kgs.6.23"/>inside the inner shrine he made two kherubs of olive-wood, <verse eID="1Kgs.6.23"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.6.26" osisID="1Kgs.6.26"/> each of them fifteen feet high, <verse eID="1Kgs.6.26"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.6.24" osisID="1Kgs.6.24"/> each with outstretched wings seven and a half feet broad,
            measuring fifteen feet from the tip of one wing to the tip of the other, <verse eID="1Kgs.6.24"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.6.25" osisID="1Kgs.6.25"/> the one kherub being the same as the other in size and shape. <verse eID="1Kgs.6.25"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.6.27" osisID="1Kgs.6.27"/>These kherubs he placed inside the inner shrine; their wings were
            spread out so that the wing of one touched one wall while the wing of the other touched the other wall, and
            their inner wings met in the middle. <verse eID="1Kgs.6.27"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.6.28" osisID="1Kgs.6.28"/>He plated the kherubs with gold. <verse eID="1Kgs.6.28"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.6.31" osisID="1Kgs.6.31"/> He made doors of olive-wood for the vestibule of the inner shrine;
            the vestibule and the pilasters formed a pentagon. <verse eID="1Kgs.6.31"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.6.32" osisID="1Kgs.6.32"/> On the two doors of olive-wood he carved kherubs, palm-trees, and
            open flowers, spreading gold over the kherubs and the palm-trees. <verse eID="1Kgs.6.32"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.6.33" osisID="1Kgs.6.33"/> For the vestibule of the nave he also made door-posts of olive-wood,
            four-cornered posts, <verse eID="1Kgs.6.33"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.6.34" osisID="1Kgs.6.34"/> and two folding doors of cypress wood, the two leaves of each
            turning on hinges. <verse eID="1Kgs.6.34"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.6.35" osisID="1Kgs.6.35"/>These he carved with kherubs, palm-trees, and open flowers,
            overlaying them with gold laid evenly upon the carvings. <verse eID="1Kgs.6.35"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.6.36" osisID="1Kgs.6.36"/> The inner court round the temple he built with three rows of
            dressed stone and one row of cedar beams. <verse eID="1Kgs.6.36"/>
       </p>
       <milestone type="pb" n="388"/>
       <p>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.6.37" osisID="1Kgs.6.37"/> The foundation of the temple of the Eternal was laid in the month
            of Ziv, in the fourth year of Solomon; <verse eID="1Kgs.6.37"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.6.38" osisID="1Kgs.6.38"/> in the month of Bui (the eighth month), in the eleventh year, the
            temple was finished in every part, exactly as planned. He took seven years to build it. <verse eID="1Kgs.6.38"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.6.11" osisID="1Kgs.6.11"/> [[Then this word from the Eternal came to Solomon: <verse eID="1Kgs.6.11"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.6.12" osisID="1Kgs.6.12"/> <q>As for this temple which you build, if you will live by my
            rules and keep my regulations and follow all my orders, living by them, then I will fulfil for you the
            promise I made to your father David; <verse eID="1Kgs.6.12"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.6.13" osisID="1Kgs.6.13"/> and I will dwell among the Israelites, I will not forsake my
           people Israel.</q>]] <verse eID="1Kgs.6.13"/>
       </p>
       <chapter eID="1Kgs.6"/>
       <chapter osisID="1Kgs.7" sID="1Kgs.7"/>
       <p>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.7.1" osisID="1Kgs.7.1"/> Solomon took thirteen years to finish the building of his own palace. <verse eID="1Kgs.7.1"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.7.2" osisID="1Kgs.7.2"/> He also built the <q>Forest of Lebanon</q> hall, a hundred and fifty
            feet long, seventy-five feet wide, and forty-five feet high, on three rows of cedar pillars with cedar supports. <verse eID="1Kgs.7.2"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.7.3" osisID="1Kgs.7.3"/> It was lined with cedar planks above the forty-five cedar pillars
            (fifteen in each row); <verse eID="1Kgs.7.3"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.7.4" osisID="1Kgs.7.4"/> there were three rows of window-frames, window facing window in each tier, <verse eID="1Kgs.7.4"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.7.5" osisID="1Kgs.7.5"/> and both doors and windows, all of them, were square-cut. <verse eID="1Kgs.7.5"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.7.6" osisID="1Kgs.7.6"/> He also built the Pillars hall, seventy-five feet long and forty-five
            feet wide, with a pillared porch in front and an entrance with steps. <verse eID="1Kgs.7.6"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.7.7" osisID="1Kgs.7.7"/> He also made the throne-room where he was to hold his court of justice,
            the Hall of Justice; it was lined with cedar-wood from floor to rafters. <verse eID="1Kgs.7.7"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.7.8" osisID="1Kgs.7.8"/> His own palace and residence in the other court, which stood nearer
            the temple, was constructed in the same way, as was the house he built for the Pharaoh's daughter
            (whom Sol­omon had married). <verse eID="1Kgs.7.8"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.7.9" osisID="1Kgs.7.9"/> These buildings were all made of huge, dressed stones, according to
            the regular dimensions of ashlar, sawn back and front, from foundation to coping, and from the court of the
            Eternal's tem­ple to the large outer court. <verse eID="1Kgs.7.9"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.7.10" osisID="1Kgs.7.10"/> The foundation consisted of huge blocks, enormous blocks, some
            fifteen feet square, some twelve feet square. <verse eID="1Kgs.7.10"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.7.11" osisID="1Kgs.7.11"/> Above these lay huge, dressed stones, cut according to the regular
            measurement, and also cedar beams. <verse eID="1Kgs.7.11"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.7.12" osisID="1Kgs.7.12"/> The large court had three rows of dressed stone and one row of
            cedar beams, enclosing the inner court of the Eternal's temple and the court of the palace. <verse eID="1Kgs.7.12"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.7.13" osisID="1Kgs.7.13"/> King Solomon sent to Tyre for Hiram, <verse eID="1Kgs.7.13"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.7.14" osisID="1Kgs.7.14"/> the son of a widow belonging to the clan of Naphtali; his father had
            been a native of Tyre, a worker in bronze. Hiram was full of skill, acute and clever at all kinds of bronze-work.
            He came to king Solomon and did all the bronze-work for him. <verse eID="1Kgs.7.14"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.7.15" osisID="1Kgs.7.15"/> He cast the two bronze columns for the vestibule of the temple; the
            one was twenty-seven feet high, eighteen feet round, and hollow, just like the other column. <verse eID="1Kgs.7.15"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.7.16" osisID="1Kgs.7.16"/> He made two capitals of molten bronze for the top of the columns,
            each capital being seven and a half feet high. <verse eID="1Kgs.7.16"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.7.17" osisID="1Kgs.7.17"/> He made two nets of trellis-work for the capitals on the top of
            the columns, a net of trellis-work for each of them. <verse eID="1Kgs.7.17"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.7.18" osisID="1Kgs.7.18"/> He also made the pomegranates; there were two rows of pomegranates
            in bronze upon each trellis-work, ... <verse eID="1Kgs.7.18"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.7.20" osisID="1Kgs.7.20"/> the pomegranates numbering two hundred to each capital. <verse eID="1Kgs.7.20"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.7.21" osisID="1Kgs.7.21"/> He set up the columns at the vestibule of the temple; the column
            on the south side was called Jachin,
           <milestone type="pb" n="389"/>
            the column on the north side Boaz. <verse eID="1Kgs.7.21"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.7.23" osisID="1Kgs.7.23"/> He also made the round metal sea or tank, fifteen feet in diameter,
            seven and a half feet high, and forty-five feet round. <verse eID="1Kgs.7.23"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.7.24" osisID="1Kgs.7.24"/> Under its brim on the outside ran a double row of gourds all round,
            cast in one piece with the tank itself, <verse eID="1Kgs.7.24"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.7.26" osisID="1Kgs.7.26"/> which was about three inches thick, its brim curling like the brim
            of a cup, like the petals of a lily; it held over sixteen thousand gallons. <verse eID="1Kgs.7.26"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.7.25" osisID="1Kgs.7.25"/> It rested on twelve bulls, three facing the north, three facing
            the west, three facing the south, and three facing the east; the tank was placed on their backs, their haunches
            being turned inward. <verse eID="1Kgs.7.25"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.7.27" osisID="1Kgs.7.27"/> He also made the ten trolleys of bronze, each one six feet long,
            six feet wide, and four and a half feet high. <verse eID="1Kgs.7.27"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.7.28" osisID="1Kgs.7.28"/> The trolleys were constructed in this way: they had panels, panels
            set in their framework, <verse eID="1Kgs.7.28"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.7.29" osisID="1Kgs.7.29"/> and on these panels were lions, bulls, and kherubs (on the framework,
            above and below the lions, bulls, and kherubs, there was bevelled work); <verse eID="1Kgs.7.29"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.7.30" osisID="1Kgs.7.30"/> every trolley had four bronze wheels, with bronze axles,
           the four wheels being underneath the framework<verse eID="1Kgs.7.30"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.7.32" osisID="1Kgs.7.32"/> (axles and wheels were cast in one piece with the trolley),  each
            wheel being two and a half feet high <verse eID="1Kgs.7.32"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.7.33" osisID="1Kgs.7.33"/> and all the wheels being shaped like chariot wheels  (axles,
            felloes, spokes, and hubs being all of molten bronze);<verse eID="1Kgs.7.33"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.7.34" osisID="1Kgs.7.34"/>at the four corners of each trolley there were four clamps, each of
            one piece with the trolley,<verse eID="1Kgs.7.34"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.7.35" osisID="1Kgs.7.35"/>while on the top of the trolley there was a round saucer, nine inches
           high <verse eID="1Kgs.7.35"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.7.36" osisID="1Kgs.7.36"/> (the flat surface on the sides of the trolley was engraved with
            kherubs, lions, and palm-trees); <verse eID="1Kgs.7.36"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.7.31" osisID="1Kgs.7.31"/>but the framework was square, not round. <verse eID="1Kgs.7.31"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.7.37" osisID="1Kgs.7.37"/>This was how the ten trolleys were made, all cast alike, all of the
            same size and shape. <verse eID="1Kgs.7.37"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.7.38" osisID="1Kgs.7.38"/>Then he made ten bronze pots, each holding three hundred and
            twenty gallons and measuring six feet; one pot rested on each of the ten trolleys,<verse eID="1Kgs.7.38"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.7.39" osisID="1Kgs.7.39"/>which he placed beside the temple,  five to the south side and
            five to the north side; the tank was placed on the south side of the temple, at the eastern corner. <verse eID="1Kgs.7.39"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.7.40" osisID="1Kgs.7.40"/> Hiram made the pots, the shovels, and the bowls; he finished all
            his work for king Solomon in building the temple of the Eternal, <verse eID="1Kgs.7.40"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.7.41" osisID="1Kgs.7.41"/> the two columns, the two rounded capitals on the tops of the columns,
            the two nets of trellis-work to cover the two capitals, <verse eID="1Kgs.7.41"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.7.42" osisID="1Kgs.7.42"/> the four hundred pomegranates for each trellis-work, <verse eID="1Kgs.7.42"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.7.43" osisID="1Kgs.7.43"/> the ten trolleys and the ten pots on the trolleys, <verse eID="1Kgs.7.43"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.7.44" osisID="1Kgs.7.44"/> the tank and the twelve bulls under the tank, <verse eID="1Kgs.7.44"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.7.45" osisID="1Kgs.7.45"/> the pots, shovels, bowls--all these articles made by Hiram for
            king Solomon in the temple of the Eternal were of polished bronze. <verse eID="1Kgs.7.45"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.7.47" osisID="1Kgs.7.47"/> There was no weighing the bronze used for making these articles,
            so enormous was the quantity; the weight of the bronze was past counting. <verse eID="1Kgs.7.47"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.7.46" osisID="1Kgs.7.46"/> Hiram cast them on the plain of Jordan, in the clay soil between
            Sukkoth and Zarethan. <verse eID="1Kgs.7.46"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.7.48" osisID="1Kgs.7.48"/> Then king Solomon placed all the articles in the temple of the Eternal
            [[the golden altar, the golden table for the Presence-bread, <verse eID="1Kgs.7.48"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.7.49" osisID="1Kgs.7.49"/> the pure gold lampstands in front of the inner shrine, five to the
            right and five to the left, with their golden ornamental flowers and lamps and tongs, <verse eID="1Kgs.7.49"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.7.50" osisID="1Kgs.7.50"/> the pure gold cups, snuffers, bowls, saucers, and fire-pans, and
            the golden hinges both for
           <milestone type="pb" n="390"/>
            the folding doors of the inner shrine or most sacred Place and for the folding doors of the temple]]. <verse eID="1Kgs.7.50"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.7.51" osisID="1Kgs.7.51"/> So all the work pre­pared bv king Solomon in the temple of the
            Eternal was finished; Solomon then brought in the votive offerings of his father David, the silver and the
            gold and the various articles, placing them in the store-chambers of the Eternal's temple. <verse eID="1Kgs.7.51"/>
       </p>
       <chapter eID="1Kgs.7"/>
       <chapter osisID="1Kgs.8" sID="1Kgs.8"/>
       <p>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.8.1" osisID="1Kgs.8.1"/> Then Solomon called together the sheikhs of Israel and all the chiefs of the
            clans, the heads of the various Israelite families, in Jerusalem, to bring the ark of the Eternal's compact up from
            David’s burg. <verse eID="1Kgs.8.1"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.8.2" osisID="1Kgs.8.2"/> The Israelites all gathered round Solomon at the festival in the month of
            Ethanim (the seventh month); <verse eID="1Kgs.8.2"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.8.3" osisID="1Kgs.8.3"/> the sheikhs of Israel all went with the priests and <verse eID="1Kgs.8.3"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.8.4" osisID="1Kgs.8.4"/> carried up the ark of the Eternal, the Trysting tent, and all the sacred
            articles inside the tent; these were carried by the priests and Levites, <verse eID="1Kgs.8.4"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.8.5" osisID="1Kgs.8.5"/> while king Solomon and all the community of Israel which had gathered round
            him walked in front of the ark, sacrificing sheep and oxen past all counting and numbering. <verse eID="1Kgs.8.5"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.8.6" osisID="1Kgs.8.6"/> The priests placed the ark of the Eternal inside the inner shrine, the most
            sacred interior, under the wings of the kherubs; <verse eID="1Kgs.8.6"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.8.7" osisID="1Kgs.8.7"/> for the wings of the kherubs stretched over the place for the ark, covering
            the ark and its poles, <verse eID="1Kgs.8.7"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.8.8" osisID="1Kgs.8.8"/> though the poles were so long that their projecting tips could be seen, not
            outside, but from the sacred hall in front of the shrine--the position they occupy to this very day. <verse eID="1Kgs.8.8"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.8.9" osisID="1Kgs.8.9"/> Inside the ark there was nothing except the two stone tablets which Moses had
            placed there at Horeb, the tablets of the compact which the Eternal made with the Israelites when they left the land
            of Egypt. <verse eID="1Kgs.8.9"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.8.10" osisID="1Kgs.8.10"/> When the priests came out of the inner shrine, a cloud filled the temple of
            the Eternal <verse eID="1Kgs.8.10"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.8.11" osisID="1Kgs.8.11"/> so densely that the priests could not stand to serve; the Eternal's
            splendour of glory filled the temple of the Eternal. <verse eID="1Kgs.8.11"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.8.12" osisID="1Kgs.8.12"/> Then said Solomon:
            <q><lg>
             <li> The sun has the Eternal set in heaven, </li>
             <li> but chosen himself to dwell in darkness; </li>
           <verse eID="1Kgs.8.12"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.8.13" osisID="1Kgs.8.13"/>
                <li> so I have built this mansion great for thee, </li>
                <li> for thee to dwell in, to eternity. </li>
            </lg></q>
           <verse eID="1Kgs.8.13"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.8.14" osisID="1Kgs.8.14"/> Then the king turned round and blessed all the gathering of Israel as they
            stood. <verse eID="1Kgs.8.14"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.8.15" osisID="1Kgs.8.15"/> He said, <q>Blessed be the Eternal the God of Israel, who spoke directly to
            my father David, and has done all that he promised! <verse eID="1Kgs.8.15"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.8.16" osisID="1Kgs.8.16"/> He said, <q>Ever since I brought my people Israel out of Egypt, I chose no
            city out of any clan of Israel to build a temple for my presence, but now have I chosen Jerusalem as my seat and
            David as lord over my people Israel.</q> <verse eID="1Kgs.8.16"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.8.17" osisID="1Kgs.8.17"/> My father David did have it in mind to build a temple in honour of the
            Eternal the God of Israel; <verse eID="1Kgs.8.17"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.8.18" osisID="1Kgs.8.18"/> but the Eternal said to my father David, <q>You had it in your mind to
            build a temple in my honour; you did well to have that in mind. <verse eID="1Kgs.8.18"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.8.19" osisID="1Kgs.8.19"/> Yet you are not to build the temple; it is your son, born of your body,
            who shall build the temple in my honour.</q> <verse eID="1Kgs.8.19"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.8.20" osisID="1Kgs.8.20"/> The Eternal has done what he promised; for I have risen to succeed my
            father David and to sit upon the throne of Israel, as the Eternal promised, and I have built the temple in honour
            of the Eternal the God of Israel; <verse eID="1Kgs.8.20"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.8.21" osisID="1Kgs.8.21"/> in it have I made a place for the ark containing
            the compact which the
           <milestone type="pb" n="391"/>
            Eternal made with our fathers when he brought them out of the land of Egypt.</q><verse eID="1Kgs.8.21"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.8.22" osisID="1Kgs.8.22"/> Then Solomon stood in front of the altar of the Eternal, in presence of all
            the community of Israel, and stretching out his hands to heaven <verse eID="1Kgs.8.22"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.8.23" osisID="1Kgs.8.23"/> he cried: <q>O Eternal, God of Israel, there is no god like thee in heaven
            above or on the earth below, who keepest thy compact and showest kindness to thy servants as they live under thine eye
            with all their heart. <verse eID="1Kgs.8.23"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.8.24" osisID="1Kgs.8.24"/> Thou hast kept thy word to thy servant David my father; thou didst make him
            thine own promise and thou hast done it, as it is this day. <verse eID="1Kgs.8.24"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.8.25" osisID="1Kgs.8.25"/> Now then, O Eternal, God of Israel, keep this thy promise to thy servant
            David my father: <q>You shall never lack a descendant in my sight to sit upon the throne of Israel, if only your
            children watch their lives, careful to live under my eye as you have done.</q> <verse eID="1Kgs.8.25"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.8.26" osisID="1Kgs.8.26"/> 0 God of Israel, pray let this promise be fulfilled which thou didst make
            to thy servant David my father. <verse eID="1Kgs.8.26"/></q>
       </p>
       <p>
           <q>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.8.27" osisID="1Kgs.8.27"/> But can God really live on earth? The very heaven, the height of heaven
            itself, cannot contain thee; and how much less this temple I have built! <verse eID="1Kgs.8.27"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.8.28" osisID="1Kgs.8.28"/> So do thou turn, O Eternal my God, to thy servant in his prayers and
            supplications, listening to the cry of prayer which thy servant lifts to thee this day, <verse eID="1Kgs.8.28"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.8.29" osisID="1Kgs.8.29"/> that thine eyes may be open, night and day, to this temple, to the place
            where thou hast promised thy presence, listening to the prayer that thy servant offers, when he turns to this
            place. <verse eID="1Kgs.8.29"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.8.30" osisID="1Kgs.8.30"/> Listen to the supplication of thy servant and of thy people Israel when
            they turn in prayer towards this place; yea, hear us in thy home, in heaven, and as thou hearest forgive
            us.</q> <verse eID="1Kgs.8.30"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.8.31" osisID="1Kgs.8.31"/><q>When a man sins against his neighbour and is adjured to swear an oath,
            when he comes and swears his oath before thine altar in this temple, <verse eID="1Kgs.8.31"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.8.32" osisID="1Kgs.8.32"/> then do thou listen in heaven, take action and decide between thy servants,
            condemning the guilty by making him suffer for his misdeeds, and vindicating the innocent by rewarding him for his
            innocence. <verse eID="1Kgs.8.32"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.8.33" osisID="1Kgs.8.33"/> When thy people Israel fall before the foe, because they have sinned against thee,
            if they repent and own thee openly and pray with supplications to thee in this temple, <verse eID="1Kgs.8.33"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.8.34" osisID="1Kgs.8.34"/> then do thou listen in heaven and forgive the sin of thy people Israel,
            letting them remain within the land which thou gavest to their fathers.</q> <verse eID="1Kgs.8.34"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.8.35" osisID="1Kgs.8.35"/><q>When the skies are shut and no rain falls, because they have sinned
            against thee, if they turn in prayer towards this place and own thee openly and give up their sin under thy
            chastisement, <verse eID="1Kgs.8.35"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.8.36" osisID="1Kgs.8.36"/> then do thou listen in heaven and forgive the sin of thy servants and thy
            people Israel, as thou teachest them the good path for their life; send rain upon thy land, which thou hast given thy
            people as their heritage. <verse eID="1Kgs.8.36"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.8.37" osisID="1Kgs.8.37"/> When there is famine in the land, or pestilence, blasting or mildew,
            locusts or caterpillars, when their enemy besieges them in any of their towns, whatever be the plague or
            trouble--<verse eID="1Kgs.8.37"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.8.38" osisID="1Kgs.8.38"/> whatever prayer and supplication is offered by any man of them, knowing
            well what plagues himself, and stretching his hands out towards this place, <verse eID="1Kgs.8.38"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.8.39" osisID="1Kgs.8.39"/> then do thou
           <milestone type="pb" n="392"/>
            listen in thy home, in heaven, and forgive them and take action, dealing with every man as he has lived, O thou who
            knowest his heart (for thou, thou only, knowest the hearts of all men), <verse eID="1Kgs.8.39"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.8.40" osisID="1Kgs.8.40"/> that they may stand in awe of thee all the days of their life in the land
            thou gavest to our fathers. <verse eID="1Kgs.8.40"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.8.41" osisID="1Kgs.8.41"/> As for the alien, who does not belong to thy people Israel but who came
            from a distant land for thy sake <verse eID="1Kgs.8.41"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.8.42" osisID="1Kgs.8.42"/> (for men shall hear of thy great fame, of thy strength and mighty force),
            when he comes and turns in prayer towards this temple, <verse eID="1Kgs.8.42"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.8.43" osisID="1Kgs.8.43"/> then do thou listen in thy home, in heaven, and do all that the alien asks
            of thee, so that all nations in the world may learn what thou art, learning to stand in awe of thee, like thy people
            Israel, and learning that thou hast taken this temple which I built to be thine own.</q><verse eID="1Kgs.8.43"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.8.44" osisID="1Kgs.8.44"/><q>When thy people march out to fight against their enemy, in any way of thine
            appointing, and pray to the Eternal, turning towards the city thou hast chosen and the temple I have built in
            honour of thee, <verse eID="1Kgs.8.44"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.8.45" osisID="1Kgs.8.45"/> then do thou listen in heaven to their prayer and supplication and uphold
            their cause.</q><verse eID="1Kgs.8.45"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.8.46" osisID="1Kgs.8.46"/><q>When they sin against thee (for there is no man who does not sin) and thou
            in thine anger leavest them to their enemies, till they are carried away prisoners to an enemy's land, far off or
            near, <verse eID="1Kgs.8.46"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.8.47" osisID="1Kgs.8.47"/> yet if they take thought in the land of their captivity and repent and
            offer supplications to thee in the land of those who took them prisoners, crying, <q>We have sinned, we have gone
            wrong, we have done evil,</q> if they repent, heart and soul, in the land of their enemies who took them prisoners,
            and pray to thee, <verse eID="1Kgs.8.47"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.8.48" osisID="1Kgs.8.48"/> turning in the direction of the land thou gavest to their fathers, the city
            thou hast chosen, and the temple I have built in honour of thee: <verse eID="1Kgs.8.48"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.8.49" osisID="1Kgs.8.49"/> then do thou listen in thy home, in heaven, to their prayer and
            supplication and uphold their cause; <verse eID="1Kgs.8.49"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.8.50" osisID="1Kgs.8.50"/> forgive thy people who have sinned against thee, forgive all their
            transgressions against thee, and grant they may be pitied by those who have taken them prisoners, <verse eID="1Kgs.8.50"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.8.51" osisID="1Kgs.8.51"/> for they are thy people, thine own possession, whom thou didst bring out
            of Egypt, out of that iron furnace. <verse eID="1Kgs.8.51"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.8.52" osisID="1Kgs.8.52"/> 0 may thine eyes be open to thy servant and thy people Israel at their
            prayers, listening to them whenever they call to thee. <verse eID="1Kgs.8.52"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.8.53" osisID="1Kgs.8.53"/> For thou didst separate them from all nations on earth to be thy very
            own, as thou didst declare by Moses thy servant when thou broughtest our fathers out of Egypt, O Lord Eternal.</q>
           <verse eID="1Kgs.8.53"/>
       <p>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.8.54" osisID="1Kgs.8.54"/> After Solomon had finished offering all this prayer and supplication to
            the Eternal, he rose from his knees before the altar of the Eternal, where he had been stretching his hands out to
            heaven; <verse eID="1Kgs.8.54"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.8.55" osisID="1Kgs.8.55"/> he now stood up and in a loud voice blessed all the community of Israel,
            saying, <verse eID="1Kgs.8.55"/>
       </p>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.8.56" osisID="1Kgs.8.56"/> <q>Blessed be the Eternal who has granted rest to his people Israel, as he
            promised; not a word has failed of all the good promises he made to us by Moses his servant. <verse eID="1Kgs.8.56"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.8.57" osisID="1Kgs.8.57"/> May the Eternal our God be with us, as he was with our fathers--never
            leaving us, never forsaking us-- <verse eID="1Kgs.8.57"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.8.58" osisID="1Kgs.8.58"/> that he may move our minds always to live as he lives, to obey his orders,
            his rules and regulations, which he laid down
           <milestone type="pb" n="393"/>
            for our fathers! <verse eID="1Kgs.8.58"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.8.59" osisID="1Kgs.8.59"/> And may these words of my supplication to the Eternal be ever present to
            the Eternal our God, day and night, that he may uphold the cause of his servant and the cause of his people Israel,
            as each day may require, <verse eID="1Kgs.8.59"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.8.60" osisID="1Kgs.8.60"/> so that all the nations of the world may learn that the Eternal is God,
            the Eternal and none else. <verse eID="1Kgs.8.60"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.8.61" osisID="1Kgs.8.61"/> Keep, then, an undivided mind for the Eternal our God, to live by his rules
            and to obey his orders, as to-day.</q> <verse eID="1Kgs.8.61"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.8.62" osisID="1Kgs.8.62"/> The king, along with all Israel, offered sacrifices before the Eternal.
           <verse eID="1Kgs.8.62"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.8.63" osisID="1Kgs.8.63"/> Solomon offered, in his sacrifice of recompense-offering to the Eternal,
            twenty-two thousand oxen and a hundred and twenty thousand sheep; <verse eID="1Kgs.8.63"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.8.64" osisID="1Kgs.8.64"/> in this way the king and all the Israelites dedicated the temple of the
            Eternal. The king consecrated that day the middle part of the court in front of the temple of the Eternal; for it
            was there that he sacrificed the victims for the burnt-offering, and offered the cereal-offering and the fat slices
            from the victims of the recompense-offerings, the bronze altar before the Eternal being too small to hold the
            burnt-offering, the cereal-offering, and the fat slices from the victims. <verse eID="1Kgs.8.64"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.8.65" osisID="1Kgs.8.65"/> Such was the festival then held in presence of the Eternal our God for
            seven days by Solomon and all Israel--a vast host, drawn from all parts, from the pass of Hamath down to the
            Wady-el-Arish. <verse eID="1Kgs.8.65"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.8.66" osisID="1Kgs.8.66"/> On the eighth day he dismissed the people, who blessed the king and went
            home rejoicing, glad in heart at all the goodness of the Eternal to his servant David and his people Israel. <verse eID="1Kgs.8.66"/>
       </p>
      <chapter eID="1Kgs.8"/>
      <chapter osisID="1Kgs.9" sID="1Kgs.9"/>
       <p>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.9.1" osisID="1Kgs.9.1"/> Now after Solomon had finished building the temple of the Eternal and the
            royal palace and all that it pleased him to erect, <verse eID="1Kgs.9.1"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.9.2" osisID="1Kgs.9.2"/> the Eternal appeared to Solomon a second time, as he had appeared to him at
            Gibeon. <verse eID="1Kgs.9.2"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.9.3" osisID="1Kgs.9.3"/> The Eternal said to him, <q>I have listened to your prayer and supplication,
            and I have done for you all you desire; I hereby consecrate this temple you have built, by fixing my presence there
            for all time; my eyes and my heart shall constantly be there. <verse eID="1Kgs.9.3"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.9.4" osisID="1Kgs.9.4"/> As for yourself, if you will live under my eye, as your father David lived,
           with upright heart and honestly, doing exactly as I have ordered you and following my rules and regulations, <verse eID="1Kgs.9.4"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.9.5" osisID="1Kgs.9.5"/> then I will make your royal throne sure over Israel for all time, as I
            promised to your father David that he would never be without a descendant on the throne of Israel. <verse eID="1Kgs.9.5"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.9.6" osisID="1Kgs.9.6"/> But if you give up following me, you or your children, if you do not keep the
            commands and rules I have set before you, but go and serve foreign gods and worship them, <verse eID="1Kgs.9.6"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.9.7" osisID="1Kgs.9.7"/> then I will cut Israel out of the land I gave them, and cast out of my sight
            this temple which I have consecrated for myself, and Israel shall become a proverb and by­word among all nations; <verse eID="1Kgs.9.7"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.9.8" osisID="1Kgs.9.8"/> this temple shall be a heap of ruins, and any passer-by shall whistle in
            amazement, saying, <q>Why has the Eternal dealt thus with this land and temple?</q> <verse eID="1Kgs.9.8"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.9.9" osisID="1Kgs.9.9"/> The answer will be, <q>Because the people forsook the Eternal their God who
            brought their fathers out of the land of Egypt; because they took up with foreign gods, worshipping and serving
            them; that is why the Eternal
           <milestone type="pb" n="394"/>
            brought all this ruin upon them.</q></q> <verse eID="1Kgs.9.9"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.9.10" osisID="1Kgs.9.10"/> At the end of twenty years, in the course of which Solomon had built the
            two buildings, the temple of the Eternal and the royal palace, <verse eID="1Kgs.9.10"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.9.11" osisID="1Kgs.9.11"/> as Hiram king of Tyre had provided Solomon with cedar-trees and fir-trees
            and gold to his heart's content, king Solomon let Hiram have twenty towns in the region of Galilee. <verse eID="1Kgs.9.11"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.9.12" osisID="1Kgs.9.12"/> When Hiram came from Tyre to inspect the towns made over to him by Solomon,
            he was not pleased with them. <verse eID="1Kgs.9.12"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.9.13" osisID="1Kgs.9.13"/> <q>My brother,</q> he said, <q>what sort of towns are these you have given
            me?</q> So he called them the <q>Cabul</q> (good-for-nothing) district. It is their name to this day. <verse eID="1Kgs.9.13"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.9.14" osisID="1Kgs.9.14"/> (For them Hiram paid to the king six hundred and ninety-three thousand
            pounds in gold.) <verse eID="1Kgs.9.14"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.9.15" osisID="1Kgs.9.15"/>This was how king Solomon raised the labour-gangs to build the temple of
            the Eternal, his own palace, the Millo and the wall of Jerusalem, Hazor, Megiddo, Gezer, <verse eID="1Kgs.9.15"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.9.17" osisID="1Kgs.9.17"/> Bcth-horon the lower, <verse eID="1Kgs.9.17"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.9.18" osisID="1Kgs.9.18"/> Baalath, Tamar in the desert land, <verse eID="1Kgs.9.18"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.9.19" osisID="1Kgs.9.19"/> all the store-towns Solomon possessed, the towns for his chariots, the
            towns for his cavalry, and whatever Solomon was pleased to build in Jerusalem, at Lebanon, and anywhere throughout his
            realm. <verse eID="1Kgs.9.19"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.9.20" osisID="1Kgs.9.20"/> Solomon raised his levy of slave-labourers, as is done to this day, from
            the descendants of the Amorites, the Hittites, the Perizzites, the Hivites, and the Jebusites, none of whom belonged
            to Israel—- <verse eID="1Kgs.9.20"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.9.21" osisID="1Kgs.9.21"/> survivors in the land whom the Israelites had not been able to exterminate.
           <verse eID="1Kgs.9.21"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.9.22" osisID="1Kgs.9.22"/> Solomon never made slaves of Israelites; they were his soldiers and
            officials, his generals, captains, chariot-leaders, and cavalry-leaders. <verse eID="1Kgs.9.22"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.9.23" osisID="1Kgs.9.23"/> The following five hundred and fifty men were Solomon's supervisors, who
            managed the la­bourers... <verse eID="1Kgs.9.23"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.9.24" osisID="1Kgs.9.24"/> Solomon brought the Pharaoh's daughter up from David's burg to the palace
            he had built for her; then he built the Millo... <verse eID="1Kgs.9.24"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.9.25" osisID="1Kgs.9.25"/> Three times a year Solomon used to offer burnt-offerings and
            recompense-offerings on the altar he had built for the Eternal, and to burn his fire-offering before the Eternal...
           <verse eID="1Kgs.9.25"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.9.26" osisID="1Kgs.9.26"/> King Solomon built a navy at Ezion-geber near Eloth in the land of Edom,
            on the shore of the Reed Sea. <verse eID="1Kgs.9.26"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.9.27" osisID="1Kgs.9.27"/> Hiram sent his men, expert seamen, to man the fleet along with the men of
            Solomon; <verse eID="1Kgs.9.27"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.9.28" osisID="1Kgs.9.28"/> they reached Ophir and brought away eighteen tons of gold for king Solomon.
           <verse eID="1Kgs.9.28"/>
       </p>
      <chapter eID="1Kgs.9"/>
      <chapter osisID="1Kgs.10" sID="1Kgs.10"/>
       <p>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.10.11" osisID="1Kgs.10.11"/> Hiram’s fleet, that brought gold from Ophir, also brought from
            Ophir a wealth of sandal-wood and jewels; <verse eID="1Kgs.10.11"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.10.12" osisID="1Kgs.10.12"/> the sandal-wood was made into pilasters for the temple of the
            Eternal and the royal palace as well as into lyres and lutes for the singers. Such wealth and quality of
            sandal­wood have never since been seen. <verse eID="1Kgs.10.12"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.10.14" osisID="1Kgs.10.14"/> The amount of gold that came to Solomon in one year was nearly
            twenty-nine tons, <verse eID="1Kgs.10.14"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.10.15" osisID="1Kgs.10.15"/> in addition to what was derived in taxes from traders and as
            tribute from Arabian emirs and from vassal-princes. <verse eID="1Kgs.10.15"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.10.16" osisID="1Kgs.10.16"/> King Solomon made two hundred shields of beaten gold; twenty
            pounds of gold went to each shield. <verse eID="1Kgs.10.16"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.10.17" osisID="1Kgs.10.17"/> He also made three hundred targes of beaten gold; about six
            pounds of gold went to each of them; the king hung these in the <q>Forest of Lebanon</q>
           <milestone type="pb" n="395"/>
           hall. <verse eID="1Kgs.10.17"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.10.18" osisID="1Kgs.10.18"/> The king also made a large ivory throne, which he overlaid with
            the finest gold; <verse eID="1Kgs.10.18"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.10.19" osisID="1Kgs.10.19"/> the throne had six steps and a rounded back, there were arms on
            each side of the seat, flanked by two lions,
           <verse eID="1Kgs.10.19"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.10.20" osisID="1Kgs.10.20"/>while twelve lions stood on each side of the six steps. No such
            throne was ever made in any kingdom. <verse eID="1Kgs.10.20"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.10.21" osisID="1Kgs.10.21"/> King Solomon's drinking service was all made of gold, and all the
            articles in the <q>Forest of Lebanon</q> hall were made of pure gold, none were silver--silver was thought
            nothing of in Solomon's day. <verse eID="1Kgs.10.21"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.10.22" osisID="1Kgs.10.22"/> For the king had a deep-sea fleet which sailed with the navy of
            Hiram; once every three years this fleet came home with gold and silver, ivory, apes, and peacocks. <verse eID="1Kgs.10.22"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.10.23" osisID="1Kgs.10.23"/> So in wealth and in wisdom king Solomon excelled all kings
            on earth. <verse eID="1Kgs.10.23"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.10.24" osisID="1Kgs.10.24"/> The whole world came to visit Solomon, to listen to the wisdom
            which God had put into his mind, <verse eID="1Kgs.10.24"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.10.25" osisID="1Kgs.10.25"/> and everyone brought his present, silver articles, gold articles,
            robes, weapons, and spices, horses and mules, so much year by year. <verse eID="1Kgs.10.25"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.10.26" osisID="1Kgs.10.26"/> In this way Solomon amassed chariots and cavalry; he had one
            thousand four hundred chariots and twelve thousand cavalry, stationed in the chariot-towns or at Jerusalem
            beside the king himself. <verse eID="1Kgs.10.26"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.10.28" osisID="1Kgs.10.28"/> Solomon's horses were imported from Muzri and from Kue; the
            royal dealers used to bring a troop of horses from Kue, paying cash for them; <verse eID="1Kgs.10.28"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.10.29" osisID="1Kgs.10.29"/> a chariot could be imported from Muzri for seventy-five pounds
            in silver, and a horse for about twenty pounds in silver (the dealers supplied all the kings of the Hittites
            and the Aramaeans at the same rate). <verse eID="1Kgs.10.29"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.10.27" osisID="1Kgs.10.27"/> The king made silver as common in Jerusalem as stones, and
            cedar-wood as plentiful as sycomore-trees in the lowlands. <verse eID="1Kgs.10.27"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.10.1" osisID="1Kgs.10.1"/> When the queen of Sheba heard about the fame of Solomon and the
            temple he had built in honour of the Eternal, she came to test him with puzzling questions. <verse eID="1Kgs.10.1"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.10.2" osisID="1Kgs.10.2"/> She came to Jerusalem with a very large retinue, with camels
            bearing spices, heaps of gold, and jewels. As soon as she reached Solomon, she opened out all that was on her
            mind; <verse eID="1Kgs.10.2"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.10.3" osisID="1Kgs.10.3"/> and Solomon answered all her questions, there was not a single
            thing hidden from the king which he could not explain to her. <verse eID="1Kgs.10.3"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.10.4" osisID="1Kgs.10.4"/> When the queen of Sheba realized all this wisdom of Solomon, when
            she saw the palace he had built, <verse eID="1Kgs.10.4"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.10.5" osisID="1Kgs.10.5"/> the food at his table, the way his courtiers were arranged and his
            servants waited, and their dress, and the cup-bearers, and the burnt-offerings he used to sacrifice in the
            temple of the Eternal, she was quite overwhelmed; <verse eID="1Kgs.10.5"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.10.6" osisID="1Kgs.10.6"/> she said to the king, <q>That was a true tale I heard in my own
            country of your words and wisdom! <verse eID="1Kgs.10.6"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.10.7" osisID="1Kgs.10.7"/> But I did not believe it till I came and saw for myself. And now I
            see not half was told me; your wisdom and prosperity far exceed what I was told. <verse eID="1Kgs.10.7"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.10.8" osisID="1Kgs.10.8"/> Happy are your wives! Happy men, these courtiers who are always
            waiting upon you and hearing your wisdom! <verse eID="1Kgs.10.8"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.10.9" osisID="1Kgs.10.9"/> Blessed be the Eternal your God who delighted in you and set you
            on the throne of Israel! It is because the Eternal loved Israel that he made you king, to govern and
            administer justice!</q> <verse eID="1Kgs.10.9"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.10.10" osisID="1Kgs.10.10"/> She presented the king with about seven hundred and fifty
            thousand pounds in gold, a wealth of spices, and jewels; no
            <milestone type="pb" n="396"/>
            supply of spices ever again came as rich as the queen of Sheba’s present to king Solomon. <verse eID="1Kgs.10.10"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.10.13" osisID="1Kgs.10.13"/> King Solomon in turn presented the queen of Sheba with whatever
           she desired, with anything she asked, besides what he bestowed upon her out of his royal bounty. Then she
           returned to her own land, she and her retinue. <verse eID="1Kgs.10.13"/>
       </p>
      <chapter eID="1Kgs.10"/>
      <chapter osisID="1Kgs.11" sID="1Kgs.11"/>
       <p>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.11.3" osisID="1Kgs.11.3"/>Now king Solomon was a lover of women; he had seven hundred royal
            wives, and three hundred mistresses. <verse eID="1Kgs.11.3"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.11.1" osisID="1Kgs.11.1"/> He married many foreign women--Moabites, Ammonites, Edomites,
            Phoenicians, and Hittites <verse eID="1Kgs.11.1"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.11.2" osisID="1Kgs.11.2"/> belonging to nations against whom the Eternal had warned the men
            of Israel, <q>You must not mix with them, nor let them mix with you, for they will be sure to seduce you to
            follow their gods.</q> Solomon clung to these women in love. <verse eID="1Kgs.11.2"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.11.4" osisID="1Kgs.11.4"/> When he grew old, he had no undivided mind for the Eternal his
            God, as his father David had; <verse eID="1Kgs.11.4"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.11.6" osisID="1Kgs.11.6"/> his wives seduced him to follow foreign gods. Solomon did what
            was evil in the eyes of the Eternal; he did not follow the Eternal faithfully, as his father David had done.
           <verse eID="1Kgs.11.6"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.11.5" osisID="1Kgs.11.5"/> For he put up shrines for Astarte the goddess of the Phoenicians,
            and for Milkom the detestable idol of the Ammonites, <verse eID="1Kgs.11.5"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.11.7" osisID="1Kgs.11.7"/> and for Kemosh the detestable idol of Moab, on a hill to the east
            of Jerusalem. <verse eID="1Kgs.11.7"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.11.8" osisID="1Kgs.11.8"/> He did the same for all his foreign wives, burning incense and
            offering sacrifice to their gods. <verse eID="1Kgs.11.8"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.11.9" osisID="1Kgs.11.9"/> The Eternal was angry with Solomon for letting himself be seduced
            from the Eternal, the God of Israel, who had twice appeared to him <verse eID="1Kgs.11.9"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.11.10" osisID="1Kgs.11.10"/> and given him this order, that he was not to follow foreign
            gods; he did not obey what the Eternal had ordered, <verse eID="1Kgs.11.10"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.11.11" osisID="1Kgs.11.11"/> and so the Eternal said to Solomon, <q>Since this is your mind,
            since you have not obeyed my compact and the rules I laid down for you, I will tear the kingdom from you
            and give it to your servant. <verse eID="1Kgs.11.11"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.11.12" osisID="1Kgs.11.12"/> Nevertheless I will not do this during your lifetime, for the
            sake of David your father; I will tear it out of your son's hands. <verse eID="1Kgs.11.12"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.11.13" osisID="1Kgs.11.13"/> Still, I will not tear away all the kingdom; I will let your
            son have one clan, for the sake of David my servant and for the sake of Jerusalem which I have chosen.</q> <verse eID="1Kgs.11.13"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.11.14" osisID="1Kgs.11.14"/> The Eternal then raised up an opponent for Solomon in Hadad the
            Edomite, who belonged to the royal family of Edom. <verse eID="1Kgs.11.14"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.11.15" osisID="1Kgs.11.15"/> For when David crushed Edom and killed every male in the
            country, <verse eID="1Kgs.11.15"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.11.17" osisID="1Kgs.11.17"/> Hadad, who was then a little boy, was taken by one of his
            father's slaves to the Pharaoh in Egypt. <verse eID="1Kgs.11.17"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.11.18" osisID="1Kgs.11.18"/> Hadad became very popular with the Pharaoh, <verse eID="1Kgs.11.18"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.11.19" osisID="1Kgs.11.19"/> who gave him to Tahpenes his queen; <verse eID="1Kgs.11.19"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.11.20" osisID="1Kgs.11.20"/> she brought up the boy in the Pharaoh's palace among the
            Pharaoh's sons. <verse eID="1Kgs.11.20"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.11.21" osisID="1Kgs.11.21"/> But when Hadad heard in Egypt that David slept with his fathers,
            he said to the Pharaoh, <q>Let me leave, let me go home.</q> <verse eID="1Kgs.11.21"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.11.22" osisID="1Kgs.11.22"/>The Pharaoh said to him, <q>What do you miss here, beside me,
            that you now wish to go home?</q> Hadad said to him, <q>You must let me go.</q> <verse eID="1Kgs.11.22"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.11.25" osisID="1Kgs.11.25"/> So Hadad returned home; he ruled over Edom and bore hard on
            Israel; such was the mischief he did. <verse eID="1Kgs.11.25"/>
       </p>
       <p>
        <verse sID="1Kgs.11.15" osisID="1Kgs.11.15"/> [[Once, when Joab the commander-in-chief had gone to bury the
         slain Israelites, <verse eID="1Kgs.11.15"/>
        <verse sID="1Kgs.11.16" osisID="1Kgs.11.16"/> he and all Israel remained for six months, crushing all Edom till
         it was utterly destroyed. <verse eID="1Kgs.11.16"/>
        <verse sID="1Kgs.11.17" osisID="1Kgs.11.17"/> Adad and some Edomites fled for
         <milestone type="pb" n="397"/>
           Egypt. <verse eID="1Kgs.11.17"/>
        <verse sID="1Kgs.11.18" osisID="1Kgs.11.18"/> They got away from Midian to Paran, and, taking some men of Paran
           with them, they went to the Pharaoh in Egypt. He gave Adad a house, assigned him an allowance, and presented
           him with some land; <verse eID="1Kgs.11.18"/>
        <verse sID="1Kgs.11.19" osisID="1Kgs.11.19"/> he also married him to Anoth, the sister of Tahpenes, <verse eID="1Kgs.11.19"/>
        <verse sID="1Kgs.11.20" osisID="1Kgs.11.20"/> who bore him a son called Genubath; and Genubath lived in the
         palace of the Pharaoh.]] <verse eID="1Kgs.11.20"/>
       </p>
       <p>
        <verse sID="1Kgs.11.23" osisID="1Kgs.11.23"/> God raised up another opponent for him in Rezon the son of Eliada,
           who had run away from his master, Hadadezer the king of Zobah. <verse eID="1Kgs.11.23"/>
        <verse sID="1Kgs.11.24" osisID="1Kgs.11.24"/> Rezon gathered men round him and became the leader of a band of
           raiders, who captured Damascus. There Rezon stayed, ruling over Damascus. <verse eID="1Kgs.11.24"/>
        <verse sID="1Kgs.11.25" osisID="1Kgs.11.25"/>He was an opponent of Israel during all the reign of Solomon. <verse eID="1Kgs.11.25"/>
       </p>
       <p>
        <verse sID="1Kgs.11.26" osisID="1Kgs.11.26"/> Then there was Jeroboam the son of Nebat, an Ephraimite from
         Zereda, whose mother Zeruah was a widow; he was in the service of Solomon, and he too rose against the king.
        <verse eID="1Kgs.11.26"/>
        <verse sID="1Kgs.11.27" osisID="1Kgs.11.27"/> This was how he came to rise against the king. Solomon was
         building the Millo and repairing the gaps in the city of his father David. <verse eID="1Kgs.11.27"/>
        <verse sID="1Kgs.11.28" osisID="1Kgs.11.28"/> Jeroboam was an extremely capable man; and when Solomon noticed
           how active the young man was, he put him in charge of all the labour-gang. <verse eID="1Kgs.11.28"/>
        <verse sID="1Kgs.11.29" osisID="1Kgs.11.29"/> One day Jeroboam was leaving Jerusalem, when the prophet Ahijah of
         Shilo met him and took him aside. The two of them were alone there, in the open country. <verse eID="1Kgs.11.29"/>
        <verse sID="1Kgs.11.30" osisID="1Kgs.11.30"/> Then Ahijah took a new robe which he had put on, and tore it into
         twelve pieces. <verse eID="1Kgs.11.30"/>
        <verse sID="1Kgs.11.31" osisID="1Kgs.11.31"/> <q>Take ten for yourself,</q> he said to Jeroboam, <q>for this is
         the message of the Eternal the God of Israel: I will tear the kingdom out of Solomon's hands and give you
         ten of the clans <verse eID="1Kgs.11.31"/>
        <verse sID="1Kgs.11.32" osisID="1Kgs.11.32"/>[[though he is to keep one clan, for the sake of my servant David
         and for the sake of Jerusalem the city I have chosen from all the clans of Israel; <verse eID="1Kgs.11.32"/>
        <verse sID="1Kgs.11.33" osisID="1Kgs.11.33"/> for they have forsaken me for the worship of Astarte the goddess
         of the Phoenicians, of Kemosh the god of Moab, and of Milkom the god of the Ammonites; they have not lived my
         life, doing what is right in my eyes and living by my rules and regulations, as David his father did. <verse eID="1Kgs.11.33"/>
        <verse sID="1Kgs.11.34" osisID="1Kgs.11.34"/> However, I will not take all the kingdom out of his hands; for the
         sake of my servant David, whom I chose, I will leave him his royalty as long as he lives, <verse eID="1Kgs.11.34"/>
        <verse sID="1Kgs.11.35" osisID="1Kgs.11.35"/> but I will take the kingdom out of his son's hands and give you
         the ten clans; <verse eID="1Kgs.11.35"/>
        <verse sID="1Kgs.11.36" osisID="1Kgs.11.36"/> his son shall have one clan, so that my servant David may always
         have one of his race before me in Jerusalem, the city I have chosen as my seat. <verse eID="1Kgs.11.36"/>
        <verse sID="1Kgs.11.37" osisID="1Kgs.11.37"/> I will take you to reign over Israel, to rule as widely as you
         please; <verse eID="1Kgs.11.37"/>
        <verse sID="1Kgs.11.38" osisID="1Kgs.11.38"/> if you listen to all my orders and live my life, doing what is
         right in my eyes, keeping my rules and regulations as my servant David did, then I will be on your side and
         establish your dynasty as I did David's]].</q><verse eID="1Kgs.11.38"/>
        <verse sID="1Kgs.11.40" osisID="1Kgs.11.40"/> Solomon therefore tried to murder Jeroboam, but Jeroboam fled away
         to Egypt, to Shishak king of Egypt, where he remained till the death of Solomon. <verse eID="1Kgs.11.40"/>
       </p>
       <p>
        <verse sID="1Kgs.11.41" osisID="1Kgs.11.41"/> As for the rest of the acts of Solomon, his deeds and his wisdom,
         are they not described in the book of the Acts of Solomon? <verse eID="1Kgs.11.41"/>
        <verse sID="1Kgs.11.42" osisID="1Kgs.11.42"/> Solomon reigned in Jerusalem over all Israel for forty years. <verse eID="1Kgs.11.42"/>
        <verse sID="1Kgs.11.43" osisID="1Kgs.11.43"/> Then Solomon slept with his fathers and was buried
        <milestone type="pb" n="398"/>
         in the city of David his father, <verse eID="1Kgs.11.43"/>
       </p>
      <chapter eID="1Kgs.11"/>
      <chapter osisID="1Kgs.12" sID="1Kgs.12"/>
       <p>
        <verse sID="1Kgs.12.2" osisID="1Kgs.12.2"/>
         As soon as Jeroboam the son of Nebat heard this--he was still in Egypt, whither he had fled to escape
         Solomon--he came back to his native town of Sareira in the highlands of Ephraim. <verse eID="1Kgs.12.2"/>
      <chapter osisID="1Kgs.11" sID="1Kgs.11"/>
        <verse sID="1Kgs.11.43" osisID="1Kgs.11.43"/> Rehoboam succeeded his father Solomon.<verse eID="1Kgs.11.43"/>
       </p>
      <chapter eID="1Kgs.11"/>
      <chapter osisID="1Kgs.12" sID="1Kgs.12"/>
       <p>
        <verse sID="1Kgs.12.1" osisID="1Kgs.12.1"/> He went to Shechem, for all Israel had gone to elect him king at
         Shechem. <verse eID="1Kgs.12.1"/>
       </p>
       <p>
        <verse sID="1Kgs.12.3" osisID="1Kgs.12.3"/> The people said to Rehoboam, <verse eID="1Kgs.12.3"/>
        <verse sID="1Kgs.12.4" osisID="1Kgs.12.4"/> <q>Your father's rule was heavy; lighten the heavy rule he imposed
           upon us and his crushing service, and we will serve you.</q> <verse eID="1Kgs.12.4"/>
        <verse sID="1Kgs.12.5" osisID="1Kgs.12.5"/> He said to them, <q>Go away for three days and then come back to
         me.</q> When the people went away, <verse eID="1Kgs.12.5"/>
        <verse sID="1Kgs.12.6" osisID="1Kgs.12.6"/> king Rehoboam consulted the old councillors who had served his
         father Solomon. He asked them what answer they would advise him to return to the people. <verse eID="1Kgs.12.6"/>
        <verse sID="1Kgs.12.7" osisID="1Kgs.12.7"/> They said, <q>If you will be a servant to this people here and now,
         serving them, if you speak favourable words to them, they will be your servants for all time.</q> <verse eID="1Kgs.12.7"/>
        <verse sID="1Kgs.12.8" osisID="1Kgs.12.8"/> But he set aside the advice of the old councillors and consulted the
         juniors of his own age in his retinue. <verse eID="1Kgs.12.8"/>
        <verse sID="1Kgs.12.9" osisID="1Kgs.12.9"/> He asked them what answer they would advise him to return to the
         demand of the people that Solomon's rule should be lightened. <verse eID="1Kgs.12.9"/>
        <verse sID="1Kgs.12.10" osisID="1Kgs.12.10"/> These juniors of his own age replied, <q>This people cried to you,
           <q>Your father's rule was heavy, make you it lighter for us?</q> Well, tell them this: <q>My little finger is
           thicker than my father's thighs, <verse eID="1Kgs.12.10"/>
        <verse sID="1Kgs.12.11" osisID="1Kgs.12.11"/> If my father's rule pressed hard on you, I will press harder still;
           my father lashed you with scourges, but I will lash you with scorpions.</q></q> <verse eID="1Kgs.12.11"/>
        <verse sID="1Kgs.12.12" osisID="1Kgs.12.12"/> On the third day all Israel came back, as king Rehoboam had told
           them. <verse eID="1Kgs.12.12"/>
        <verse sID="1Kgs.12.13" osisID="1Kgs.12.13"/> The king gave them a harsh answer. He set aside the advice given
           him by his senior councillors, <verse eID="1Kgs.12.13"/>
        <verse sID="1Kgs.12.14" osisID="1Kgs.12.14"/> and spoke to the people as the juniors had advised: <q>My father's
           rule pressed hard on you, but I will press harder still; my father lashed you with scourges, but I will lash
           you with scorpions.</q> <verse eID="1Kgs.12.14"/>
        <verse sID="1Kgs.12.15" osisID="1Kgs.12.15"/> So the king refused to heed the people. (This was a turn of things
           brought about by the Eternal, to carry out the word which he had sent by Ahijah of Shilo to Jeroboam the son of
           Nebat.) <verse eID="1Kgs.12.15"/>
        <verse sID="1Kgs.12.16" osisID="1Kgs.12.16"/> When all Israel saw that the king refused to heed them, the people
           retorted to the king,
           <lg>
            <l> What part have we in David? </l>
            <l> We’re done with Jesse’s son! </l>
            <l> Look to your own house, David, now! </l>
            <l> Home, Israel, to your homes! </l>
           </lg>
        <verse eID="1Kgs.12.16"/>
        <verse sID="1Kgs.12.18" osisID="1Kgs.12.18"/> When king Rehoboam sent them Adoniram, who was in charge of the
           labour-gangs, all Israel stoned him to death; whereupon king Rehoboam mounted his chariot in a hurry to
           escape to Jerusalem. <verse eID="1Kgs.12.18"/>
       </p>
       <p>
        <verse sID="1Kgs.12.19" osisID="1Kgs.12.19"/> So Israel rebelled against the dynasty of David, as it still
         does. <verse eID="1Kgs.12.19"/>
        <verse sID="1Kgs.12.20" osisID="1Kgs.12.20"/> When all Israel heard that Jeroboam had returned to the country,
           they summoned him to a popular assembly and elected him king over all Israel, only the clan of Judah being
           left loyal to the dynasty of David. <verse eID="1Kgs.12.20"/>
       </p>
       <p>
        <verse sID="1Kgs.12.21" osisID="1Kgs.12.21"/> On reaching Jerusalem, Rehoboam mustered all the men of Judah and
           of the clan of Benjamin, a hundred and eighty thousand picked men-at-arms, to attack Israel and recover the
           kingdom for Rehoboam the son of Solomon. <verse eID="1Kgs.12.21"/>
        <verse sID="1Kgs.12.22" osisID="1Kgs.12.22"/> But this message 22 came from the Eternal to She-
        <milestone type="pb" n="399"/>
           maiah, a man of God: <verse eID="1Kgs.12.22"/>
        <verse sID="1Kgs.12.23" osisID="1Kgs.12.23"/> <q>Give this message from the Eternal to Rehoboam the son of
           Solomon, king of Judah, and to all the men of Judah and Benjamin, and to the rest of the people. <verse eID="1Kgs.12.23"/>
        <verse sID="1Kgs.12.24" osisID="1Kgs.12.24"/> <q>You shall not march or fight against your fellows in Israel.
           Back home, every man of you! What has happened, I have caused to happen!</q></q> They listened to this
           message from the Eternal and returned home, as the Eternal had bidden them. <verse eID="1Kgs.12.24"/>
       </p>
       <p>
        <verse sID="1Kgs.12.25" osisID="1Kgs.12.25"/> Jeroboam fortified Shechem in the highlands of Ephraim and lived
           there. Later on, he left it and fortified Penuel. <verse eID="1Kgs.12.25"/>
        <verse sID="1Kgs.12.26" osisID="1Kgs.12.26"/> Then Jeroboam thought to himself, <q>The kingdom will go back to
           the dynasty of David; <verse eID="1Kgs.12.26"/>
        <verse sID="1Kgs.12.27" osisID="1Kgs.12.27"/> if these people go up to sacrifice at the temple of the Eternal in
           Jerusalem, then their heart will turn to their lord again, to Rehoboam the king of Judah, and they will kill
           me.</q> <verse eID="1Kgs.12.27"/>
        <verse sID="1Kgs.12.28" osisID="1Kgs.12.28"/> So he thought the matter over. He made two golden calves and said
           to the people, <q>You need not go up any longer to Jerusalem; here are your gods, O Israel, the gods that
           brought you from the land of Egypt!</q> <verse eID="1Kgs.12.28"/>
        <verse sID="1Kgs.12.29" osisID="1Kgs.12.29"/> One of them he placed at Bethel, and the other at Dan. <verse eID="1Kgs.12.29"/>
        <verse sID="1Kgs.12.30" osisID="1Kgs.12.30"/> This proved a sin for Israel, for the people went to worship the
           one at Bethel and the other at Dan. <verse eID="1Kgs.12.30"/>
        <verse sID="1Kgs.12.31" osisID="1Kgs.12.31"/> He also turned some shrines into temples, and made priests from the
           masses, who were not Levitical. <verse eID="1Kgs.12.31"/>
       </p>
       <p>
        <verse sID="1Kgs.12.32" osisID="1Kgs.12.32"/> Jeroboam fixed a festival on the fifteenth day of the eighth month,
           like the festival held in Judah, when he offered sacrifices on the altar to the calves and placed at Bethel the
           priests of the shrines that he had made.
        <verse eID="1Kgs.12.32"/>
        <verse sID="1Kgs.12.33" osisID="1Kgs.12.33"/> It was on the fifteenth day of the eighth month that he sacrificed on
         the altar he had made at Bethel, a month he had chosen out of his own head, fixing a festival for the Israelites
         and offering sacrifice with incense on the altar. <verse eID="1Kgs.12.33"/>
       </p>
      <chapter eID="1Kgs.12"/>
      <chapter osisID="1Kgs.13" sID="1Kgs.13"/>
       <p>
        <verse sID="1Kgs.13.1" osisID="1Kgs.13.1"/> Then came a man of God from Judah to Bethel, moved by the Eternal,
           just as Jeroboam was standing ready to burn incense at the altar. <verse eID="1Kgs.13.1"/>
        <verse sID="1Kgs.13.2" osisID="1Kgs.13.2"/> He cried out against the altar, moved by a word from the Eternal,
         <q>O altar, altar, this is the Eternal's message: <q>A child called Josiah shall be born to the dynasty of
         David, and he shall sacrifice on you the priests of the shrines who burn incense on you; on you shall bones
         of men be burned!</q></q> <verse eID="1Kgs.13.2"/>
        <verse sID="1Kgs.13.3" osisID="1Kgs.13.3"/> At the same time he announced this miracle predicted by the Eternal,
         <q>The altar shall be split up and the refuse on it flung aside!</q> <verse eID="1Kgs.13.3"/>
        <verse sID="1Kgs.13.4" osisID="1Kgs.13.4"/> When the king heard what the man of God had cried against the altar
         at Bethel, Jeroboam raised his hand from the altar and said, <q>Arrest him.</q> But the hand he had raised
         against him withered up, so that he could not draw it back. <verse eID="1Kgs.13.4"/>
        <verse sID="1Kgs.13.5" osisID="1Kgs.13.5"/> Also, the altar split and the refuse was flung aside, by the very
         miracle which the man of God had predicted as inspired by the Eternal. <verse eID="1Kgs.13.5"/>
        <verse sID="1Kgs.13.6" osisID="1Kgs.13.6"/> The king appealed to the man of God, <q>Do appease the Eternal your
         God and pray for me, that my hand may be restored to me again.</q> At the intercession of the man of God, the
         king's hand was restored to him, as it had been before. <verse eID="1Kgs.13.6"/>
        <verse sID="1Kgs.13.7" osisID="1Kgs.13.7"/> Then said the king to the man of God, <q>Come home with me and
           refresh yourself, and I will present you with a reward.</q> <verse eID="1Kgs.13.7"/>
        <verse sID="1Kgs.13.8" osisID="1Kgs.13.8"/> But the
           <milestone type="pb" n="400"/>
           man of God replied, <q>Though you were to present me with half of your house, I would not enter it with you,
           nor will I eat bread or drink water here; <verse eID="1Kgs.13.8"/>
        <verse sID="1Kgs.13.9" osisID="1Kgs.13.9"/> for the Eternal's orders to me were that I was neither to eat nor
           to drink, nor to go back by the road I came.</q> <verse eID="1Kgs.13.9"/>
        <verse sID="1Kgs.13.10" osisID="1Kgs.13.10"/> So he took another road and did not go back by the road he had
           come to Bethel. <verse eID="1Kgs.13.10"/>
       </p>
       <p>
        <verse sID="1Kgs.13.11" osisID="1Kgs.13.11"/> At Bethel there was a certain old prophet. His sons came and told
           him all that the man of God had done that day at Bethel, telling their father also what he
           had said to the king. <verse eID="1Kgs.13.11"/>
        <verse sID="1Kgs.13.12" osisID="1Kgs.13.12"/> <q>Which road did he take?</q> said their father. His sons pointed
           out the road taken by the man of God from Judah. <verse eID="1Kgs.13.12"/>
        <verse sID="1Kgs.13.13" osisID="1Kgs.13.13"/> Then he told his sons to saddle his ass. When they had saddled his
           ass, <verse eID="1Kgs.13.13"/>
        <verse sID="1Kgs.13.14" osisID="1Kgs.13.14"/> he rode away after the man of God, whom he found seated under an
           oak. He said, <q>Are you the man of God from Judah?</q> <q>Yes,</q> he replied. <verse eID="1Kgs.13.14"/>
        <verse sID="1Kgs.13.15" osisID="1Kgs.13.15"/> Then he said, <q>Come home with me and have some food.</q> <verse eID="1Kgs.13.15"/>
        <verse sID="1Kgs.13.16" osisID="1Kgs.13.16"/> He answered, <q>I cannot go back with you, nor can I eat or drink
           here, <verse eID="1Kgs.13.16"/>
        <verse sID="1Kgs.13.17" osisID="1Kgs.13.17"/> for I was told by the Eternal neither to eat nor to drink here,
           nor to return by the road I came.</q> <verse eID="1Kgs.13.17"/>
        <verse sID="1Kgs.13.18" osisID="1Kgs.13.18"/> The old prophet said, <q>I am a prophet too, and an angel said to
           me, by order of the Eternal, that I was to bring you back with me to my house, to eat and drink.</q> (This
           was a lie.) <verse eID="1Kgs.13.18"/>
        <verse sID="1Kgs.13.19" osisID="1Kgs.13.19"/> So he went back along with him and ate and drank in his house.
        <verse eID="1Kgs.13.19"/>
        <verse sID="1Kgs.13.20" osisID="1Kgs.13.20"/> But as they were sitting at table, a word came from the Eternal
           to the prophet who had brought the man back; <verse eID="1Kgs.13.20"/>
        <verse sID="1Kgs.13.21" osisID="1Kgs.13.21"/> he called out to the man of God from Judah, <q>This is the
           Eternal's word: since you have scouted the order of the Eternal and disobeyed what the Eternal your God
           commanded you, <verse eID="1Kgs.13.21"/>
        <verse sID="1Kgs.13.22" osisID="1Kgs.13.22"/> coming back and taking food where he forbade you to take food,
           your corpse shall never reach the tomb of your fathers.</q> <verse eID="1Kgs.13.22"/>
        <verse sID="1Kgs.13.23" osisID="1Kgs.13.23"/> After he had eaten and drunk, the old prophet saddled the ass for
           him; off he went, <verse eID="1Kgs.13.23"/>
        <verse sID="1Kgs.13.24" osisID="1Kgs.13.24"/> but a lion met him on the road and killed him; his corpse lay on
           the road, with the ass standing beside it, and also the lion. <verse eID="1Kgs.13.24"/>
        <verse sID="1Kgs.13.25" osisID="1Kgs.13.25"/> Some passers-by saw the corpse lying on the road, with the lion
           beside it, and they went and told the news to the people at the town-gate where the old prophet was sitting.
        <verse eID="1Kgs.13.25"/>
        <verse sID="1Kgs.13.26" osisID="1Kgs.13.26"/> When the prophet who had induced him to return heard the news, he
           said, <q>That is the man of God who scouted the orders of the Eternal; so the Eternal has given him over to a
           lion which has tom and killed him, just as the Eternal predicted to him.</q> <verse eID="1Kgs.13.26"/>
        <verse sID="1Kgs.13.27" osisID="1Kgs.13.27"/> <q>Saddle my ass,</q> he said to his sons. They saddled it, and he
           rode off to find the corpse lying on the road, <verse eID="1Kgs.13.27"/>
        <verse sID="1Kgs.13.28" osisID="1Kgs.13.28"/> with the ass and the lion standing beside it; the lion had neither
           eaten the corpse nor torn the ass. <verse eID="1Kgs.13.28"/>
        <verse sID="1Kgs.13.29" osisID="1Kgs.13.29"/> So the prophet lifted the corpse of the man of God on to his ass
        <verse eID="1Kgs.13.29"/>
        <verse sID="1Kgs.13.30" osisID="1Kgs.13.30"/> and brought it back to the town to be buried in his own tomb.
           <q>Alas! my brother!</q> men wailed. <verse eID="1Kgs.13.30"/>
        <verse sID="1Kgs.13.31" osisID="1Kgs.13.31"/> When the man had been buried, the old prophet said to his sons,
           <q>When I die, bury me in the tomb where the man of God is buried, lay my bones beside his. <verse eID="1Kgs.13.31"/>
        <verse sID="1Kgs.13.32" osisID="1Kgs.13.32"/> For his threat, inspired by the Eternal, against the altar at
           Bethel and against all the shrines on the heights throughout the towns of Samaria shall certainly be
           fulfilled.</q> <verse eID="1Kgs.13.32"/>
       </p>
       <milestone type="pb" n="401"/>
       <p>
        <verse sID="1Kgs.13.33" osisID="1Kgs.13.33"/> All this did not make Jeroboam give up his evil practices; he
         again chose priests for the shrines from the masses, he consecrated anyone he liked, and the man became a
         priest of the shrines. <verse eID="1Kgs.13.33"/>
        <verse sID="1Kgs.13.34" osisID="1Kgs.13.34"/> This proved a sin for the dynasty of Jeroboam, and led to its
         being swept off the earth and abolished. <verse eID="1Kgs.13.34"/>
       </p>
      <chapter eID="1Kgs.13"/>
   </div>