   <div type="book" osisID="1Kgs">
    <milestone type="pb" n="379"/>
    <chapter osisID="1Kgs.1" sID="1Kgs.1"/>
       <p>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.1" osisID="1Kgs.1.1"/> King David was an old man, well advanced in years, and although they covered him
           with the bed-clothes he could not keep himself warm. <verse eID="1Kgs.1.1"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.2" osisID="1Kgs.1.2"/> So his attendants said to the king, <q>Let some young girl be sought for my lord
           the king; let her wait upon the king and take care of him; let her lie in your bosom, that my lord the king may get
           warmth.</q> <verse eID="1Kgs.1.2"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.3" osisID="1Kgs.1.3"/> All over Israel they sought for a beautiful maiden, and found Abishag of Shunem,
           whom they brought to the king; <verse eID="1Kgs.1.3"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.4" osisID="1Kgs.1.4"/> she was most beautiful, and she took care of the king and attended to him. But
            the king had no intercourse with her. <verse eID="1Kgs.1.4"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.5" osisID="1Kgs.1.5"/> Now Adonijah the son of Haggith prided himself that he was to be king; he set up
            chariots and cavalry of his own, with fifty men to run in front. <verse eID="1Kgs.1.5"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.6" osisID="1Kgs.1.6"/> (Adonijah had been born next to Absalom. His father had never checked him all
            his life, by asking what he meant by his conduct. Also, he was a very handsome fellow.) <verse eID="1Kgs.1.6"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.7" osisID="1Kgs.1.7"/> He negotiated with Joab the son of Zeruiah and with Abiathar the priest, both of
            whom adhered to him and gave him their support, <verse eID="1Kgs.1.7"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.8" osisID="1Kgs.1.8"/> although Zadok the priest, Benaiah the son of Jehoiada, Nathan the prophet,
            Shimei, Rei, and David’s veterans, did not side with Adonijah. <verse eID="1Kgs.1.8"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.9" osisID="1Kgs.1.9"/> He then sacrificed sheep, oxen, and fatted cattle at the Serpent’s Stone beside
            Fuller’s Spring, inviting all his brothers, the king’s sons, and all the royal officials from Judah, <verse eID="1Kgs.1.9"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.10" osisID="1Kgs.1.10"/> but not Nathan the prophet, nor Benaiah, nor the veterans nor his brother
            Solomon. <verse eID="1Kgs.1.10"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.11" osisID="1Kgs.1.11"/> So Nathan went to Solomon's mother Bathsheba and said to her, <q>Have you not
            heard that Adonijah the son of Haggith has become king, without the knowledge of David our lord? <verse eID="1Kgs.1.11"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.12" osisID="1Kgs.1.12"/> Come now, let me advise you how to save your own life and the life of your son
            Solomon. <verse eID="1Kgs.1.12"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.13" osisID="1Kgs.1.13"/> Go at once to king David and ask him, <q>My lord, O king, did you not swear to
            your humble servant that Solomon my son should reign after you and sit upon your throne? Why, then, doesAdonijah
            reign?</q> <verse eID="1Kgs.1.13"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.14" osisID="1Kgs.1.14"/> While you are talking to the king, I will come in behind you and confirm what
            you say.</q> <verse eID="1Kgs.1.14"/>
       </p>
     <p>
         <verse sID="1Kgs.1.15" osisID="1Kgs.1.15"/> Bathsheba went to the king in his chamber. (The king was a very old man, and
          Abishag of Shunem attended to him.) <verse eID="1Kgs.1.15"/>
         <verse sID="1Kgs.1.16" osisID="1Kgs.1.16"/> Bathsheba bowed and did homage to the king, and the king asked what she desired. <verse eID="1Kgs.1.16"/>
         <verse sID="1Kgs.1.17" osisID="1Kgs.1.17"/> <q>My lord,</q> she replied, <q>you swore by the Eternal your God to your humble
          servant that her son Solomon was to reign after you and sit upon your throne. <verse eID="1Kgs.1.17"/>
         <verse sID="1Kgs.1.18" osisID="1Kgs.1.18"/> And here is Adonijah reigning, though you know nothing of it, my lord king! <verse eID="1Kgs.1.18"/>
         <verse sID="1Kgs.1.19" osisID="1Kgs.1.19"/> He has sacrificed oxen, fatted cattle, and sheep, plenty of them, and he has
          invited all the king’s sons, along with Abiathar the priest and Joab the commander-in-chief, but not your servant Solomon. <verse eID="1Kgs.1.19"/>
         <verse sID="1Kgs.1.20" osisID="1Kgs.1.20"/> Now, my lord king, all Israel looks to you to decide for them who is to succeed to
          the throne of my lord king. <verse eID="1Kgs.1.20"/>
         <verse sID="1Kgs.1.21" osisID="1Kgs.1.21"/> Otherwise the result will be that, when my lord king sleeps with his fathers, I
          and my son Solomon will have to suffer.</q> <verse eID="1Kgs.1.21"/>
         <verse sID="1Kgs.1.22" osisID="1Kgs.1.22"/> Just as she was
          <milestone type="pb" n="380"/>
          talking to the king, in came the prophet Nathan. <verse eID="1Kgs.1.22"/>
         <verse sID="1Kgs.1.23" osisID="1Kgs.1.23"/> The king was told that the prophet Nathan was present, and as he entered the
          king’s presence he bowed before the king, face to the ground. <verse eID="1Kgs.1.23"/>
         <verse sID="1Kgs.1.24" osisID="1Kgs.1.24"/> <q>My lord, O king,</q> said Nathan, <q>have you given orders that Adonijah is to
          reign after you and sit upon your throne? <verse eID="1Kgs.1.24"/>
         <verse sID="1Kgs.1.25" osisID="1Kgs.1.25"/> For he has gone down to-day and sacrificed oxen, sheep, and fatted cattle, plenty
          of them, inviting all the king’s sons, with Joab the commander-in-chief and Abiathar the priest. There they are, eating and
          drinking and shouting, <q>Long live king Adonijah!</q> <verse eID="1Kgs.1.25"/>
         <verse sID="1Kgs.1.26" osisID="1Kgs.1.26"/> But I, your humble servant, I and Zadok the priest and Benaiah the son of Jehoiada
          and your son Solomon have not been invited. <verse eID="1Kgs.1.26"/>
         <verse sID="1Kgs.1.27" osisID="1Kgs.1.27"/> If this is by order of my lord king, then you have not let your servants know who
          is to succeed to the throne of my lord king.</q> <verse eID="1Kgs.1.27"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.28" osisID="1Kgs.1.28"/> King David then ordered Bathsheba to be recalled. She came in and stood before
            the king, <verse eID="1Kgs.1.28"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.29" osisID="1Kgs.1.29"/> and the king swore, <q>By the life of the Eternal who has rescued my life from
            every strait, <verse eID="1Kgs.1.29"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.30" osisID="1Kgs.1.30"/> as I swore to you by the Eternal, the God of Israel, that your son Solomon
            should reign after me and succeed to my throne, so will I do this very day.</q> <verse eID="1Kgs.1.30"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.31" osisID="1Kgs.1.31"/> Bathsheba bowed her face to the ground and did homage to the king; <q>May my
            lord king David live for ever!</q> she cried. <verse eID="1Kgs.1.31"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.32" osisID="1Kgs.1.32"/> Then king David had Zadok the priest, Nathan the prophet, and Benaiah the son
            of Jehoiada summoned to his presence. When they appeared before the king, <verse eID="1Kgs.1.32"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.33" osisID="1Kgs.1.33"/> the king said to them, <q>Take your lord’s personal troops, mount my son
            Solomon upon my own mule, and convey him to Gihon; <verse eID="1Kgs.1.33"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.34" osisID="1Kgs.1.34"/> there let him be anointed king over Israel by Zadok the priest and Nathan the
            prophet; blow a trumpet blast and proclaim, <q>Long live king Solomon!</q> <verse eID="1Kgs.1.34"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.35" osisID="1Kgs.1.35"/> Then march up behind him, as he returns to seat himself on my throne, for he is
            to succeed me, and I appoint him supreme head of Israel and Judah.</q> <verse eID="1Kgs.1.35"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.36" osisID="1Kgs.1.36"/> <q>So be it,</q> said Benaiah the son of Jehoiada to the king. <q>May the
            Eternal confirm this order of my lord king! <verse eID="1Kgs.1.36"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.37" osisID="1Kgs.1.37"/> As the Eternal has been with my lord king, so may he be with Solomon, making his
            throne even greater than the throne of my lord king David!</q> <verse eID="1Kgs.1.37"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.38" osisID="1Kgs.1.38"/> Then Zadok the priest, Nathan the prophet, Benaiah the son of Jehoiada, and the
            foreign body-guard marched down; they mounted Solomon upon king David's mule and conveyed him to Gihon, <verse eID="1Kgs.1.38"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.39" osisID="1Kgs.1.39"/> where Zadok the priest took the vial of oil from the sacred Tent and anointed
            Solomon; a trumpet blast was blown, and the troops all shouted, <q>Long live king Solomon!</q> <verse eID="1Kgs.1.39"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.40" osisID="1Kgs.1.40"/> The troops all marched up behind him, dancing and cheering in their delight, so
            loudly that the earth seemed to be splitting with their noise. <verse eID="1Kgs.1.40"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.41" osisID="1Kgs.1.41"/> Adonijah and his guests all heard it, as they were finishing their feast.
            Hearing the sound of the trumpet, Joab said, <q>What does this uproar in city mean?</q> <verse eID="1Kgs.1.41"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.42" osisID="1Kgs.1.42"/> Just as he was speaking, in came Jonathan the son of Abiathar the priest.
            <q>Come along,</q> said Adonijah, <q>you are an honest fellow, you bring good news.</q> <verse eID="1Kgs.1.42"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.43" osisID="1Kgs.1.43"/> Jonathan answered Adonijah, “But our lord king David has made Solomon
           <milestone type="pb" n="381"/>
            king! <verse eID="1Kgs.1.43"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.44" osisID="1Kgs.1.44"/> The king sent Zadok the priest, Nathan the prophet, Benaiah the son of
            Jehoiada, and the foreign body-guard along with him; they mounted him on the king’s mule; <verse eID="1Kgs.1.44"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.45" osisID="1Kgs.1.45"/> Zadok the priest and Nathan the prophet anointed him king at Gihon; and they
            have come back rejoicing till the city resounds. That is the noise you heard! <verse eID="1Kgs.1.45"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.46" osisID="1Kgs.1.46"/> Solomon is seated on the throne of the realm, <verse eID="1Kgs.1.46"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.47" osisID="1Kgs.1.47"/> and the royal troops have gone to congratulate our lord king David, shouting,
            <q>God make Solomon's fame greater even than your fame, and his throne greater even than your throne! The king bowed on
                his couch. <verse eID="1Kgs.1.47"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.48" osisID="1Kgs.1.48"/> The king also said, <q>Blessed be the Eternal, the God of Israel, who has
            actually allowed me this day to see a son of mine sitting on my throne!</q></q> <verse eID="1Kgs.1.48"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.49" osisID="1Kgs.1.49"/> The guests of Adonijah were all terrified; every man of them got up and went
            home. <verse eID="1Kgs.1.49"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.50" osisID="1Kgs.1.50"/> Adonijah himself, in terror of Solomon, got up and ran to catch hold of the
            knobs of the altar. <verse eID="1Kgs.1.50"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.51" osisID="1Kgs.1.51"/> Solomon was told, <q>Adonijah is terrified of king Solomon; he has caught hold
            of the knobs of the altar, crying, <q>Let king Solomon first of all swear to me that he will not have his servant
            murdered!</q></q> <verse eID="1Kgs.1.51"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.52" osisID="1Kgs.1.52"/> Solomon said, <q>If he proves himself an honest man, not a hair of him shall
            fall to the ground; but if he is convicted of crime, then die he must.</q> <verse eID="1Kgs.1.52"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.53" osisID="1Kgs.1.53"/> Then king Solomon sent and had him taken from the altar; he came and did homage
            to king Solomon, and Solomon bade him go home. <verse eID="1Kgs.1.53"/>
       </p>
    <chapter eID="1Kgs.1"/>
   </div>