   <div type="book" osisID="1Kgs">
    <milestone type="pb" n="379"/>
    <chapter osisID="1Kgs.1" sID="1Kgs.1"/>
       <p>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.1" osisID="1Kgs.1.1"/> King David was an old man, well advanced in years, and although they covered him
           with the bed-clothes he could not keep himself warm. <verse eID="1Kgs.1.1"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.2" osisID="1Kgs.1.2"/> So his attendants said to the king, <q>Let some young girl be sought for my lord
           the king; let her wait upon the king and take care of him; let her lie in your bosom, that my lord the king may get
           warmth.</q> <verse eID="1Kgs.1.2"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.3" osisID="1Kgs.1.3"/> All over Israel they sought for a beautiful maiden, and found Abishag of Shunem,
           whom they brought to the king; <verse eID="1Kgs.1.3"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.4" osisID="1Kgs.1.4"/> she was most beautiful, and she took care of the king and attended to him. But
            the king had no intercourse with her. <verse eID="1Kgs.1.4"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.5" osisID="1Kgs.1.5"/> Now Adonijah the son of Haggith prided himself that he was to be king; he set up
            chariots and cavalry of his own, with fifty men to run in front. <verse eID="1Kgs.1.5"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.6" osisID="1Kgs.1.6"/> (Adonijah had been born next to Absalom. His father had never checked him all
            his life, by asking what he meant by his conduct. Also, he was a very handsome fellow.) <verse eID="1Kgs.1.6"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.7" osisID="1Kgs.1.7"/> He negotiated with Joab the son of Zeruiah and with Abiathar the priest, both of whom adhered to him and gave him their sup- 8 port, although Zadok the priest, Benaiah the son of Jehoiada, Nathan the prophet, Shimei, Rei, and David’s veterans, did 9 not side with Adonijah. He then sacrificed sheep, oxen, and fatted cattle at the Serpent’s Stone beside Fuller’s Spring, inviting all his brothers, the king’s sons, and all the royal io officials from Judah, but not Nathan the prophet, nor Bena­iah, nor the veterans, nor his brother Solomon.
           So	Nathan went to Solomon's u mother Bathsheba and said to her, “Have you not heard that Adonijah the son of Haggith has become king, without the knowl­edge of David our lord? Come 12 now, let me advise you how to save your own life and the life of your son Solomon. Go at once to 13 king David and ask him, ‘My lord,, 0 king, did you not swear to your humble servant that Solomon my son should reign after you and sit upon your throne? Why, then, does Adoni­jah reign?’ While you are talk- 14 ing to the king, I will come in behind you and confirm what you say.”
           <verse eID="1Kgs.1.7"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.8" osisID="1Kgs.1.8"/>
           <verse eID="1Kgs.1.8"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.9" osisID="1Kgs.1.9"/>
           <verse eID="1Kgs.1.9"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.10" osisID="1Kgs.1.10"/>
           <verse eID="1Kgs.1.10"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.11" osisID="1Kgs.1.11"/>
           <verse eID="1Kgs.1.11"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.12" osisID="1Kgs.1.12"/>
           <verse eID="1Kgs.1.12"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.13" osisID="1Kgs.1.13"/>
           <verse eID="1Kgs.1.13"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.14" osisID="1Kgs.1.14"/>
           <verse eID="1Kgs.1.14"/>
       </p>
     <p>
         <verse sID="1Kgs.1.15" osisID="1Kgs.1.15"/>
         Bathsheba went to the king in his chamber. (The king was a very old man, and Abishag of Shunem attended to him.) Bathsheba bowed and did 16 homage to the king, and the king asked what she desired. “My lord,” she replied, “you 17 swore by the Eternal your God to your humble servant that her son Solomon was to reign after you and sit upon your throne. And here is Adonijah reigning, 18 though you know nothing of it, my lord king! He has sacrificed 19 oxen, fatted cattle, and sheep, plenty of them, and he has in­vited all the king’s sons, along with Abiathar the priest and Joab the commander-in-chief, but not your servant Solomon. Now, my lord king, all Israel 20 looks to you to decide for them who is to succeed to the throne of my lord king. Otherwise the 21 result will be that, when my lord king sleeps with his fathers,
         I and my son Solomon will have to suffer.” Just as she was 22
         talking to the king, in came
         the prophet Nathan. The king was told that the prophet Na­than was present, and as he entered the king’s presence he bowed before the king, face to
         the ground. “My lord, 0 king,’’ said Nathan, “have you given orders that Adonijah is to reign after you and sit upon your
         throne? For he has gone down to-day and sacrificed oxen, sheep, and fatted cattle, plenty of them, inviting all the king’s sons, with Joab the commander- in-chief and Abiathar the priest. There they are, eating and drinking and shouting, ‘Long
         live king Adonijah!’ But I, your humble servant, I and Zadok the priest and Benaiah the son of Jehoiada and your son Solomon have not been
         invited. If this is by order of my lord king, then you have not let your servants know who is to succeed to the throne of my lord king.”
         <verse eID="1Kgs.1.15"/>
         <verse sID="1Kgs.1.16" osisID="1Kgs.1.16"/>
         <verse eID="1Kgs.1.16"/>
         <verse sID="1Kgs.1.17" osisID="1Kgs.1.17"/>
         <verse eID="1Kgs.1.17"/>
         <verse sID="1Kgs.1.18" osisID="1Kgs.1.18"/>
         <verse eID="1Kgs.1.18"/>
         <verse sID="1Kgs.1.19" osisID="1Kgs.1.19"/>
         <verse eID="1Kgs.1.19"/>
         <verse sID="1Kgs.1.20" osisID="1Kgs.1.20"/>
         <verse eID="1Kgs.1.20"/>
         <verse sID="1Kgs.1.21" osisID="1Kgs.1.21"/>
         <verse eID="1Kgs.1.21"/>
         <verse sID="1Kgs.1.22" osisID="1Kgs.1.22"/>
         <verse eID="1Kgs.1.22"/>
         <verse sID="1Kgs.1.23" osisID="1Kgs.1.23"/>
         <verse eID="1Kgs.1.23"/>
         <verse sID="1Kgs.1.24" osisID="1Kgs.1.24"/>
         <verse eID="1Kgs.1.24"/>
         <verse sID="1Kgs.1.25" osisID="1Kgs.1.25"/>
         <verse eID="1Kgs.1.25"/>
         <verse sID="1Kgs.1.26" osisID="1Kgs.1.26"/>
         <verse eID="1Kgs.1.26"/>
         <verse sID="1Kgs.1.27" osisID="1Kgs.1.27"/>
         <verse eID="1Kgs.1.27"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.28" osisID="1Kgs.1.28"/>
           King David then ordered Bathsheba to be recalled. She came in and stood before the
           king, and the king swore, “By the fife of the Eternal who has rescued my life from every
           strait, as I swore to you by the Eternal, the God of Israel, that your son Solomon should reign after me and suc­ceed to my throne, so will I do
           this very day.” Bathsheba bowed her face to the ground and did homage to the king; “May my lord king David live
           for ever!” she cried. Then king David had Zadok the priest, Nathan the prophet, and Bena­iah the son of Jehoiada sum­moned to his presence. When they appeared before the king,
           the king said to them, “Take your lord’s personal troops,
           mount my son Solomon upon my own mule, and convey him to Gihon; there let him be 34 anointed king over Israel by Zadok the priest and Nathan the prophet; blow a trumpet blast and proclaim, ‘Long live king Solomon!’ Then march 35 up behind him, as he returns to seat himself on my throne, for he is to succeed me, and I ap­point him supreme head of Israel and Judah.” “So be it,” 36 said Benaiah the son of Jehoiada to the king. “May the Eternal confirm this order of my lord king! As the Eternal has been 37 with my lord king, so may he be with Solomon, making his throne even greater than the throne of my lord king David!”
           Then Zadok the priest, 38 Nathan the prophet, Benaiah the son of Jehoiada, and the foreign body-guard marched down; they mounted Solomon upon king David’s mule and conveyed him to Gihon, where Zadok the 39 priest took the vial of oil from the sacred Tent and anointed Solomon; a trumpet blast was blown, and the troops all shouted, “Long live king Solo­mon!” The troops all marched 40 up behind him, dancing and cheering in their delight, so loudly that the earth seemed to be splitting with their noise.
           Adonijah and his guests all 41 heard it, as they were finishing their feast. Hearing the sound , of the trumpet, Joab said, ” “What does this uproar irr4.be city mean?” Just as.-he was 42 speaking, in came Jonathan the son of Abiathar the priest. “Come along,” said Adonijah, “you are an honest fellow, you bring good news.” Jonathan 43 answered Adonijah, “But our lord king David has made Solo-
           mon king! The king sent Zadok the priest, Nathan the prophet, Benaiah the son of Jehoiada, and the foreign body-guard along with him; they mounted
           him on the king’s mule; Zadok the priest and Nathan the prophet anointed him king at Gihon; and they have come back rejoicing till the city resounds. That is the noise you heard!
           Solomon is seated on the throne
           of the realm, and the royal troops have gone to congratu­late our lord king David, shout­ing, ‘God make Solomon’s fame greater even than your fame, and his throne greater even than your throne!’ The king
           bowed on his couch. The king also said, ‘Blessed be the Eter­nal, the God of Israel, who has actually allowed me this day to see a son of mine sitting on
           my throne!’ ” The guests of Adonijah were all terrified; every man of them got up and
           went home. Adonijah himself, in terror of Solomon, got up and ran to catch hold of the knobs
           of the altar. Solomon was told, “Adonijah is terrified of king Solomon; he has caught hold of the knobs of the altar, crying, ‘Let king Solomon first of all swear to me that he will not have his servant murdered!’ ”
           Solomon said, “If he proves himself an honest man, not a hair of him shall fall to the ground; but if he is convicted of
           crime, then die he must.” Then king Solomon sent and had him taken from the altar; he came and did homage to king Solo­mon, and Solomon bade him go home.
           <verse eID="1Kgs.1.28"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.29" osisID="1Kgs.1.29"/>
           <verse eID="1Kgs.1.29"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.30" osisID="1Kgs.1.30"/>
           <verse eID="1Kgs.1.30"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.31" osisID="1Kgs.1.31"/>
           <verse eID="1Kgs.1.31"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.32" osisID="1Kgs.1.32"/>
           <verse eID="1Kgs.1.32"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.33" osisID="1Kgs.1.33"/>
           <verse eID="1Kgs.1.33"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.34" osisID="1Kgs.1.34"/>
           <verse eID="1Kgs.1.34"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.35" osisID="1Kgs.1.35"/>
           <verse eID="1Kgs.1.35"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.36" osisID="1Kgs.1.36"/>
           <verse eID="1Kgs.1.36"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.37" osisID="1Kgs.1.37"/>
           <verse eID="1Kgs.1.37"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.38" osisID="1Kgs.1.38"/>
           <verse eID="1Kgs.1.38"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.39" osisID="1Kgs.1.39"/>
           <verse eID="1Kgs.1.39"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.40" osisID="1Kgs.1.40"/>
           <verse eID="1Kgs.1.40"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.41" osisID="1Kgs.1.41"/>
           <verse eID="1Kgs.1.41"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.42" osisID="1Kgs.1.42"/>
           <verse eID="1Kgs.1.42"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.43" osisID="1Kgs.1.43"/>
           <verse eID="1Kgs.1.43"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.44" osisID="1Kgs.1.44"/>
           <verse eID="1Kgs.1.44"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.45" osisID="1Kgs.1.45"/>
           <verse eID="1Kgs.1.45"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.46" osisID="1Kgs.1.46"/>
           <verse eID="1Kgs.1.46"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.47" osisID="1Kgs.1.47"/>
           <verse eID="1Kgs.1.47"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.48" osisID="1Kgs.1.48"/>
           <verse eID="1Kgs.1.48"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.49" osisID="1Kgs.1.49"/>
           <verse eID="1Kgs.1.49"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.50" osisID="1Kgs.1.50"/>
           <verse eID="1Kgs.1.50"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.51" osisID="1Kgs.1.51"/>
           <verse eID="1Kgs.1.51"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.52" osisID="1Kgs.1.52"/>
           <verse eID="1Kgs.1.52"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.53" osisID="1Kgs.1.53"/>
           <verse eID="1Kgs.1.53"/>
       </p>
    <chapter eID="1Kgs.1"/>
   </div>