   <div type="book" osisID="1Kgs">
    <milestone type="pb" n="379"/>
    <chapter osisID="1Kgs.1" sID="1Kgs.1"/>
       <p>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.1" osisID="1Kgs.1.1"/> King David was an old man, well advanced in years, and although they covered him
           with the bed-clothes he could not keep himself warm. <verse eID="1Kgs.1.1"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.2" osisID="1Kgs.1.2"/> So his attendants said to the king, <q>Let some young girl be sought for my lord
           the king; let her wait upon the king and take care of him; let her lie in your bosom, that my lord the king may get
           warmth.</q> <verse eID="1Kgs.1.2"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.3" osisID="1Kgs.1.3"/> All over Israel they sought for a beautiful maiden, and found Abishag of Shunem,
           whom they brought to the king; <verse eID="1Kgs.1.3"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.4" osisID="1Kgs.1.4"/> she was most beautiful, and she took care of the king and attended to him. But
            the king had no intercourse with her. <verse eID="1Kgs.1.4"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.5" osisID="1Kgs.1.5"/> Now Adonijah the son of Haggith prided himself that he was to be king; he set up
            chariots and cavalry of his own, with fifty men to run in front. <verse eID="1Kgs.1.5"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.6" osisID="1Kgs.1.6"/> (Adonijah had been born next to Absalom. His father had never checked him all
            his life, by asking what he meant by his conduct. Also, he was a very handsome fellow.) <verse eID="1Kgs.1.6"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.7" osisID="1Kgs.1.7"/> He negotiated with Joab the son of Zeruiah and with Abiathar the priest, both of
            whom adhered to him and gave him their support, <verse eID="1Kgs.1.7"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.8" osisID="1Kgs.1.8"/> although Zadok the priest, Benaiah the son of Jehoiada, Nathan the prophet,
            Shimei, Rei, and David’s veterans, did not side with Adonijah. <verse eID="1Kgs.1.8"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.9" osisID="1Kgs.1.9"/> He then sacrificed sheep, oxen, and fatted cattle at the Serpent’s Stone beside
            Fuller’s Spring, inviting all his brothers, the king’s sons, and all the royal officials from Judah, <verse eID="1Kgs.1.9"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.10" osisID="1Kgs.1.10"/> but not Nathan the prophet, nor Benaiah, nor the veterans nor his brother
            Solomon. <verse eID="1Kgs.1.10"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.11" osisID="1Kgs.1.11"/> So Nathan went to Solomon's mother Bathsheba and said to her, <q>Have you not
            heard that Adonijah the son of Haggith has become king, without the knowledge of David our lord? <verse eID="1Kgs.1.11"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.12" osisID="1Kgs.1.12"/> Come now, let me advise you how to save your own life and the life of your son
            Solomon. <verse eID="1Kgs.1.12"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.13" osisID="1Kgs.1.13"/> Go at once to king David and ask him, <q>My lord, O king, did you not swear to
            your humble servant that Solomon my son should reign after you and sit upon your throne? Why, then, doesAdonijah
            reign?</q> <verse eID="1Kgs.1.13"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.14" osisID="1Kgs.1.14"/> While you are talking to the king, I will come in behind you and confirm what
            you say.</q> <verse eID="1Kgs.1.14"/>
       </p>
     <p>
         <verse sID="1Kgs.1.15" osisID="1Kgs.1.15"/> Bathsheba went to the king in his chamber. (The king was a very old man, and
          Abishag of Shunem attended to him.) <verse eID="1Kgs.1.15"/>
         <verse sID="1Kgs.1.16" osisID="1Kgs.1.16"/> Bathsheba bowed and did homage to the king, and the king asked what she desired. <verse eID="1Kgs.1.16"/>
         <verse sID="1Kgs.1.17" osisID="1Kgs.1.17"/> <q>My lord,</q> she replied, <q>you swore by the Eternal your God to your humble
          servant that her son Solomon was to reign after you and sit upon your throne. <verse eID="1Kgs.1.17"/>
         <verse sID="1Kgs.1.18" osisID="1Kgs.1.18"/> And here is Adonijah reigning, though you know nothing of it, my lord king! <verse eID="1Kgs.1.18"/>
         <verse sID="1Kgs.1.19" osisID="1Kgs.1.19"/> He has sacrificed oxen, fatted cattle, and sheep, plenty of them, and he has
          invited all the king’s sons, along with Abiathar the priest and Joab the commander-in-chief, but not your servant Solomon. <verse eID="1Kgs.1.19"/>
         <verse sID="1Kgs.1.20" osisID="1Kgs.1.20"/> Now, my lord king, all Israel looks to you to decide for them who is to succeed to
          the throne of my lord king. <verse eID="1Kgs.1.20"/>
         <verse sID="1Kgs.1.21" osisID="1Kgs.1.21"/> Otherwise the result will be that, when my lord king sleeps with his fathers, I
          and my son Solomon will have to suffer.</q> <verse eID="1Kgs.1.21"/>
         <verse sID="1Kgs.1.22" osisID="1Kgs.1.22"/> Just as she was
          <milestone type="pb" n="380"/>
          talking to the king, in came the prophet Nathan. <verse eID="1Kgs.1.22"/>
         <verse sID="1Kgs.1.23" osisID="1Kgs.1.23"/> The king was told that the prophet Nathan was present, and as he entered the
          king’s presence he bowed before the king, face to the ground. <verse eID="1Kgs.1.23"/>
         <verse sID="1Kgs.1.24" osisID="1Kgs.1.24"/> <q>My lord, O king,</q> said Nathan, <q>have you given orders that Adonijah is to
          reign after you and sit upon your throne? <verse eID="1Kgs.1.24"/>
         <verse sID="1Kgs.1.25" osisID="1Kgs.1.25"/> For he has gone down to-day and sacrificed oxen, sheep, and fatted cattle, plenty
          of them, inviting all the king’s sons, with Joab the commander-in-chief and Abiathar the priest. There they are, eating and
          drinking and shouting, <q>Long live king Adonijah!</q> <verse eID="1Kgs.1.25"/>
         <verse sID="1Kgs.1.26" osisID="1Kgs.1.26"/> But I, your humble servant, I and Zadok the priest and Benaiah the son of Jehoiada
          and your son Solomon have not been invited. <verse eID="1Kgs.1.26"/>
         <verse sID="1Kgs.1.27" osisID="1Kgs.1.27"/> If this is by order of my lord king, then you have not let your servants know who
          is to succeed to the throne of my lord king.</q> <verse eID="1Kgs.1.27"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.28" osisID="1Kgs.1.28"/> King David then ordered Bathsheba to be recalled. She came in and stood before
            the king, <verse eID="1Kgs.1.28"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.29" osisID="1Kgs.1.29"/> and the king swore, <q>By the life of the Eternal who has rescued my life from
            every strait, <verse eID="1Kgs.1.29"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.30" osisID="1Kgs.1.30"/> as I swore to you by the Eternal, the God of Israel, that your son Solomon
            should reign after me and succeed to my throne, so will I do this very day.</q> <verse eID="1Kgs.1.30"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.31" osisID="1Kgs.1.31"/> Bathsheba bowed her face to the ground and did homage to the king; <q>May my
            lord king David live for ever!</q> she cried. <verse eID="1Kgs.1.31"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.32" osisID="1Kgs.1.32"/> Then king David had Zadok the priest, Nathan the prophet, and Benaiah the son
            of Jehoiada summoned to his presence. When they appeared before the king, <verse eID="1Kgs.1.32"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.33" osisID="1Kgs.1.33"/> the king said to them, <q>Take your lord’s personal troops, mount my son
            Solomon upon my own mule, and convey him to Gihon; <verse eID="1Kgs.1.33"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.34" osisID="1Kgs.1.34"/> there let him be anointed king over Israel by Zadok the priest and Nathan the
            prophet; blow a trumpet blast and proclaim, <q>Long live king Solomon!</q> <verse eID="1Kgs.1.34"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.35" osisID="1Kgs.1.35"/> Then march up behind him, as he returns to seat himself on my throne, for he is
            to succeed me, and I appoint him supreme head of Israel and Judah.</q> <verse eID="1Kgs.1.35"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.36" osisID="1Kgs.1.36"/> <q>So be it,</q> said Benaiah the son of Jehoiada to the king. <q>May the
            Eternal confirm this order of my lord king! <verse eID="1Kgs.1.36"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.37" osisID="1Kgs.1.37"/> As the Eternal has been with my lord king, so may he be with Solomon, making his
            throne even greater than the throne of my lord king David!</q> <verse eID="1Kgs.1.37"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.38" osisID="1Kgs.1.38"/> Then Zadok the priest, Nathan the prophet, Benaiah the son of Jehoiada, and the
            foreign body-guard marched down; they mounted Solomon upon king David's mule and conveyed him to Gihon, <verse eID="1Kgs.1.38"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.39" osisID="1Kgs.1.39"/> where Zadok the priest took the vial of oil from the sacred Tent and anointed
            Solomon; a trumpet blast was blown, and the troops all shouted, <q>Long live king Solomon!</q> <verse eID="1Kgs.1.39"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.40" osisID="1Kgs.1.40"/> The troops all marched up behind him, dancing and cheering in their delight, so
            loudly that the earth seemed to be splitting with their noise. <verse eID="1Kgs.1.40"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.41" osisID="1Kgs.1.41"/> Adonijah and his guests all heard it, as they were finishing their feast.
            Hearing the sound of the trumpet, Joab said, <q>What does this uproar in city mean?</q> <verse eID="1Kgs.1.41"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.42" osisID="1Kgs.1.42"/> Just as he was speaking, in came Jonathan the son of Abiathar the priest.
            <q>Come along,</q> said Adonijah, <q>you are an honest fellow, you bring good news.</q> <verse eID="1Kgs.1.42"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.43" osisID="1Kgs.1.43"/> Jonathan answered Adonijah, “But our lord king David has made Solomon
           <milestone type="pb" n="381"/>
            king! <verse eID="1Kgs.1.43"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.44" osisID="1Kgs.1.44"/> The king sent Zadok the priest, Nathan the prophet, Benaiah the son of
            Jehoiada, and the foreign body-guard along with him; they mounted him on the king’s mule; <verse eID="1Kgs.1.44"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.45" osisID="1Kgs.1.45"/> Zadok the priest and Nathan the prophet anointed him king at Gihon; and they
            have come back rejoicing till the city resounds. That is the noise you heard! <verse eID="1Kgs.1.45"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.46" osisID="1Kgs.1.46"/> Solomon is seated on the throne of the realm, <verse eID="1Kgs.1.46"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.47" osisID="1Kgs.1.47"/> and the royal troops have gone to congratulate our lord king David, shouting,
            <q>God make Solomon's fame greater even than your fame, and his throne greater even than your throne! The king bowed on
                his couch. <verse eID="1Kgs.1.47"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.48" osisID="1Kgs.1.48"/> The king also said, <q>Blessed be the Eternal, the God of Israel, who has
            actually allowed me this day to see a son of mine sitting on my throne!</q></q> <verse eID="1Kgs.1.48"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.49" osisID="1Kgs.1.49"/> The guests of Adonijah were all terrified; every man of them got up and went
            home. <verse eID="1Kgs.1.49"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.50" osisID="1Kgs.1.50"/> Adonijah himself, in terror of Solomon, got up and ran to catch hold of the
            knobs of the altar. <verse eID="1Kgs.1.50"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.51" osisID="1Kgs.1.51"/> Solomon was told, <q>Adonijah is terrified of king Solomon; he has caught hold
            of the knobs of the altar, crying, <q>Let king Solomon first of all swear to me that he will not have his servant
            murdered!</q></q> <verse eID="1Kgs.1.51"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.52" osisID="1Kgs.1.52"/> Solomon said, <q>If he proves himself an honest man, not a hair of him shall
            fall to the ground; but if he is convicted of crime, then die he must.</q> <verse eID="1Kgs.1.52"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.1.53" osisID="1Kgs.1.53"/> Then king Solomon sent and had him taken from the altar; he came and did homage
            to king Solomon, and Solomon bade him go home. <verse eID="1Kgs.1.53"/>
       </p>
      <chapter eID="1Kgs.1"/>
      <chapter osisID="1Kgs.2" sID="1Kgs.2"/>
       <p>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.2.1" osisID="1Kgs.2.1"/>When David's time to die was near, he gave this charge to his son Solomon. <verse eID="1Kgs.2.1"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.2.2" osisID="1Kgs.2.2"/> <q>I am going the way of all the earth; be strong then, show yourself a man, <verse eID="1Kgs.2.2"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.2.3" osisID="1Kgs.2.3"/> and do your duty to the Eternal your God, by living his fife, by following his
            rules and orders and regulations and directions, as written in the law of Moses, so that, whatever you do and wherever you
            turn, you may have success, <verse eID="1Kgs.2.3"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.2.4" osisID="1Kgs.2.4"/> that the Eternal may fulfil his promise to me that if my children are careful
            how they live, living loyally under his eye with all their mind and all their soul, I shall never lack a man upon the
            throne of Israel. <verse eID="1Kgs.2.4"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.2.5" osisID="1Kgs.2.5"/> Again, you know what Joab the son of Zeruiah did to me, how he treated the two
            commanders of Israel, Abner the son of Ner and Amasa the son of Jether, how he murdered them, taking vengeance during peace
            for blood shed during war, staining the very girdle round his waist and the shoes on his feet with innocent blood. <verse eID="1Kgs.2.5"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.2.6" osisID="1Kgs.2.6"/> Choose your own time, but never let his grey head go to the grave in peace. <verse eID="1Kgs.2.6"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.2.7" osisID="1Kgs.2.7"/> Be kind to the family of Barzillai the Gileadite, and let them be among the guests
            at your table, for they fed me when I fled from your brother Absalom. <verse eID="1Kgs.2.7"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.2.8" osisID="1Kgs.2.8"/> You have also with you Shimei the Benjamite, the son of Gera, from Bahurim.
            Bitterly did he curse me on the day when I made my way to Mahanaim; but when he came to meet me at the Jordan I swore to
            him by the Eternal that I would not put him to death. <verse eID="1Kgs.2.8"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.2.9" osisID="1Kgs.2.9"/> Do not you let him go unpunished; you have your wits about you, you know what to
            do with him, to bring down his grey head to death with blood.</q><verse eID="1Kgs.2.9"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.2.10" osisID="1Kgs.2.10"/> Then David slept with his fathers and was buried in
            <milestone type="pb" n="382"/> David’s burg. <verse eID="1Kgs.2.10"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.2.11" osisID="1Kgs.2.11"/> For forty years David had reigned over Israel, seven years at Hebron and
            thirty-three years in Jerusalem. <verse eID="1Kgs.2.11"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.2.12" osisID="1Kgs.2.12"/> Solomon sat on the throne of his father David, and his kingdom was firmly
            established. <verse eID="1Kgs.2.12"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.2.13" osisID="1Kgs.2.13"/> Adonijah the son of Haggith then went to Bathsheba the mother of Solomon and
            bowed before her. <q>Do you come as a friend?</q> she asked. <q>Yes,</q> he answered, <verse eID="1Kgs.2.13"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.2.14" osisID="1Kgs.2.14"/> adding, <q>I have something to say to you.</q> <q>Say it,</q>  she said; <verse eID="1Kgs.2.14"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.2.15" osisID="1Kgs.2.15"/> so he went on, <q>You know the kingdom was mine, all Israel fully expected me to be
            king; however, the kingdom has passed from me to my brother, for it was his by the will of the Eternal. <verse eID="1Kgs.2.15"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.2.16" osisID="1Kgs.2.16"/>Now I am asking you one favour: do not refuse me.</q> <q>Go on,</q> she said. <verse eID="1Kgs.2.16"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.2.17" osisID="1Kgs.2.17"/> So he continued, <q>Pray ask king Solomon (he will not refuse you) to let me
            have Abishag of Shunem as my wife.</q> <verse eID="1Kgs.2.17"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.2.18" osisID="1Kgs.2.18"/><q>Very well,</q> said Bathsheba, <q>I will speak for you to the king.</q> <verse eID="1Kgs.2.18"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.2.19" osisID="1Kgs.2.19"/> So Bathsheba went to speak to king Solomon on behalf of Adonijah. The king rose
            to meet her and kissed her; then, seating himself on his throne, he had a chair placed for the king’s mother, who seated
            herself at his right hand. <verse eID="1Kgs.2.19"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.2.20" osisID="1Kgs.2.20"/> <q>I have a small favour to ask from you,</q> she said; <q>do not refuse me.</q>
            <q>Ask it, my mother,</q> said the king, <q>I will not refuse you.</q> <verse eID="1Kgs.2.20"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.2.21" osisID="1Kgs.2.21"/> So she said, <q>Let Abishag of Shunem be given to your brother Adonijah in
            marriage.</q> <verse eID="1Kgs.2.21"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.2.22" osisID="1Kgs.2.22"/> <q>Abishag of Shunem for Adonijah?</q> answered king Solomon. <q>Why do you
            ask that? Ask the kingdom for him as well!--he is my older brother and he has Abiathar the priest and Joab the son of
            Zerulah on his side!</q> <verse eID="1Kgs.2.22"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.2.23" osisID="1Kgs.2.23"/> And king Solomon swore by the Eternal, <q>God kill me and worse, if this plea of
            Adonijah does not cost him his life! <verse eID="1Kgs.2.23"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.2.24" osisID="1Kgs.2.24"/> By the life of the Eternal who has established me and set me on the throne of
            my father David and given me a family as he promised, Adonijah shall die this very day!</q> <verse eID="1Kgs.2.24"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.2.25" osisID="1Kgs.2.25"/> So king Solomon sent and had Adonijah killed by Benaiah the son of Jehoiada,
            who struck him down. <verse eID="1Kgs.2.25"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.2.26" osisID="1Kgs.2.26"/> The king said to Abiathar the priest, <q>Away with you to your estate at
            Anathoth! You deserve to die this day, but I will not put you to death, since you carried the ark of the Eternal before
            my father David and shared all the hard­ships of my father.</q> <verse eID="1Kgs.2.26"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.2.27" osisID="1Kgs.2.27"/> (This expulsion of Abiathar from the priesthood of the Eternal by Solomon was
            in fulfilment of what the Eternal had predicted about the household of Eli at Shilo.) <verse eID="1Kgs.2.27"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.2.28" osisID="1Kgs.2.28"/> When	the	news of	this reached Joab,	who had	supported Adonijah although he
            had not supported Absalom, Joab fled to the Eternal's Tent and caught hold of the knobs of the altar. <verse eID="1Kgs.2.28"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.2.29" osisID="1Kgs.2.29"/> When Solomon was told that Joab had fled to the Eternal's Tent and was at the
            altar there, Solomon sent to ask Joab why he had fled to the altar. <q>Because I was afraid of you,</q> Joab replied,
            <q>I fled to the Eternal.</q> Then Solomon sent Benaiah the son of Jehoiada to strike him down. <verse eID="1Kgs.2.29"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.2.30" osisID="1Kgs.2.30"/> Benaiah went to the Eternal's Tent and gave him the king's order to come away.
            <q>No,</q> said Joab, <q>I will die here.</q> When Benaiah took back his message to the king, telling him what Joab had
            <milestone type="pb" n="383"/>
            said in reply to him, <verse eID="1Kgs.2.30"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.2.31" osisID="1Kgs.2.31"/> the king said, <q>Take him at his word; strike him down and have him buried--so
            freeing me and my father's house from the guilt of the blood shed wantonly by Joab. <verse eID="1Kgs.2.31"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.2.32" osisID="1Kgs.2.32"/> The Eternal will make his murders fall on his own head, for he struck down two
            men higher and better than himself, Abner the son of Ner, commander of Israel, and Amasa the son of Jether, commander of
            Judah, murdering them without the knowledge of my father David. <verse eID="1Kgs.2.32"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.2.33" osisID="1Kgs.2.33"/> So shall the guilt of their murder come back upon the head of Joab and his
            descendants to all time. To David and his descendants, to his dynasty and throne, may there be peace from the Eternal for
            all time!</q> <verse eID="1Kgs.2.33"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.2.34" osisID="1Kgs.2.34"/> Then Benaiah the son of Jehoiada went and struck him down, killing him; he was
            buried at his own house in the open country of Judah, <verse eID="1Kgs.2.34"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.2.35" osisID="1Kgs.2.35"/> and the king put Benaiah the son of Jehoiada into his post as
            commander-in-chief, putting Zadok the priest in place of Abiathar. <verse eID="1Kgs.2.35"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.2.36" osisID="1Kgs.2.36"/> Then the king sent and summoned Shimei. <q>Build yourself a house in
            Jerusalem,</q> he said, <q>and live there; never leave it in any direction. <verse eID="1Kgs.2.36"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.2.37" osisID="1Kgs.2.37"/> The day you leave it and cross the Kidron-ravine, you die--be sure of that!
            Your blood be on your own head!</q> <verse eID="1Kgs.2.37"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.2.38" osisID="1Kgs.2.38"/> <q>Very good,</q> said Shimei to the king, <q>as my lord the king orders, so
            will your servant do.</q> For a long time Shimei did remain inside Jerusalem. <verse eID="1Kgs.2.38"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.2.39" osisID="1Kgs.2.39"/> But three years later two slaves of Shimei ran away to Achish son of Maakah,
            king of Gath, and when Shimei was told that his slaves were at Gath <verse eID="1Kgs.2.39"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.2.40" osisID="1Kgs.2.40"/> he saddled his ass and rode to Achish at Gath in search of his slaves. From
            Gath Shimei brought his slaves back. <verse eID="1Kgs.2.40"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.2.41" osisID="1Kgs.2.41"/> But when Solomon was informed that Shimei had returned to Jerusalem from a
            visit to Gath, <verse eID="1Kgs.2.41"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.2.42" osisID="1Kgs.2.42"/> the king sent for Shimei and asked him, <q>Did I not make you swear by the
            Eternal, did I not warn you, to be sure of this, that on the day you left and went anywhere outside you were to die?
            Did you not say to me, <q>Very good, I obey?</q> <verse eID="1Kgs.2.42"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.2.43" osisID="1Kgs.2.43"/> Why have you not kept your oath to the Eternal and the orders I enjoined upon
            you?</q> <verse eID="1Kgs.2.43"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.2.44" osisID="1Kgs.2.44"/> The king added, <q>Well does your own heart know all the evil you did to my
            father David. The Eternal returns that evil on your own head! <verse eID="1Kgs.2.44"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.2.45" osisID="1Kgs.2.45"/> But king Solomon shall be blessed and David's throne established before the
            Eternal for all time.</q> <verse eID="1Kgs.2.45"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.2.46" osisID="1Kgs.2.46"/> Then, by order of the king, Benaiah went and struck down Shimei dead. <verse eID="1Kgs.2.46"/>
       </p>
       <chapter eID="1Kgs.2"/>
       <chapter osisID="1Kgs.4" sID="1Kgs.4"/>
       <p>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.4.21" osisID="1Kgs.4.21"/> Now Solomon had complete control of the kingdom. <verse eID="1Kgs.4.21"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.4.20" osisID="1Kgs.4.20"/> Judah and Israel were as numerous as the sand on the seashore; they ate and
            drank and enjoyed themselves. <verse eID="1Kgs.4.20"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.4.25" osisID="1Kgs.4.25"/> Judah and Israel were safe, every man living under his own vine and under his
            own fig-tree, from Dan to Beersheba, all the days of Solomon; <verse eID="1Kgs.4.25"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.4.24" osisID="1Kgs.4.24"/> for he ruled all west of the Euphrates, from Thapsakus to Gaza, over all the
            kings west of the Euphrates, and he enjoyed peace on every side. <verse eID="1Kgs.4.24"/>
       </p>
      <chapter eID="1Kgs.4"/>
      <chapter osisID="1Kgs.3" sID="1Kgs.3"/>
       <p>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.3.3" osisID="1Kgs.3.3"/>Now Solomon loved the o Eternal, living by the rules laid down by his father David;
            only, he sacrificed and burned incense at the shrines. <verse eID="1Kgs.3.3"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.3.2" osisID="1Kgs.3.2"/> [[The people also sacrificed at the shrines, because no temple had yet been built
            in honour of the Eternal.]] <verse eID="1Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.3.4" osisID="1Kgs.3.4"/> One day the king went to sacrifice
            <milestone type="pb" n="384"/> at Gibeon, as that was the chief shrine; a thousand victims Solomon used to sacrifice on the
           altar there. <verse eID="1Kgs.3.4"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.3.5" osisID="1Kgs.3.5"/> The Eternal appeared to Solomon in a dream by night at Gibeon; God said to him,
            <q>Ask what I am to give you.</q> <verse eID="1Kgs.3.5"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.3.6" osisID="1Kgs.3.6"/> Solomon answered, <q>Thou hast proved thyself most generous to thy servant David
            my father, as he lived before thee a loyal and honest life with upright mind, and thou hast reserved this great boon for
            him, a son to sit upon his throne this day. <verse eID="1Kgs.3.6"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.3.7" osisID="1Kgs.3.7"/> And now, O Eternal my God, thou hast made thy servant king instead of David my
            father; and I am a mere child, I know not how to go about my business. <verse eID="1Kgs.3.7"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.3.8" osisID="1Kgs.3.8"/> Thy servant is surrounded by thine own chosen people, a vast host, too great to be
            numbered or counted. <verse eID="1Kgs.3.8"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.3.9" osisID="1Kgs.3.9"/> So grant thy servant a thoughtful mind for governing thy people, that I may
            distinguish right and wrong. For who can bear the weight of this government?</q> <verse eID="1Kgs.3.9"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.3.10" osisID="1Kgs.3.10"/> It pleased the Eternal that Solomon had asked this,<verse eID="1Kgs.3.10"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.3.11" osisID="1Kgs.3.11"/> God said to him, <q>Because you have asked this, because you have asked neither
            long fife for yourself nor wealth for yourself nor death to your enemies, but insight and justice, <verse eID="1Kgs.3.11"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.3.12" osisID="1Kgs.3.12"/> I now do as you have asked; I hereby give you a wise, thoughtful mind, so that
            never afterwards shall your equal rise, as never has your equal lived. <verse eID="1Kgs.3.12"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.3.13" osisID="1Kgs.3.13"/> Also, I give you what you did not ask, both wealth and honour, so that no king
            shall ever be your equal. <verse eID="1Kgs.3.13"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.3.14" osisID="1Kgs.3.14"/> And if you will live my life, keeping my rules and orders, as did your father
            David, I will give you a long life.</q> <verse eID="1Kgs.3.14"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.3.15" osisID="1Kgs.3.15"/> Then Solomon woke; it was a dream! He went to Jerusalem, where he stood in
            front of the ark of the Eternal's compact, sacrificing burnt-offerings and recompense-offerings, and feasting all his
            officers. <verse eID="1Kgs.3.15"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.3.16" osisID="1Kgs.3.16"/> Two harlots then came to the king and stood before him. <verse eID="1Kgs.3.16"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.3.17" osisID="1Kgs.3.17"/> One woman said, <q>O my lord, this woman and I live in the same house. I bore a
            child in the house beside her, <verse eID="1Kgs.3.17"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.3.18" osisID="1Kgs.3.18"/> and three days later she bore a child also; we were together, there was no one
            else in the house, only we two by ourselves. <verse eID="1Kgs.3.18"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.3.19" osisID="1Kgs.3.19"/> During the night her child died, for she overlaid it. <verse eID="1Kgs.3.19"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.3.20" osisID="1Kgs.3.20"/> So she got up at midnight and took away my child, while your humble servant was
            asleep; she laid the child in her bosom and put her dead child in my bosom. <verse eID="1Kgs.3.20"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.3.21" osisID="1Kgs.3.21"/> When I rose in the morning to suckle my child, there it lay dead! But as I
            looked at it carefully in the morning-light, it was not my son whom I had borne.</q> <verse eID="1Kgs.3.21"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.3.22" osisID="1Kgs.3.22"/> The other woman said, <q>No, the living child belongs to me, the dead is
            yours!</q> The first woman retorted, <q>No, the dead child belongs to you, the living child is mine!</q> So they wrangled
            before the king. <verse eID="1Kgs.3.22"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.3.23" osisID="1Kgs.3.23"/> The king mused: <q>One says, <q>This living son is mine, the dead belongs to
            you</q>; the other says, <q>No, the dead son is yours, mine is the living one.</q></q> <verse eID="1Kgs.3.23"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.3.24" osisID="1Kgs.3.24"/> Then said the king, <q>Fetch me a sword.</q> A sword was brought in. <verse eID="1Kgs.3.24"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.3.25" osisID="1Kgs.3.25"/> The king then gave his orders, <q>Cut the living child in two, and give half
            to the one, half to the other.</q> <verse eID="1Kgs.3.25"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.3.26" osisID="1Kgs.3.26"/> At this the mother of the living child, whose heart yearned for her boy, cried
            to the king, <q>O my lord, give her the living child, never lull it!</q> The other woman said, <q>No, divide
            <milestone type="pb" n="385"/>
            it; neither of us shall have it.</q>
           <verse eID="1Kgs.3.26"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.3.27" osisID="1Kgs.3.27"/> The king replied, <q>Give yonder woman the living child, instead of killing
            it; she is its mother!</q> <verse eID="1Kgs.3.27"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.3.28" osisID="1Kgs.3.28"/> All Israel heard of this decision of the king, and they stood in awe of the
           king, seeing that he had God's own wisdom for doing justice. <verse eID="1Kgs.3.28"/>
       </p>
       <chapter eID="1Kgs.3"/>
       <chapter osisID="1Kgs.4" sID="1Kgs.4"/>
       <p>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.4.1" osisID="1Kgs.4.1"/> King Solomon reigned over all Israel. <verse eID="1Kgs.4.1"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.4.2" osisID="1Kgs.4.2"/> His ministers of state were: Azariah the son of Zadok as priest, <verse eID="1Kgs.4.2"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.4.3" osisID="1Kgs.4.3"/> Elihoreph and Ahijah the sons of Shisha as secretaries, Jehoshaphat
            the son of Ahilud as chancellor, <verse eID="1Kgs.4.3"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.4.4" osisID="1Kgs.4.4"/> and Benaiah the son of Jehoiada as commander-in-chief [[Zadok and
            Abiathar were priests.]] <verse eID="1Kgs.4.4"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.4.5" osisID="1Kgs.4.5"/> Azariah the son of Nathan was head of the prefects, Zabud the son
            of Nathan was the king’s adviser, <verse eID="1Kgs.4.5"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.4.6" osisID="1Kgs.4.6"/> Ahishar was prefect of the palace, and Adoniram the son of Abda was
            in charge of the labour levy. <verse eID="1Kgs.4.6"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.4.7" osisID="1Kgs.4.7"/> Solomon had twelve prefects over all Israel, who provided the food
            for the king and his household, each man having to supply food for one month a year; <verse eID="1Kgs.4.7"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.4.8" osisID="1Kgs.4.8"/> their names were Ben-hur (over the highlands of Ephraim),<verse eID="1Kgs.4.8"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.4.9" osisID="1Kgs.4.9"/> Bendeker (over Makaz, Shaalbim, Beth-shemesh, and Elonbeth-hanan), <verse eID="1Kgs.4.9"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.4.10" osisID="1Kgs.4.10"/> Ben-hesed (over Arubboth, besides Soko and all the land of Hepher), <verse eID="1Kgs.4.10"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.4.11" osisID="1Kgs.4.11"/> Ben-abinadab (over all the uplands of Dor) who was married to
            Solomon's daughter Taphath, <verse eID="1Kgs.4.11"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.4.12" osisID="1Kgs.4.12"/>Baana the son of Ahilud (over Taanak, Megiddo, and the whole of
            Beth-shean next Zarethan below Jezreel, from Beth-shean to Abel-meholah as far as the other side of Jokmeam), <verse eID="1Kgs.4.12"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.4.13" osisID="1Kgs.4.13"/> Ben-geber (over Ramoth-gilead, with the tent-villages in Gilead
            belonging to Jair the son of Manasseh, and the region of Argob in Bashan, containing sixty large towns
            walled and bolted with bronze), <verse eID="1Kgs.4.13"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.4.14" osisID="1Kgs.4.14"/> Ahinadab the son of Iddo (over Mahanaim), <verse eID="1Kgs.4.14"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.4.15" osisID="1Kgs.4.15"/> Ahimaaz (over Naphtali) who was married to Solomon's daughter
            Basemath, <verse eID="1Kgs.4.15"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.4.16" osisID="1Kgs.4.16"/> Baana the son of Hushai (over Asher and Aloth), <verse eID="1Kgs.4.16"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.4.17" osisID="1Kgs.4.17"/> Jehoshaphat the son of Paruali (over Issachar), <verse eID="1Kgs.4.17"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.4.18" osisID="1Kgs.4.18"/> Shimei the son of Ela (over Benjamin), <verse eID="1Kgs.4.18"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.4.19" osisID="1Kgs.4.19"/> and Geber the son of Uri (over the land of Gad, the country of
            Sihon king of the Amorites and of Og king of Bashan). All these prefects were Under a single chief. <verse eID="1Kgs.4.19"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.4.27" osisID="1Kgs.4.27"/> They provided the food for king Solomon and for all guests
            admitted to king Solomon's table, each taking a month. They saw that nothing was wanting. <verse eID="1Kgs.4.27"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.4.28" osisID="1Kgs.4.28"/> Also they each brought, as they were bound, barley and straw for
            the horses and coursers, wherever the cavalry were stationed. <verse eID="1Kgs.4.28"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.4.22" osisID="1Kgs.4.22"/> Solomon's provision for a single day was three hundred and thirty
            bushels of fine flour, six hundred and sixty bushels of meal, <verse eID="1Kgs.4.22"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.4.23" osisID="1Kgs.4.23"/> ten fatted oxen, twenty meadow-fed oxen, and a hundred sheep,
            besides harts, gazelles, roebucks, and guinea-fowl. <verse eID="1Kgs.4.23"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.4.29" osisID="1Kgs.4.29"/> Now God gave Solomon wisdom and ample insight and breadth of mind
            like the broad sea-sands; <verse eID="1Kgs.4.29"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.4.30" osisID="1Kgs.4.30"/> Solomon's wisdom surpassed the wisdom of all Arabs in the east
            and all Egypt, <verse eID="1Kgs.4.30"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.4.31" osisID="1Kgs.4.31"/> for he was wiser than any man, wiser even than Ethan the Ezrahite,
            and Heman, Kalkol, and Darda, the sons of Mahol; his fame reached to all the nations around. <verse eID="1Kgs.4.31"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.4.32" osisID="1Kgs.4.32"/> He composed three thousand aphorisms, and his songs numbered one
            thousand and five. <verse eID="1Kgs.4.32"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.4.33" osisID="1Kgs.4.33"/>He could talk about any plant, from a cedar in Lebanon to a hyssop
            in the wall; he could also talk of animals, birds,
           <milestone type="pb" n="386"/> reptiles, and fish.
           <verse eID="1Kgs.4.33"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.4.34" osisID="1Kgs.4.34"/> People came from every nation, deputed by all the kings in the
            world, who had heard of Solomon’s wisdom, in order to listen to his wisdom. <verse eID="1Kgs.4.34"/>
       </p>
      <chapter eID="1Kgs.4"/>
       <chapter osisID="1Kgs.3" sID="1Kgs.3"/>
       <p>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.3.1" osisID="1Kgs.3.1"/> Solomon became the son-in-law of the Pharaoh, king of Egypt; he
            married the Pha­raoh's daughter and took her to David's burg till he had finished building his own palace
            and the Eternal's temple and the wall round Jerusalem. <verse eID="1Kgs.3.1"/>
       </p>
       <chapter eID="1Kgs.3"/>
       <chapter osisID="1Kgs.9" sID="1Kgs.9"/>
       <p>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.9.16" osisID="1Kgs.9.16"/> The Pha­raoh, king of Egypt, marched north, captured Gezer and
            burnt it, killing the Canaanites who lived in the town; then he presented it as a dowry to his daughter,
            Solomon's wife. <verse eID="1Kgs.9.16"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.9.17" osisID="1Kgs.9.17"/>Solo­mon rebuilt Gezer. <verse eID="1Kgs.9.17"/>
       </p>
       <chapter eID="1Kgs.9"/>
      <chapter osisID="1Kgs.5" sID="1Kgs.5"/>
       <p>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.5.1" osisID="1Kgs.5.1"/> When Hiram king of Tyre heard that it was Solomon who had been
            consecrated king instead of his father, he sent his officers to Solomon; for Hiram had always been friendly
            to David. <verse eID="1Kgs.5.1"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.5.2" osisID="1Kgs.5.2"/> Then Solomon sent this message to Hiram:
           <verse eID="1Kgs.5.2"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.5.3" osisID="1Kgs.5.3"/> <q>You know how my father David could not build a temple in honour
            of the Eternal his God, until the Eternal had crushed under him the warlike foes who surrounded him. <verse eID="1Kgs.5.3"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.5.4" osisID="1Kgs.5.4"/> The Eternal my God has now given me rest on every side; I have
            neither foe nor misfortune, <verse eID="1Kgs.5.4"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.5.5" osisID="1Kgs.5.5"/> and I propose to build a temple in honour of the Eternal, my God,
            as the Eternal told my father David that <q>your son, whom I place on your throne, shall build the temple in
            my honour.</q> <verse eID="1Kgs.5.5"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.5.6" osisID="1Kgs.5.6"/> Now give orders that cedars be felled for me on Lebanon; my
            servants will join your servants, and I will pay you any wage you fix for your servants; for you know we
            have no one fit to fell timber like the Phoenicians.</q> <verse eID="1Kgs.5.6"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.5.7" osisID="1Kgs.5.7"/> When Hiram heard what Solomon said, he was overjoyed. <q>Blessed be
            the Eternal the God of Israel this day,</q> he cried, <q>for granting David a wise son to rule this great
            people!</q> <verse eID="1Kgs.5.7"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.5.8" osisID="1Kgs.5.8"/> Hiram sent this message to Solomon: <q>I have heard your message;
            I will do all you desire in the matter of cedars and firs; <verse eID="1Kgs.5.8"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.5.9" osisID="1Kgs.5.9"/> my servants shall bring the timber down from Lebanon to the sea,
            and I will make the logs into floats to reach any spot you decide upon; then I will have them broken up for
            you to take away. You will meet my wishes by providing the food for my servants.</q><verse eID="1Kgs.5.9"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.5.10" osisID="1Kgs.5.10"/> So Hiram gave Solomon all the cedar and fir-wood that he desired, <verse eID="1Kgs.5.10"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.5.11" osisID="1Kgs.5.11"/>while Solomon gave Hiram two hundred and twenty thousand bushels
            of wheat and a hundred and eighty gallons of beaten oil as food for his servants--such was Solomon's annual
            gift to Hiram.
           <verse eID="1Kgs.5.11"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.5.12" osisID="1Kgs.5.12"/> Solomon and Hiram were at peace; the two men made an alliance
            with each other. <verse eID="1Kgs.5.12"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.5.13" osisID="1Kgs.5.13"/> Solomon raised a labour-force from all Israel, a levy of thirty
            thousand men, <verse eID="1Kgs.5.13"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.5.14" osisID="1Kgs.5.14"/> whom he sent to Lebanon in relays, ten thousand a month; one
            month they were at Lebanon and two months at home. Adoniram was in charge of this forced levy. <verse eID="1Kgs.5.14"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.5.15" osisID="1Kgs.5.15"/> Solomon also had seventy thousand carriers and eighty thousand
            stone-masons in the hills, <verse eID="1Kgs.5.15"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.5.16" osisID="1Kgs.5.16"/> as well as three thousand three hundred foremen, who controlled
            the workmen. <verse eID="1Kgs.5.16"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.5.17" osisID="1Kgs.5.17"/>By order of the king, they quarried huge, expensive blocks of
            stone, to have the foundation of the temple laid with dressed stone. <verse eID="1Kgs.5.17"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.5.18" osisID="1Kgs.5.18"/> Solomon's builders and Hiram's builders dressed the stones and
           ran grooved edges round them, besides
           <milestone type="pb" n="387"/>
           preparing the timber and the stones for building the temple.<verse eID="1Kgs.5.18"/>
       </p>
       <chapter eID="1Kgs.5"/>
       <chapter osisID="1Kgs.6" sID="1Kgs.6"/>
       <p>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.6.1" osisID="1Kgs.6.1"/> [[It was in the four hundred and eightieth year after the
            Israelites left Egypt, in the fourth year of Solomon's reign, and in the second month of that year, the
            month Ziv, that he began to build the temple of the Eternal.]] <verse eID="1Kgs.6.1"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.6.2" osisID="1Kgs.6.2"/> The temple which king Solomon built for the Eternal was ninety feet
            long, thirty feet broad, and forty-five feet high. <verse eID="1Kgs.6.2"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.6.3" osisID="1Kgs.6.3"/> The porch before the nave was thirty feet long, corresponding to
            the breadth of the temple, and fifteen feet wide.
           <verse eID="1Kgs.6.3"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.6.4" osisID="1Kgs.6.4"/> He made windows with gratings for the temple, and built wings round
            the wall of the temple, round both the nave and the inner shrine; <verse eID="1Kgs.6.4"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.6.5-1Kgs.6.6" osisID="1Kgs.6.5 1Kgs.6.6" n="5-6"/> he put side-rooms all round, the lower
            row of them about seven and a half feet wide, the middle row nine feet wide, and the top row about ten and a
            half feet wide--allowing space all round the outside wall so that the ends of the planks upholding the rows
            need not pierce the walls of the temple. <verse eID="1Kgs.6.5-1Kgs.6.6"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.6.7" osisID="1Kgs.6.7"/> [[The temple was built throughout of stones roughly dressed at the
            quarry; not a sound of hammer, chisel, or any iron tool was ever heard during the building of the temple.]] <verse eID="1Kgs.6.7"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.6.8" osisID="1Kgs.6.8"/> The entrance into the lower side-rooms was on the south side of the
            temple; you climbed to the middle row, and from the middle row to the top row, through trap-doors. <verse eID="1Kgs.6.8"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.6.10" osisID="1Kgs.6.10"/> Thus did he build the temple and finish it, roofing it over with
            cedar. <verse eID="1Kgs.6.10"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.6.9" osisID="1Kgs.6.9"/> Each row of side-rooms built against the temple was about seven and
            a half feet high, and they rested on cedar planks against the temple. <verse eID="1Kgs.6.9"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.6.15" osisID="1Kgs.6.15"/> The walls inside he lined with cedar planks, overlaying the
            interior from the floor to the rafters of the ceiling with wood, and covering the floor itself with fir. <verse eID="1Kgs.6.15"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.6.16" osisID="1Kgs.6.16"/> At the far end of the temple he built off a space of thirty feet
            as an inner shrine, the most sacred interior; <verse eID="1Kgs.6.16"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.6.17" osisID="1Kgs.6.17"/> the nave or hall in front of it was sixty feet long, <verse eID="1Kgs.6.17"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.6.20" osisID="1Kgs.6.20"/> but the inner shrine was thirty feet square. <verse eID="1Kgs.6.20"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.6.21" osisID="1Kgs.6.21"/> In front of the inner shrine he made an altar of cedar; <verse eID="1Kgs.6.21"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.6.23" osisID="1Kgs.6.23"/>inside the inner shrine he made two kherubs of olive-wood, <verse eID="1Kgs.6.23"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.6.26" osisID="1Kgs.6.26"/> each of them fifteen feet high, <verse eID="1Kgs.6.26"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.6.24" osisID="1Kgs.6.24"/> each with outstretched wings seven and a half feet broad,
            measuring fifteen feet from the tip of one wing to the tip of the other, <verse eID="1Kgs.6.24"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.6.25" osisID="1Kgs.6.25"/> the one kherub being the same as the other in size and shape. <verse eID="1Kgs.6.25"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.6.27" osisID="1Kgs.6.27"/>These kherubs he placed inside the inner shrine; their wings were
            spread out so that the wing of one touched one wall while the wing of the other touched the other wall, and
            their inner wings met in the middle. <verse eID="1Kgs.6.27"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.6.28" osisID="1Kgs.6.28"/>He plated the kherubs with gold. <verse eID="1Kgs.6.28"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.6.31" osisID="1Kgs.6.31"/> He made doors of olive-wood for the vestibule of the inner shrine;
            the vestibule and the pilasters formed a pentagon. <verse eID="1Kgs.6.31"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.6.32" osisID="1Kgs.6.32"/> On the two doors of olive-wood he carved kherubs, palm-trees, and
            open flowers, spreading gold over the kherubs and the palm-trees. <verse eID="1Kgs.6.32"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.6.33" osisID="1Kgs.6.33"/> For the vestibule of the nave he also made door-posts of olive-wood,
            four-cornered posts, <verse eID="1Kgs.6.33"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.6.34" osisID="1Kgs.6.34"/> and two folding doors of cypress wood, the two leaves of each
            turning on hinges. <verse eID="1Kgs.6.34"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.6.35" osisID="1Kgs.6.35"/>These he carved with kherubs, palm-trees, and open flowers,
            overlaying them with gold laid evenly upon the carvings. <verse eID="1Kgs.6.35"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.6.36" osisID="1Kgs.6.36"/> The inner court round the temple he built with three rows of
            dressed stone and one row of cedar beams. <verse eID="1Kgs.6.36"/>
       </p>
       <milestone type="pb" n="388"/>
       <p>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.6.37" osisID="1Kgs.6.37"/> The foundation of the temple of the Eternal was laid in the month
            of Ziv, in the fourth year of Solomon; <verse eID="1Kgs.6.37"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.6.38" osisID="1Kgs.6.38"/> in the month of Bui (the eighth month), in the eleventh year, the
            temple was finished in every part, exactly as planned. He took seven years to build it. <verse eID="1Kgs.6.38"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.6.11" osisID="1Kgs.6.11"/> [[Then this word from the Eternal came to Solomon: <verse eID="1Kgs.6.11"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.6.12" osisID="1Kgs.6.12"/> <q>As for this temple which you build, if you will live by my
            rules and keep my regulations and follow all my orders, living by them, then I will fulfil for you the
            promise I made to your father David; <verse eID="1Kgs.6.12"/>
           <verse sID="1Kgs.6.13" osisID="1Kgs.6.13"/> and I will dwell among the Israelites, I will not forsake my
            people Israel.</q>]] <verse eID="1Kgs.6.13"/>
       </p>
      <chapter eID="1Kgs.6"/>
   </div>