   <div type="book" osisID="1Sam">
    <milestone type="pb" n="306"/>
    <chapter osisID="1Sam.1" sID="1Sam.1"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.1.1" osisID="1Sam.1.1"/>There was a man of Ramah, a Zuphite from the highlands of Ephraim, whose name
       was Elkanah---the son of Jeroham, the son of Elihu, the son of Tohu, the son of Zuph. He was an Ephraimite, <verse eID="1Sam.1.1"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.1.2" osisID="1Sam.1.2"/> and he had two wives, one called Hannah and the other Peninnah; Peninnah had
       children, but Hannah had no children. <verse eID="1Sam.1.2"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.1.3" osisID="1Sam.1.3"/> Now this man used to go up from his town, year by year, to worship and to
       sacrifice to the Lord of hosts at Shilo, where Eli and his two sons, Hophni and Phinehas, were priests to the
       Eternal. <verse eID="1Sam.1.3"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.1.4" osisID="1Sam.1.4"/> He used to give his wife Penin­nah and all her sons and daugh­ters shares of
       the sacrificial meat, <verse eID="1Sam.1.4"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.1.5" osisID="1Sam.1.5"/> but, though he loved Hannah, he gave her only a sin­gle share, because the
       Eternal had shut up her womb. <verse eID="1Sam.1.5"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.1.6" osisID="1Sam.1.6"/> Her rival used to taunt her bit­terly, to irritate her, because the Eternal
       had shut up her womb; <verse eID="1Sam.1.6"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.1.7" osisID="1Sam.1.7"/> and this went on year after year--whenever she went up to the house of the
       Eternal, she taunted Hannah. <verse eID="1Sam.1.7"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.1.4" osisID="1Sam.1.4"/> One day when Elkanah was sacrificing, Hannah wept and would not eat. <verse eID="1Sam.1.4"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.1.8" osisID="1Sam.1.8"/> So her husband Elkanah said to her, <q>Hannah, why are you weeping? Why are
       you not eating? Why is your heart sad? Am I not more to you than ten sons?</q> <verse eID="1Sam.1.8"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.1.9" osisID="1Sam.1.9"/> But after they had eaten the boiled flesh and had drunk, Hannah rose and
       stood before the Eternal where Eli the priest was sitting on his chair at the door­posts of the temple of the Eternal.
      <verse eID="1Sam.1.9"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.1.10" osisID="1Sam.1.10"/> With a sore heart she prayed to the Eternal, weeping bitterly, <verse eID="1Sam.1.10"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.1.11" osisID="1Sam.1.11"/> and she made this vow: <q>O Lord of hosts, if thou wilt in­deed look upon
       the plight of thy servant and remember me and not forget thy servant, but wilt give thy servant a son, then I will
       give him to the Eternal for the whole of his life; and no razor shall ever touch his head.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.1.11"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.1.12" osisID="1Sam.1.12"/> As she went on praying before the Eternal, Eli noticed her mouth--<verse eID="1Sam.1.12"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.1.13" osisID="1Sam.1.13"/> for Hannah was speaking to herself; only her lips moved, her voice was not
       heard. Eli thought she was drunk. <verse eID="1Sam.1.13"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.1.14" osisID="1Sam.1.14"/> So Eli said to her, <q>How long will you go on, you drunken creature? Away
       with you, go and sleep off your drunkenness!</q> <verse eID="1Sam.1.14"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.1.15" osisID="1Sam.1.15"/> But Hannah replied, <q>No, sir, I am a sorely tried woman, I have drunk
       neither wine nor liquor; I have been pouring out my soul be­fore the Eternal. <verse eID="1Sam.1.15"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.1.16" osisID="1Sam.1.16"/> Do not take your servant for a depraved woman; it is under my stress of
       grief and provocation that I have been speaking all the time.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.1.16"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.1.17" osisID="1Sam.1.17"/> Then Eli answered, <q>Go and prosper; may the God of Israel grant you what
       you have asked him!</q> <verse eID="1Sam.1.17"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.1.18" osisID="1Sam.1.18"/> And she said, <q>May your servant find favour in your eyes!</q> <verse eID="1Sam.1.18"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.1.19" osisID="1Sam.1.19"/> So the woman went away; she ate, and her face was sad no longer. In the
       morning they rose, worshipped before the Eternal, and returned home to Ramah. Elkanah had inter­course with Hannah his
       wife, and the Eternal remembered her; <verse eID="1Sam.1.19"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.1.20" osisID="1Sam.1.20"/> so Hannah conceived, and at the turn of the year she bore a son, calling
       his name Samuel or <q>God-asked.</q> <q>For,</q> she said, <q>I asked the Eternal for him.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.1.20"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.1.21" osisID="1Sam.1.21"/> Elkanah went up with all
       <milestone type="pb" n="307"/>
       his household to offer to the Eternal the yearly sacrifice and what he had vowed, <verse eID="1Sam.1.21"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.1.22" osisID="1Sam.1.22"/> but Hannah did not go up. <q>Once the child is weaned,</q> she told her
       husband, <q>then I will bring him; we shall appear before the Eternal, and he shall remain there for ever.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.1.22"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.1.23" osisID="1Sam.1.23"/> Elkanah her husband said to her, <q>Do what­ever you think right; wait
       till you have weaned him, and may the Eternal let you carry out your purpose.</q> So Hannah waited and suckled her son
       till she weaned him. <verse eID="1Sam.1.23"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.1.24" osisID="1Sam.1.24"/> Then, after weaning him, she took him with her, along with a
       three-year-old bullock, a bushel of flour, and a bottle of wine; she entered the house of the Eternal at Shilo,
       accompanied by the boy, <verse eID="1Sam.1.24"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.1.25" osisID="1Sam.1.25"/> and, after the bullock had been slain, she brought the boy to Eli. <verse eID="1Sam.1.25"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.1.26" osisID="1Sam.1.26"/> <q>As sure as you live, sir,</q> she said, <q>I am the woman who stood
       beside you here, praying to the Eternal. <verse eID="1Sam.1.26"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.1.27" osisID="1Sam.1.27"/> I prayed about this boy, and the Eternal has granted me what I asked. <verse eID="1Sam.1.27"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.1.28" osisID="1Sam.1.28"/> So I have lent him to the Eternal; as long as he lives he is loaned to the
       Eternal.</q><verse eID="1Sam.1.28"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eID="1Sam.1"/>
    <chapter osisID="1Sam.2" sID="1Sam.2"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.2.1" osisID="1Sam.2.1"/>[[Hannah sang this prayer:
      <lg>
       <l> My heart thrills to the Eternal, </l>
       <l> my powers are heightened by my God, </l>
       <l> my lips exult over my foes, </l>
       <l> for I joy in thy deliverance. </l>
      <verse eID="1Sam.2.1"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.2.2" osisID="1Sam.2.2"/>
       <l> None is divine like the Eternal, </l>
       <l> no Power is steadfast like our God. </l>
      <verse eID="1Sam.2.2"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.2.3" osisID="1Sam.2.3"/>
       <l> No more of your proud vaunts! </l>
       <l> No mouthing of your taunts! </l>
       <l> For the Eternal is a God who knows it all, </l>
       <l> and what men do he judges. </l>
      <verse eID="1Sam.2.3"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.2.4" osisID="1Sam.2.4"/>
       <l> The strong man’s bow is broken, </l>
       <l> and the stumbling are braced up; </l>
      <verse eID="1Sam.2.4"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.2.5" osisID="1Sam.2.5"/>
       <l> those who had plenty have to work for bread, </l>
       <l> and hungry people have to toil no more; </l>
       <l> the barren woman has seven chil­dren now, </l>
       <l> and the mother of many is pining. </l>
      <verse eID="1Sam.2.5"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.2.6" osisID="1Sam.2.6"/>
       <l> The Eternal kills, the Eternal life bestows, </l>
       <l> he lowers to death and he lifts up, </l>
      <verse eID="1Sam.2.6"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.2.7" osisID="1Sam.2.7"/>
       <l> the Eternal makes poor, the Eternal makes rich, </l>
       <l> he lays low and he raises, </l>
      <verse eID="1Sam.2.7"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.2.8" osisID="1Sam.2.8"/>
       <l> he lifts the poor out of the dust, </l>
       <l> he raises beggars from the rub­bish heap, </l>
       <l> seating them next to nobles, </l>
       <l> to give them thrones of splendour. </l>
       <l> [[For the pillars of the earth be­long to the Eternal, </l>
       <l> and on them he set the world.]] </l>
      <verse eID="1Sam.2.8"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.2.9" osisID="1Sam.2.9"/>
       <l> He will guard the steps of his godly folk, </l>
       <l> but evil men shall perish in the dark </l>
       <l> (for no man's strength makes him mighty).</l>
      <verse eID="1Sam.2.9"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.2.10" osisID="1Sam.2.10"/>
       <l> The Eternal will crush his enemies, </l>
       <l> the Most High in heaven will shatter them </l>
       <l> (the Eternal's judgments shall cover the wide world), </l>
       <l> to add power to his king, </l>
       <l> to heighten the strength of his anointed one.]]</l>
      </lg>
      <verse eID="1Sam.2.10"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.2.11" osisID="1Sam.2.11"/> Then Hannah left him there before the Eternal, and went to Ramah; but the
       boy ministered to the Eternal in presence of Eli the priest. <verse eID="1Sam.2.11"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.2.12" osisID="1Sam.2.12"/> Now the sons of Eli were depraved creatures; they cared nothing for the
       Eternal nor for the regular dues of a priest. <verse eID="1Sam.2.12"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.2.13" osisID="1Sam.2.13"/> Whenever a man offered sacrifice, the priest’s servant would come, as the
       flesh was being boiled, with a three-pronged fork in his hand, <verse eID="1Sam.2.13"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.2.14" osisID="1Sam.2.14"/> which he plunged into the pot or kettle or basin or dish; whatever the
       fork brought up, the priest took for himself. So they treated ail the Israelites who came to sac­rifice at Shilo to
       the Eternal. <verse eID="1Sam.2.14"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.2.15" osisID="1Sam.2.15"/> In fact, even before the fat was burned, the priest’s servant
       <milestone type="pb" n="308"/>
       would come and tell the man who was sacrificing, <q>Let the priest have some flesh for roast­ing; he wants raw flesh
       from you, not boiled.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.2.15"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.2.16" osisID="1Sam.2.16"/> If the man said to him, <q>First let the fat be burned, and then take as
       much as you want,</q> he would answer, <q>No, you must give it to me at once, or I will take it by force.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.2.16"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.2.17" osisID="1Sam.2.17"/> The sin of the young men was very great before the Eternal, for it meant
       disdain of what was offered to the Eternal. <verse eID="1Sam.2.17"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.2.18" osisID="1Sam.2.18"/> Samuel, a boy girt with a linen apron, ministered before the Eternal, <verse eID="1Sam.2.18"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.2.19" osisID="1Sam.2.19"/> and his mother used to make him a little robe, which she brought to him
       year by year when she came up with her husband to offer the yearly sacrifice. <verse eID="1Sam.2.19"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.2.20" osisID="1Sam.2.20"/> Eli would bless Elkanah and his wife, saying,<q>May the Eternal repay
       you with off­spring from this woman, for the loan she has made to the Eter­nal!</q> Then they would go home. <verse eID="1Sam.2.20"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.2.21" osisID="1Sam.2.21"/> And the Eternal re­membered Hannah, so that she conceived and bore three
       sons and two daughters. Meantime the boy Samuel grew up before the Eternal. <verse eID="1Sam.2.21"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.2.22" osisID="1Sam.2.22"/> Now Eli was very old. When­ever he heard how his sons were behaving
       towards all Israel, and how they lay with the women caretakers at the door of the Trysting tent, <verse eID="1Sam.2.22"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.2.23" osisID="1Sam.2.23"/> he said to them, <q>Why are you behaving like this? I hear of it from all
       the people. <verse eID="1Sam.2.23"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.2.24" osisID="1Sam.2.24"/> No, my sons, it is no good report that I hear the people of the Eternal
       repeating. <verse eID="1Sam.2.24"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.2.25" osisID="1Sam.2.25"/> If one man sins against another man, God will mediate for him, but if a
       man sins against the Eternal, who can intercede on hi behalf?</q> However, they would not listen to what their
       father said, for the Eternal was resolved to slay them. <verse eID="1Sam.2.25"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.2.26" osisID="1Sam.2.26"/> Meantime Samuel grew up to be a fine boy in the eyes of the Eter­nal and
       of men. <verse eID="1Sam.2.26"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.2.27" osisID="1Sam.2.27"/> Now a man of God came to Eli and gave him this message from the Eternal.
       <q>Did I not reveal myself to your father's household when they were in Egypt, slaves to the court of the Pharaoh?
      <verse eID="1Sam.2.27"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.2.28" osisID="1Sam.2.28"/> Did I not choose him from all the clans of Israel to be my priest, to go
       up to my altar, to burn sacrifice, and to bear the ephod in my presence? Did I not assign to your father's household
       as food all that the Israelites offer by fire? <verse eID="1Sam.2.28"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.2.29" osisID="1Sam.2.29"/> Why, then, do you cast an envious eye upon my sacrifices and offer­ings,
       letting your sons override me and fattening yourselves under my very eyes upon the first-fruits of all that Israel
       my people offers? <verse eID="1Sam.2.29"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.2.30" osisID="1Sam.2.30"/> Therefore the Eternal, the God of Israel, de­clares, I had meant your
       house­hold and your father's house­hold to live in my favour for ever; but now, says the Eternal, far be that from me;
       those who honour me I will honour, and those who despise me shall be derided. <verse eID="1Sam.2.30"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.2.31" osisID="1Sam.2.31"/> The day is coming when I will cut off your off­spring and the offspring of
       your father’s household till there is not an old man left in your household; <verse eID="1Sam.2.31"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.2.32" osisID="1Sam.2.32"/> then in your straits you shall look enviously on all the prosperity I
       award to Is­rael. <verse eID="1Sam.2.32"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.2.33" osisID="1Sam.2.33"/> One of your family I will not cut off from my altar, I will spare him to
       consume his eyes with longing and to wear out his heart; but the greater part of your household shall die by the
       sword of men. <verse eID="1Sam.2.33"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.2.34" osisID="1Sam.2.34"/> What is to befall your two sons Hophni and Phinehas shall be an omen for
       you; both are to die on the
       <milestone type="pb" n="309"/>
       same day. <verse eID="1Sam.2.34"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.2.35" osisID="1Sam.2.35"/> But I will raise up for myself a faithful priest, who is to do whatever I
       plan and desire; I will found a family for him that lasts; he shall live in the favour of my anointed king for ever,
      <verse eID="1Sam.2.35"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.2.36" osisID="1Sam.2.36"/> and any survivor of your household shall come and do him obeisance for a
       pit­tance of money and a piece of bread, crying, <q>Do put me in some priestly position, that I may get a bite of
       food to eat.</q></q> <verse eID="1Sam.2.36"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eID="1Sam.2"/>
    <chapter osisID="1Sam.3" sID="1Sam.3"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.3.1" osisID="1Sam.3.1"/>The boy Samuel was minis­tering to the Eternal in pres­ence of Eli. A word
       from the Eternal was rare in those days; <verse eID="1Sam.3.1"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.3.2" osisID="1Sam.3.2"/> visions were not common. But one day, after Eli had lain down in his place
       (his eyes had begun to grow dim, so that he could not see), <verse eID="1Sam.3.2"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.3.3" osisID="1Sam.3.3"/> when the lamp of God was still burning, and Samuel was lying in the temple
       of the Eternal beside the ark of God, <verse eID="1Sam.3.3"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.3.4" osisID="1Sam.3.4"/> then the Eternal called, <q>Samuel! Samuel!</q> He answered, <q>Here I
       am,</q> <verse eID="1Sam.3.4"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.3.5" osisID="1Sam.3.5"/> and ran to Eli, saying, <q>Here I am; you called me.</q> But he said,
       <q>I did not call you; lie down again.</q> So he went and lay down. <verse eID="1Sam.3.5"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.3.6" osisID="1Sam.3.6"/> Once more the Eternal called, <q>Sam­uel! Samuel!</q> Then Samuel got up and
       went to Eli; <q>Here I am,</q> he said; <q>you did call me.</q> But he answered, <q>I did not call you, my son; lie
        down 7 again.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.3.6"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.3.7" osisID="1Sam.3.7"/> Now Samuel did not yet know the Eternal, and the word of the Eternal had
       not yet been disclosed to him. <verse eID="1Sam.3.7"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.3.8" osisID="1Sam.3.8"/> So when the Eternal called Samuel again, the third time, he got up and went
       to Eli, saying, <q>Here I am; you did call me.</q> Eli now saw that the Eternal was calling the lad; <verse eID="1Sam.3.8"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.3.9" osisID="1Sam.3.9"/> so Eli told Samuel, <q>Go and lie down; if you are called, you must say,
       <q>Speak, O Eternal; thy servant is listening.</q></q> Then Samuel went and lay down in his place, <verse eID="1Sam.3.9"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.3.10" osisID="1Sam.3.10"/> and the Eternal came and stood, calling as usual, <q>Sam­uel! Samuel!</q>
       Samuel said, <q>Speak, thy servant is listen­ing</q>; <verse eID="1Sam.3.10"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.3.11" osisID="1Sam.3.11"/> and the Eternal said to Samuel, <q>I am about to do a deed in Israel that
       will make the ears of all who hear it ring; <verse eID="1Sam.3.11"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.3.12" osisID="1Sam.3.12"/> on that day I will execute against Eli all that I have said about his
       household from be­ginning to end. <verse eID="1Sam.3.12"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.3.13" osisID="1Sam.3.13"/> You must tell him that I will punish his house­hold for ever, because he
       knew that his sons were blaspheming God and yet he did not check them. <verse eID="1Sam.3.13"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.3.14" osisID="1Sam.3.14"/> Therefore have I sworn to the household of Eli that the guilt of Eli's
       household shall never be expiated, neither by sacrifices nor by offering.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.3.14"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.3.15" osisID="1Sam.3.15"/> Samuel lay till morning; in the morning he rose and opened the doors of
       the house of the Eter­nal, but he was afraid to let Eli know the vision. <verse eID="1Sam.3.15"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.3.16" osisID="1Sam.3.16"/> Eli called Samuel, however, and said, <q>Samuel, my son.</q> <q>Here I
       am,</q> he said. <verse eID="1Sam.3.16"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.3.17" osisID="1Sam.3.17"/> And he said, <q>What was it that the Eternal told you? Come, do not hide
       it from me. God kill you and worse, if you hide from me a single word of what he told you!</q> <verse eID="1Sam.3.17"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.3.18" osisID="1Sam.3.18"/> So Samuel told him everything, and hid nothing from him. <q>It is the
       Eternal,</q> said Eli, <q>let him do what he thinks good!</q> <verse eID="1Sam.3.18"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.3.19" osisID="1Sam.3.19"/> Now Samuel grew up, and the Eternal was with him and let none of his
       words prove a fail­ure; <verse eID="1Sam.3.19"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.3.20" osisID="1Sam.3.20"/> all Israel from Dan to Beersheba knew that Samuel was accredited as a
       prophet of the Eternal. <verse eID="1Sam.3.20"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.3.21" osisID="1Sam.3.21"/> Once more the Eternal was to be seen at Shilo, for at Shilo the Eternal
       revealed himself to Samuel, and Samuel’s word reached all Is­rael. <verse eID="1Sam.3.21"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eID="1Sam.3"/>
    <milestone type="pb" n="310"/>
    <chapter osisID="1Sam.4" sID="1Sam.4"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.4.1" osisID="1Sam.4.1"/> In those days the Philistines mustered to make war on Israel; Israel
       marched out to fight the Philistines and camped at Help-stone, while the Philistines camped at Aphek.
      <verse eID="1Sam.4.1"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.4.2" osisID="1Sam.4.2"/> The Philis­tines drew up in battle array against Israel; it was a stiff
       fight, but Israel was routed before the Philistines, who slew four thousand of their army in the open country. <verse eID="1Sam.4.2"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.4.3" osisID="1Sam.4.3"/> When the troops returned to their camp, the sheikhs of Israel said, 
      <q>Why has the Eternal routed us to-day before the Phil­istines? Let us fetch the ark of our God from Shilo, that he
       may come among us and rescue us from the power of our enemies.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.4.3"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.4.4" osisID="1Sam.4.4"/> So the people sent to Shilo and brought away the ark of the Eternal
       (throned on the kherubs), and, along with the ark of God, Eli’s two sons Hophni and Phinehas. <verse eID="1Sam.4.4"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.4.5" osisID="1Sam.4.5"/> When the ark of the Eternal reached the camp, all Is­rael raised a mighty
       shout, till the earth resounded; <verse eID="1Sam.4.5"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.4.6" osisID="1Sam.4.6"/> and when the Philistines heard the noise of the shout, they said, <q>What
       is this noise of mighty shouting in the camp of the Hebrews?</q> When they learned that the ark of the Eternal had
       arrived in the camp, <verse eID="1Sam.4.6"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.4.7" osisID="1Sam.4.7"/> the Philistines were afraid. <q>These are their gods,</q> they said, <q>who
       have come to them in camp!</q> <q>Woe to us!</q> they said, <q>This has never hap­pened before. <verse eID="1Sam.4.7"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.4.8" osisID="1Sam.4.8"/> Woe to us! Who can rescue us from the power of these mighty gods? These are
       the gods that struck the Egyptians with all manner of plagues and pestilence. <verse eID="1Sam.4.8"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.4.9" osisID="1Sam.4.9"/> But courage, Philistines! Be men, that you may not be slaves to the
       Hebrews as they have been slaves to you.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.4.9"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.4.10" osisID="1Sam.4.10"/> So the Philistines fought, and Israel was beaten--every man scurried
       home, and there was a terrible slaughter, for thirty thousand infantry of Israel fell, <verse eID="1Sam.4.10"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.4.11" osisID="1Sam.4.11"/> the ark of God was captured, and Eli's two sons perished, Hophni and
       Phinehas. <verse eID="1Sam.4.11"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.4.12" osisID="1Sam.4.12"/> A Benjamite ran from the ranks and reached Shilo on the same day, with
       his clothes torn and earth scattered over his head. <verse eID="1Sam.4.12"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.4.13" osisID="1Sam.4.13"/> When he arrived, (Eli was sitting on his seat be­side the gate of the
       temple, watching the road; his heart was trembling for the ark of God. All the town made an outcry when the man
       came into the town with the news; <verse eID="1Sam.4.13"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.4.14" osisID="1Sam.4.14"/> and when Eli heard the noise of the outcry, he said, <q>What is the
       meaning of this uproar?</q> The man hurried on his way to tell Eli <verse eID="1Sam.4.14"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.4.15" osisID="1Sam.4.15"/> [[Eli was ninety-eight years old, and his eyes were so dim that he could
       not see]]. <verse eID="1Sam.4.15"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.4.16" osisID="1Sam.4.16"/> The man said to Eli, <q>I am the man who has come from the camp; I fled
       from the ranks to-day.</q> He asked, <q>And how did things go, my son?</q> <verse eID="1Sam.4.16"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.4.17" osisID="1Sam.4.17"/> The messenger said, <q>Israel fled be­fore the Philistines, there was a
       terrible slaughter of the troops, your two sons are dead, and the ark of God has been cap­tured.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.4.17"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.4.18" osisID="1Sam.4.18"/> When he mentioned the ark of God, Eli fell back from his seat beside the
       gate; his neck was broken, and he died--for he was old and heavy. He had been over Israel for forty years. <verse eID="1Sam.4.18"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.4.19" osisID="1Sam.4.19"/> His daughter-in-law, the wife of Phinehas, was pregnant and on the point
       of being delivered; when she heard the news about the capture of the ark of God and the death of her father-in-law
       and of her
       <milestone type="pb" n="311"/>
       husband, she bent forward and bore a child, for her birth-pangs came on her. <verse eID="1Sam.4.19"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.4.20" osisID="1Sam.4.20"/> As she was dying, the women standing round her said to her, <q>Fear not,
       you have borne a son.</q> But she said nothing, she never heeded them. <verse eID="1Sam.4.20"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.4.21" osisID="1Sam.4.21"/> So they named the child Ichabod, or Noglory, saying, <q>The glory is gone
       from Israel</q>--on account of the cap­ture of the ark of God, and on account of her father-in-law and her husband. <verse eID="1Sam.4.21"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eID="1Sam.4"/>
    <chapter osisID="1Sam.5" sID="1Sam.5"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.5.1" osisID="1Sam.5.1"/>The Philistines took the ark of God and brought it from Helpstone to Ashdod;
      <verse eID="1Sam.5.1"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.5.2" osisID="1Sam.5.2"/> then the Philistines took the ark of God and brought it into the temple of
       DagOn, placing it beside Dagon. <verse eID="1Sam.5.2"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.5.3" osisID="1Sam.5.3"/> But when the folk of Ashdod rose next morning, and went to the temple of
       Dagon and looked in, there lay Dagon flat on his face on the ground, in front of the ark of the Eter­nal! <verse eID="1Sam.5.3"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.5.4" osisID="1Sam.5.4"/> They lifted up Dagon and put him in his place again. But when they rose
       next morn­ing, there lay Dagon flat on his face on the ground in front of the ark of the Eternal--the head and both
       the hands of Dagon severed on the threshold, and only the trunk of Dagon left! <verse eID="1Sam.5.4"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.5.5" osisID="1Sam.5.5"/> (This is why the priests of Dagon, and all who enter the temple of Dagon,
       to this day, never step on the threshold of Dagon in Ashdod, but leap over it.) <verse eID="1Sam.5.5"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.5.6" osisID="1Sam.5.6"/> Then the Eternal laid a heavy hand upon the folk of Ashdod; he wasted them,
       striking both Ashdod and all its territory with tumours. <verse eID="1Sam.5.6"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.5.7" osisID="1Sam.5.7"/> When the men of Ashdod saw this, they said, <q>The ark of the God of Israel
       must not remain among us any longer, for his hand is severe on us and on Dagon our God.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.5.7"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.5.8" osisID="1Sam.5.8"/> So they sent and summoned all the Philistine tyrants, saying, <q>What are
       we to do with the ark of the God of Israel?</q> They replied, <q>Let the ark of the God of Israel be brought round
       to Gath.</q> They brought the ark of the God of Israel round to Gath, <verse eID="1Sam.5.8"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.5.9" osisID="1Sam.5.9"/> but, after they had brought it round, the hand of the Eternal struck that
       town; there was a terrible panic, for he struck the men of the town, both young and old, till tu­mours broke out upon
       them. <verse eID="1Sam.5.9"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.5.10" osisID="1Sam.5.10"/> So they sent the ark of God to Ekron. But when the ark of God came to
       Ekron, the Ekronites cried out, <q>They have brought round the ark of the God of Israel to us, to slay us and our
       people!</q> <verse eID="1Sam.5.10"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.5.11" osisID="1Sam.5.11"/> So they sent and summoned all the Philistine tyrants, saying, <q>Send the
       ark of the God of Israel away back to its own place, that it may not slay us and our people.</q> For there was a
       deadly panic all over the town; God laid a heavy hand upon them there; <verse eID="1Sam.5.11"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.5.12" osisID="1Sam.5.12"/> the men who did not die were struck down with tumours, and the wail of
       the town rose up to heaven. <verse eID="1Sam.5.12"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eID="1Sam.5"/>
    <chapter osisID="1Sam.6" sID="1Sam.6"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.6.1" osisID="1Sam.6.1"/>For seven months the ark of the Eternal remained in the land of the
       Philistines. <verse eID="1Sam.6.1"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.6.2" osisID="1Sam.6.2"/> Then the Philistines summoned their priests and magicians. <q>What are we
       to do with the ark of the Eternal?</q> they asked; <q>tell us how we should send it to its own place.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.6.2"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.6.3" osisID="1Sam.6.3"/> And they replied, <q>If you are sending away the ark of the God of Israel,
       you must not send it away empty; you must render him some reparation. Then you will be cured, and you will learn why
       his hand still presses on you.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.6.3"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.6.4" osisID="1Sam.6.4"/> They asked, <q>What is the
       <milestone type="pb" n="312"/>
       reparation we must offer to him?</q> <q>Five golden tumours,</q> they said, <q>and five golden mice, ac­cording to
       the number of the Philistine tyrants, for one plague was upon you all and upon your tyrants. <verse eID="1Sam.6.4"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.6.5" osisID="1Sam.6.5"/> So you must make images of your tu­mours and images of your mice that are
       spoiling the country, and thus do honour to the God of Israel; perhaps he will take his hand off you and your gods
       and your land. <verse eID="1Sam.6.5"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.6.6" osisID="1Sam.6.6"/> Why will you stiffen yourselves, as the Egyp­tians and the Pharaoh
       stiffened themselves? Was it not only after God had made fools of them, that they let Israel depart? <verse eID="1Sam.6.6"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.6.7" osisID="1Sam.6.7"/> Now then, make a new cart and take two milch cows which have never been in
       har­ness; fasten the cows to the cart, and leave their calves behind them at home; <verse eID="1Sam.6.7"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.6.8" osisID="1Sam.6.8"/> then take the ark of the Eternal and place it on the cart, putting into a
       box beside it the golden objects you are offering by way of reparation. Send the cart away on its journey, <verse eID="1Sam.6.8"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.6.9" osisID="1Sam.6.9"/> and if it takes the road in the direction of Israel’s territory, towards
       Beth-shemesh, then it is the Eternal who has inflicted this great damage upon us; but if not, then we shall
       understand it was not his hand that struck us--it was an accident that befell us.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.6.9"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.6.10" osisID="1Sam.6.10"/> The men did so. They took two milch cows and fas­tened them to the cart,
       shutting their calves up at home, <verse eID="1Sam.6.10"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.6.11" osisID="1Sam.6.11"/> and on the cart they placed the ark of the Eternal and the box with the
       golden mice and the images of their tumours. <verse eID="1Sam.6.11"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.6.12" osisID="1Sam.6.12"/> The cows made straight along the road to Beth-shemesh; they kept to the
       one high-road, low­ing as they went, and turning neither to the right nor to the left, while the Philistine tyrants
       followed them up to the frontier at Beth-shemesh. <verse eID="1Sam.6.12"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.6.13" osisID="1Sam.6.13"/> The folk of Beth-shemesh were harvesting their wheat in the valley, and
       when they looked up and saw the ark, they went joyfully to meet it. <verse eID="1Sam.6.13"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.6.14" osisID="1Sam.6.14"/> The cart moved into the field of Joshua the Beth-shemeshite and stopped
       there. <verse eID="1Sam.6.14"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.6.15" osisID="1Sam.6.15"/>A large altar-stone was there; so they split up the wood of the cart and
       offered the cows as a burnt-offering to the Eter­nal. [[The Levites took down the ark of the Eternal and the box
       containing the golden ob­jects, and placed them on the large altar-stone, and the men of Beth-shemesh offered that
       day burnt-offerings and ordi­nary sacrifices to the Eternal.]] <verse eID="1Sam.6.15"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.6.16" osisID="1Sam.6.16"/> When the five Philistine tyrants saw this, they re­turned that very day to
       Ekron. <verse eID="1Sam.6.16"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.6.17" osisID="1Sam.6.17"/> [[These are the golden tumours which the Philistines gave up as
       reparation to the Eternal; there was one for Ashdod, one for Gaza, one for Ashkelon, one for Gath, and one for
       Ekron; <verse eID="1Sam.6.17"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.6.18" osisID="1Sam.6.18"/> the golden mice also corresponded to the number of all the Philis­tine
       towns belonging to the five tyrants, both fortified towns and country villages]]. And still to this day the large
       altar-stone, beside which they set down the ark of the Eternal, stands in the field of Joshua the Beth-shemeshite.
      <verse eID="1Sam.6.18"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.6.19" osisID="1Sam.6.19"/> The sons of Jeconiah, however, did not rejoice along with the men of
       Beth-shemesh when they saw the ark of the Eternal; so he struck [[fifty thousand and]] seventy of them. And the
       folk mourned because the Eternal had smitten the folk with a heavy slaughter. <verse eID="1Sam.6.19"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.6.20" osisID="1Sam.6.20"/> The men of
       <milestone type="pb" n="313"/>
       Beth-shemesh said, <q>Who can stand before the Eternal, this dread God? Whither can we have him sent, to leave us
       alone?</q> <verse eID="1Sam.6.20"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.6.21" osisID="1Sam.6.21"/> So they sent messen­gers to the inhabitants of Kiriath-jearim, saying,
       <q>The Philis­tines have brought back the ark of the Eternal. Come down and take it to be with you.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.6.21"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eID="1Sam.6"/>
    <chapter osisID="1Sam.7" sID="1Sam.7"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.7.1" osisID="1Sam.7.1"/>The men of Kiriath-jearim came and took the ark of the Eternal, bringing it
       to the house of Abinadab on the hill and con­secrating Eleazar his son to look after the ark of the Eternal. <verse eID="1Sam.7.1"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.7.2" osisID="1Sam.7.2"/> From the day that the ark of the Eternal remained at Kir­iath-jearim (the
       days length­ened out into twenty years), all the house of Israel turned after the Eternal. <verse eID="1Sam.7.2"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.7.3" osisID="1Sam.7.3"/> Samuel said to all the house of Israel, <q>If you are returning with all
       your heart to the Eternal, then put away from yourselves the foreign gods and the Astartes, set your hearts on the
       Eternal and worship him alone, and he will rescue you from the power of the Philistines.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.7.3"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.7.4" osisID="1Sam.7.4"/> So the Israelites did put away the Baals and the As­tartes, and worshipped
       the Eternal alone. <verse eID="1Sam.7.4"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.7.5" osisID="1Sam.7.5"/> Then Samuel said, <q>Gather all Israel at Mizpah, and I will pray to the
       Eternal for you.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.7.5"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.7.6" osisID="1Sam.7.6"/> They gath­ered at Mizpah, drew water and poured it out before the Eternal,
       and fasted on that day, confessing that they had sinned against the Eternal. (It was at Mizpah that Samuel managed
       the affairs of Israel.) <verse eID="1Sam.7.6"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.7.7" osisID="1Sam.7.7"/> When the Philistines heard that the Israelites had gathered at Mizpah, the
       Philistine ty­rants proceeded to attack Israel. On hearing of this, the Israelites were terrified of the Philistines;
      <verse eID="1Sam.7.7"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.7.8" osisID="1Sam.7.8"/> and the Israelites said to Sam­uel, <q>Do not cease crying to the Eternal
       our God for us, to save us from the power of the Philis­tines.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.7.8"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.7.9" osisID="1Sam.7.9"/> So Samuel took a sucking-lamb and offered it up to the Eternal as a whole
       burnt-offering; he cried to the Eternal for Israel, and the Eternal an­swered him, <verse eID="1Sam.7.9"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.7.10" osisID="1Sam.7.10"/> for when the Philis­tines approached to fight against Israel just as
       Samuel was offering up the burnt-offering, the Eternal thundered loudly that day against the Philistines and routed
       them; <verse eID="1Sam.7.10"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.7.11" osisID="1Sam.7.11"/> they were crushed before Israel, and the men of Israel, pouring out of
       Mizpah, pursued the Philistines and routed them, till the chase passed under Beth-horon. <verse eID="1Sam.7.11"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.7.12" osisID="1Sam.7.12"/> Then Samuel took a stone and erected it between Mizpah and Jeshanah,
       naming it Helpstone. <q>This is witness,</q> he said, <q>that the Eternal has helped us.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.7.12"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.7.13" osisID="1Sam.7.13"/> So the Philistines were subdued; they no longer crossed the frontiers of
       Israel. Indeed, all the days of Samuel the hand of the Eter­nal was against the Philistines; <verse eID="1Sam.7.13"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.7.14" osisID="1Sam.7.14"/> the towns which the Philistines had taken from Israel were handed back to
       Israel, from Ekron to Gath, and their terri­tory was also freed by Israel from the power of the Philis­tines. (Also
       there was peace between Israel and the Amorites.) <verse eID="1Sam.7.14"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.7.15" osisID="1Sam.7.15"/> Samuel managed the affairs of Israel all the days of his life; <verse eID="1Sam.7.15"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.7.16" osisID="1Sam.7.16"/> he went on circuit every year to Bethel, Gilgal, and Mizpah, de­ciding the
       affairs of Israel at all those places, <verse eID="1Sam.7.16"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.7.17" osisID="1Sam.7.17"/> and returning to Ramah, where his home was, where he ruled Israel and
       where he built an altar to the Eternal. <verse eID="1Sam.7.17"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eID="1Sam.7"/>
    <chapter osisID="1Sam.8" sID="1Sam.8"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.8.1" osisID="1Sam.8.1"/>When Samuel grew old, he made his sons manage Israel;
      <verse eID="1Sam.8.1"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.8.2" osisID="1Sam.8.2"/>the name of his eldest son was
       <milestone type="pb" n="314"/>
       Joel, the name of his second was Abijah, and they ruled at Beersheba. <verse eID="1Sam.8.2"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.8.3" osisID="1Sam.8.3"/> But his sons did not follow his footsteps; they turned aside for money,
       they took bribes and tampered with justice. <verse eID="1Sam.8.3"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.8.4" osisID="1Sam.8.4"/> So all the sheikhs of Israel gathered and went to Samuel at Ramah, <verse eID="1Sam.8.4"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.8.5" osisID="1Sam.8.5"/> saying, <q>You are old, and your sons are not following your footsteps.
       Now appoint a king for us, to rule us like all other nations.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.8.5"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.8.6" osisID="1Sam.8.6"/> It displeased Samuel to hear them asking for a king to rule them. So
       Samuel prayed to the Eternal; <verse eID="1Sam.8.6"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.8.7" osisID="1Sam.8.7"/> the Eternal said to Samuel, <q>Listen to the voice of the peo­ple, listen
       to whatever they say to you; for it is not you whom they have rejected, it is I whom they have rejected as their
       king. <verse eID="1Sam.8.7"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.8.8" osisID="1Sam.8.8"/> They are treating you exactly as they have treated me, ever since I
       brought them up out of Egypt, forsaking me and worshipping foreign gods. <verse eID="1Sam.8.8"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.8.9" osisID="1Sam.8.9"/> So listen to their voice; only, give them a solemn warning, and explain to
       them the methods of the king who shall reign over them.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.8.9"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eID="1Sam.8"/>
    <chapter osisID="1Sam.10" sID="1Sam.10"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.10.17" osisID="1Sam.10.17"/> Then Samuel called the people together to the Eternal at Mizpah <verse eID="1Sam.10.17"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.10.18" osisID="1Sam.10.18"/> and gave the Israelites this message from the Eternal, the God of
       Israel. <q>I brought up Israel from Egypt, I rescued you from the power of the Egyptians and from the power of all
       the realms that were oppressing you; <verse eID="1Sam.10.18"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.10.19" osisID="1Sam.10.19"/> and to-day you have rejected your God, who has himself saved you from
       all your calamities and distresses; you have said <q>no</q> to me and claimed a king.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.10.19"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eID="1Sam.10"/>
    <chapter osisID="1Sam.8" sID="1Sam.8"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.8.11" osisID="1Sam.8.11"/> Then he added, <q>Here are the methods of the king who shall reign over
       you; your sons he will take and place them in his chariots and among his horsemen and to run before his chariots;
      <verse eID="1Sam.8.11"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.8.12" osisID="1Sam.8.12"/> he will put them in command of his regiments and companies; some will
       have to plough his ground and reap his harvest, to make his arms and construct his char­iots; <verse eID="1Sam.8.12"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.8.13" osisID="1Sam.8.13"/> your daughters he will take for perfumers and cooks and bakers; <verse eID="1Sam.8.13"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.8.14" osisID="1Sam.8.14"/> he will take the pick of your fields and vine­yards and olive-yards and
       pre­sent them to his courtiers; <verse eID="1Sam.8.14"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.8.15" osisID="1Sam.8.15"/> a tenth part of your arable land and vineyards he will present to his
       officers and courtiers; <verse eID="1Sam.8.15"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.8.16" osisID="1Sam.8.16"/> your slaves, male and female, and the pick of your cattle and your
       asses, he will take and use for his own ends; <verse eID="1Sam.8.16"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.8.17" osisID="1Sam.8.17"/> a tenth part of your flocks he will take; and you yourselves shall be
       slaves to him. <verse eID="1Sam.8.17"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.8.18" osisID="1Sam.8.18"/> Then you will cry out on account of the king whom you have chosen for
       yourselves, but the Eternal will not answer you then.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.8.18"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.8.19" osisID="1Sam.8.19"/> However, the people would not listen to the voice of Samuel. <q>No,</q>
       they said, <q>we must have a king over us, <verse eID="1Sam.8.19"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.8.20" osisID="1Sam.8.20"/> to be like all the other nations, that our king may rule us and march in
       front of us and fight our battles.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.8.20"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.8.21" osisID="1Sam.8.21"/> When Samuel heard all that the people said, he repeated it in the
       hear­ing of the Eternal, <verse eID="1Sam.8.21"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.8.22" osisID="1Sam.8.22"/> and the Eternal said to Samuel, <q>Listen to their voice and make them a
       king.</q> So Samuel said to the men of Israel, <q>Well then, present yourselves before the Eternal in your clans
       and septs.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.8.22"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eID="1Sam.8"/>
    <chapter osisID="1Sam.10" sID="1Sam.10"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.10.20" osisID="1Sam.10.20"/> And Samuel made all the clans of Israel approach; the clan of Benjamin
       was selected by lot, <verse eID="1Sam.10.20"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.10.21" osisID="1Sam.10.21"/> and when he made the clan of Benjamin approach in their families, the
       family of the Matrites was selected by lot, and when he made the family of the Matrites approach man by man,
       <milestone type="pb" n="315"/>
       Saul the son of Kish was selected by lot. But when they looked for him, he was not to be found. <verse eID="1Sam.10.21"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.10.22" osisID="1Sam.10.22"/> So they asked the Eternal again, <q>Is the man here yet?</q> The
       Eternal answered, <q>He has hidden himself among the baggage.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.10.22"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.10.23" osisID="1Sam.10.23"/> Then they ran and brought him forward, and as he stood among the
       people he was a head taller than any of them. <verse eID="1Sam.10.23"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.10.24" osisID="1Sam.10.24"/> And Samuel told all the people, <q>Do you see whom the Eternal has
       chosen? There is not a man like him among all the people!</q> Then all the people shouted aloud, <q>Long live the
       king!</q> <verse eID="1Sam.10.24"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eID="1Sam.10"/>
    <chapter osisID="1Sam.12" sID="1Sam.12"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.12.1" osisID="1Sam.12.1"/>Then said Samuel to all Israel, <q>I have listened to your voice, to
       whatever you said to me, and I have put a king over you. <verse eID="1Sam.12.1"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.12.2" osisID="1Sam.12.2"/> There, the king marches in front of you; but as for me, I am old and
       grey­headed, and my sons are grown­up men among you. I have gone in front of you from my youth to this day. <verse eID="1Sam.12.2"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.12.3" osisID="1Sam.12.3"/> Here I am! Testify against me in presence of the Eternal and of his
      anointed king; whose ox have I seized, whose ass have I seized, whom have I maltreated, whom have I defrauded, from
      whom have I accepted a bribe or even a pair of sandals? Testify against me, and I will restore it to you.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.12.3"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.12.4" osisID="1Sam.12.4"/> They said, <q>You have never maltreated us, nor defrauded us, nor accepted
       any bribe from anyone.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.12.4"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.12.5" osisID="1Sam.12.5"/> So he said to them, <q>The Eternal is witness and his anointed king is
       witness this day against you, that you have found nothing to accuse me of!</q> <q>He is witness,</q> they replied.
      <verse eID="1Sam.12.5"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.12.6" osisID="1Sam.12.6"/> And Samuel said to the people, <q>The Eternal is witness, he who
       equipped Moses and Aaron, and brought up your fathers from the land of Egypt! <verse eID="1Sam.12.6"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.12.7" osisID="1Sam.12.7"/> Now stand there, that I may argue with you before the Eternal and
       recount all the saving deeds done by the Eternal for you and for your fathers. <verse eID="1Sam.12.7"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.12.8" osisID="1Sam.12.8"/> When Jacob went to Egypt, the Egyptians oppressed them, and your fathers
       cried to the Eternal; then the Eternal sent Moses and Aaron to bring your fathers out of Egypt, and settled them in
       this place. <verse eID="1Sam.12.8"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.12.9" osisID="1Sam.12.9"/> But they forgot the Eternal their God. So he sold them into the hand of
       Sisera, commander of the army of Jabin king of Hazor, and into the hand of the Philis­tines, and into the hand of
       the king of Moab, who fought against them. <verse eID="1Sam.12.9"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.12.10" osisID="1Sam.12.10"/> Then they cried to the Eternal, saying, <q>We have sinned, for we have
       for­saken the Eternal and wor­shipped the Baals and the Astartes; but rescue us from the power of our enemies, and we
       will worship thee.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.12.10"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.12.11" osisID="1Sam.12.11"/> So the Eternal sent Jerubbaal and Barak and Jephthah and Sam­uel, and
       rescued you from the power of your enemies on every side, till you lived in safety. <verse eID="1Sam.12.11"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.12.12" osisID="1Sam.12.12"/> Yet, when you saw Nahash king of Ammon coming to at­tack you, you said
       to me, <q>No, we must have a king to reign over us</q>--though the Eternal your God is your king. <verse eID="1Sam.12.12"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.12.13" osisID="1Sam.12.13"/> See, here is the king you have chosen! See, the Eternal has set a king
       over you! <verse eID="1Sam.12.13"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.12.14" osisID="1Sam.12.14"/> If you will reverence the Eternal and wor­ship him and listen to his
       voice and not rebel against the com­mand of the Eternal, if both you and the king who reigns over you are followers
       of the Eternal your God, well and good. <verse eID="1Sam.12.14"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.12.15" osisID="1Sam.12.15"/> But if you will not listen to the voice of the Eternal, if you rebel
       against the command of
       <milestone type="pb" n="316"/>
       the Eternal, then shall the hand of the Eternal be against you and your king.
      <verse eID="1Sam.12.15"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.12.16" osisID="1Sam.12.16"/> Now then, stand and see this wonder which the Eternal is about to
       perform before your eyes. <verse eID="1Sam.12.16"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.12.17" osisID="1Sam.12.17"/> Is it not wheat harvest to-day? Well, I will call upon the Eter­nal to
       send thunder and rain, and you shall know and see what a wicked thing you have done in the sight of the Eternal by
       asking a king.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.12.17"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.12.18" osisID="1Sam.12.18"/> So Samuel called to the Eter­nal, and that day the Eternal did send
       thunder and rain, till all the people were terrified of the Eternal and of Samuel. <verse eID="1Sam.12.18"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.12.19" osisID="1Sam.12.19"/> Then all the people said to Samuel, <q>Pray to the Eternal your God
       for your servants, lest we die; for, in addition to all our sins, we have wickedly asked a king.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.12.19"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.12.20" osisID="1Sam.12.20"/> Sam­uel said to the people, <q>Fear not; you have done this wrong
       indeed; only, do not swerve from following the Eternal, but worship the Eternal with all your heart, <verse eID="1Sam.12.20"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.12.21" osisID="1Sam.12.21"/> and never swerve in search of vain idols which cannot profit you nor
       save you--vain they are! <verse eID="1Sam.12.21"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.12.22" osisID="1Sam.12.22"/> For the sake of his own great credit, the Eternal will not abandon his
       people; for the Eternal has undertaken to make you a people for himself. <verse eID="1Sam.12.22"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.12.23" osisID="1Sam.12.23"/> Besides, for my part, far be it from me to sin against the Eternal by
       ceasing to pray for you; I will instruct you in the good and right path. <verse eID="1Sam.12.23"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.12.24" osisID="1Sam.12.24"/> Only reverence the Eternal and serve him loyally with all your heart;
       for you see what a wonder he has performed in your presence. <verse eID="1Sam.12.24"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.12.25" osisID="1Sam.12.25"/> But if you persist in doing wrong, both you and your king will be
       swept away.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.12.25"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eID="1Sam.12"/>
    <chapter osisID="1Sam.10" sID="1Sam.10"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.10.25" osisID="1Sam.10.25"/>Thus did Samuel explain to the people the methods of the kingdom; he
       wrote them on a scroll, which he deposited in the presence of the Eternal. Then Samuel dismissed all the people,
       every man to his house. <verse eID="1Sam.10.25"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.10.26" osisID="1Sam.10.26"/> Saul too went to his house at Gibeah, followed by the brave men of the
       nation, whose hearts God had touched. <verse eID="1Sam.10.26"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.10.27" osisID="1Sam.10.27"/> But a number of low characters said, <q>How can this fellow deliver
       us?</q> They despised him and they did not offer him any present. <verse eID="1Sam.10.27"/>
     </p>
     <p>* * *</p>
    <chapter eID="1Sam.10"/>
    <chapter osisID="1Sam.9" sID="1Sam.9"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.9.1" osisID="1Sam.9.1"/>There was a man belonging a to Gibeah in Benjamin, whose name was Kish,
       the son of Abiel, the son of Zeror, the son of Becorath, the son of Apliiah; he was a Benjamite, a man of
       substance, <verse eID="1Sam.9.1"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.9.2" osisID="1Sam.9.2"/> and he had a son whose name was Saul, a man in the prime of life and
       stalwart--there was not a man among the Israelites more stalwart than he was; he was a head taller than any of the
       people. <verse eID="1Sam.9.2"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.9.3" osisID="1Sam.9.3"/> Now some asses of Kish, Saul's father, were lost. So Kish told Saul his son
       to take one of the servants with him and go off in search of the asses. <verse eID="1Sam.9.3"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.9.4" osisID="1Sam.9.4"/> They made their way through the highlands of Ephraim and through the
       district of Shali-shah, but failed to find them; they made their way through the district of Shaalim, but the asses
       were not there; they made their way through the district of the Benjamites, but failed to find them. <verse eID="1Sam.9.4"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.9.5" osisID="1Sam.9.5"/> When they reached the district of Zuph, Saul said to his servant who was
       with him, <q>Come, let us go back, in case my father ceases to care about the asses and is anxious about us.</q>
      <verse eID="1Sam.9.5"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.9.6" osisID="1Sam.9.6"/> The servant said to him, <q>But there is a man of God in this town, a man
       who is highly respected; whatever he
       <milestone type="pb" n="317"/>
       says is sure to come true. Let us go there; perhaps he can tell us something about the errand we are on.</q>
      <verse eID="1Sam.9.6"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.9.7" osisID="1Sam.9.7"/><q>But suppose we go,</q> said Saul to his servant, <q>what shall we offer
       the man? Our sacks are empty of bread, and there is no present to offer the man. What have we got?</q> <verse eID="1Sam.9.7"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.9.8" osisID="1Sam.9.8"/> The servant answered Saul again, <q>I have ninepence here for you to give
       the man of God, that he may tell us about our errand.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.9.8"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.9.10" osisID="1Sam.9.10"/><q>Good,</q> said Saul to his servant, <q>come, let us go.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.9.10"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.9.11" osisID="1Sam.9.11"/> So they went to the town where the man of God lived. As they were
       climbing the as­cent to the town, they met some young girls coming out to draw water, and asked them, <q>Is the
       seer here?</q> <verse eID="1Sam.9.11"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.9.9" osisID="1Sam.9.9"/> (Formerly in Israel, when a man went to consult God, he said, <q>Come, let
       us go to the seer,</q> for the prophet of to-day used formerly to be called a <q>seer.</q>) <verse eID="1Sam.9.9"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.9.12" osisID="1Sam.9.12"/> The girls answered, <q>Yes, there he is in front of you: he has just
       come into the town this mo­ment, for the people are sacri­ficing to-day on the height. <verse eID="1Sam.9.12"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.9.13" osisID="1Sam.9.13"/> As soon as you enter the town you will find him, before he goes up to
       the height; for the people will not eat till he comes; he is to bless the sacrifice, and after that the guests
       partake. Go up, then, for you will meet him this moment.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.9.13"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.9.14" osisID="1Sam.9.14"/> So they went up to the town.
     </p>
     <p>
       They had just entered the gate-house, when there was Sam­uel, coming out in their direc­tion, on his way up to the
       height! <verse eID="1Sam.9.14"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.9.15" osisID="1Sam.9.15"/> (Now, the day before Saul ar­rived, the Eternal had whispered to Samuel,
      <verse eID="1Sam.9.15"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.9.16" osisID="1Sam.9.16"/><q>About this time to­morrow I will send you a man from the district of
       Benjamin, and you shall anoint him to be prince over my people Israel; he is to rescue them from the power of the
       Philistines, for I have seen the affliction of my people, and their cry has reached me.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.9.16"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.9.17" osisID="1Sam.9.17"/> So, when Samuel saw Saul, the Eternal reminded him, <q>Here is the man
      of whom I told you, <q>this man shall wield authority over my people.</q></q>) <verse eID="1Sam.9.17"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.9.18" osisID="1Sam.9.18"/> Saul went up to Samuel in the gate-house and said, <q>Pray tell me where
       the seer's house is.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.9.18"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.9.19" osisID="1Sam.9.19"/> And Samuel answered Saul, <q>I am the seer. Go up to the height in front
       of me, for you must eat with me to-day; in the morning I will let you go, telling you all that is in your mind. <verse eID="1Sam.9.19"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.9.20" osisID="1Sam.9.20"/> As for your asses that were lost three days ago, do not worry about
       them; they have been found. But the honours of Israel, to whom do they belong? Are they not for you and for all
       your father’s household?</q> <verse eID="1Sam.9.20"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.9.21" osisID="1Sam.9.21"/> Saul answered, <q>Am I not a Benjamite, a member of the smallest clan in
       Israel? Is not my fam­ily the humblest of all the septs in the clan of Benjamin? Why, then, do you talk to me in
       this way?</q> <verse eID="1Sam.9.21"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.9.22" osisID="1Sam.9.22"/> But Samuel took Saul and his servant and brought them into the
       dining-hall, where he seated them at the head of the guests (who were about thirty in number); <verse eID="1Sam.9.22"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.9.23" osisID="1Sam.9.23"/> then Samuel said to the cook, <q>Bring the portion I gave you, the
       portion I told you to put aside.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.9.23"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.9.24" osisID="1Sam.9.24"/> So the cook lifted the leg and the rump and put them before Saul, and
       Samuel said, <q>There, the flesh is put before you! Eat; it has been reserved for you till the hour appointed, that
       you might eat this among the guests.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.9.24"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.9.25" osisID="1Sam.9.25"/> So Saul ate with Samuel that day, and after they went down
       <milestone type="pb" n="318"/>
       from the height to the town, a couch was spread for Saul upon the house-top, and he lay down to sleep. <verse eID="1Sam.9.25"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.9.26" osisID="1Sam.9.26"/> At day-break Samuel called to Saul upon the house­top, <q>Arise, that I
       may speed you on your way.</q> So Saul got up, and he and Samuel went out into the street. <verse eID="1Sam.9.26"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.9.27" osisID="1Sam.9.27"/> They were walk­ing down to the outskirts of the town, when Samuel said
       to Saul, <q>Tell the servant to go on ahead; but stop here yourself, that I may unfold to you God's mesasage.</q>
      <verse eID="1Sam.9.27"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eID="1Sam.9"/>
    <chapter osisID="1Sam.10" sID="1Sam.10"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.10.1" osisID="1Sam.10.1"/>Then Samuel,taking a flask of oil, poured it over his head and kissed
       him, saying, <q>Has not the Eternal anointed you to be prince over his people Israel? You shall wield authority
       over the people of the Eternal and rescue them from the power of their enemies. And this shall be the sign that
       the Eternal has anointed you to be prince over his heritage; <verse eID="1Sam.10.1"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.10.2" osisID="1Sam.10.2"/>when you leave me to-day you will find two men near Rachel’s tomb on
       the frontier of Benjamin; they will tell you that the asses you went in search of have been found, and your father
       has ceased to care about the asses but is anxious about you; he says, <q>What am I to do about my son?</q> <verse eID="1Sam.10.2"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.10.3" osisID="1Sam.10.3"/> Then, as you pass forward and reach the oak at Tabor, you will be met by
       three men going up to God at Bethel, one carrying three kids, one carrying three loaves of bread, and one carrying
       a bottle of wine; <verse eID="1Sam.10.3"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.10.4" osisID="1Sam.10.4"/> they will salute you and give you two loaves of bread, which you must
       accept from them. <verse eID="1Sam.10.4"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.10.5" osisID="1Sam.10.5"/> After that you will reach God's Gibeah, where the prefect of the
       Philistines is stationed; and as you approach the town, you will meet a band of dervishes coming down from the
       height with lutes, drums, flutes, and lyres playing in front of them while they prophesy; <verse eID="1Sam.10.5"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.10.6" osisID="1Sam.10.6"/> the spirit of the Eternal will then inspire you till you proph­esy along
       with them and become a different man. <verse eID="1Sam.10.6"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.10.7" osisID="1Sam.10.7"/> Now, as these signs befall you, do whatever the occasion demands, for
       God is with you. <verse eID="1Sam.10.7"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.10.8" osisID="1Sam.10.8"/> [[You must go down to Gilgal before me, and I will come down to join
       you there, to offer burnt-offerings and sacrifice recompense-offer­ings; you must wait for seven days till I join
       you and tell you what to do.]]</q> <verse eID="1Sam.10.8"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.10.9" osisID="1Sam.10.9"/> And after he had turned to leave Samuel, God did change his nature. A1l
       these signs oc­curred, that day. <verse eID="1Sam.10.9"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.10.10" osisID="1Sam.10.10"/> Just as he reached Gibeah, a band of der­vishes met him; he prophesied
       along with them, <verse eID="1Sam.10.10"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.10.11" osisID="1Sam.10.11"/> and when people who knew him of old saw him prophesying along with the
       dervishes, they all said to each other, <q>Whatever has come over the son of Kish? Saul among the dervishes!</q>
      <verse eID="1Sam.10.11"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.10.12" osisID="1Sam.10.12"/> <q>Among men of no family!</q> as one local man ob­served. (So it
       passed into a proverb, <q>Saul among the der­vishes!</q>) <verse eID="1Sam.10.12"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.10.13" osisID="1Sam.10.13"/> When he had finished prophesying, he went home. <verse eID="1Sam.10.13"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.10.14" osisID="1Sam.10.14"/> Saul's uncle asked him and his servant, <q>Where have you been?</q>
       <q>In search of the asses,</q> said he, <q>and when we saw they were not to be found, we went to Samuel.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.10.14"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.10.15" osisID="1Sam.10.15"/> Then Saul's uncle asked, <q>Now tell me what Samuel said to you.</q>
      <verse eID="1Sam.10.15"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.10.16" osisID="1Sam.10.16"/> And Saul said to his uncle, <q>Why, he told us that the asses had been
       found!</q> He said noth­ing about the matter of the kingdom. <verse eID="1Sam.10.16"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eID="1Sam.10"/>
    <chapter osisID="1Sam.11" sID="1Sam.11"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.11.1" osisID="1Sam.11.1"/>About a month later, Nahash the Ammonite marched up and besieged
       <milestone type="pb" n="319"/>
       Jabesh-gilead, and the men of Jabesh-gilead all said to Nahash, <q>Make terms with us, and we will be your
       servants.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.11.1"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.11.2" osisID="1Sam.11.2"/> Nahash the Ammonite said to them, <q>I will make terms with you upon
       this condition, that I gouge out every man's right eye. So shall I stamp disgrace upon all Israel.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.11.2"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.11.3" osisID="1Sam.11.3"/> <q>Give us seven days' res­pite,</q> said the sheikhs of Jabesh, <q>that
       we may send messengers through all the territory of Is­rael. Then, if there is no one to rescue us, we will come
       out to you.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.11.3"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.11.4" osisID="1Sam.11.4"/> The messengers came to Saul's town of Gibeah and told their story to
       the people. All the people wept aloud. <verse eID="1Sam.11.4"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.11.5" osisID="1Sam.11.5"/> Saul, who was just coming home be­hind the oxen from the field, asked,
       <q>What is the matter with the people? Why are they weep­ing? So they told him what the men of Jabesh said.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.11.5"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.11.6" osisID="1Sam.11.6"/> The spirit of the Eternal inspired Saul mightily, when he heard this;
       his anger blazed up. <verse eID="1Sam.11.6"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.11.7" osisID="1Sam.11.7"/> He took a yoke of oxen, cut them in pieces, and sent them by the hand
       of messengers all over the territory of Israel, saying, <q>Who­ever does not come forward to follow Saul [[and
       Samuel]], so shall his oxen be treated!</q> The terror of the Eternal fell upon the people, and they gathered as
       one man. <verse eID="1Sam.11.7"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.11.8" osisID="1Sam.11.8"/> He numbered them at Bezek, three hundred thousand Israel­ites and thirty
       thousand men of Judah; <verse eID="1Sam.11.8"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.11.9" osisID="1Sam.11.9"/> then he told the mes­sengers to tell the men of Jabesh-gilead, <q>You
       will be delivered to­morrow, when the sun grows hot.</q> The messengers went and told the men of Jabesh, who were
       delighted; <verse eID="1Sam.11.9"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.11.10" osisID="1Sam.11.10"/> they said to Nahash, <q>We will come out to you to­morrow, and you can
       do whatever you like to us.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.11.10"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.11.11" osisID="1Sam.11.11"/> But on the morrow Saul arranged the peo­ple in three columns, and they
       made their way into the camp during the morning watch and routed the Ammonites till noon­day; the survivors were so
       scat­tered that no two men were left together. <verse eID="1Sam.11.11"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.11.12" osisID="1Sam.11.12"/> [[Then said the people to Samuel, <q>Who says Saul shall not reign
       over us? Bring such men, that we may put them to death.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.11.12"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.11.13" osisID="1Sam.11.13"/> But Saul said, <q>Not a man shall be put to death this day, for the
       Eternal has done a saving deed in Israel this day.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.11.13"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.11.14" osisID="1Sam.11.14"/> Then Samuel said to the people, <q>Come, let us go to Gilgal and
       ratify the kingdom there.</q>]] <verse eID="1Sam.11.14"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.11.15" osisID="1Sam.11.15"/> And all the people went to Gilgal, and at Gilgal they made Saul king
       in presence of the Eternal; there they sacrificed recompense-offerings in presence of the Eter­nal, and there Saul
       and all the men of Israel rejoiced exceeding­ly. <verse eID="1Sam.11.15"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eID="1Sam.11"/>
    <chapter osisID="1Sam.13" sID="1Sam.13"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.13.1" osisID="1Sam.13.1"/> [[Saul was . . . years old when he began to reign, and he reigned for
       . . . years over Israel.]] <verse eID="1Sam.13.1"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.13.2" osisID="1Sam.13.2"/> Saul picked three thousand men of Israel; two thousand were with Saul
       at Michmash and in the highlands of Bethel, one thousand were with Jonathan at Geba in Ben­jamin; the rest of the
       people he sent home, each man to his own tent. <verse eID="1Sam.13.2"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.13.3" osisID="1Sam.13.3"/> Jonathan defeated the prefect of the Philistines at Gibeah, and the
       Philistines heard a rumour that <q>the Hebrews had re­volted,</q> while Saul had the alarm sounded throughout all
       the land, <verse eID="1Sam.13.3"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.13.4" osisID="1Sam.13.4"/> till Israel heard a rumour that Saul had defeated the prefect of the
       Philistines and that Israel was in bad odour with the Philistines. Then the peo­ple rallied to Saul at Gilgal.
      <verse eID="1Sam.13.4"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.13.5" osisID="1Sam.13.5"/> The Philistines mustered to fight
       <milestone type="pb" n="320"/>
       against Israel with three thou­sand chariots, six thousand cav­alry, and infantry as numerous as the sand on the
       sea-shore: they marched up and camped at Michmash, east of Beth-aven. <verse eID="1Sam.13.5"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.13.6" osisID="1Sam.13.6"/> And when the men of Israel saw they were in straits (for the people
       were hard pressed), the people hid in caves and holes and rocks and tombs and pits; <verse eID="1Sam.13.6"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.13.7" osisID="1Sam.13.7"/> many crossed the Jordan into the land of Gad and Gilead. <verse eID="1Sam.13.7"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.13.8" osisID="1Sam.13.8"/> [[Saul was still at Gilgal, and the people were trembling and
     </p>
     <p>
      deserting him. <verse eID="1Sam.13.8"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.13.9" osisID="1Sam.13.9"/> He waited seven days, according to the time fixed by Samuel; but
       Samuel did not come to Gilgal, and meantime the people were scattering from him. <verse eID="1Sam.13.9"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.13.10" osisID="1Sam.13.10"/> So Saul said, <q>Bring the burnt-offering and the
       recompense-offerings here to me!</q> And he offered the burnt-offering. No sooner had he finished offering the
       burnt-offering than Samuel ar­rived. Saul went out to meet and greet him, <verse eID="1Sam.13.10"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.13.11" osisID="1Sam.13.11"/> but Samuel said, <q>What have you done?</q> Saul answered, <q>I saw
       the people were scattering from me, and you did not come at the time fixed, and the Philistines were massing at
       Michmash; <verse eID="1Sam.13.11"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.13.12" osisID="1Sam.13.12"/> so I thought, the Philistines will now pounce on us at Gilgal, and
       I have not appeased the Eternal. Hence I forced my­self to offer the burnt-offering.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.13.12"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.13.13" osisID="1Sam.13.13"/> <q>You have done a senseless thing,</q> said Samuel to Saul;
       <q>if you had obeyed the command of the Eternal your God, which he commanded you, then the Eternal would have
       established your kingdom over Israel forever. <verse eID="1Sam.13.13"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.13.14" osisID="1Sam.13.14"/> But now your kingdom shall not stand. The Eternal has discovered a
       man to his mind, and the Eternal has ap­pointed him to be prince over his people, because you have not obeyed
       what the Eternal commanded you.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.13.14"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.13.15" osisID="1Sam.13.15"/> Then Samuel went on his way from Gilgal.]]
     </p>
     <p>
       Saul numbered the people who were left with him, about six hundred men. <verse eID="1Sam.13.15"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.13.16" osisID="1Sam.13.16"/> Saul, Jonathan his son, and the people with them, remained at Geba
       in Benjamin, while the Philistines camped at Michmash. <verse eID="1Sam.13.16"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.13.17" osisID="1Sam.13.17"/> And raiders issued from the Philis­tine camp in three columns; one
       column took the road to Ophrah in the district of Shual, <verse eID="1Sam.13.17"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.13.18" osisID="1Sam.13.18"/> another column went in the direction of Beth-horon, and an­other
       column in the direction of the hill overlooking the wady of Hyaenas and facing the open country. <verse eID="1Sam.13.18"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.13.19" osisID="1Sam.13.19"/> [[No blacksmith was to be found anywhere in the land of Israel: for
       the Philistines were afraid of the Hebrews mak­ing swords or spears for them­selves. <verse eID="1Sam.13.19"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.13.20" osisID="1Sam.13.20"/> The Israelites all went down to the Philistines, each to get his
       ploughshare, his coulter, his axe, and his mattock sharp­ened . . . <verse eID="1Sam.13.20"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.13.22" osisID="1Sam.13.22"/> Thus, on the day of the battle of Michmash, none of the people with
       Saul and Jonathan had sword or spear--though Saul and Jonathan had weapons.]] <verse eID="1Sam.13.22"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.13.23" osisID="1Sam.13.23"/> The main body of the Philistines then moved to the pass of
       Michmash. <verse eID="1Sam.13.23"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eID="1Sam.13"/>
    <chapter osisID="1Sam.14" sID="1Sam.14"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.14.1" osisID="1Sam.14.1"/>One day Jonathan the son of Saul said to his young armour-bearer,
       <q>Come on, let us cross over to the Philistine garrison on the other side.</q> But he did not tell his father
      <verse eID="1Sam.14.1"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.14.2" osisID="1Sam.14.2"/> (Saul was on the outskirts of Geba, sitting under the
       pomegranate-tree beside the threshing-floor; the people with him numbered about six hundred men, <verse eID="1Sam.14.2"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.14.3" osisID="1Sam.14.3"/> and Ahijah the son of Ahitub, the
       <milestone type="pb" n="321"/>
       brother of Ichabod, the son of Phinehas, the son of Eli, the priest of the Eternal at Shilo, bore the ephod).
       Nor did the people know that Jonathan had gone. <verse eID="1Sam.14.3"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.14.4" osisID="1Sam.14.4"/> Between the passes where Jonathan planned to cross over to the
       Philistine garrison, there was a rocky crag on the one side and a rocky crag on the other: the name of the one
       was Bozez, the name of the other Seneh; <verse eID="1Sam.14.4"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.14.5" osisID="1Sam.14.5"/> the one crag rose to the north in front of Michmash, the other to
       the south in front of Geba. <verse eID="1Sam.14.5"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.14.6" osisID="1Sam.14.6"/> <q>Come on,</q> said Jona­than to his young armour-bearer, <q>let
       us cross over to this uncircumcised garrison; perhaps the Eternal will do something for us, for the Eternal
       never has any difficulty about delivering his people, by means of many or by means of few.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.14.6"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.14.7" osisID="1Sam.14.7"/> His armour-bearer said to him, <q>Do whatever you have a mind to; I
       am with you; your mind is my mind.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.14.7"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.14.8" osisID="1Sam.14.8"/> Then Jonathan said, <q>Look here, we will cross over and show
       ourselves to the men. <verse eID="1Sam.14.8"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.14.9" osisID="1Sam.14.9"/> If they say to us, <q>Stand where you are, till we get at you!</q>
       then we will stand still, we will to not go up to them; <verse eID="1Sam.14.9"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.14.10" osisID="1Sam.14.10"/> but if they say, <q>Come up to us!</q> then up we go, for that
       will be the sign that the Eternal puts them into our hands.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.14.10"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.14.11" osisID="1Sam.14.11"/> So the pair of them showed themselves to the Philistine garrison,
       and the Philistines said, <q>Look at the mice creeping out of their hiding-holes!</q> <verse eID="1Sam.14.11"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.14.12" osisID="1Sam.14.12"/> The men of the garrison called out to Jonathan and his
       armour-bearer, <q>Come up to us, and we will tell you something!</q> Then Jonathan said to his armour-bearer,
       <q>Climb up behind me, for the Eternal has put them into the hand of Is­rael.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.14.12"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.14.13" osisID="1Sam.14.13"/> Up Jonathan climbed on his hands and his feet, his armour-bearer
       after him; the Philistines fell before Jonathan, his armour-bearer despatched them after him, <verse eID="1Sam.14.13"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.14.14" osisID="1Sam.14.14"/> and in the first attack of Jonathan and his armour-bearer they
       slew about twenty men ... <verse eID="1Sam.14.14"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.14.15" osisID="1Sam.14.15"/> A panic spread in the camp, over the open coun­try and among all
       the troops, till both the garrison and the raiders were panic-stricken; there was an earthquake, and then a
       divine access of panic.<verse eID="1Sam.14.15"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.14.16" osisID="1Sam.14.16"/>Saul's sentinels on the outlook at Geba in Benjamin noticed the
       camp swaying hither and thither, <verse eID="1Sam.14.16"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.14.17" osisID="1Sam.14.17"/> and Saul said to the troops with him, <q>Search and see who has
       left us?</q> When they had searched, Jonathan and his armour-bearer were not present. <verse eID="1Sam.14.17"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.14.18" osisID="1Sam.14.18"/> So Saul said to Ahijah, <q>Bring the ephod here</q> (for at that
       time he bore the ephod in front of Is­rael). <verse eID="1Sam.14.18"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.14.19" osisID="1Sam.14.19"/> While Saul was talking to the priest, the tumult in the
       Philistine camp grew worse and worse. So Saul said to the priest, <q>Take your hand off it</q>; <verse eID="1Sam.14.19"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.14.20" osisID="1Sam.14.20"/> then Saul and all the troops with him mustered and went into
       battle; every Philistine’s sword was turned against his fellow, there was a mighty con­fusion, <verse eID="1Sam.14.20"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.14.21" osisID="1Sam.14.21"/> and even Hebrews who had hitherto been on the side of the
       Philistines and had accompanied them to the camp, now turned to side with the Israelites who accompanied Saul
       and Jonathan. <verse eID="1Sam.14.21"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.14.22" osisID="1Sam.14.22"/> Besides that, as soon as all the men of Israel who were hiding in
       the highlands of Ephraim, heard that the Philistines had taken to flight, they too pursued them in the battle.
      <verse eID="1Sam.14.22"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.14.23" osisID="1Sam.14.23"/> So the Eternal delivered Israel that day. The battle swept past
       Beth-horon; <verse eID="1Sam.14.23"/>
      <milestone type="pb" n="322"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.14.24" osisID="1Sam.14.24"/> all the troops with Saul num­bered about ten thousand men, and the
       fighting spread over the highlands of Ephraim.
     </p>
     <p>
       On that day Saul made a vow and laid an oath on the troops, saying, <q>A curse on any man who eats any food
       before eve­ning, till I take vengeance on my enemies!</q> <verse eID="1Sam.14.24"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.14.25" osisID="1Sam.14.25"/> There was honey on the surface of the ground, <verse eID="1Sam.14.25"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.14.26" osisID="1Sam.14.26"/> but when the troops came to the honeycombs, no man put his hand to
       his mouth, although the bees had gone; the troops were in terror of the oath. <verse eID="1Sam.14.26"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.14.27" osisID="1Sam.14.27"/> But Jonathan had not heard his father laying an oath on the
       troops; so he stretched out the tip of the club in his hand and dipped it in the honey, and when he put his
       hands with honey to his mouth, his eyes brightened. <verse eID="1Sam.14.27"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.14.28" osisID="1Sam.14.28"/> One of the men spoke up and said, <q>Your father strictly bound
       the troops by an oath, saying, <q>A curse on the man who eats any food to-day,</q> and the troops agreed to the
       oath!</q> <verse eID="1Sam.14.28"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.14.29" osisID="1Sam.14.29"/> Then Jonathan said, <q>My father has undone the na­tion! Look how
       my eyes have brightened, because I tasted this morsel of honey! <verse eID="1Sam.14.29"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.14.30" osisID="1Sam.14.30"/> How much greater then would have been the slaughter of the
       Philis­tines this day, had the troops only eaten freely of the spoil of their enemies!</q> <verse eID="1Sam.14.30"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.14.31" osisID="1Sam.14.31"/> From noon to nightfall, they struck down the Philistines that day,
       till the troops were exhausted; <verse eID="1Sam.14.31"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.14.32" osisID="1Sam.14.32"/> then the troops rushed on the spoil, seizing sheep, oxen, and
       calves, and felling them to the earth; the troops ate them, blood and all. <verse eID="1Sam.14.32"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.14.33" osisID="1Sam.14.33"/> But when Saul was told, <q>the troops are sinning against the
       Eternal by eating flesh with the blood in it,</q> he said to his informants, <q>Roll a large altar-stone
       here.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.14.33"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.14.34" osisID="1Sam.14.34"/> Saul added, <q>Go through the troops and tell them that every man
       is to bring me his ox or sheep and slay it here; they are not to sin against the Eternal by eating flesh with
       the blood in it.</q> So all the troops brought to the Eternal what each had in his hand, and slew it there. <verse eID="1Sam.14.34"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.14.35" osisID="1Sam.14.35"/> Thus Saul put up an altar to the Eternal; it was the first altar
       that he had built to the Eternal. <verse eID="1Sam.14.35"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.14.36" osisID="1Sam.14.36"/> Then Saul said, <q>Let us go down to pursue the Philistines by
       night and harry them till morning; let us not leave a man of them alive.</q> The troops said, <q>As you
       please. But the priest said, <q>Let us consult God here.</q></q> <verse eID="1Sam.14.36"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.14.37" osisID="1Sam.14.37"/> So Saul asked God, <q>Shall I go down to pursue the Philistines?
      Wilt thou hand them over to Israel?</q> God did not answer him that day. <verse eID="1Sam.14.37"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.14.38" osisID="1Sam.14.38"/> So Saul said, <q>Come here, all you chieftains of the army,
       discover and de­tect the man in whom the sin lies to-day. <verse eID="1Sam.14.38"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.14.39" osisID="1Sam.14.39"/> By the life of the Eternal, Israel's deliverer, though it were
       Jonathan my son, he shall be put to death!</q> Not one of all the soldiers said a word. <verse eID="1Sam.14.39"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.14.40" osisID="1Sam.14.40"/> Then he said to all Israel, <q>You stand on one side, and
       Jonathan and I will take the other side.</q> The army said to Saul, <q>As you please.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.14.40"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.14.41" osisID="1Sam.14.41"/> Then Saul prayed, <q>O thou Eternal, God of Israel, why hast thou
       not answered thy servant to­day? If the sin lies in me or in Jonathan my son, then, O Eter­nal, God of Israel,
       let the lot be <q>urim</q>; but if the sin lies in thy people Israel, let the lot be <q>thummim.</q></q> Saul
       and Jonathan were taken by the lot; the army escaped. Then Saul said, <q>Throw the lot between me and Jonathan
       my son. <verse eID="1Sam.14.41"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.14.42" osisID="1Sam.14.42"/> Whichever
       <milestone type="pb" n="323"/>
       of us the Eternal Lakes, he shall die.</q> The army said to Saul, <q>This must not be,</q> but Saul overruled
       the army, and when the lot was thrown between himself and his son Jonathan, Jonathan was taken. <verse eID="1Sam.14.42"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.14.43" osisID="1Sam.14.43"/> <q>Tell me,</q> said Saul to Jonathan, <q>what have you done?</q>
       Jonathan told him, <q>I did taste a morsel of honey on the tip of the club I was carrying. Here I am! I am
       quite ready to die!</q> <verse eID="1Sam.14.43"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.14.44" osisID="1Sam.14.44"/> <q>God kill me and worse, Jona­than,</q> said Saul, <q>but die you
       must.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.14.44"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.14.45" osisID="1Sam.14.45"/> However, the army said to Saul, <q>Jonathan die!--Jonathan who won
       this great victory for Israel? Never! By the life of the Eternal, not a hair of his head shall fall to the
       ground, for he has con­quered by God's help this day.</q> So the army rescued Jonathan from death. <verse eID="1Sam.14.45"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.14.46" osisID="1Sam.14.46"/> Saul gave up his pursuit of the Philistines, and the Philistines
       went back to their own land. <verse eID="1Sam.14.46"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.14.47" osisID="1Sam.14.47"/> [[When Saul took the king­dom over Israel, he fought against all
       his enemies on every side, against Moab, against the Ammonites, against Edom, against the king of Zobah, and
       against the Philistines; wher­ever he turned, he was victorious; <verse eID="1Sam.14.47"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.14.48" osisID="1Sam.14.48"/> he did great exploits, defeating the Amalekites and rescuing
       Israel from the power of their plunderers. <verse eID="1Sam.14.48"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.14.49" osisID="1Sam.14.49"/> Saul's sons were Jonathan, Ishbaal, and Malchishua; the names of
       his two daughters were Merab, the elder, and Michal the younger; <verse eID="1Sam.14.49"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.14.50" osisID="1Sam.14.50"/> the name of Saul's wife was Ahinoam, the daughter of Ahimaaz, and
       the name of his commander-in-chief was Abner the son of Ner, Saul’s uncle <verse eID="1Sam.14.50"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.14.51" osisID="1Sam.14.51"/> (Kish, Saul’s father, and Ner, Abner’s father, were sons of Abiel).]]
      <verse eID="1Sam.14.51"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.14.52" osisID="1Sam.14.52"/> But all through the reign of Saul there was hard lighting with the
       Philistines, and when­ever Saul saw a man of valour or vigour, he attached him to his retinue. <verse eID="1Sam.14.52"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eID="1Sam.14"/>
    <chapter osisID="1Sam.15" sID="1Sam.15"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.15.1" osisID="1Sam.15.1"/>Samuel said to Saul, <q>The Eternal sent me to anoint you king over
       his people Israel. Now listen to the voice of the Eternal’s words. <verse eID="1Sam.15.1"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.15.2" osisID="1Sam.15.2"/> This is what the Lord of hosts says: <q>I intend to punish Amalek
       for what he did to Israel, when he opposed them on their way up from Egypt. <verse eID="1Sam.15.2"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.15.3" osisID="1Sam.15.3"/> Go and defeat Amalek; massacre him and all that belongs to him, do
       not spare him, slay both men and women, child and infant, ox and sheep, camel and ass.</q></q> <verse eID="1Sam.15.3"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.15.4" osisID="1Sam.15.4"/> So Saul summoned the troops, mustering them at Telem, to the number
       of two hundred thousand infan­try and ten thousand men of Judah. <verse eID="1Sam.15.4"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.15.5" osisID="1Sam.15.5"/> When he reached the town of Amalek, he lay in wait in the valley.
      <verse eID="1Sam.15.5"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.15.6" osisID="1Sam.15.6"/> Then Saul told the Kenites, <q>Be off, withdraw from the Amalekites
       lest I de­stroy you along with them; for you acted kindly to all the Israelites as they came up from Egypt.</q>
       So the Kenites with­drew from the Amalekites, <verse eID="1Sam.15.6"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.15.7" osisID="1Sam.15.7"/> and Saul routed the Amalekites from Telem as far as to Shur on the
       east of Egypt; <verse eID="1Sam.15.7"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.15.8" osisID="1Sam.15.8"/> he took Agag king of Amalek alive, and massacred all the people,
       giving no quarter. <verse eID="1Sam.15.8"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.15.9" osisID="1Sam.15.9"/> But Saul and the troops spared Agag and the best, the fattest, of
       the flocks and herds, and the lambs, though they destroyed whatever property was common and worthless. <verse eID="1Sam.15.9"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.15.10" osisID="1Sam.15.10"/> Then a message from the Eternal came to Sam­uel: <verse eID="1Sam.15.10"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.15.11" osisID="1Sam.15.11"/> <q>I am sorry that I ever made Saul king, for he has given up
       following me, he has not car­ried out my orders.</q> Samuel
       <milestone type="pb" n="324"/> was angry with the Eternal and protested to him all night. <verse eID="1Sam.15.11"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.15.12" osisID="1Sam.15.12"/> Then in the morning Samuel went to meet Saul. Samuel was told,
       <q>Saul went to Karmel, where he has just erected a trophy; he has gone down to Gilgal.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.15.12"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.15.13" osisID="1Sam.15.13"/> When Samuel came to him, Saul said, <q>The Eternal bless you! I
       have carried out the Eternal’s orders.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.15.13"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.15.14" osisID="1Sam.15.14"/> <q>Then,</q> Samuel asked, <q>what is this bleating of sheep in
       my ears? What is this lowing of cattle that I hear?</q> <verse eID="1Sam.15.14"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.15.15" osisID="1Sam.15.15"/> Saul said, <q>They have been taken from the Amalekites; the
       troops spared the best of the sheep and oxen for a sacrifice to the Eternal your God; the rest we have
       destroyed.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.15.15"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.15.16" osisID="1Sam.15.16"/> <q>Silence!</q> said Sam­uel, <q>let me tell you what the Eternal
       told me last night.</q> <q>Say on,</q> said Saul. <verse eID="1Sam.15.16"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.15.17" osisID="1Sam.15.17"/> And Sam­uel proceeded, <q>You may think little of yourself, but
       are you not at the head of the clans of Israel? The Eternal anointed you king over Israel, <verse eID="1Sam.15.17"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.15.18" osisID="1Sam.15.18"/> and the Eternal sent you on a mission, saying, <q>Go and destroy
       these sinners of Amalekites; fight against them till they are wiped out.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.15.18"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.15.19" osisID="1Sam.15.19"/> Why, then, have you not obeyed the voice of the Eter­nal? Why have
       you darted on the spoil and done wrong in the eyes of the Eternal?</q> <verse eID="1Sam.15.19"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.15.20" osisID="1Sam.15.20"/> Saul said to Samuel, <q>I have obeyed the voice of the Eternal. I
       have gone on the mission which the Eternal sent me. I have caught Agag king of Amalek, and I have destroyed
       the Amalekites. <verse eID="1Sam.15.20"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.15.21" osisID="1Sam.15.21"/> But the troops took some of the sheep and oxen, the best of what
       had been doomed to destruc­tion, for a sacrifice to the Eternal your God.</q><verse eID="1Sam.15.21"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.15.22" osisID="1Sam.15.22"/> Then Samuel said,
       <lg>
        <l> Does the Eternal delight in burnt-offering and sacrifice </l>
        <l> as he does in obedience to his word? </l>
        <l> Obedience is better far than sac­rifice, </l>
        <l> to heed him better than fat flesh of rams. </l>
      <verse eID="1Sam.15.22"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.15.23" osisID="1Sam.15.23"/>
        <l> For rebellion is as bad as the sin of divination, </l>
        <l> and self-will as bad as the in­iquity of idols. </l>
        <l> Because you have set the Eter­nal’s word aside, </l>
        <l> he has set you aside from being king. </l>
       </lg>
      <verse eID="1Sam.15.23"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.15.24" osisID="1Sam.15.24"/> Then said Saul to Samuel, <q>I have done wrong: I have broken the
       command of the Eternal and your instructions. It was be­cause I was afraid of the troops, that I did what they
       demanded. <verse eID="1Sam.15.24"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.15.25" osisID="1Sam.15.25"/> Pray pardon my sin, come back with me that I may worship the
       Eternal.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.15.25"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.15.26" osisID="1Sam.15.26"/> But Samuel said to Saul, <q>No, I will not come back with you,
       for you have set aside the word of the Eternal, and the Eternal has set you aside from being king over
       Israel.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.15.26"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.15.27" osisID="1Sam.15.27"/> As Samuel turned away, Saul caught at the skirt of his robe, and
       it tore. <verse eID="1Sam.15.27"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.15.28" osisID="1Sam.15.28"/> Then Samuel said to him, <q>The Eternal has to-day torn the
       kingdom of Israel from you, and given it to a neighbour of yours, a better man than yourself. <verse eID="1Sam.15.28"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.15.29" osisID="1Sam.15.29"/> The Splendour of Israel, he will never lie nor change his mind;
       he is not a man, to change his mind.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.15.29"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.15.30" osisID="1Sam.15.30"/> <q>I have done wrong,</q> said Saul, <q>but pray show me respect
       be­fore the sheikhs of my people and before Israel; come back with me that I may worship the Eternal your
       God.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.15.30"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.15.31" osisID="1Sam.15.31"/> So Samuel turned back after Saul, and Saul worshipped the Eter­nal.
      <verse eID="1Sam.15.31"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.15.32" osisID="1Sam.15.32"/> Then said Samuel, <q>Bring Agag the Amalekite king here to me.</q>
       Agag came to him with
       <milestone type="pb" n="325"/>
       tottering steps; <q>Death is a bitter thing,</q> said Agag. <verse eID="1Sam.15.32"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.15.33" osisID="1Sam.15.33"/> But Samuel said, <q>As your sword has bereaved women, so shall
       your mother be most bitterly bereaved</q>; and Samuel hacked Agag to pieces before the Eter­nal at Gilgal. <verse eID="1Sam.15.33"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.15.34" osisID="1Sam.15.34"/> Then Samuel went to Ramah, while Saul went home to his native
       town of Gibeah. <verse eID="1Sam.15.34"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.15.35" osisID="1Sam.15.35"/> Samuel never saw Saul again before he died, for Samuel grieved
       over Saul. Now the Eternal was sorry he had ever made Saul king over Israel; <verse eID="1Sam.15.35"/>
    <chapter eID="1Sam.15"/>
    <chapter osisID="1Sam.16" sID="1Sam.16"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.16.1" osisID="1Sam.16.1"/>and the Eternal said to Samuel, <q>How long are you going to grieve
       over Saul, when I have set him aside from being king over Israel? Fill your horn with oil; come, I will send
       you to Jesse the Bethlehemite, for I have looked out a king among his sons.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.16.1"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.16.2" osisID="1Sam.16.2"/> <q>How can I go?</q> said Samuel; <q>Saul will hear about it and
       kill me.</q> But the Eternal said, <q>Take a calf with you and say that you have come to sacrifice to the
       Eternal. <verse eID="1Sam.16.2"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.16.3" osisID="1Sam.16.3"/> In­vite Jesse to the sacrifice--I will tell you what to do--and
       anoint the man whom I point out to you.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.16.3"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.16.4" osisID="1Sam.16.4"/> Samuel did what the Eternal told him, and when he came to Bethlehem,
       the sheikhs of the town came trembling to meet him; they said, <q>Does your visit mean good?</q> <verse eID="1Sam.16.4"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.16.5" osisID="1Sam.16.5"/> <q>Yes,</q> he replied, <q>I have come to sacri­fice to the Eternal.
       Consecrate yourselves and rejoice with me at the sacrifice.</q> He conse­crated Jesse and his sons him­self,
       inviting them to the sacrifice; <verse eID="1Sam.16.5"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.16.6" osisID="1Sam.16.6"/> and when they came, and he saw Eliab, he said, <q>Surely the
       Eternal's anointed is before him now!</q> <verse eID="1Sam.16.6"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.16.7" osisID="1Sam.16.7"/> But the Eternal said to Samuel, <q>Do not look at his appearance or
       at the height of his stature; I have passed him by, for the Eternal does not see as man sees; man looks at the
       outward appearance, but the Eternal looks at the heart.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.16.7"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.16.8" osisID="1Sam.16.8"/> Then Jesse called Abinadab, and put him before Samuel; but he said,
       <q>The Eternal has not chosen this one either.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.16.8"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.16.9" osisID="1Sam.16.9"/> Then Jesse made Shammah walk past; but Samuel said, <q>The Eternal
       has not chosen this one either.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.16.9"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.16.10" osisID="1Sam.16.10"/> Jesse made seven of his sons walk past Samuel, and Samuel said to
       Jesse, <q>The Eternal has not chosen these.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.16.10"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.16.11" osisID="1Sam.16.11"/> Then Samuel asked Jesse, <q>Are all your sons here?</q> He
       answered, <q>There is still the youngest, but he is a shepherd with the flock.</q> <q>Send and fetch him,</q>
       said Sam­uel; <q>we must not sit down to our banquet till he is here.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.16.11"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.16.12" osisID="1Sam.16.12"/> Jesse sent and brought him in; he was ruddy, a lad with fine eyes
       and of a handsome ap­pearance. And the Eternal said, <q>Go and anoint him; this is the man!</q> <verse eID="1Sam.16.12"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.16.13" osisID="1Sam.16.13"/> So Samuel took the horn of oil and anointed him among his
       brothers; and from that day onward the spirit of the Eternal inspired David strongly. Then Samuel rose and
       went to Ramah. <verse eID="1Sam.16.13"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.16.14" osisID="1Sam.16.14"/> Now the spirit of the Eternal departed from Saul, and an evil
       spirit from the Eternal scared him. <verse eID="1Sam.16.14"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.16.15" osisID="1Sam.16.15"/> So Saul's courtiers said to him, <q>Here is an evil spirit from
       God scaring you! <verse eID="1Sam.16.15"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.16.16" osisID="1Sam.16.16"/> Let your servants now before you offer a suggestion: let them
       discover some skilful player on the lyre; then, whenever the evil spirit overpowers you, he can play music,
       and you will get better.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.16.16"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.16.17" osisID="1Sam.16.17"/> Saul answered his courtiers, <q>Look me out a man who plays well,
       and bring him to me,</q> <verse eID="1Sam.16.17"/>
      <milestone type="pb" n="326"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.16.18" osisID="1Sam.16.18"/> One of the young men put in, <q>I have noticed a son of Jesse the
       Bethlehemite, who is a skil­ful player, a brave man, a sol­dier, quick-witted, a man of good presence, and the
       Eternal is with him.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.16.18"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.16.19" osisID="1Sam.16.19"/> So Saul sent messengers to Jesse, saying, <q>Send me your son
       David, who is with the flock.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.16.19"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.16.20" osisID="1Sam.16.20"/> Jesse took ten loaves of bread, a bottle of wine, and a kid, and
       sent them by his son David to Saul; <verse eID="1Sam.16.20"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.16.21" osisID="1Sam.16.21"/> and when David came to Saul and presented himself, Saul loved him
       and made him one of his armour-bearers. <verse eID="1Sam.16.21"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.16.22" osisID="1Sam.16.22"/> Then Saul sent to Jesse, saying, <q>Let David enter my service;
       he has won my favour.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.16.22"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.16.23" osisID="1Sam.16.23"/>Whenever the evil spirit from God overpowered Saul, David would
       take the lyre and play music, till Saul breathed freely; then all would be well, and the evil spirit would
       depart from him. <verse eID="1Sam.16.23"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eID="1Sam.16"/>
    <chapter osisID="1Sam.17" sID="1Sam.17"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.17.1" osisID="1Sam.17.1"/>Now the Philistines mus­tered their forces for war; they mustered at
       Sokoh, which belongs to Judah, camping be­tween Sokoh and Azekah at Ephesdammim. <verse eID="1Sam.17.1"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.17.2" osisID="1Sam.17.2"/> Saul and the men of Israel mustered and camped in the valley of
       Elah, where they drew up in battle array against the Philistines, <verse eID="1Sam.17.2"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.17.3" osisID="1Sam.17.3"/> the Philistines occupying the hills on one side and the Israelites
       oc­cupying the hills on the other side, with the valley between them. <verse eID="1Sam.17.3"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.17.4" osisID="1Sam.17.4"/> From the ranks of the Philistines a champion walked forward called
       Goliath of Gath; he was about ten feet high, <verse eID="1Sam.17.4"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.17.5" osisID="1Sam.17.5"/> he had a bronze helmet on his head, and he wore a bronze
       breast­plate of scaled armour, weighing about two hundred pounds; <verse eID="1Sam.17.5"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.17.6" osisID="1Sam.17.6"/> he had bronze greaves on his legs, and a bronze javelin slung
       between his shoulders; <verse eID="1Sam.17.6"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.17.7" osisID="1Sam.17.7"/> the shaft of his spear was as large as a weav­er’s beam, and the
       head of his iron spear weighed twenty-five pounds. (His shield-bearer went in front of him.) <verse eID="1Sam.17.7"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.17.8" osisID="1Sam.17.8"/> He stood and shouted to the forces of Israel, <q>Why form up in
       line of battle? Am not I a Philistine, and you are slaves of Saul? Choose a man for yourselves, and let him
       come down to me; <verse eID="1Sam.17.8"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.17.9" osisID="1Sam.17.9"/> if he can fight with me and kill me, then we will be your slaves,
       but if I overcome him and kill him, then you shall be our slaves and serve us.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.17.9"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.17.10" osisID="1Sam.17.10"/> The Philistine added, <q>I thus defy this day the forces of
       Israel! Give me a man, and let us have a fight!</q> <verse eID="1Sam.17.10"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.17.11" osisID="1Sam.17.11"/> When Saul and all Israel heard these words of the Philistines,
       they were dismayed and daunted. <verse eID="1Sam.17.11"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.17.12" osisID="1Sam.17.12"/> [[David was the son of an Ephrathite belonging to Bethle­hem in
       Judah, whose name was Jesse; he had eight sons, and, by the time Saul reigned, he was an old man, <verse eID="1Sam.17.12"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.17.13" osisID="1Sam.17.13"/> too old to enlist with his three eldest sons, who had followed
       Saul to war. The names of his three sons who had gone to the war were, Eliab the eldest, next to him Abinadab,
       and thirdly Shammah. <verse eID="1Sam.17.13"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.17.14" osisID="1Sam.17.14"/> David was the youngest; the three eldest had followed Saul.]] <verse eID="1Sam.17.14"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.17.15" osisID="1Sam.17.15"/> David used to go to and fro, attending Saul and pasturing his
       father's sheep at Bethlehem. <verse eID="1Sam.17.15"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.17.16" osisID="1Sam.17.16"/> For forty days the Philistine champion went for­ward and took his
       stand, morn­ing and evening. <verse eID="1Sam.17.16"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.17.17" osisID="1Sam.17.17"/> [[Now Jesse said to his son David, <q>Take your brothers a bushel
       of this roasted grain and these ten loaves; quick, carry them to your brothers in the camp. <verse eID="1Sam.17.17"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.17.18" osisID="1Sam.17.18"/> Also, take these ten milk-cheeses to the commander of their
       regiment. Ask how
       <milestone type="pb" n="327"/>
       your brothers are, and bring me news of them. <verse eID="1Sam.17.18"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.17.19" osisID="1Sam.17.19"/> Saul and they and all the men of Israel are in the valley of
       Elah, fighting the Philistines.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.17.19"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.17.20" osisID="1Sam.17.20"/> So David got up next morning, and, leaving the flock in charge of
       a herdsman, he took what Jesse had told him and went as he was bidden. Just as he reached the entrenchment,
       the army going out to the battle-line was shouting the war-cry, <verse eID="1Sam.17.20"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.17.21" osisID="1Sam.17.21"/> and Israel and the Philistines drew up in battle array, army
       against army. <verse eID="1Sam.17.21"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.17.22" osisID="1Sam.17.22"/> So David left his pack­ages in the hands of the man who kept the
       stores, and ran into the ranks, to find out how his brothers were. <verse eID="1Sam.17.22"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.17.23" osisID="1Sam.17.23"/> As he was talk­ing to them, up came the cham­pion from the ranks of
       the Philistines; he was a Philistine of Gath, called Goliath. He uttered his usual challenge, and David heard
       it. <verse eID="1Sam.17.23"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.17.24" osisID="1Sam.17.24"/> All the men of Israel fled from the man in terror, as soon as they
       saw him; <verse eID="1Sam.17.24"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.17.25" osisID="1Sam.17.25"/> said the men of Israel, <q>Have you seen the man who has come
       forward? He has come forward to defy Israel! The king will richly endow any man who kills him; he will give
       him his daugh­ter, and make his father's house­hold free in Israel.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.17.25"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.17.26" osisID="1Sam.17.26"/> David said to the bystanders, <q>What shall be done for the man
       who kills yonder Philistine and wipes off the disgrace from Is­rael? For who is this uncircumcised Philistine,
       to dare insult the armies of the living God?</q> <verse eID="1Sam.17.26"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.17.27" osisID="1Sam.17.27"/> The troops answered him as above, telling him what would be done
       for the man who killed the Philistine. <verse eID="1Sam.17.27"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.17.28" osisID="1Sam.17.28"/> But Eliab his eldest brother heard him talking to the men, and
       Eliab's anger blazed against David. <q>Why have you come here?</q> he asked. <q>Whom did you leave in charge
       of that poor flock in the open country? I know your forward­ness and your self-will; you came to see the
       battle!</q> <verse eID="1Sam.17.28"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.17.29" osisID="1Sam.17.29"/> <q>What have I done now?</q> said David; <q>I merely asked a
       question.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.17.29"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.17.30" osisID="1Sam.17.30"/> Then turning to another quarter he made the same inquiry as
       before, and the troops replied as they had done at first. <verse eID="1Sam.17.30"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.17.31" osisID="1Sam.17.31"/> On hearing what David said, people repeated it to Saul; then they
       took and brought him to Saul.]] <verse eID="1Sam.17.31"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.17.32" osisID="1Sam.17.32"/> And David said to Saul, <q>Let not my lord’s courage fail him;
       your servant will go and fight the Philistine.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.17.32"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.17.33" osisID="1Sam.17.33"/> Saul said to David, <q>You are not able to attack this
       Philistine and fight him; you are only a youth, and he has been a warrior from his youth!</q> <verse eID="1Sam.17.33"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.17.34" osisID="1Sam.17.34"/> But David said to Saul, <q>Your servant used to keep sheep for
       his father, and when a lion or even a bear came and seized a sheep from the flock, <verse eID="1Sam.17.34"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.17.35" osisID="1Sam.17.35"/> I would be after him, I would strike him, and rescue it from his
       mouth; if he turned against me, I would catch him by the chin and kill him with a blow. <verse eID="1Sam.17.35"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.17.36" osisID="1Sam.17.36"/> Your servant has killed both lions and bears. And this
       uncircumcised Philistine shall fare like one of them, for insulting the armies of the living God! <verse eID="1Sam.17.36"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.17.37" osisID="1Sam.17.37"/> The Eternal who rescued me from the paw of the lion and the paw
       of the bear,</q> said David, <q>he will rescue me from the hand of this Philis­tine.</q> Then said Saul to
       David, <q>Go, and may the Eternal be with you!</q> <verse eID="1Sam.17.37"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.17.38" osisID="1Sam.17.38"/> Saul dressed David in his own clothing, put a bronze helmet on
       his head, and clad him in a coat of mail. <verse eID="1Sam.17.38"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.17.39" osisID="1Sam.17.39"/> David buckled his sword over his coat and tried to walk, but in
       vain, for he was not used to such armour. So David said
       <milestone type="pb" n="328"/>
       to Saul, <q>I cannot move with these; I am not used to them.</q> And David put them off; <verse eID="1Sam.17.39"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.17.40" osisID="1Sam.17.40"/> he grasped his club, picked five smooth stones from the stream
       and put them in the shepherd's bag that served him for a knap­sack, took his sling in his hand, and went to
       meet the Philistine. <verse eID="1Sam.17.40"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.17.41" osisID="1Sam.17.41"/> [[The Philistine came on towards David, and in front of him went
       his shield-bearer.]] <verse eID="1Sam.17.41"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.17.42" osisID="1Sam.17.42"/> But when the Philistine looked and saw David, he despised him
       for his youth. <verse eID="1Sam.17.42"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.17.43" osisID="1Sam.17.43"/> <q>Am I a dog,</q> said the Philistine to David, <q>that you
       attack me with a club?</q> And the Philistine cursed David by his gods. <verse eID="1Sam.17.43"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.17.44" osisID="1Sam.17.44"/> <q>Come here,</q> said the Philistine to David, <q>and I will
       give your flesh to the birds of the air and the beasts of the field.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.17.44"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.17.45" osisID="1Sam.17.45"/> Then David answered the Philistine, <q>You attack me with sword
       and spear and jave­lin, but I attack you in the name of the Lord of hosts, the God of the armies of Israel,
       which you have insulted this day. <verse eID="1Sam.17.45"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.17.46" osisID="1Sam.17.46"/> The Eternal will deliver you into my hands, and I will cut off
       your head and give your corpse and the corpses of the Philistine host to the birds of the air and the wild
       beasts of the earth, so that all the world may learn that Is­rael has a God, <verse eID="1Sam.17.46"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.17.47" osisID="1Sam.17.47"/> till all here pres­ent learn that the Eternal does not save by
       sword and spear--the fight is in the Eternal’s hands, and he will put you in our power.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.17.47"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.17.48" osisID="1Sam.17.48"/> As the Philistine then started to approach and attack David, David
       hurried forward to meet the Philistine. <verse eID="1Sam.17.48"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.17.49" osisID="1Sam.17.49"/> Putting his hand into the bag, David took out a stone and slung
       it, striking the Philistine on the forehead; the stone sank into his forehead, and he dropped on his face to
       the ground. <verse eID="1Sam.17.49"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.17.50" osisID="1Sam.17.50"/> [[David overcame the Philistine with sling and stone, stripping
       the Philistine and kill­ing him. David had no sword in his hand.]] <verse eID="1Sam.17.50"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.17.51" osisID="1Sam.17.51"/> Then David ran and stood over the Philistine, drew his sword from
       the sheath and killed him, cutting his head off. When the Philistines saw their champion was dead, they ran
       away, <verse eID="1Sam.17.51"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.17.52" osisID="1Sam.17.52"/> and the men of Israel and of Judah rose with a shout and chased
       the Philistines as far as the entrance to Gath and the gates of Ekron, till the wounded men of the Philistines
       dropped all along the way from Shaaraim to Gath and Ekron. <verse eID="1Sam.17.52"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.17.53" osisID="1Sam.17.53"/> Then the Israelites came back from chasing the Philistines and
       plundered their camp. <verse eID="1Sam.17.53"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.17.54" osisID="1Sam.17.54"/> David took and brought the head of the Philistine to Jeru­salem,
       but the armour he kept in his tent. <verse eID="1Sam.17.54"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.17.55" osisID="1Sam.17.55"/> [[When Saul saw David going out to encounter the Philistine, he
       said to Abner the general of the army, <q>Abner, whose son is this lad?</q> <q>By your life, O king,</q> said
       Abner, <q>I cannot tell!</q> <verse eID="1Sam.17.55"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.17.56" osisID="1Sam.17.56"/> The king said, <q>Find out whose son the youth is.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.17.56"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.17.57" osisID="1Sam.17.57"/> So, when David came back from killing the Philistine, Ab­ner took
       him and brought him before Saul with the Philistine's head in his hand. <verse eID="1Sam.17.57"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.17.58" osisID="1Sam.17.58"/> Saul said to him, <q>Whose son are you, my lad?</q> David
       replied, <q>I am the son of your servant Jesse the Bethlehemite.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.17.58"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eID="1Sam.17"/>
    <chapter osisID="1Sam.18" sID="1Sam.18"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.18.1" osisID="1Sam.18.1"/>By the time that David had finished talking to Saul, Jonathan's soul
       was knit to David's--Jona­than loved him as himself. <verse eID="1Sam.18.1"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.18.2" osisID="1Sam.18.2"/> That very day Saul kept him, and would not allow him to return to
       his father's house; <verse eID="1Sam.18.2"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.18.3" osisID="1Sam.18.3"/> and Jonathan made a compact with David (for he loved him as
       <milestone type="pb" n="329"/>
       himself); <verse eID="1Sam.18.3"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.18.4" osisID="1Sam.18.4"/> Jonathan stripped himself of his robe and gave it to David, along
       with his ac­coutrements, including his sword and bow and girdle. <verse eID="1Sam.18.4"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.18.5" osisID="1Sam.18.5"/> Saul put him in command of troops, and David went about his
       business, proving successful in every commission of Saul; he was a favourite with all the people and with
       Saul's  cour­tiers.]] <verse eID="1Sam.18.5"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.18.6" osisID="1Sam.18.6"/> On their return, as David came back from killing the Philistine,
       the women came dancing out of all the towns of Israel to meet king Saul with tambourines and paeans of joy and
       cymbals; <verse eID="1Sam.18.6"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.18.7" osisID="1Sam.18.7"/> as they danced, the women sang to each other,
       <lg>
        <l> Saul has slain his thousands, </l>
        <l> David tens of thousands! </l>
       </lg>
      <verse eID="1Sam.18.7"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.18.8" osisID="1Sam.18.8"/> This made Saul furious, it irri­tated him. <q>They give David tens
       of thousands,</q> he said, <q>and I get only thousands! What more can he have, but the kingdom itself?</q> <verse eID="1Sam.18.8"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.18.9" osisID="1Sam.18.9"/> From that day Saul kept his eye on David. <verse eID="1Sam.18.9"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.18.10" osisID="1Sam.18.10"/> [[Next day an evil spirit from God overpowered Saul, till he
       raved within his house. David was playing music for him as usual, and Saul had a spear in his hand; <verse eID="1Sam.18.10"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.18.11" osisID="1Sam.18.11"/> he raised the spear, saying to himself, <q>I will pin David to
       the wall.</q> But David evaded him twice over.]] <verse eID="1Sam.18.11"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.18.12" osisID="1Sam.18.12"/> Saul was afraid of David, be­cause the Eternal was with him and
       had departed from Saul; <verse eID="1Sam.18.12"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.18.13" osisID="1Sam.18.13"/> so Saul removed him from his presence and put him in com­mand of
       a regiment, and he went about his business at the head of the troops. <verse eID="1Sam.18.13"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.18.14" osisID="1Sam.18.14"/> In all his movements David proved skilful and successful, and the
       Eternal was with him. <verse eID="1Sam.18.14"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.18.15" osisID="1Sam.18.15"/> When Saul saw how skilful and successful he was, he stood in awe
       of him. <verse eID="1Sam.18.15"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.18.16" osisID="1Sam.18.16"/> But all Israel and Judah loved David, as they saw him going out
       and in about his business. <verse eID="1Sam.18.16"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.18.17" osisID="1Sam.18.17"/> [[Then said Saul to David,<q>Here is my oldest daughter Merab, I
       will give her to you in marriage; only be a brave man and fight the battles of the Eternal</q> (for Saul
       thought, <q>Let not my hand strike him down, but the hand of the Philistines</q>). <verse eID="1Sam.18.17"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.18.18" osisID="1Sam.18.18"/> David said to Saul, <q>Who am I, who are my folk, what is my
       father's sept in Israel, that I should be son-in-law to the king?</q> <verse eID="1Sam.18.18"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.18.19" osisID="1Sam.18.19"/> However, when the time came for Merab, Saul's daughter, to be
       given to David, she was given in mar­riage to Adriel the Meholathite.]] <verse eID="1Sam.18.19"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.18.20" osisID="1Sam.18.20"/> Now Michal, Saul's daughter, was in love with David. When Saul
       was told this, he was de­lighted. <verse eID="1Sam.18.20"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.18.21" osisID="1Sam.18.21"/> (Saul thought, <q>I will give her to him in order to im­peril him,
       that the hand of the Philistines may strike him down. He must make himself my son-in-law now by means of the
       Philistines!</q>) <verse eID="1Sam.18.21"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.18.22" osisID="1Sam.18.22"/> So Saul ordered his attendants to communicate privately with
       David and to tell him, <q>The king is delighted with you, all his courtiers love you; now, then, be the king's
       son-in-law.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.18.22"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.18.23" osisID="1Sam.18.23"/> Saul's attendants said this in the hearing of David. But David
       said, <q>And do you think it an easy matter for a poor man like myself, a man of no position, to become the
       king's son-in-law?</q> <verse eID="1Sam.18.23"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.18.24" osisID="1Sam.18.24"/> Saul's attendants then reported what David had said, <verse eID="1Sam.18.24"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.18.25" osisID="1Sam.18.25"/> and Saul replied, <q>You must tell David that the king does not
       desire any payment for the bride except a hundred foreskins of the Philistines--for vengeance on the king's
       ene­mies!</q> (Saul’s idea was to
       <milestone type="pb" n="330"/>
       make David fall by the hand of the Philistines.) <verse eID="1Sam.18.25"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.18.26" osisID="1Sam.18.26"/> When his attendants told this to David, David gladly agreed to
       be the king’s son-in-law. Before the time fixed, <verse eID="1Sam.18.26"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.18.27" osisID="1Sam.18.27"/> David went off, he and his men; they killed a hun­dred of the
       Philistines, and David brought their foreskins, paying the full toll of them to the king, in order to become
       the king's son-in-law. So Saul gave him Michal his daughter in marriage.<verse eID="1Sam.18.27"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.18.28" osisID="1Sam.18.28"/> But when Saul saw that the Eternal was with David and that all
       Israel loved him, <verse eID="1Sam.18.28"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.18.29" osisID="1Sam.18.29"/> Saul was still more afraid of David. [[Saul continued to be
       hostile to David. <verse eID="1Sam.18.29"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.18.30" osisID="1Sam.18.30"/> The Philistine leaders used to make sallies; and whenever they
       made sallies, David acted more skilfully and successfully than all the officers of Saul, so that his
       reputation stood high.]] <verse eID="1Sam.18.30"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eID="1Sam.18"/>
    <chapter osisID="1Sam.19" sID="1Sam.19"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.19.1" osisID="1Sam.19.1"/>Saul ordered his son Jona­than and all his officers to kill David.
      <verse eID="1Sam.19.1"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.19.2" osisID="1Sam.19.2"/> But Jonathan, Saul’s son, was greatly delighted with David, and
       Jonathan told David, <q>My father Saul means to kill you; now, do take care to-morrow morning, stay in some
       secret spot and hide yourself. <verse eID="1Sam.19.2"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.19.3" osisID="1Sam.19.3"/> I will go out and stand be­side my father in the field where you
       are lying; I will talk to my father about you, and if I hear anything I will tell you.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.19.3"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.19.4" osisID="1Sam.19.4"/> So Jonathan spoke favourably of David to Saul his father. He said,
       <q>Let not the king sin against his servant David; he has not sinned against you, he has acted most loyally to
        you. <verse eID="1Sam.19.4"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.19.5" osisID="1Sam.19.5"/> He took his life in his hand when he killed the Philistine, and
       the Eternal won a mighty victory for Israel. You saw that yourself, and you rejoiced. Why, then, sin against
       innocent blood by killing David for no reason?</q> <verse eID="1Sam.19.5"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.19.6" osisID="1Sam.19.6"/> Saul listened to what Jonathan said, and Saul swore, <q>By the
       life of the Eternal, he shall not be put to death!</q> <verse eID="1Sam.19.6"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.19.7" osisID="1Sam.19.7"/> Then Jonathan called David, and Jonathan told him all this;
       Jonathan brought David to Saul, and he attended him as before. <verse eID="1Sam.19.7"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.19.8" osisID="1Sam.19.8"/> But, when war broke out again, and David marched off to fight with
       the Philistines and inflicted heavy losses on them, till they fled before him, <verse eID="1Sam.19.8"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.19.9" osisID="1Sam.19.9"/> an evil spirit from the Eternal overpowered Saul, as he sat in his
       house, spear in hand. David was playing music, <verse eID="1Sam.19.9"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.19.10" osisID="1Sam.19.10"/> and Saul tried to pin David to the wall with the spear. But
       David slipped aside from Saul, and he drove the spear into the wall. David fled and made his escape. <verse eID="1Sam.19.10"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.19.11" osisID="1Sam.19.11"/> That night Saul sent messengers to David's house to watch it, so
       as to kill him in the morn­ing. But Michal, David's wife, warned him, saying, <q>If you do not save your life
       to-night, you will be a dead man to-morrow.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.19.11"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.19.12" osisID="1Sam.19.12"/> Then Michal lowered David out of the window; away he fled and
       made his escape. <verse eID="1Sam.19.12"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.19.13" osisID="1Sam.19.13"/> Taking their household god, Michal laid it in the bed; she put
       a wrapper of goats' hair round its head, and covered it with the clothes, <verse eID="1Sam.19.13"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.19.14" osisID="1Sam.19.14"/> and when Saul sent messengers to seize David, she said, <q>He is
       ill.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.19.14"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.19.15" osisID="1Sam.19.15"/> Saul sent back the messengers to find David, saying, <q>Bring
       him here to me in his bed, that I may kill him!</q> <verse eID="1Sam.19.15"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.19.16" osisID="1Sam.19.16"/> And when the messengers went in, there was the household god in
       bed, with the wrapper of goats' hair round its head! <verse eID="1Sam.19.16"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.19.17" osisID="1Sam.19.17"/> Saul said to Michal, <q>Why have you deceived me like this and
       let my enemy go
       <milestone type="pb" n="331"/>
       free?</q> And Michal answered Saul, <q>He said to me, <q>Let me go! Why should I kill you?</q></q>
      <verse eID="1Sam.19.17"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.19.18" osisID="1Sam.19.18"/> [[When David fled and es­caped, he went to Samuel at Ramah and
       told him all that Saul had done to him. Then he and Samuel went to stay at Naioth. <verse eID="1Sam.19.18"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.19.19" osisID="1Sam.19.19"/> When Saul was in­formed that David was there, at Naioth in Ramah,
      <verse eID="1Sam.19.19"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.19.20" osisID="1Sam.19.20"/> Saul sent messengers to seize David; but when they saw the
       fervour of the dervishes prophesying, with Samuel at their head, the spirit of God came over the messen­gers
       of Saul till they too prophesied. <verse eID="1Sam.19.20"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.19.21" osisID="1Sam.19.21"/> On hearing this, Saul sent other messengers, and they too
       prophesied. A third time he sent messengers, and they too prophesied. <verse eID="1Sam.19.21"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.19.22" osisID="1Sam.19.22"/> Then Saul grew furious; he went himself to Ramah, and when he
       reached the well at the threshing-floor on the height, he asked, <q>Where are Samuel and David?</q> Some one
       said, <q>Yonder at Naioth in Ramah.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.19.22"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.19.23" osisID="1Sam.19.23"/> So he started for Naioth in Ramah; the spirit of God came over
       him too, and on he went prophesying till he reached Naioth in Ramah, <verse eID="1Sam.19.23"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.19.24" osisID="1Sam.19.24"/> where he stripped off his clothes and prophesied before Samuel
       and lay naked all that day and all that night. Hence the say­ing, <q>Saul among the der­vishes!</q>]] <verse eID="1Sam.19.24"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eID="1Sam.19"/>
    <chapter osisID="1Sam.20" sID="1Sam.20"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.20.1" osisID="1Sam.20.1"/>Then [[David fled from Naioth in Ramah.]] David went and said to
       Jonathan, <q>What have I done? What is my guilt? What wrong have I done to your father, that he is seeking my
       life?</q> <verse eID="1Sam.20.1"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.20.2" osisID="1Sam.20.2"/> <q>Never!</q> said Jonathan, <q>you are not to be put to death! My
       father never does anything, slight or serious, without letting me know; and why should my father hide that
       from me? No, no!</q> <verse eID="1Sam.20.2"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.20.3" osisID="1Sam.20.3"/> But David retorted, <q>Your father is well aware that I am in
       favour with you; so he says to himself, <q>Jonathan must know nothing of this, in case it hurts him.</q> But
       as surely as the Eternal lives, as surely as you live yourself, there is only a step between me and death!</q>
      <verse eID="1Sam.20.3"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.20.4" osisID="1Sam.20.4"/> Then Jonathan said to David, <q>What do you want me to do for
       you?</q> <verse eID="1Sam.20.4"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.20.5" osisID="1Sam.20.5"/> David said to Jonathan, <q>To-morrow is the new-moon festival, but
       I will not sit at table with the king; you must let me go and hide in the field till evening. <verse eID="1Sam.20.5"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.20.6" osisID="1Sam.20.6"/> If your father misses me, then say, <q>David begged leave of me to
       run to Bethlehem, his town; a yearly sacrifice is being held there for all the clan!</q> <verse eID="1Sam.20.6"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.20.7" osisID="1Sam.20.7"/> If he says, <q>All right,</q> then your servant is in no danger.
       But if he is angry, be sure he has resolved upon some mischief. <verse eID="1Sam.20.7"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.20.8" osisID="1Sam.20.8"/> Come now, be kind to your servant, for you took your servant into
       a sacred compact with yourself. If I am guilty, kill me yourself; why drag me to your father?</q> <verse eID="1Sam.20.8"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.20.9" osisID="1Sam.20.9"/><q>Never!</q> said Jonathan; <q>if I find out that my father has
       resolved on some mischief to you, I will tell you.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.20.9"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.20.10" osisID="1Sam.20.10"/> Then David asked Jonathan, <q>Who will tell me if your father
       gives you a rough answer?</q> <verse eID="1Sam.20.10"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.20.11" osisID="1Sam.20.11"/> [[Jonathan said to David, <q>Come, let us go out to the field.</q>
       So they both went out to the field, <verse eID="1Sam.20.11"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.20.12" osisID="1Sam.20.12"/> and Jonathan said to David, <q>O Eternal, the God of Israel, be
       witness that I will sound my father to-morrow about this time, and if he is well-disposed to David, then I
       will send to let you know; <verse eID="1Sam.20.12"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.20.13" osisID="1Sam.20.13"/> and if there is any mischief afoot--may the
       <milestone type="pb" n="332"/>
       Eternal kill Jonathan and worse, if I bring mischief upon you! No, I will let you know, that you may get away
       safely. May the Eternal be with you as he has been with my father! <verse eID="1Sam.20.13"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.20.14" osisID="1Sam.20.14"/> If I survive it, you will show me God's own kindness? <verse eID="1Sam.20.14"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.20.15" osisID="1Sam.20.15"/> And if I die, you will never cut off your kindness from my
       household? No, when the Eternal cuts off every one of David's enemies from the face of the earth, <verse eID="1Sam.20.15"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.20.16" osisID="1Sam.20.16"/> Jonathan's name shall not be cut off from the household of
       David! And may the Eternal requite David’s enemies!</q> <verse eID="1Sam.20.16"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.20.17" osisID="1Sam.20.17"/> Then Jonathan again swore his oath to David, by his love to him;
       for he loved him like himself.]] <verse eID="1Sam.20.17"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.20.18" osisID="1Sam.20.18"/> Jonathan said to him, <q>To­morrow is the new-moon fes­tival, and
       you will be missed, your place will be empty. <verse eID="1Sam.20.18"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.20.19" osisID="1Sam.20.19"/> By the third day, you will be greatly missed. You must go to the
       spot where you hid yon day, and sit down there beside the stone-heap. <verse eID="1Sam.20.19"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.20.20" osisID="1Sam.20.20"/> On the third day I will shoot arrows beside it, as if I were
       shooting at a mark; <verse eID="1Sam.20.20"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.20.21" osisID="1Sam.20.21"/> then I will send the boy to go and find the arrows. If I call to
       the boy, <q>Look, the arrows are on this side of you, pick them up,</q> then come forward; all goes well for
       you, and by the life of the Eternal, there is nothing the matter. <verse eID="1Sam.20.21"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.20.22" osisID="1Sam.20.22"/> But if I tell the boy, <q>Look, the arrows are ahead of you,</q>
       then be off--the Eternal sends you away. <verse eID="1Sam.20.22"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.20.23" osisID="1Sam.20.23"/> And as for the promise we have made, you and I, the Eternal is
       always a witness between you and me!</q> <verse eID="1Sam.20.23"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.20.24" osisID="1Sam.20.24"/> So David hid in the field. And when the new-moon festival came,
       the king sat down at table to eat; <verse eID="1Sam.20.24"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.20.25" osisID="1Sam.20.25"/> the king sat on his seat as usual, on the seat beside the wall,
       Jonathan sat opposite him, and Abner sat beside Saul; but David’s place was empty. <verse eID="1Sam.20.25"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.20.26" osisID="1Sam.20.26"/> That day, however, Saul said nothing; he thought something had
       happened to David, or that he had not had himself purified. <verse eID="1Sam.20.26"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.20.27" osisID="1Sam.20.27"/> But when David's place was empty on the second day, the day
       after the new-moon festival, Saul said to Jonathan his son, <q>Why has not the son of Jesse come to table,
       yesterday or to­day?</q> <verse eID="1Sam.20.27"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.20.28" osisID="1Sam.20.28"/> Jonathan replied to Saul, <q>David begged leave of me to go to
       Bethlehem; <verse eID="1Sam.20.28"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.20.29" osisID="1Sam.20.29"/> he said, <q>Pray let me go, for our clan has a sacrifice in the
       town, and my brothers have ordered me to be there; so, if you approve, pray let me slip away to see my
       brothers.</q> That is why he has not come to the king’s table.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.20.29"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.20.30" osisID="1Sam.20.30"/> Then Saul blazed out against Jonathan. <q>You son of a run­away
       slave-girl!</q> he said, <q>don’t I know that you are a com­panion of the son of Jesse, to your own shame and
       to the shame and disgrace of your mother? <verse eID="1Sam.20.30"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.20.31" osisID="1Sam.20.31"/> As long as the son of Jesse lives on earth, neither you nor your
       kingdom will be stable. Come, send and bring him to me, for he is to die.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.20.31"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.20.32" osisID="1Sam.20.32"/> Then Jonathan answered his father Saul, <q>Why should he be put
       to death? What has he done?</q> <verse eID="1Sam.20.32"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.20.33" osisID="1Sam.20.33"/> But Saul raised his spear to strike him; so Jonathan knew his
       father had resolved to put David to death. <verse eID="1Sam.20.33"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.20.34" osisID="1Sam.20.34"/> Then Jonathan rose from table in hot anger and refused to eat on
       the second day of the month, because his father had insulted him. <verse eID="1Sam.20.34"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.20.35" osisID="1Sam.20.35"/>Next morning, Jonathan went out to the field, at the time he had
       fixed with David; a little lad was with him, <verse eID="1Sam.20.35"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.20.36" osisID="1Sam.20.36"/> and he said to the lad. <q>Run and find the
       <milestone type="pb" n="333"/>
       arrows I shoot.</q> As the lad ran, he shot another arrow ahead of him, <verse eID="1Sam.20.36"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.20.37" osisID="1Sam.20.37"/> and when the lad reached the place where the first arrow lay
       which Jonathan had shot, Jonathan called after him, <q>Isn't the arrow ahead of you?</q> <verse eID="1Sam.20.37"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.20.38" osisID="1Sam.20.38"/> <q>Hur­ry,</q> he called after the lad, <q>quick, do not stop!</q>
       So Jona­than’s lad gathered up the arrow's and came to his master; <verse eID="1Sam.20.38"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.20.39" osisID="1Sam.20.39"/> the lad knew nothing, it was only Jonathan and David who
       understood the meaning of it. <verse eID="1Sam.20.39"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.20.40" osisID="1Sam.20.40"/> [[Then Jonathan gave his weap­ons to his lad, and told him to
       carry them to the town. <verse eID="1Sam.20.40"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.20.41" osisID="1Sam.20.41"/> As soon as the lad had gone, David rose from beside the
       stone-heap, and fell with his face to the ground, prostrating himself three times; then they kissed one
       another and wept with one another till ... <verse eID="1Sam.20.41"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.20.42" osisID="1Sam.20.42"/> And Jonathan said to David, <q>Go away safe; as for what we have
       sworn in the name of the Eternal, the Eternal will always be between me and you and between my offspring and
       your offspring.</q>]] So David rose and went away, while Jonathan went to the town. <verse eID="1Sam.20.42"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eID="1Sam.20"/>
    <chapter osisID="1Sam.21" sID="1Sam.21"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.21.1" osisID="1Sam.21.1"/>David then went to Ahimelek the priest at Nob. Ahimelek came
       trembling to meet David; he said to him, <q>Why are you alone, and nobody with you?</q> <verse eID="1Sam.21.1"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.21.2" osisID="1Sam.21.2"/> David said to Ahim­elek the priest, <q>The king has ordered me on a
       mission, and told me, <q>No one is to know any­thing of the mission on which I am sending you or of my orders
       to you.</q> I have arranged for the young soldiers to meet at a certain spot. <verse eID="1Sam.21.2"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.21.3" osisID="1Sam.21.3"/> Now then, if you have five loaves of bread at hand, or whatever
       you can find, give it to me.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.21.3"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.21.4" osisID="1Sam.21.4"/> The priest replied to David, <q>There is no ordinary bread at
       hand, but there is consecrated bread. If only the young soldiers have kept clear of women</q> <verse eID="1Sam.21.4"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.21.5" osisID="1Sam.21.5"/> David answered the priest, <q>Why, women have been kept away from
       us, as always when I am on the march. The men’s pouches have been consecrated, even though this is an
       ordinary mission; how much more so will they and their pouches be to-day with the bread?</q> <verse eID="1Sam.21.5"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.21.6" osisID="1Sam.21.6"/> So the priest gave him consecrated bread, for the only bread there
       was Presence-bread which had been removed from the presence of the Eternal, to let hot bread be placed there
       the same day. <verse eID="1Sam.21.6"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.21.7" osisID="1Sam.21.7"/> (Now one of Saul's servants was there, that day, detained in
       presence of the Eternal; his name was Doeg the Edomite, he was the driver of the mules that belonged to
       Saul.) <verse eID="1Sam.21.7"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.21.8" osisID="1Sam.21.8"/> Then David asked Ahimelek, <q>Have you not a spear or sword at
       hand? I have not brought my own sword nor my weapon with me, for the king’s mission was urgent.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.21.8"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.21.9" osisID="1Sam.21.9"/> The priest said, <q>The sword of Goliath the Philistine, whom you
       killed in the valley of Elah, there it is, wrapped in a cloth, behind the ephod! If you care to take that for
       yourself, take it; there is no other here.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.21.9"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.21.10" osisID="1Sam.21.10"/> <q>There is none like it,</q> said David, <q>give it to me!</q>
      <verse eID="1Sam.21.10"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.21.11" osisID="1Sam.21.11"/> [[That day David fled away in terror of Saul to Achish, king of
       Gath. But the officers of Achish said to him, <q>Is this not David the king of the land? Was it not to this
       man that they sang as they danced?--
       <lg>
        <l> Saul has slain his thousands, </l>
        <l> David tens of thousands.</l>
       </lg></q>
      <verse eID="1Sam.21.11"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.21.12" osisID="1Sam.21.12"/> David took their words to heart: he wras terribly afraid of
       Achish king of Gath, <verse eID="1Sam.21.12"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.21.13" osisID="1Sam.21.13"/> so he pretended to
       <milestone type="pb" n="334"/>
       them to be insane; they had to hold him as if he was in a frenzy; he thumped on the doors, and let his
       spittle run down his beard. <verse eID="1Sam.21.13"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.21.14" osisID="1Sam.21.14"/> Then Achish said to his officers, <q>You see the man is mad. Why
       bring him to me? <verse eID="1Sam.21.14"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.21.15" osisID="1Sam.21.15"/> Am I in want of madmen, that you bring this fellow to rave in my
       presence? Is this fellow to enter my house?</q>]] <verse eID="1Sam.21.15"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eID="1Sam.21"/>
    <chapter osisID="1Sam.22" sID="1Sam.22"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.22.1" osisID="1Sam.22.1"/>So David went away and made his escape to the stronghold of
       Adullam; when his brothers and all his father's clan heard of it, they went down to him there, <verse eID="1Sam.22.1"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.22.2" osisID="1Sam.22.2"/> and everyone who was in difficulties, everyone who was in debt,
       everyone who had a grievance, gathered round him; he was their leader, and he had about four hundred men
       with him. <verse eID="1Sam.22.2"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.22.3" osisID="1Sam.22.3"/> He then moved to Mizpeh in Moab, and said to the king of Moab,
       <q>Let me leave my father and mother with you, till I see what God will do for me.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.22.3"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.22.4" osisID="1Sam.22.4"/> So he left them with the king of Moab, and they stayed with him
       all the time that David was in the stronghold. <verse eID="1Sam.22.4"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.22.5" osisID="1Sam.22.5"/> But the prophet Gad said to David, <q>Do not remain at Miz­peh; get
       away to the land of Judah.</q> So David went off to the forest of Hereth. <verse eID="1Sam.22.5"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.22.6" osisID="1Sam.22.6"/> When Saul heard that David and his men had been discovered (Saul
       was seated under the tamarisk-tree on the height at Gibeah, spear in hand, with all his officers standing
       round him), <verse eID="1Sam.22.6"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.22.7" osisID="1Sam.22.7"/> Saul said to his officers who stood round him, <q>Benjamites,
       listen! Is the son of Jesse going to give each of you fields and vineyards, or is he going to make you all
       com­manders of regiments and captains of companies--<verse eID="1Sam.22.7"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.22.8" osisID="1Sam.22.8"/> that you have all conspired against me? No one tells me when my
       son makes a compact with the son of Jesse; no one cares enough for me to tell me that my son has stirred up
       my servant to be my enemy, as he is this day!</q> <verse eID="1Sam.22.8"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.22.9" osisID="1Sam.22.9"/> Then Doeg the Edomite, who was in attendance upon Saul's officers,
       replied, <q>I saw the son of Jesse come to Nob, to Ahimelek the son of Ahitub, <verse eID="1Sam.22.9"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.22.10" osisID="1Sam.22.10"/> who consulted the Eternal for him and gave him provisions and
       the sword of Goliath the Philistine.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.22.10"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.22.11" osisID="1Sam.22.11"/> The king then sent for Ahimelek the priest, the son of Ahitub,
       and all his father's clan, the priests at Nob. They all came to the king, <verse eID="1Sam.22.11"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.22.12" osisID="1Sam.22.12"/> and Saul said, <q>Listen to this, O son of Ahitub!</q> He
       replied, <q>Here I am, my lord.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.22.12"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.22.13" osisID="1Sam.22.13"/> And Saul said to him, <q>Why have you conspired against me, you
       and the son of Jesse? You gave him bread and a sword, you consulted God for him, that he might rise against
       me as an enemy, which he does this day.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.22.13"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.22.14" osisID="1Sam.22.14"/> Ahimelek answered the king, <q>And which of all your officers
       is equal to David, a trusted officer, the king’s son-in-law, captain of your bodyguard, and honoured in your
       household? <verse eID="1Sam.22.14"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.22.15" osisID="1Sam.22.15"/> Is this the first time I have consulted God for him? No, no;
       let not the king accuse his servant or any of my father's clan; your serv­ant has not the slightest knowl­edge
       of this affair.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.22.15"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.22.16" osisID="1Sam.22.16"/> But the king said, <q>Die you must, Ahimelek, you and all your
       father's clan!</q> <verse eID="1Sam.22.16"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.22.17" osisID="1Sam.22.17"/> And the king said to his escort, <q>Wheel round and kill the
       priests of the Eter­nal; they were in league with David too, they knew he was running away, and they never
       told me!</q> But the king's officers would not lift their
       <milestone type="pb" n="335"/>
       hands to strike down the priests of the Eternal. <verse eID="1Sam.22.17"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.22.18" osisID="1Sam.22.18"/> So the king said to Doeg, <q>Wheel round and strike the priests
       down.</q> And Doeg the Edomite wheeled round and struck the priests down; he killed that day eighty-five men
       who wore the linen sacerdotal apron; <verse eID="1Sam.22.18"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.22.19" osisID="1Sam.22.19"/> he also cap­tured Nob, the town of the priests, giving no
       quarter, but massacring men and women, children and infants, oxen, asses, and sheep. <verse eID="1Sam.22.19"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.22.20" osisID="1Sam.22.20"/>One of the sons of Ahimelek the son of Ahitub escaped, how­ever,
       a man called Abiathar. He fled to David, <verse eID="1Sam.22.20"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.22.21" osisID="1Sam.22.21"/> and when Abiathar told David that Saul had slain the priests of
       the Eternal, <verse eID="1Sam.22.21"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.22.22" osisID="1Sam.22.22"/> David said to Abiathar, <q>I knew that day, since Doeg the
       Edomite was there, that he would be certain to tell Saul; I am to blame for the death of all your father's
       clan. <verse eID="1Sam.22.22"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.22.23" osisID="1Sam.22.23"/>Stay with me, do not fear; whoever seeks your life must seek my
       life; you are in safe keeping with me.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.22.23"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eID="1Sam.22"/>
    <chapter osisID="1Sam.23" sID="1Sam.23"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.23.1" osisID="1Sam.23.1"/>When David was told that the Philistines were at­tacking Keilah and
       plundering the threshing-floors, <verse eID="1Sam.23.1"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.23.2" osisID="1Sam.23.2"/> David con­sulted the Eternal; he asked, <q>Shall I go and fight
       these Philistines?</q> And the Eternal said to David, <q>Go and fight the Philistines and rescue Keilah.</q>
      <verse eID="1Sam.23.2"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.23.3" osisID="1Sam.23.3"/> But David’s men said to him, <q>We are afraid here in Judah; how
       much more, then, if we go to Keilah against the armies of the Philistines?</q> <verse eID="1Sam.23.3"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.23.4" osisID="1Sam.23.4"/> So David again consulted the Eter­nal, and the Eternal replied,
       <q>March away down to Keilah, for I will put the Philistines into your hands.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.23.4"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.23.5" osisID="1Sam.23.5"/> So David and his men went to Keilah; they fought the Philistines,
       carried off their cattle, and inflicted heavy slaughter on them. Thus David rescued the inhabitants of
       Keilah. <verse eID="1Sam.23.5"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.23.7" osisID="1Sam.23.7"/> When Saul was told that David had gone to Keilah, Saul said,
       <q>God has handed him over to me! He has trapped himself by entering a town with gates and bars.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.23.7"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.23.8" osisID="1Sam.23.8"/> So Saul summoned all the people to war, to go down to Keilah in
       order to besiege David and his men. <verse eID="1Sam.23.8"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.23.9" osisID="1Sam.23.9"/> David knew the mischief that Saul was plotting against him, so he
       said to Abiathar the priest, <q>Bring the ephod here</q> <verse eID="1Sam.23.9"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.23.6" osisID="1Sam.23.6"/> (when Abiathar the son of Ahimelek fled to David at Keilah, he
       came down with the ephod in his hand). <verse eID="1Sam.23.6"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.23.10" osisID="1Sam.23.10"/> Then said David, <q>O Eternal, God of Israel, thy servant has
       heard for certain that Saul intends to come to Keilah, to destroy the town on my account. <verse eID="1Sam.23.10"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.23.11" osisID="1Sam.23.11"/> Will Saul come down, as thy servant has heard? O Eternal, God of
       Israel, pray tell thy servant!</q>  The Eternal said, <q>He will come down.</q><verse eID="1Sam.23.11"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.23.12" osisID="1Sam.23.12"/> Then said David, <q>Will the burghers of Keilah hand over me
       and my men to Saul?</q> The Eternal said, <q>They will.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.23.12"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.23.13" osisID="1Sam.23.13"/> So David and his men, about six hundred in number, got away
       from Keilah and roamed at large; and when Saul was told that David had escaped from Keilah he gave up his
       expedition. <verse eID="1Sam.23.13"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.23.14" osisID="1Sam.23.14"/> David kept to the fastnesses in the desert, and stayed in the
       highlands; Saul searched for him every day, but the Eternal did not put him into his hands. <verse eID="1Sam.23.14"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.23.15" osisID="1Sam.23.15"/> Now David was afraid because Saul had come out to seek his life;
       David was at Horesha in the desert of Ziph, <verse eID="1Sam.23.15"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.23.16" osisID="1Sam.23.16"/> but Jonathan, Saul's son, went away to David at Horesha and
       <milestone type="pb" n="336"/>
       encouraged him from God: <verse eID="1Sam.23.16"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.23.17" osisID="1Sam.23.17"/> <q>Do not be afraid,</q> he said to him, <q>the hand of Saul my
       father will never find you; you shall be king over Israel, and I shall be next you; Saul my father knows that
       well.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.23.17"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.23.18" osisID="1Sam.23.18"/> So they two made a compact before the Eternal; David remained at
       Horesha, while Jonathan went away home. <verse eID="1Sam.23.18"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.23.19" osisID="1Sam.23.19"/> Then up came the Ziphites to Saul at Gibeah, say­ing, <q>Is not
       David hiding among us, in the fastnesses at Horesha? <verse eID="1Sam.23.19"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.23.20" osisID="1Sam.23.20"/> Come down then, O king, as is your heart’s desire, and it will
       remain for us to put him into the king’s hands.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.23.20"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.23.21" osisID="1Sam.23.21"/> <q>The Eternal bless you!</q> said Saul, <q>you have had pity
       on me. <verse eID="1Sam.23.21"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.23.22" osisID="1Sam.23.22"/> Now go and make further plans, find out and make sure of the
       spot where his fleeting foot rests, and who has seen him there; for I am told he is very cunning. <verse eID="1Sam.23.22"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.23.23" osisID="1Sam.23.23"/> Be on the alert, then, ascertain all the hiding-places where he
       lurks, and be sure to come back to me; then I will go with you, and, if he is in the country, I will hunt
       him through all the divisions of Judah.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.23.23"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.23.24" osisID="1Sam.23.24"/> So they started ahead of Saul for Ziph.
     </p>
     <p>
       David and his men were in the steppes of Maon, in the wady of the Arabah to the south of the Jeshimon.<verse eID="1Sam.23.24"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.23.25" osisID="1Sam.23.25"/> When Saul and his men went in search of him, David got word of
       it and went down to the crag that is in the steppes of Maon. On learning this, Saul pursued David into the
       steppes of Maon; <verse eID="1Sam.23.25"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.23.26" osisID="1Sam.23.26"/> Saul moved along one side of the hill, while David and his men
       were on the other side, David hurrying in alarm to get away, for fear of Saul, and Saul and his men closing
       in to capture David and his men--<verse eID="1Sam.23.26"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.23.27" osisID="1Sam.23.27"/> when a messenger reached Saul, saying, <q>Hurry back, for the
       Philistines have made a raid upon the land!</q> <verse eID="1Sam.23.27"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.23.28" osisID="1Sam.23.28"/> So Saul returned from his pursuit of David and went to fight
       the Philistines. Hence the spot was called <q>The Crag of Escapes.</q>
      <verse eID="1Sam.23.28"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.23.29" osisID="1Sam.23.29"/> David retired from it and stayed in the fastnesses of Engedi.<verse eID="1Sam.23.29"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eID="1Sam.23"/>
    <chapter osisID="1Sam.24" sID="1Sam.24"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.24.1" osisID="1Sam.24.1"/>Now, after coming back from his pursuit of the Philistines, Saul
       was told that David was in the steppes of Engedi. <verse eID="1Sam.24.1"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.24.2" osisID="1Sam.24.2"/> So Saul took three thousand picked men from all Israel and went
       in search of David and his men to the east of the Wildgoat crags; <verse eID="1Sam.24.2"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.24.3" osisID="1Sam.24.3"/> on his way he came to some sheepfolds, where there was a cave.
       Saul went inside to relieve himself. Now David and his men were seated in the recesses of the cave; <verse eID="1Sam.24.3"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.24.4" osisID="1Sam.24.4"/> and David's men whispered to him, <q>Here is the day on which the
       Eternal promised that he would put your enemy in your power and let you do what you like to him.</q>
      <verse eID="1Sam.24.4"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.24.6" osisID="1Sam.24.6"/> But he said to his men, <q>The Eternal forbid that I should do
       this to my lord, to the Eternal's anointed!--that I should lift my hand against him, when he is the Eternal’s
       anointed!</q> <verse eID="1Sam.24.6"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.24.7" osisID="1Sam.24.7"/> With these words David restrained his men and would not let them
       attack Saul. <verse eID="1Sam.24.7"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.24.4" osisID="1Sam.24.4"/> But David got up and secretly cut off the skirt of Saul's robe<verse eID="1Sam.24.4"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.24.5" osisID="1Sam.24.5"/> (though afterwards David reproached himself for having cut off
       Saul’s skirt). <verse eID="1Sam.24.5"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.24.7" osisID="1Sam.24.7"/> Meanwhile Saul left the cave and went on his way. <verse eID="1Sam.24.7"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.24.8" osisID="1Sam.24.8"/> Then David also got up and went out of the cave, calling after
       Saul, <q>My lord king!</q> When Saul looked back, David bowed his face to the ground and did obeisance. <verse eID="1Sam.24.8"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.24.9" osisID="1Sam.24.9"/> David said to Saul, <q>Why do
       <milestone type="pb" n="337"/>
       you listen to men who tell you that David means to injure you? <verse eID="1Sam.24.9"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.24.10" osisID="1Sam.24.10"/> Why, you see for your­self to-day that the Eternal put you in my
       power inside the cave; but I refused to kill you, I had mercy on you; I said, <q>I will not lift my hand
       against my lord, for he is the Eternal's anointed.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.24.10"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.24.11" osisID="1Sam.24.11"/> Yes, my father, look here, look at the skirt of your robe in my
       hand! I cut off the skirt of your robe instead of killing you; and by that you may be sure there is neither
       evil nor guilt on my hands; I have not sinned against you, though you are scheming to take my life. <verse eID="1Sam.24.11"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.24.12" osisID="1Sam.24.12"/> May the Eternal judge between me and you! May the Eternal
       avenge me upon you! But my hand shall never strike you! <verse eID="1Sam.24.12"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.24.13" osisID="1Sam.24.13"/> As the old proverb runs, <q>Evil men bring evil on
       themselves</q>; my hand shall never strike you. <verse eID="1Sam.24.13"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.24.14" osisID="1Sam.24.14"/> Whom is the king of Israel after? Whom are you chasing? a cur!
       a flea! <verse eID="1Sam.24.14"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.24.15" osisID="1Sam.24.15"/> May the Eternal be judge and decide between me and you! May the
       Eternal see to it, and defend my cause and free me from your hand!</q> <verse eID="1Sam.24.15"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.24.16" osisID="1Sam.24.16"/> When David had finished saying this to Saul, Saul said, <q>Is
       that your voice, David my son?</q> And Saul wept aloud. <verse eID="1Sam.24.16"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.24.17" osisID="1Sam.24.17"/> <q>You are a better man than I am,</q> he said to David; <q>you
       have done good to me, and I have done evil to you. <verse eID="1Sam.24.17"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.24.18" osisID="1Sam.24.18"/> And to-day you have crowned your kindness to me by not killing
       me when the Eternal had put me in your power--<verse eID="1Sam.24.18"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.24.19" osisID="1Sam.24.19"/>for who lets an enemy go scot-free, when he has come across him?
       So may the Eternal reward you with good for this good you have done to me! <verse eID="1Sam.24.19"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.24.20" osisID="1Sam.24.20"/> Now I know you are certain to be king and that the kingdom of
       Israel is to be settled fast by you. <verse eID="1Sam.24.20"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.24.21" osisID="1Sam.24.21"/> Swear to me, then, by the Eternal, that you will not cut off my
       offspring when I am gone, and that you will not de­stroy my name out of my father's clan.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.24.21"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.24.22" osisID="1Sam.24.22"/> David swore this to Saul; then Saul went home, while David and
       his men went up to the fastness. <verse eID="1Sam.24.22"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eID="1Sam.24"/>
    <chapter osisID="1Sam.25" sID="1Sam.25"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.25.1" osisID="1Sam.25.1"/>[[When Samuel died, all Israel gathered to mourn for him, and
       they buried him in his house at Ramah;]] David then moved down to tbe steppes of Maon. <verse eID="1Sam.25.1"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.25.2" osisID="1Sam.25.2"/> Now there was a man in Maon whose business was at Karmel, a
       wealthy man with three thousand sheep and a thousand goats. He was shear­ing his sheep at Karmel. <verse eID="1Sam.25.2"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.25.3" osisID="1Sam.25.3"/>(The man's name was Nabal and his wife's name was Abigail; the
       woman was shrewd and hand­some, but the man was rough and boorish--he was a Calebite.) <verse eID="1Sam.25.3"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.25.4" osisID="1Sam.25.4"/> When David in the steppes heard that Nabal was shearing his
       sheep, <verse eID="1Sam.25.4"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.25.5" osisID="1Sam.25.5"/> David sent off ten young men; David told the young men to go up
       to Kar­mel, to Nabal, and greet him thus in David’s name: <verse eID="1Sam.25.5"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.25.6" osisID="1Sam.25.6"/> <q>Brother, may you prosper, may your household and all your
       belongings prosper! <verse eID="1Sam.25.6"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.25.7" osisID="1Sam.25.7"/> I hear you have men shearing. Now your shepherds have been
       beside us, and all the time they were at Karmel we never jeered at them, nor did they miss any­thing; <verse eID="1Sam.25.7"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.25.8" osisID="1Sam.25.8"/> ask your young men, and they will tell you that. Let my young
       men therefore find favour with you, for we come to you on a feast-day; give anything you have at hand to
       your servants and to David your son.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.25.8"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.25.9" osisID="1Sam.25.9"/> When David's young men arrived, they said all this to
       <milestone type="pb" n="338"/>
       Nabal in the name of David. <verse eID="1Sam.25.9"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.25.10" osisID="1Sam.25.10"/> But Nabal started up and an­swered David's servants, <q>Who is
       David? Who is the son of Jesse? There are plenty of slaves nowadays all running away from their masters!
      <verse eID="1Sam.25.10"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.25.11" osisID="1Sam.25.11"/> And I am to take my bread and my wine and the meat I have
       killed for my own shearers, and give it to men from--I know not where?</q> <verse eID="1Sam.25.11"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.25.12" osisID="1Sam.25.12"/> Then David’s young men turned away and went back to tell him
       all this. <verse eID="1Sam.25.12"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.25.13" osisID="1Sam.25.13"/> <q>Every man buckle on his sword,</q> said David to his men.
       They buckled on their swords, David also buckled on his sword, and about four hundred men fol­lowed David,
       while two hundred remained with the stores. <verse eID="1Sam.25.13"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.25.14" osisID="1Sam.25.14"/> Now one of the shepherd lads had told Abigail the wife of
       Nabal that <q>David sent mes­sengers from the steppes to greet our master, and he railed at them. <verse eID="1Sam.25.14"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.25.15" osisID="1Sam.25.15"/> But these men were very good to us; we were never jeered at,
       we never missed anything when we were beside them in the fields; all the time we were tending the sheep
       beside them, <verse eID="1Sam.25.15"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.25.16" osisID="1Sam.25.16"/> they were a protection to us, night and day. <verse eID="1Sam.25.16"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.25.17" osisID="1Sam.25.17"/> Now make up your mind, consider what you should do, for there
       is trouble brewing against our master and all his household--such an ill-tempered creature he is, no one
       can say a word to him!</q> <verse eID="1Sam.25.17"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.25.18" osisID="1Sam.25.18"/> Then Abigail quickly took two hundred loaves, two bottles of
       wine, five roasted sheep, two bushels of parched grain, a hundred bunches of raisins, and two hundred
       fig-cakes; she put them on asses, <verse eID="1Sam.25.18"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.25.19" osisID="1Sam.25.19"/> and told her young men to go on in front of her, and she
       would follow (but she did not tell her husband Nabal). <verse eID="1Sam.25.19"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.25.20" osisID="1Sam.25.20"/> She was riding on her ass down the side of the hill, when she
       met David and his men also coming down in her direction. <verse eID="1Sam.25.20"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.25.21" osisID="1Sam.25.21"/> David had been saying, <q>So it was all for nothing that I
       guarded that fellow's goods and chattels in the steppes! Not one of his belongings went a-missing, and he
       has returned me evil for good! <verse eID="1Sam.25.21"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.25.22" osisID="1Sam.25.22"/> God kill David and more than kill him, if I leave the fellow
       a single male alive by to-morrow morning!</q> <verse eID="1Sam.25.22"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.25.23" osisID="1Sam.25.23"/> But when Abigail saw David, she hurriedly alighted from her
       ass, fell on her face before David, and bowed to the ground; <verse eID="1Sam.25.23"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.25.24" osisID="1Sam.25.24"/> she fell at his feet saying, <q>On me, my lord, on me let the
       guilt fall! Let your maidservant address you, pray listen to the words of your maidservant. <verse eID="1Sam.25.24"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.25.25" osisID="1Sam.25.25"/> Ah, my lord, pay no heed to that worthless creature
       Nabal!--he is like his name. <q>Nabal,</q> <q>Churl,</q> is his name, and churl is his nature! Your humble
       servant never saw the young men of my lord, whom you sent--<verse eID="1Sam.25.25"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.25.26" osisID="1Sam.25.26"/>no, my lord, by the life of the Eternal, by your own life, she
       did not! Now, as the Eternal has kept you from the guilt of bloodshed, from taking revenge with your own
       hands, may your enemies and those who try to harm my lord fare like Nabal! <verse eID="1Sam.25.26"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.25.27" osisID="1Sam.25.27"/> Here is a present which your servant has brought to my lord;
       let it be handed to the young men who follow my lord. <verse eID="1Sam.25.27"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.25.28" osisID="1Sam.25.28"/> Pray forgive aught that your humble servant has done amiss;
       for the Eternal will assuredly found a lasting family for my lord, since my lord is fighting the battles
       of the Eter­nal: no evil is to be found in you ever since you were born. <verse eID="1Sam.25.28"/>
      <milestone type="pb" n="339"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.25.29" osisID="1Sam.25.29"/> Men may rise to pursue you and seek your life, but my lord's
       life shall be wrapt up safe among the living in care of the Eternal your God; as for the lives of your
       enemies, he will fling them away, like stones out of a sling. <verse eID="1Sam.25.29"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.25.30" osisID="1Sam.25.30"/> When the Eternal has done to my lord all the good he has
       promised, when he has made you prince over Israel, <verse eID="1Sam.25.30"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.25.31" osisID="1Sam.25.31"/> then you will have no qualms of con­science; my lord will not
       re­proach himself for needless bloodshed, for taking his own revenge. And when the Eternal has prospered my
       lord, pray re­member your humble servant.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.25.31"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.25.32" osisID="1Sam.25.32"/> David said to Abigail, <q>Blessed be the Eternal, the God of
       Israel, for sending you to meet me this day! <verse eID="1Sam.25.32"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.25.33" osisID="1Sam.25.33"/> Blessed be your tact, blessed be yourself, for saving me this
       day from the guilt of bloodshed and from avenging myself! <verse eID="1Sam.25.33"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.25.34" osisID="1Sam.25.34"/> For as sure as the Eternal, the God of Israel, lives, who has
       kept me from harming you, unless you had hurried to meet me, Nabal would not have had one male left him by
       morning!</q> <verse eID="1Sam.25.34"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.25.35" osisID="1Sam.25.35"/> Then David accepted the present she had brought him; he said
       to her, <q>Go up to your home in peace; I have listened to your plea and granted your request!</q> <verse eID="1Sam.25.35"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.25.36" osisID="1Sam.25.36"/> Now when Abigail reached Nabal, there he was, ban­queting in
       his house like a monarch; Nabal was in high spirits, for he was quite drunk, so that Abigail did not tell
       him anything at all till day-break. <verse eID="1Sam.25.36"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.25.37" osisID="1Sam.25.37"/> In the morning, when Nabal had recovered from his wine, his
       wife told him all this, and his spirits sank, he became motionless like stone. <verse eID="1Sam.25.37"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.25.38" osisID="1Sam.25.38"/> Ten days later the Eternal struck Nabal, and he died. <verse eID="1Sam.25.38"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.25.39" osisID="1Sam.25.39"/> When David heard that Nabal was dead, he said, <q>Blessed be
       the Eternal, who has avenged my insult upon Nabal and kept his servant back from evil! The Eternal has
       made Nabal's evil-doing fall back on his own head.</q> Then David sent an offer of marriage to Abigail, to
       make her his wife. <verse eID="1Sam.25.39"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.25.40" osisID="1Sam.25.40"/> And when David's servants came to Abi­gail at Karmel, and said
       to her, <q>David has sent us to you that he may make you his wife,</q> <verse eID="1Sam.25.40"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.25.41" osisID="1Sam.25.41"/> Abigail rose and bowed her face to the ground, saying,
       <q>Your humble servant here is a slave, ready to wash the feet of my lord’s servants!</q> <verse eID="1Sam.25.41"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.25.42" osisID="1Sam.25.42"/> Then Abigail rose quickly and mounted an ass, followed by
       five maids-in-waiting; she followed David’s messengers and became his wife. <verse eID="1Sam.25.42"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.25.43" osisID="1Sam.25.43"/> David also took Ahinoam of Jezreel, and they both became his
       wives <verse eID="1Sam.25.43"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.25.44" osisID="1Sam.25.44"/> (for Saul had given his daughter Michal, David's wife, to
       Palti, the son of Laish, who belonged to Gallim). <verse eID="1Sam.25.44"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eID="1Sam.25"/>
    <chapter osisID="1Sam.26" sID="1Sam.26"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.26.1" osisID="1Sam.26.1"/>Then the Ziphites came to Saul at Gibeah saying, <q>Is not David
       hiding on the hill of Hachilah, overlooking the Jeshimon?</q> <verse eID="1Sam.26.1"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.26.2" osisID="1Sam.26.2"/> So Saul started and went down to the desert of Ziph,
       accompanied by three thousand picked men of Israel, to search for David in the desert of Ziph. <verse eID="1Sam.26.2"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.26.3" osisID="1Sam.26.3"/> Saul camped on the hill of Hachilah, overlooking the Jeshimon.
      David was keeping to the desert, and when he saw that Saul was pursuing him into the desert, <verse eID="1Sam.26.3"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.26.4" osisID="1Sam.26.4"/> David sent out spies and discovered that Saul had reached ...
      <verse eID="1Sam.26.4"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.26.5" osisID="1Sam.26.5"/> So David started and reached the spot where Saul had camped.
       David took a look at the spot where Saul was lying, with
       <milestone type="pb" n="340"/>
       Abner, son of Ner, the com­mander of his army; Saul was lying inside the entrenchment, with the troops
       posted round him. <verse eID="1Sam.26.5"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.26.6" osisID="1Sam.26.6"/> Then David asked Ahimelek the Hittite and Abishai the son of
       Zerulah, Joab's brother, <q>Who will come down with me to Saul, to the camp?</q> Abishai said, <q>I will
       go down with you.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.26.6"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.26.7" osisID="1Sam.26.7"/> So David and Abishai made their way into the lines by night,
       and there lay Saul asleep inside the entrench­ment, his spear fixed in the ground at his head, and Abner
       and the troops lying round him! <verse eID="1Sam.26.7"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.26.8" osisID="1Sam.26.8"/> Then said Abishai to David, <q>God has put your enemy into your
       power to-day; do let me pin him to the ground with his own spear! Just one stroke! I will not need to
       strike him twice!</q> <verse eID="1Sam.26.8"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.26.9" osisID="1Sam.26.9"/> But David said to Abishai, <q>Do not murder him; for who can
       lay hands upon the Eternal’s anointed and be innocent?</q> <verse eID="1Sam.26.9"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.26.10" osisID="1Sam.26.10"/> David added, <q>By the life of the Eternal, the Eternal shall
       strike him, his day of death shall come, or he shall go into battle and be swept away. <verse eID="1Sam.26.10"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.26.11" osisID="1Sam.26.11"/> The Eternal forbid that I should raise my hand against the
       Eternal's anointed! But take the spear at his head and the jug of water, and let us be off!</q> <verse eID="1Sam.26.11"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.26.12" osisID="1Sam.26.12"/> So David took the spear and the jug of water from Saul's head,
       and they went off; no one saw them, no one knew any­thing, no one awoke, they were all asleep, for a deep
       sleep from the Eternal had overcome them. <verse eID="1Sam.26.12"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.26.13" osisID="1Sam.26.13"/> Then David went across and stood on the top of a hill at some
       distance, with a wide space between; <verse eID="1Sam.26.13"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.26.14" osisID="1Sam.26.14"/> and David called to the troops and to Abner son of Ner,
       <q>Abner, will you not answer?</q> Abner replied, <q>Who is that calling?</q> <verse eID="1Sam.26.14"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.26.15" osisID="1Sam.26.15"/> And David said to Abner, <q>Are you not a champion? Who in
       Israel is like you? Why then have you not kept guard over your lord the king? Some one got in to murder
       the king your lord! <verse eID="1Sam.26.15"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.26.16" osisID="1Sam.26.16"/> This is a bad business. By the life of the Eternal, you
       deserve to die for failing to keep guard over your lord, over the Eternal's anointed! Look here, see
       where the king’s spear is, and the jug of water that was beside his head!</q> <verse eID="1Sam.26.16"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.26.17" osisID="1Sam.26.17"/> Saul recognized David's voice; he said, <q>Is that your voice,
       my son David?</q> David said, <q>It is my voice, my lord, O king.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.26.17"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.26.18" osisID="1Sam.26.18"/> And he went on; <q>Why is my lord pursuing his servant? What
       have I done? What guilt stains my hands? <verse eID="1Sam.26.18"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.26.19" osisID="1Sam.26.19"/> Pray let my lord listen to what his servant says. If it is
       the Eternal who has roused you against me, may he be propi­tiated by an offering! But if it be men, a curse
       on them in the presence of the Eternal!--for they have banished me this day from all contact with the
       Eternal's own land, bidding me go and worship other gods. <verse eID="1Sam.26.19"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.26.20" osisID="1Sam.26.20"/> Oh, may my blood not fall to the ground far from the
       Eternal's presence!--for the king of Israel is out to seek my life, like a vulture hunting a partridge on
       the hills.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.26.20"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.26.21" osisID="1Sam.26.21"/> Then Saul said, <q>I have done wrong: come back, David my son,
       I will never hurt you again, since you held my life sacred this day. I have acted senselessly, I have gone
       far astray.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.26.21"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.26.22" osisID="1Sam.26.22"/> David answered, <q>Here is the king’s spear; let one of the
       young men come across and fetch it. <verse eID="1Sam.26.22"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.26.23" osisID="1Sam.26.23"/> May the Eternal reward each of us for his honesty and
       fidelity! The
       <milestone type="pb" n="341"/>
       Eternal put you in my power to-day, and I refused to raise my hand against the Eternal's anointed. <verse eID="1Sam.26.23"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.26.24" osisID="1Sam.26.24"/> Now, as I set great store by your life to-day, so may the
       Eternal set great store by my life and rescue me from all distress!</q> <verse eID="1Sam.26.24"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.26.25" osisID="1Sam.26.25"/> Then said Saul to David, <q>A blessing on you, David my son!
       You will do great things, and you are sure to win.</q> So David went away and Saul returned home. <verse eID="1Sam.26.25"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eID="1Sam.26"/>
    <chapter osisID="1Sam.27" sID="1Sam.27"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.27.1" osisID="1Sam.27.1"/>David said to himself, <q>I shall be killed by Saul some day;
       the only thing for me is to escape to the land of the Philistines; then Saul will despair of searching for
       me any longer within the bound­aries of Israel, and I shall escape from his grasp.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.27.1"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.27.2" osisID="1Sam.27.2"/> So David started across country, he and the six hundred men who
       were with him, and they went to Achish the son of Maoch, king of Gath. <verse eID="1Sam.27.2"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.27.3" osisID="1Sam.27.3"/> David stayed with Achish at Gath, he and his men, every man
       with his household, and David with his two wives, Ahinoam the Jezreelitess, and Abigail the Karmelitess
       who had been Nabal's wife. <verse eID="1Sam.27.3"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.27.4" osisID="1Sam.27.4"/> When Saul was told that David had fled to Gath, he searched for
       him no longer. <verse eID="1Sam.27.4"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.27.5" osisID="1Sam.27.5"/> Then said David to Achish, <q>If you will grant me a favour,
       let me settle in one of the towns in the open country, that I may stay there. Why should your servant live
       in the royal town beside you?</q> <verse eID="1Sam.27.5"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.27.6" osisID="1Sam.27.6"/> Then Achish gave him Ziklag; that is why Ziklag belongs to the
       kings of Judah to this very day. <verse eID="1Sam.27.6"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.27.7" osisID="1Sam.27.7"/> The length of time that David stayed at Ziklag in the open
       country of the Philistines was a year and four months. <verse eID="1Sam.27.7"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.27.8" osisID="1Sam.27.8"/> Now David and his men made raids upon the Geshurites, the
       Gizrites, and the Amalekites, who inhabit the country stretching from Telam in the direction of Shur,
       towards the land of Egypt. <verse eID="1Sam.27.8"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.27.9" osisID="1Sam.27.9"/> When David conquered a country, he left neither men nor women
       alive; he seized sheep, oxen, asses, camels, and cloth­ing, and made his way back to Achish. <verse eID="1Sam.27.9"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.27.10" osisID="1Sam.27.10"/> Achish would ask, <q>Where have you been raiding to-day?</q>
       David would answer, <q>against the southern part of Judah,</q> or <q>against the south­ern tract of the
       Jerahmeelites,</q> or <q>against the southern tract of the Kenites.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.27.10"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.27.11" osisID="1Sam.27.11"/> David never left a man or woman alive, to be brought to Gath,
       <q>in case,</q> he thought, <q>they may betray us.</q> So David acted, such was his practice all the time
       he stayed in the country of the Philistines; <verse eID="1Sam.27.11"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.27.12" osisID="1Sam.27.12"/> and Achish trusted David, thinking that as he had brought
       himself into bad odour with Israel his own people, he would always remain his vassal. <verse eID="1Sam.27.12"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eID="1Sam.27"/>
    <chapter osisID="1Sam.28" sID="1Sam.28"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.28.1" osisID="1Sam.28.1"/>During these days the Philistines mustered their forces for war,
       to fight against Israel, and Achish said to David, <q>Be sure of this, you must march out with me in the
       army, you and your men.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.28.1"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.28.2" osisID="1Sam.28.2"/> <q>Very well,</q> said David to Achish, <q>you will now learn
       what your servant can do.</q> So Achish said to David, <q>Then I make you captain of my body­guard for
       life.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.28.2"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eID="1Sam.28"/>
    <chapter osisID="1Sam.29" sID="1Sam.29"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.29.1" osisID="1Sam.29.1"/>The Philistines mustered all their forces at Aphek, the
       Israelites camping beside the fountain at Jezreel. <verse eID="1Sam.29.1"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.29.2" osisID="1Sam.29.2"/> The Philistine tyrants were marching past by companies and
       regi­ments, David and his men in the rearguard with Achish, <verse eID="1Sam.29.2"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.29.3" osisID="1Sam.29.3"/> when
       <milestone type="pb" n="342"/>
       the Philistine authorities asked, <q>Who are these Hebrews?</q> Achish said to the Philistine
       authorities, <q>This is David, a servant of Saul king of Israel, who has been with me here for two years;
       I have never found anything wrong with him from the time he joined me up till now.</q>
      <verse eID="1Sam.29.3"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.29.4" osisID="1Sam.29.4"/> But the Philistine au­thorities were angry with him; the
       Philistine authorities said to him, <q>Send the man back, make him return to the post you assigned him; he
       must not march down with us to battle, lest he thwart us when we are at war. How could this fellow best
       appease his master? Surely by letting him have the heads of our men there! <verse eID="1Sam.29.4"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.29.5" osisID="1Sam.29.5"/> Is this not the David of whom they sang to each other as they
       danced?--
       <lg>
        <l> Saul has slain his thousands, </l>
        <l> David tens of thousands!</l>
       </lg></q> <verse eID="1Sam.29.5"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.29.6" osisID="1Sam.29.6"/> So Achish called David. <q>By the life of the Eternal,</q> he
       said, <q>you are an honest fellow, and to my mind it is right that you should share all my enterprises in
       war, for I have never found anything wrong with you from the time you came to me up till now. But the
       tyrants do not approve of you. <verse eID="1Sam.29.6"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.29.7" osisID="1Sam.29.7"/> So go back, and go peaceably, not to dis­please the Philistine
       tyrants.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.29.7"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.29.8" osisID="1Sam.29.8"/> <q>But what have I done?</q> said David to Achish. <q>What
       fault have you found with your servant, all the time I have been in your service down to this day, that I
       may not go and fight against the enemies of my lord the king?</q> <verse eID="1Sam.29.8"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.29.9" osisID="1Sam.29.9"/> Achish an­swered David, <q>I know, you are as blameless to my
       mind as an angel of God. But the Philistine authorities have de­clared that you must not accompany us to
       battle. <verse eID="1Sam.29.9"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.29.10" osisID="1Sam.29.10"/> So rise in the morning, you and the servants of your lord who
       came with you, and be off to the place I assigned you; harbour no evil design, for to my mind you are
       honest; but as soon as you get up in the morning, as soon as it is light, be off.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.29.10"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.29.11" osisID="1Sam.29.11"/> So David made an early start in the morning, he and his men,
       to return to the land of the Philistines. The Philistines marched up to Jezreel. <verse eID="1Sam.29.11"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eID="1Sam.29"/>
    <chapter osisID="1Sam.30" sID="1Sam.30"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.30.1" osisID="1Sam.30.1"/>Now by the time David and his men reached Ziklag on the third
       day, the Amalekites had raided the Negeb and Zik­lag; they had stormed Ziklag and burned it down, <verse eID="1Sam.30.1"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.30.2" osisID="1Sam.30.2"/> taking prisoners the women and all in the town, young and old.
       Instead of kill­ing anyone, they carried them off and made away. <verse eID="1Sam.30.2"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.30.3" osisID="1Sam.30.3"/> So when David and his men reached the town, there it lay,
       burned down; their wives, their sons, and their daughters had been taken pris­oners! <verse eID="1Sam.30.3"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.30.5" osisID="1Sam.30.5"/> David's two wives had also been taken prisoners, Ahinoam the
       Jezreelitess and Abi­gail, once wife of Nabal the Karmelite. <verse eID="1Sam.30.5"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.30.4" osisID="1Sam.30.4"/> Then David and his men wept aloud, till they could weep no
       more. <verse eID="1Sam.30.4"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.30.6" osisID="1Sam.30.6"/> David was in serious difficulties; the men spoke of stoning
       him, for their souls were sore, every man for his sons and daughters. But David relied on the Eternal his
       God and took courage. <verse eID="1Sam.30.6"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.30.7" osisID="1Sam.30.7"/> He said to Abiathar the priest, the son of Ahimelek, <q>Bring
       me the ephod here.</q> So Abiathar brought the ephod to David, <verse eID="1Sam.30.7"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.30.8" osisID="1Sam.30.8"/> and David consulted the Eternal; he asked, <q>Shall I pursue
       these raiders? Shall I overtake them?</q> The answer was, <q>Pursue them; you will be sure to overtake
       them, you will be sure to effect
       <milestone type="pb" n="343"/>
       a rescue.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.30.8"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.30.9" osisID="1Sam.30.9"/> So David went off, he and the six hundred men who were with
       him; they reached the wady of Besor, where those who had to be left behind remained; two hundred were
       left behind, too tired to cross the wady of Besor. <verse eID="1Sam.30.9"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.30.10" osisID="1Sam.30.10"/> Mean­time David and four hundred men went on with the
       pursuit. <verse eID="1Sam.30.10"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.30.11" osisID="1Sam.30.11"/> The troops found an Egyptian in the prairie, and when they
       took him to David, they gave him food to eat and water to drink, <verse eID="1Sam.30.11"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.30.12" osisID="1Sam.30.12"/> they gave him a piece of fig-cake and two clusters of
       raisins; after eating, he revived, for he had neither eaten bread nor drunk water for three days and
       three nights. <verse eID="1Sam.30.12"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.30.13" osisID="1Sam.30.13"/> Then David said to him, <q>To whom do you belong? Where do
       you come from?</q> He said, <q>I am an Egyptian lad, the servant of an Amalekite; my master aban­doned me
       because I turned ill three days ago. <verse eID="1Sam.30.13"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.30.14" osisID="1Sam.30.14"/> We raided the southern tract of the Kerethites, the southern
       tract belonging to Judah, and the southern tract of Caleb; we also burned down Ziklag.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.30.14"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.30.15" osisID="1Sam.30.15"/> David said to him, <q>Will you take me down to these
       raiders?</q> He said, <q>Swear by God that you will neither kill me nor hand me over to my master, and I
       will take you down to these raiders.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.30.15"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.30.16" osisID="1Sam.30.16"/> When he took David down, there they were, scattered over all
       the country, eating and drinking and making merry over the enormous spoil they had taken from all the
       land of the Philistines and from the land of Judah! <verse eID="1Sam.30.16"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.30.17" osisID="1Sam.30.17"/> David harried them from twilight to evening, in order to
       wipe them out; not a man escaped, except four hun­dred youths who rode on camels and got clear away. <verse eID="1Sam.30.17"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.30.18" osisID="1Sam.30.18"/> David re­covered all whom the Amalekites had captured; he
       rescued his own two wives, <verse eID="1Sam.30.18"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.30.19" osisID="1Sam.30.19"/> and not one was missing, young or old, sons or daughters,
       nothing of the spoil or of anything that had been captured; David brought it all back. <verse eID="1Sam.30.19"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.30.20" osisID="1Sam.30.20"/> He also captured all the flocks and herds, and the people
       drove them in front of him, shouting; <q>This is David’s spoil!</q>
      <verse eID="1Sam.30.20"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.30.21" osisID="1Sam.30.21"/> Then David came to the two hundred men who had been too
       tired to follow him, so that he had to leave them behind at the wady of Besor; they came forward to meet
       David and the troops with him, and on draw­ing near they saluted the com­pany. <verse eID="1Sam.30.21"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.30.22" osisID="1Sam.30.22"/> But the scoundrels and low creatures in David's com­pany all
       declared, <q>Since they did not march along with us, we will not give them any of the spoil we have
       recovered--ex­cept that every man can have his wife and children to take home with him.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.30.22"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.30.23" osisID="1Sam.30.23"/> David said, <q>You must not do this, brothers, after what
      the Eternal has done for us, preserving us and hand­ing over the invaders to us. <verse eID="1Sam.30.23"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.30.24" osisID="1Sam.30.24"/> Who would obey such an order? No,
       <lg>
        <l> As is the share of the fighting man, </l>
        <l> So is the share of the man who stays by the stores; </l>
       </lg>
       they shall share alike.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.30.24"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.30.25" osisID="1Sam.30.25"/> (From that day on, he made this a rule and precedent for
       Israel; it is so to this day.) <verse eID="1Sam.30.25"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.30.26" osisID="1Sam.30.26"/> On arriving at Ziklag, David sent some of the spoil to the
       sheikhs of Judah, according to their towns, saying, <q>Here is a present for you, from the spoil of the
       enemies of the Eternal</q>; <verse eID="1Sam.30.26"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.30.27" osisID="1Sam.30.27"/> he sent this present to those in Bethuel, to those in
       Ramoth of the Negeb, to those in Jattir, <verse eID="1Sam.30.27"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.30.28" osisID="1Sam.30.28"/> to those in Aroer, to
       <milestone type="pb" n="344"/>
       those in Siphmoth, to those in Eshtemoa, <verse eID="1Sam.30.28"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.30.29" osisID="1Sam.30.29"/> to those in Karmel, to those in the towns of the
       Jerahmeelites and the Kenites, <verse eID="1Sam.30.29"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.30.30" osisID="1Sam.30.30"/> to those in Hormah, to those in Beersheba, to those in
       Ether, to those in Hebron, <verse eID="1Sam.30.30"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.30.31" osisID="1Sam.30.31"/> and to all the places where David and his men had been
       accustomed to stay. <verse eID="1Sam.30.11"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eID="1Sam.30"/>
    <chapter osisID="1Sam.28" sID="1Sam.28"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.28.3" osisID="1Sam.28.3"/>When Samuel had died, all Israel had mourned for him and buried
       him in his own town of Ramah.   Now Saul had cleared the mediums and wizards out of the country. <verse eID="1Sam.28.3"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.28.4" osisID="1Sam.28.4"/> But when the Philistines mustered and went into camp at
       Shunem, and when Saul mustered all Is­rael to encamp at Gilboa, <verse eID="1Sam.28.4"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.28.5" osisID="1Sam.28.5"/> Saul was afraid, and, his heart trembling with terror at the
       sight of the Philistine army, <verse eID="1Sam.28.5"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.28.6" osisID="1Sam.28.6"/> he consulted the Eternal; but the Eternal would not answer him
       either by dreams or by the sacred lot or by prophets. <verse eID="1Sam.28.6"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.28.7" osisID="1Sam.28.7"/> Then Saul said to his courtiers, <q>Find me a witch, that I
       may go and consult her.</q> His courtiers said, <q>There is a witch at Endor.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.28.7"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.28.8" osisID="1Sam.28.8"/> So Saul, dis­guising himself and changing his clothes, went
       with two men to the woman by night; he said to her, <q>Inquire for me as a medium; bring me up the ghost
       of some one whom I name to you.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.28.8"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.28.9" osisID="1Sam.28.9"/> The woman said to him, <q>You know what Saul has done, cutting
       mediums and wizards out of the country! Why, then, are you laying a trap for my life, to have me put to
       death?</q> <verse eID="1Sam.28.9"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.28.10" osisID="1Sam.28.10"/> Then Saul swore to her by the Eternal, <q>By the life of the
       Eternal, this will not involve you in any guilt!</q> <verse eID="1Sam.28.10"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.28.11" osisID="1Sam.28.11"/> So the woman said, <q>Whom shall I bring up for you?</q>
      <q>Bring up Samuel,</q> he said. <verse eID="1Sam.28.11"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.28.12" osisID="1Sam.28.12"/> The woman looked at Saul and screamed; the woman said to
       Saul, <q>Why have you deceived me? You are Saul!</q> <verse eID="1Sam.28.12"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.28.13" osisID="1Sam.28.13"/> The king said to her, <q>Have no fear! What do you see?</q>
       The woman said to Saul, <q>I see a god coming up out of the earth.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.28.13"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.28.14" osisID="1Sam.28.14"/> He said to her, <q>What is he like?</q> She said, <q>It is
       an old man coming up; he is covered with a mantle.</q> So Saul knew it was Samuel; he bowed with his face
       to the ground and did obeisance. <verse eID="1Sam.28.14"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.28.15" osisID="1Sam.28.15"/> Then Samuel said to Saul, <q>Why have you disturbed me by
       bringing me up?</q> Saul an­swered, <q>I am in deep trouble; the Philistines are attacking me, and God has
       abandoned me; he answers me no more, either by prophet or by dreams; so I have called you to tell me what
       to do.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.28.15"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.28.16" osisID="1Sam.28.16"/> But Samuel said, <q>Why ask me, when the Eternal has
       abandoned you, to side with your rival? <verse eID="1Sam.28.16"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.28.17" osisID="1Sam.28.17"/> [[The Eternal has treated you as he declared by me that he
       would; the Eternal has torn the kingdom out of your hand and given it to David, your neighbour. <verse eID="1Sam.28.17"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.28.18" osisID="1Sam.28.18"/> It is because you did not obey the voice of the Eternal,
       because you did not carry out his fierce anger against Amalek, that the Eternal has done this to you
       to-day. <verse eID="1Sam.28.18"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.28.19" osisID="1Sam.28.19"/> And the Eternal will put Israel along with yourself into the
       power of the Philis­tines.]] To-morrow you shall fall, with your sons at your side, and the Eternal will
       put the army of Israel into the power of the Philistines.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.28.19"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.28.20" osisID="1Sam.28.20"/> Saul was overcome and fell at full length on the ground,
       aghast at what Samuel said; there was no strength in him, for he had eaten nothing all day and all night.
      <verse eID="1Sam.28.20"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.28.21" osisID="1Sam.28.21"/> So the woman went up to Saul, and, seeing he
       <milestone type="pb" n="345"/>
       was in agony, she said to him, <q>Your servant has done what you said; I have taken my life in my hands
       and done what you told me. Now do what your servant tells you; <verse eID="1Sam.28.21"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.28.22" osisID="1Sam.28.22"/> let me put a bite of food before you, that you may eat it
       and get strength for your journey.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.28.22"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.28.23" osisID="1Sam.28.23"/> But he refused; he said, <q>I will not eat.</q> However, his
       at­tendants as well as the woman urged him, and he listened to them; he got up from the ground and sat on
       the couch. <verse eID="1Sam.28.23"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.28.24" osisID="1Sam.28.24"/> The woman hurried to kill a fatted calf which she had in the
       house; she also kneaded some flour, baking unleavened cakes with it. <verse eID="1Sam.28.24"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.28.25" osisID="1Sam.28.25"/> She put the food before Saul and his attendants; they ate
       it, rose, and went away that night. <verse eID="1Sam.28.25"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eID="1Sam.28"/>
    <chapter osisID="1Sam.31" sID="1Sam.31"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.31.1" osisID="1Sam.31.1"/>When the Philistines made their attack on Israel, the men of
       Israel fled from the Philistines and dropped slain upon mount Gilboa. <verse eID="1Sam.31.1"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.31.2" osisID="1Sam.31.2"/> The Phil­istines overtook Saul and his sons; they slew
       Jonathan, Abinadab, and Malchishua, Saul's sons. <verse eID="1Sam.31.2"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.31.3" osisID="1Sam.31.3"/> Saul himself was hard pressed in the fight; the archers got at
       him, and he was badiy wounded by the archers. <verse eID="1Sam.31.3"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.31.4" osisID="1Sam.31.4"/> Then Saul said to his armour-bearer, <q>Draw your sword and
       run me through, lest these uncircumcised creatures come and make a fool of me.</q> But his armour-bearer
       would not; he was terrified. So Saul took his own sword and fell on it. <verse eID="1Sam.31.4"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.31.5" osisID="1Sam.31.5"/> And when his armour-bearer saw that Saul was dead, he also
       fell on his sword and died with him. <verse eID="1Sam.31.5"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.31.6" osisID="1Sam.31.6"/> Thus Saul, his three sons, his armour-bearer, and all his men,
       died together on the same day. <verse eID="1Sam.31.6"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.31.7" osisID="1Sam.31.7"/> (When the men of Israel on the opposite side of the valley and
       the folk on the other side of the Jordan saw that the men of Israel had fled and that Saul and his sons
       were dead, they abandoned their towns and took to flight; the Philistines then came and occupied them.) <verse eID="1Sam.31.7"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.31.8" osisID="1Sam.31.8"/> Next day, when the Philistines went to strip the slain, they
       found Saul and his three sons lying dead on mount Gilboa. <verse eID="1Sam.31.8"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.31.9" osisID="1Sam.31.9"/> So they cut off Saul's head and stripped off his armour,
       sending messengers all round the Philistine country to carry the good news to their idols and people. <verse eID="1Sam.31.9"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.31.10" osisID="1Sam.31.10"/> His armour they placed in the temple of Astarte; his body
       they exposed on the walls of Beth-shan. <verse eID="1Sam.31.10"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.31.11" osisID="1Sam.31.11"/> But when the inhabitants of Jabesh-gilead heard what the
       Philistines had done to Saul, <verse eID="1Sam.31.11"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.31.12" osisID="1Sam.31.12"/> all the braves set out to march by night, and took the
       bodies of Saul and his sons from the walls of Beth-shan; when they reached Ja-besh, they lamented over
       them there; <verse eID="1Sam.31.12"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.31.13" osisID="1Sam.31.13"/> then they buried their bodies under the tamarisk-tree at
       Jabesh, fasting for seven days. <verse eID="1Sam.31.13"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eID="1Sam.31"/>
   </div>