   <div type="book" osisID="1Sam">
    <milestone type="pb" n="306"/>
    <chapter osisID="1Sam.1" sID="1Sam.1"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.1.1" osisID="1Sam.1.1"/>There was a man of Ramah, a Zuphite from the highlands of Ephraim, whose name
       was Elkanah---the son of Jeroham, the son of Elihu, the son of Tohu, the son of Zuph. He was an Ephraimite, <verse eID="1Sam.1.1"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.1.2" osisID="1Sam.1.2"/> and he had two wives, one called Hannah and the other Peninnah; Peninnah had
       children, but Hannah had no children. <verse eID="1Sam.1.2"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.1.3" osisID="1Sam.1.3"/> Now this man used to go up from his town, year by year, to worship and to
       sacrifice to the Lord of hosts at Shilo, where Eli and his two sons, Hophni and Phinehas, were priests to the
       Eternal. <verse eID="1Sam.1.3"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.1.4" osisID="1Sam.1.4"/> He used to give his wife Penin­nah and all her sons and daugh­ters shares of
       the sacrificial meat, <verse eID="1Sam.1.4"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.1.5" osisID="1Sam.1.5"/> but, though he loved Hannah, he gave her only a sin­gle share, because the
       Eternal had shut up her womb. <verse eID="1Sam.1.5"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.1.6" osisID="1Sam.1.6"/> Her rival used to taunt her bit­terly, to irritate her, because the Eternal
       had shut up her womb; <verse eID="1Sam.1.6"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.1.7" osisID="1Sam.1.7"/> and this went on year after year--whenever she went up to the house of the
       Eternal, she taunted Hannah. <verse eID="1Sam.1.7"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.1.4" osisID="1Sam.1.4"/> One day when Elkanah was sacrificing, Hannah wept and would not eat. <verse eID="1Sam.1.4"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.1.8" osisID="1Sam.1.8"/> So her husband Elkanah said to her, <q>Hannah, why are you weeping? Why are
       you not eating? Why is your heart sad? Am I not more to you than ten sons?</q> <verse eID="1Sam.1.8"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.1.9" osisID="1Sam.1.9"/> But after they had eaten the boiled flesh and had drunk, Hannah rose and
       stood before the Eternal where Eli the priest was sitting on his chair at the door­posts of the temple of the Eternal.
      <verse eID="1Sam.1.9"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.1.10" osisID="1Sam.1.10"/> With a sore heart she prayed to the Eternal, weeping bitterly, <verse eID="1Sam.1.10"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.1.11" osisID="1Sam.1.11"/> and she made this vow: <q>O Lord of hosts, if thou wilt in­deed look upon
       the plight of thy servant and remember me and not forget thy servant, but wilt give thy servant a son, then I will
       give him to the Eternal for the whole of his life; and no razor shall ever touch his head.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.1.11"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.1.12" osisID="1Sam.1.12"/> As she went on praying before the Eternal, Eli noticed her mouth--<verse eID="1Sam.1.12"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.1.13" osisID="1Sam.1.13"/> for Hannah was speaking to herself; only her lips moved, her voice was not
       heard. Eli thought she was drunk. <verse eID="1Sam.1.13"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.1.14" osisID="1Sam.1.14"/> So Eli said to her, <q>How long will you go on, you drunken creature? Away
       with you, go and sleep off your drunkenness!</q> <verse eID="1Sam.1.14"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.1.15" osisID="1Sam.1.15"/> But Hannah replied, <q>No, sir, I am a sorely tried woman, I have drunk
       neither wine nor liquor; I have been pouring out my soul be­fore the Eternal. <verse eID="1Sam.1.15"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.1.16" osisID="1Sam.1.16"/> Do not take your servant for a depraved woman; it is under my stress of
       grief and provocation that I have been speaking all the time.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.1.16"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.1.17" osisID="1Sam.1.17"/> Then Eli answered, <q>Go and prosper; may the God of Israel grant you what
       you have asked him!</q> <verse eID="1Sam.1.17"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.1.18" osisID="1Sam.1.18"/> And she said, <q>May your servant find favour in your eyes!</q> <verse eID="1Sam.1.18"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.1.19" osisID="1Sam.1.19"/> So the woman went away; she ate, and her face was sad no longer. In the
       morning they rose, worshipped before the Eternal, and returned home to Ramah. Elkanah had inter­course with Hannah his
       wife, and the Eternal remembered her; <verse eID="1Sam.1.19"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.1.20" osisID="1Sam.1.20"/> so Hannah conceived, and at the turn of the year she bore a son, calling
       his name Samuel or <q>God-asked.</q> <q>For,</q> she said, <q>I asked the Eternal for him.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.1.20"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.1.21" osisID="1Sam.1.21"/> Elkanah went up with all
       <milestone type="pb" n="307"/>
       his household to offer to the Eternal the yearly sacrifice and what he had vowed, <verse eID="1Sam.1.21"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.1.22" osisID="1Sam.1.22"/> but Hannah did not go up. <q>Once the child is weaned,</q> she told her
       husband, <q>then I will bring him; we shall appear before the Eternal, and he shall remain there for ever.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.1.22"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.1.23" osisID="1Sam.1.23"/> Elkanah her husband said to her, <q>Do what­ever you think right; wait
       till you have weaned him, and may the Eternal let you carry out your purpose.</q> So Hannah waited and suckled her son
       till she weaned him. <verse eID="1Sam.1.23"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.1.24" osisID="1Sam.1.24"/> Then, after weaning him, she took him with her, along with a
       three-year-old bullock, a bushel of flour, and a bottle of wine; she entered the house of the Eternal at Shilo,
       accompanied by the boy, <verse eID="1Sam.1.24"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.1.25" osisID="1Sam.1.25"/> and, after the bullock had been slain, she brought the boy to Eli. <verse eID="1Sam.1.25"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.1.26" osisID="1Sam.1.26"/> <q>As sure as you live, sir,</q> she said, <q>I am the woman who stood
       beside you here, praying to the Eternal. <verse eID="1Sam.1.26"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.1.27" osisID="1Sam.1.27"/> I prayed about this boy, and the Eternal has granted me what I asked. <verse eID="1Sam.1.27"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.1.28" osisID="1Sam.1.28"/> So I have lent him to the Eternal; as long as he lives he is loaned to the
       Eternal.</q><verse eID="1Sam.1.28"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eID="1Sam.1"/>
    <chapter osisID="1Sam.2" sID="1Sam.2"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.2.1" osisID="1Sam.2.1"/>[[Hannah sang this prayer:
      <lg>
       <l> My heart thrills to the Eternal, </l>
       <l> my powers are heightened by my God, </l>
       <l> my lips exult over my foes, </l>
       <l> for I joy in thy deliverance. </l>
      <verse eID="1Sam.2.1"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.2.2" osisID="1Sam.2.2"/>
       <l> None is divine like the Eternal, </l>
       <l> no Power is steadfast like our God. </l>
      <verse eID="1Sam.2.2"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.2.3" osisID="1Sam.2.3"/>
       <l> No more of your proud vaunts! </l>
       <l> No mouthing of your taunts! </l>
       <l> For the Eternal is a God who knows it all, </l>
       <l> and what men do he judges. </l>
      <verse eID="1Sam.2.3"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.2.4" osisID="1Sam.2.4"/>
       <l> The strong man’s bow is broken, </l>
       <l> and the stumbling are braced up; </l>
      <verse eID="1Sam.2.4"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.2.5" osisID="1Sam.2.5"/>
       <l> those who had plenty have to work for bread, </l>
       <l> and hungry people have to toil no more; </l>
       <l> the barren woman has seven chil­dren now, </l>
       <l> and the mother of many is pining. </l>
      <verse eID="1Sam.2.5"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.2.6" osisID="1Sam.2.6"/>
       <l> The Eternal kills, the Eternal life bestows, </l>
       <l> he lowers to death and he lifts up, </l>
      <verse eID="1Sam.2.6"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.2.7" osisID="1Sam.2.7"/>
       <l> the Eternal makes poor, the Eternal makes rich, </l>
       <l> he lays low and he raises, </l>
      <verse eID="1Sam.2.7"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.2.8" osisID="1Sam.2.8"/>
       <l> he lifts the poor out of the dust, </l>
       <l> he raises beggars from the rub­bish heap, </l>
       <l> seating them next to nobles, </l>
       <l> to give them thrones of splendour. </l>
       <l> [[For the pillars of the earth be­long to the Eternal, </l>
       <l> and on them he set the world.]] </l>
      <verse eID="1Sam.2.8"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.2.9" osisID="1Sam.2.9"/>
       <l> He will guard the steps of his godly folk, </l>
       <l> but evil men shall perish in the dark </l>
       <l> (for no man's strength makes him mighty).</l>
      <verse eID="1Sam.2.9"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.2.10" osisID="1Sam.2.10"/>
       <l> The Eternal will crush his enemies, </l>
       <l> the Most High in heaven will shatter them </l>
       <l> (the Eternal's judgments shall cover the wide world), </l>
       <l> to add power to his king, </l>
       <l> to heighten the strength of his anointed one.]]</l>
      </lg>
      <verse eID="1Sam.2.10"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.2.11" osisID="1Sam.2.11"/> Then Hannah left him there before the Eternal, and went to Hamah; but the
       boy ministered to the Eternal in presence of Eli the priest. <verse eID="1Sam.2.11"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.2.12" osisID="1Sam.2.12"/> Now the sons of Eli were depraved creatures; they cared nothing for the
       Eternal nor for the regular dues of a priest. <verse eID="1Sam.2.12"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.2.13" osisID="1Sam.2.13"/> Whenever a man offered sacrifice, the priest’s servant would come, as the
       flesh was being boiled, with a three-pronged fork in his hand, <verse eID="1Sam.2.13"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.2.14" osisID="1Sam.2.14"/> which he plunged into the pot or kettle or basin or dish; whatever the
       fork brought up, the priest took for himself. So they treated ail the Israelites who came to sac­rifice at Shilo to
       the Eternal. <verse eID="1Sam.2.14"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.2.15" osisID="1Sam.2.15"/> In fact, even before the fat was burned, the priest’s servant
       <milestone type="pb" n="308"/>
       would come and tell the man who was sacrificing, <q>Let the priest have some flesh for roast­ing; he wants raw flesh
       from you, not boiled.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.2.15"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.2.16" osisID="1Sam.2.16"/> If the man said to him, <q>First let the fat be burned, and then take as
       much as you want,</q> he would answer, <q>No, you must give it to me at once, or I will take it by force.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.2.16"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.2.17" osisID="1Sam.2.17"/> The sin of the young men was very great before the Eternal, for it meant
       disdain of what was offered to the Eternal. <verse eID="1Sam.2.17"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.2.18" osisID="1Sam.2.18"/> Samuel, a boy girt with a linen apron, ministered before the Eternal, <verse eID="1Sam.2.18"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.2.19" osisID="1Sam.2.19"/> and his mother used to make him a little robe, which she brought to him
       year by year when she came up with her husband to offer the yearly sacrifice. <verse eID="1Sam.2.19"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.2.20" osisID="1Sam.2.20"/> Eli would bless Elkanah and his wife, saying,<q>May the Eternal repay
       you with off­spring from this woman, for the loan she has made to the Eter­nal!</q> Then they would go home. <verse eID="1Sam.2.20"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.2.21" osisID="1Sam.2.21"/> And the Eternal re­membered Hannah, so that she conceived and bore three
       sons and two daughters. Meantime the boy Samuel grew up before the Eternal. <verse eID="1Sam.2.21"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.2.22" osisID="1Sam.2.22"/> Now Eli was very old. When­ever he heard how his sons were behaving
       towards all Israel, and how they lay with the women caretakers at the door of the Trysting tent, <verse eID="1Sam.2.22"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.2.23" osisID="1Sam.2.23"/> he said to them, <q>Why are you behaving like this? I hear of it from all
       the people. <verse eID="1Sam.2.23"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.2.24" osisID="1Sam.2.24"/> No, my sons, it is no good report that I hear the people of the Eternal
       repeating. <verse eID="1Sam.2.24"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.2.25" osisID="1Sam.2.25"/> If one man sins against another man, God will mediate for him, but if a
       man sins against the Eternal, who can intercede on hi behalf?</q> However, they would not listen to what their
       father said, for the Eternal was resolved to slay them. <verse eID="1Sam.2.25"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.2.26" osisID="1Sam.2.26"/> Meantime Samuel grew up to be a fine boy in the eyes of the Eter­nal and
       of men. <verse eID="1Sam.2.26"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.2.27" osisID="1Sam.2.27"/> Now a man of God came to Eli and gave him this message from the Eternal.
       <q>Did I not reveal myself to your father's household when they were in Egypt, slaves to the court of the Pharaoh?
      <verse eID="1Sam.2.27"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.2.28" osisID="1Sam.2.28"/> Did I not choose him from all the clans of Israel to be my priest, to go
       up to my altar, to burn sacrifice, and to bear the ephod in my presence? Did I not assign to your father's household
       as food all that the Israelites offer by fire? <verse eID="1Sam.2.28"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.2.29" osisID="1Sam.2.29"/> Why, then, do you cast an envious eye upon my sacrifices and offer­ings,
       letting your sons override me and fattening yourselves under my very eyes upon the first-fruits of all that Israel
       my people offers? <verse eID="1Sam.2.29"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.2.30" osisID="1Sam.2.30"/> Therefore the Eternal, the God of Israel, de­clares, I had meant your
       house­hold and your father's house­hold to live in my favour for ever; but now, says the Eternal, far be that from me;
       those who honour me I will honour, and those who despise me shall be derided. <verse eID="1Sam.2.30"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.2.31" osisID="1Sam.2.31"/> The day is coming when I will cut off your off­spring and the offspring of
       your father’s household till there is not an old man left in your household; <verse eID="1Sam.2.31"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.2.32" osisID="1Sam.2.32"/> then in your straits you shall look enviously on all the prosperity I
       award to Is­rael. <verse eID="1Sam.2.32"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.2.33" osisID="1Sam.2.33"/> One of your family I will not cut off from my altar, I will spare him to
       consume his eyes with longing and to wear out his heart; but the greater part of your household shall die by the
       sword of men. <verse eID="1Sam.2.33"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.2.34" osisID="1Sam.2.34"/> What is to befall your two sons Hophni and Phinehas shall be an omen for
       you; both are to die on the
       <milestone type="pb" n="309"/>
       same day. <verse eID="1Sam.2.34"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.2.35" osisID="1Sam.2.35"/> But I will raise up for myself a faithful priest, who is to do whatever I
       plan and desire; I will found a family for him that lasts; he shall live in the favour of my anointed king for ever,
      <verse eID="1Sam.2.35"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.2.36" osisID="1Sam.2.36"/> and any survivor of your household shall come and do him obeisance for a
       pit­tance of money and a piece of bread, crying, <q>Do put me in some priestly position, that I may get a bite of
       food to eat.</q></q> <verse eID="1Sam.2.36"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eID="1Sam.2"/>
    <chapter osisID="1Sam.3" sID="1Sam.3"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.3.1" osisID="1Sam.3.1"/>The boy Samuel was minis­tering to the Eternal in pres­ence of Eli. A word
       from the Eternal was rare in those days; <verse eID="1Sam.3.1"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.3.2" osisID="1Sam.3.2"/> visions were not common. But one day, after Eli had lain down in his place
       (his eyes had begun to grow dim, so that he could not see), <verse eID="1Sam.3.2"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.3.3" osisID="1Sam.3.3"/> when the lamp of God was still burning, and Samuel was lying in the temple
       of the Eternal beside the ark of God, <verse eID="1Sam.3.3"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.3.4" osisID="1Sam.3.4"/> then the Eternal called, <q>Samuel! Samuel!</q> He answered, <q>Here I
       am,</q> <verse eID="1Sam.3.4"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.3.5" osisID="1Sam.3.5"/> and ran to Eli, saying, <q>Here I am; you called me.</q> But he said,
       <q>I did not call you; lie down again.</q> So he went and lay down. <verse eID="1Sam.3.5"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.3.6" osisID="1Sam.3.6"/> Once more the Eternal called, <q>Sam­uel! Samuel!</q> Then Samuel got up and
       went to Eli; <q>Here I am,</q> he said; <q>you did call me.</q> But he answered, <q>I did not call you, my son; lie
        down 7 again.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.3.6"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.3.7" osisID="1Sam.3.7"/> Now Samuel did not yet know the Eternal, and the word of the Eternal had
       not yet been disclosed to him. <verse eID="1Sam.3.7"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.3.8" osisID="1Sam.3.8"/> So when the Eternal called Samuel again, the third time, he got up and went
       to Eli, saying, <q>Here I am; you did call me.</q> Eli now saw that the Eternal was calling the lad; <verse eID="1Sam.3.8"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.3.9" osisID="1Sam.3.9"/> so Eli told Samuel, <q>Go and lie down; if you are called, you must say,
       <q>Speak, O Eternal; thy servant is listening.</q></q> Then Samuel went and lay down in his place, <verse eID="1Sam.3.9"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.3.10" osisID="1Sam.3.10"/> and the Eternal came and stood, calling as usual, <q>Sam­uel! Samuel!</q>
       Samuel said, <q>Speak, thy servant is listen­ing</q>; <verse eID="1Sam.3.10"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.3.11" osisID="1Sam.3.11"/> and the Eternal said to Samuel, <q>I am about to do a deed in Israel that
       will make the ears of all who hear it ring; <verse eID="1Sam.3.11"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.3.12" osisID="1Sam.3.12"/> on that day I will execute against Eli all that I have said about his
       household from be­ginning to end. <verse eID="1Sam.3.12"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.3.13" osisID="1Sam.3.13"/> You must tell him that I will punish his house­hold for ever, because he
       knew that his sons were blaspheming God and yet he did not check them. <verse eID="1Sam.3.13"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.3.14" osisID="1Sam.3.14"/> Therefore have I sworn to the household of Eli that the guilt of Eli's
       household shall never be expiated, neither by sacrifices nor by offering.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.3.14"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.3.15" osisID="1Sam.3.15"/> Samuel lay till morning; in the morning he rose and opened the doors of
       the house of the Eter­nal, but he was afraid to let Eli know the vision. <verse eID="1Sam.3.15"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.3.16" osisID="1Sam.3.16"/> Eli called Samuel, however, and said, <q>Samuel, my son.</q> <q>Here I
       am,</q> he said. <verse eID="1Sam.3.16"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.3.17" osisID="1Sam.3.17"/> And he said, <q>What was it that the Eternal told you? Come, do not hide
       it from me. God kill you and worse, if you hide from me a single word of what he told you!</q> <verse eID="1Sam.3.17"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.3.18" osisID="1Sam.3.18"/> So Samuel told him everything, and hid nothing from him. <q>It is the
       Eternal,</q> said Eli, <q>let him do what he thinks good!</q> <verse eID="1Sam.3.18"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.3.19" osisID="1Sam.3.19"/> Now Samuel grew up, and the Eternal was with him and let none of his
       words prove a fail­ure; <verse eID="1Sam.3.19"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.3.20" osisID="1Sam.3.20"/> all Israel from Dan to Beersheba knew that Samuel was accredited as a
       prophet of the Eternal. <verse eID="1Sam.3.20"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.3.21" osisID="1Sam.3.21"/> Once more the Eternal was to be seen at Shilo, for at Shilo the Eternal
       revealed himself to Samuel, and Samuel’s word reached all Is­rael. <verse eID="1Sam.3.21"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eID="1Sam.3"/>
    <milestone type="pb" n="310"/>
    <chapter osisID="1Sam.4" sID="1Sam.4"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.4.1" osisID="1Sam.4.1"/> In those days the Philistines mustered to make war on Israel; Israel
       marched out to fight the Philistines and camped at Help-stone, while the Philistines camped at Aphek.
      <verse eID="1Sam.4.1"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.4.2" osisID="1Sam.4.2"/> The Philis­tines drew up in battle array against Israel; it was a stiff
       fight, but Israel was routed before the Philistines, who slew four thousand of their army in the open country. <verse eID="1Sam.4.2"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.4.3" osisID="1Sam.4.3"/> When the troops returned to their camp, the sheikhs of Israel said, 
      <q>Why has the Eternal routed us to-day before the Phil­istines? Let us fetch the ark of our God from Shilo, that he
       may come among us and rescue us from the power of our enemies.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.4.3"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.4.4" osisID="1Sam.4.4"/> So the people sent to Shilo and brought away the ark of the Eternal
       (throned on the kherubs), and, along with the ark of God, Eli’s two sons Hophni and Phinehas. <verse eID="1Sam.4.4"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.4.5" osisID="1Sam.4.5"/> When the ark of the Eternal reached the camp, all Is­rael raised a mighty
       shout, till the earth resounded; <verse eID="1Sam.4.5"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.4.6" osisID="1Sam.4.6"/> and when the Philistines heard the noise of the shout, they said, <q>What
       is this noise of mighty shouting in the camp of the Hebrews?</q> When they learned that the ark of the Eternal had
       arrived in the camp, <verse eID="1Sam.4.6"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.4.7" osisID="1Sam.4.7"/> the Philistines were afraid. <q>These are their gods,</q> they said, <q>who
       have come to them in camp!</q> <q>Woe to us!</q> they said, <q>This has never hap­pened before. <verse eID="1Sam.4.7"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.4.8" osisID="1Sam.4.8"/> Woe to us! Who can rescue us from the power of these mighty gods? These are
       the gods that struck the Egyptians with all manner of plagues and pestilence. <verse eID="1Sam.4.8"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.4.9" osisID="1Sam.4.9"/> But courage, Philistines! Be men, that you may not be slaves to the
       Hebrews as they have been slaves to you.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.4.9"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.4.10" osisID="1Sam.4.10"/> So the Philistines fought, and Israel was beaten--every man scurried
       home, and there was a terrible slaughter, for thirty thousand infantry of Israel fell, <verse eID="1Sam.4.10"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.4.11" osisID="1Sam.4.11"/> the ark of God was captured, and Eli's two sons perished, Hophni and
       Phinehas. <verse eID="1Sam.4.11"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.4.12" osisID="1Sam.4.12"/> A Benjamite ran from the ranks and reached Shilo on the same day, with
       his clothes torn and earth scattered over his head. <verse eID="1Sam.4.12"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.4.13" osisID="1Sam.4.13"/> When he arrived, (Eli was sitting on his seat be­side the gate of the
       temple, watching the road; his heart was trembling for the ark of God. All the town made an outcry when the man
       came into the town with the news; <verse eID="1Sam.4.13"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.4.14" osisID="1Sam.4.14"/> and when Eli heard the noise of the outcry, he said, <q>What is the
       meaning of this uproar?</q> The man hurried on his way to tell Eli <verse eID="1Sam.4.14"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.4.15" osisID="1Sam.4.15"/> [[Eli was ninety-eight years old, and his eyes were so dim that he could
       not see]]. <verse eID="1Sam.4.15"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.4.16" osisID="1Sam.4.16"/> The man said to Eli, <q>I am the man who has come from the camp; I fled
       from the ranks to-day.</q> He asked, <q>And how did things go, my son?</q> <verse eID="1Sam.4.16"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.4.17" osisID="1Sam.4.17"/> The messenger said, <q>Israel fled be­fore the Philistines, there was a
       terrible slaughter of the troops, your two sons are dead, and the ark of God has been cap­tured.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.4.17"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.4.18" osisID="1Sam.4.18"/> When he mentioned the ark of God, Eli fell back from his seat beside the
       gate; his neck was broken, and he died--for he was old and heavy. He had been over Israel for forty years. <verse eID="1Sam.4.18"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.4.19" osisID="1Sam.4.19"/> His daughter-in-law, the wife of Phinehas, was pregnant and on the point
       of being delivered; when she heard the news about the capture of the ark of God and the death of her father-in-law
       and of her
       <milestone type="pb" n="311"/>
       husband, she bent forward and bore a child, for her birth-pangs came on her. <verse eID="1Sam.4.19"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.4.20" osisID="1Sam.4.20"/> As she was dying, the women standing round her said to her, <q>Fear not,
       you have borne a son.</q> But she said nothing, she never heeded them. <verse eID="1Sam.4.20"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.4.21" osisID="1Sam.4.21"/> So they named the child Ichabod, or Noglory, saying, <q>The glory is gone
       from Israel</q>--on account of the cap­ture of the ark of God, and on account of her father-in-law and her husband. <verse eID="1Sam.4.21"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eID="1Sam.4"/>
    <chapter osisID="1Sam.5" sID="1Sam.5"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.5.1" osisID="1Sam.5.1"/>The Philistines took the ark of God and brought it from Helpstone to Ashdod;
      <verse eID="1Sam.5.1"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.5.2" osisID="1Sam.5.2"/> then the Philistines took the ark of God and brought it into the temple of
       DagOn, placing it beside Dagon. <verse eID="1Sam.5.2"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.5.3" osisID="1Sam.5.3"/> But when the folk of Ashdod rose next morning, and went to the temple of
       Dagon and looked in, there lay Dagon flat on his face on the ground, in front of the ark of the Eter­nal! <verse eID="1Sam.5.3"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.5.4" osisID="1Sam.5.4"/> They lifted up Dagon and put him in his place again. But when they rose
       next morn­ing, there lay Dagon flat on his face on the ground in front of the ark of the Eternal--the head and both
       the hands of Dagon severed on the threshold, and only the trunk of Dagon left! <verse eID="1Sam.5.4"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.5.5" osisID="1Sam.5.5"/> (This is why the priests of Dagon, and all who enter the temple of Dagon,
       to this day, never step on the threshold of Dagon in Ashdod, but leap over it.) <verse eID="1Sam.5.5"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.5.6" osisID="1Sam.5.6"/> Then the Eternal laid a heavy hand upon the folk of Ashdod; he wasted them,
       striking both Ashdod and all its territory with tumours. <verse eID="1Sam.5.6"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.5.7" osisID="1Sam.5.7"/> When the men of Ashdod saw this, they said, <q>The ark of the God of Israel
       must not remain among us any longer, for his hand is severe on us and on Dagon our God.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.5.7"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.5.8" osisID="1Sam.5.8"/> So they sent and summoned all the Philistine tyrants, saying, <q>What are
       we to do with the ark of the God of Israel?</q> They replied, <q>Let the ark of the God of Israel be brought round
       to Gath.</q> They brought the ark of the God of Israel round to Gath, <verse eID="1Sam.5.8"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.5.9" osisID="1Sam.5.9"/> but, after they had brought it round, the hand of the Eternal struck that
       town; there was a terrible panic, for he struck the men of the town, both young and old, till tu­mours broke out upon
       them. <verse eID="1Sam.5.9"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.5.10" osisID="1Sam.5.10"/> So they sent the ark of God to Ekron. But when the ark of God came to
       Ekron, the Ekronites cried out, <q>They have brought round the ark of the God of Israel to us, to slay us and our
       people!</q> <verse eID="1Sam.5.10"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.5.11" osisID="1Sam.5.11"/> So they sent and summoned all the Philistine tyrants, saying, <q>Send the
       ark of the God of Israel away back to its own place, that it may not slay us and our people.</q> For there was a
       deadly panic all over the town; God laid a heavy hand upon them there; <verse eID="1Sam.5.11"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.5.12" osisID="1Sam.5.12"/> the men who did not die were struck down with tumours, and the wail of
       the town rose up to heaven. <verse eID="1Sam.5.12"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eID="1Sam.5"/>
    <chapter osisID="1Sam.6" sID="1Sam.6"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.6.1" osisID="1Sam.6.1"/>For seven months the ark of the Eternal remained in the land of the
       Philistines. <verse eID="1Sam.6.1"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.6.2" osisID="1Sam.6.2"/> Then the Philistines summoned their priests and magicians. <q>What are we
       to do with the ark of the Eternal?</q> they asked; <q>tell us how we should send it to its own place.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.6.2"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.6.3" osisID="1Sam.6.3"/> And they replied, <q>If you are sending away the ark of the God of Israel,
       you must not send it away empty; you must render him some reparation. Then you will be cured, and you will learn why
       his hand still presses on you.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.6.3"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.6.4" osisID="1Sam.6.4"/> They asked, <q>What is the
       <milestone type="pb" n="312"/>
       reparation we must offer to him?</q> <q>Five golden tumours,</q> they said, <q>and five golden mice, ac­cording to
       the number of the Philistine tyrants, for one plague was upon you all and upon your tyrants. <verse eID="1Sam.6.4"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.6.5" osisID="1Sam.6.5"/> So you must make images of your tu­mours and images of your mice that are
       spoiling the country, and thus do honour to the God of Israel; perhaps he will take his hand off you and your gods
       and your land. <verse eID="1Sam.6.5"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.6.6" osisID="1Sam.6.6"/> Why will you stiffen yourselves, as the Egyp­tians and the Pharaoh
       stiffened themselves? Was it not only after God had made fools of them, that they let Israel depart? <verse eID="1Sam.6.6"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.6.7" osisID="1Sam.6.7"/> Now then, make a new cart and take two milch cows which have never been in
       har­ness; fasten the cows to the cart, and leave their calves behind them at home; <verse eID="1Sam.6.7"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.6.8" osisID="1Sam.6.8"/> then take the ark of the Eternal and place it on the cart, putting into a
       box beside it the golden objects you are offering by way of reparation. Send the cart away on its journey, <verse eID="1Sam.6.8"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.6.9" osisID="1Sam.6.9"/> and if it takes the road in the direction of Israel’s territory, towards
       Beth-shemesh, then it is the Eternal who has inflicted this great damage upon us; but if not, then we shall
       understand it was not his hand that struck us--it was an accident that befell us.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.6.9"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.6.10" osisID="1Sam.6.10"/> The men did so. They took two milch cows and fas­tened them to the cart,
       shutting their calves up at home, <verse eID="1Sam.6.10"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.6.11" osisID="1Sam.6.11"/> and on the cart they placed the ark of the Eternal and the box with the
       golden mice and the images of their tumours. <verse eID="1Sam.6.11"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.6.12" osisID="1Sam.6.12"/> The cows made straight along the road to Beth-shemesh; they kept to the
       one high-road, low­ing as they went, and turning neither to the right nor to the left, while the Philistine tyrants
       followed them up to the frontier at Beth-shemesh. <verse eID="1Sam.6.12"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.6.13" osisID="1Sam.6.13"/> The folk of Beth-shemesh were harvesting their wheat in the valley, and
       when they looked up and saw the ark, they went joyfully to meet it. <verse eID="1Sam.6.13"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.6.14" osisID="1Sam.6.14"/> The cart moved into the field of Joshua the Beth-shemeshite and stopped
       there. <verse eID="1Sam.6.14"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.6.15" osisID="1Sam.6.15"/>A large altar-stone was there; so they split up the wood of the cart and
       offered the cows as a burnt-offering to the Eter­nal. [[The Levites took down the ark of the Eternal and the box
       containing the golden ob­jects, and placed them on the large altar-stone, and the men of Beth-shemesh offered that
       day burnt-offerings and ordi­nary sacrifices to the Eternal.]] <verse eID="1Sam.6.15"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.6.16" osisID="1Sam.6.16"/> When the five Philistine tyrants saw this, they re­turned that very day to
       Ekron. <verse eID="1Sam.6.16"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.6.17" osisID="1Sam.6.17"/> [[These are the golden tumours which the Philistines gave up as
       reparation to the Eternal; there was one for Ashdod, one for Gaza, one for Ashkelon, one for Gath, and one for
       Ekron; <verse eID="1Sam.6.17"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.6.18" osisID="1Sam.6.18"/> the golden mice also corresponded to the number of all the Philis­tine
       towns belonging to the five tyrants, both fortified towns and country villages]]. And still to this day the large
       altar-stone, beside which they set down the ark of the Eternal, stands in the field of Joshua the Beth-shemeshite.
      <verse eID="1Sam.6.18"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.6.19" osisID="1Sam.6.19"/> The sons of Jeconiah, however, did not rejoice along with the men of
       Beth-shemesh when they saw the ark of the Eternal; so he struck [[fifty thousand and]] seventy of them. And the
       folk mourned because the Eternal had smitten the folk with a heavy slaughter. <verse eID="1Sam.6.19"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.6.20" osisID="1Sam.6.20"/> The men of
       <milestone type="pb" n="313"/>
       Beth-shemesh said, <q>Who can stand before the Eternal, this dread God? Whither can we have him sent, to leave us
       alone?</q> <verse eID="1Sam.6.20"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.6.21" osisID="1Sam.6.21"/> So they sent messen­gers to the inhabitants of Kiriath-jearim, saying,
       <q>The Philis­tines have brought back the ark of the Eternal. Come down and take it to be with you.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.6.21"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eID="1Sam.6"/>
    <chapter osisID="1Sam.7" sID="1Sam.7"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.7.1" osisID="1Sam.7.1"/>The men of Kiriath-jearim came and took the ark of the Eternal, bringing it
       to the house of Abinadab on the hill and con­secrating Eleazar his son to look after the ark of the Eternal. <verse eID="1Sam.7.1"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.7.2" osisID="1Sam.7.2"/> From the day that the ark of the Eternal remained at Kir­iath-jearim (the
       days length­ened out into twenty years), all the house of Israel turned after the Eternal. <verse eID="1Sam.7.2"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.7.3" osisID="1Sam.7.3"/> Samuel said to all the house of Israel, <q>If you are returning with all
       your heart to the Eternal, then put away from yourselves the foreign gods and the Astartes, set your hearts on the
       Eternal and worship him alone, and he will rescue you from the power of the Philistines.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.7.3"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.7.4" osisID="1Sam.7.4"/> So the Israelites did put away the Baals and the As­tartes, and worshipped
       the Eternal alone. <verse eID="1Sam.7.4"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.7.5" osisID="1Sam.7.5"/> Then Samuel said, <q>Gather all Israel at Mizpah, and I will pray to the
       Eternal for you.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.7.5"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.7.6" osisID="1Sam.7.6"/> They gath­ered at Mizpah, drew water and poured it out before the Eternal,
       and fasted on that day, confessing that they had sinned against the Eternal. (It was at Mizpah that Samuel managed
       the affairs of Israel.) <verse eID="1Sam.7.6"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.7.7" osisID="1Sam.7.7"/> When the Philistines heard that the Israelites had gathered at Mizpah, the
       Philistine ty­rants proceeded to attack Israel. On hearing of this, the Israelites were terrified of the Philistines;
      <verse eID="1Sam.7.7"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.7.8" osisID="1Sam.7.8"/> and the Israelites said to Sam­uel, <q>Do not cease crying to the Eternal
       our God for us, to save us from the power of the Philis­tines.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.7.8"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.7.9" osisID="1Sam.7.9"/> So Samuel took a sucking-lamb and offered it up to the Eternal as a whole
       burnt-offering; he cried to the Eternal for Israel, and the Eternal an­swered him, <verse eID="1Sam.7.9"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.7.10" osisID="1Sam.7.10"/> for when the Philis­tines approached to fight against Israel just as
       Samuel was offering up the burnt-offering, the Eternal thundered loudly that day against the Philistines and routed
       them; <verse eID="1Sam.7.10"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.7.11" osisID="1Sam.7.11"/> they were crushed before Israel, and the men of Israel, pouring out of
       Mizpah, pursued the Philistines and routed them, till the chase passed under Beth-horon. <verse eID="1Sam.7.11"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.7.12" osisID="1Sam.7.12"/> Then Samuel took a stone and erected it between Mizpah and Jeshanah,
       naming it Helpstone. <q>This is witness,</q> he said, <q>that the Eternal has helped us.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.7.12"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.7.13" osisID="1Sam.7.13"/> So the Philistines were subdued; they no longer crossed the frontiers of
       Israel. Indeed, all the days of Samuel the hand of the Eter­nal was against the Philistines; <verse eID="1Sam.7.13"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.7.14" osisID="1Sam.7.14"/> the towns which the Philistines had taken from Israel were handed back to
       Israel, from Ekron to Gath, and their terri­tory was also freed by Israel from the power of the Philis­tines. (Also
       there was peace between Israel and the Amorites.) <verse eID="1Sam.7.14"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.7.15" osisID="1Sam.7.15"/> Samuel managed the affairs of Israel all the days of his life; <verse eID="1Sam.7.15"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.7.16" osisID="1Sam.7.16"/> he went on circuit every year to Bethel, Gilgal, and Mizpah, de­ciding the
       affairs of Israel at all those places, <verse eID="1Sam.7.16"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.7.17" osisID="1Sam.7.17"/> and returning to Ramah, where his home was, where he ruled Israel and
       where he built an altar to the Eternal. <verse eID="1Sam.7.17"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eID="1Sam.7"/>
    <chapter osisID="1Sam.8" sID="1Sam.8"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.8.1" osisID="1Sam.8.1"/>When Samuel grew old, he made his sons manage Israel;
      <verse eID="1Sam.8.1"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.8.2" osisID="1Sam.8.2"/>the name of his eldest son was
       <milestone type="pb" n="314"/>
       Joel, the name of his second was Abijah, and they ruled at Beersheba. <verse eID="1Sam.8.2"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.8.3" osisID="1Sam.8.3"/> But his sons did not follow his footsteps; they turned aside for money,
       they took bribes and tampered with justice. <verse eID="1Sam.8.3"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.8.4" osisID="1Sam.8.4"/> So all the sheikhs of Israel gathered and went to Samuel at Ramah, <verse eID="1Sam.8.4"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.8.5" osisID="1Sam.8.5"/> saying, <q>You are old, and your sons are not following your footsteps.
       Now appoint a king for us, to rule us like all other nations.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.8.5"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.8.6" osisID="1Sam.8.6"/> It displeased Samuel to hear them asking for a king to rule them. So
       Samuel prayed to the Eternal; <verse eID="1Sam.8.6"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.8.7" osisID="1Sam.8.7"/> the Eternal said to Samuel, <q>Listen to the voice of the peo­ple, listen
       to whatever they say to you; for it is not you whom they have rejected, it is I whom they have rejected as their
       king. <verse eID="1Sam.8.7"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.8.8" osisID="1Sam.8.8"/> They are treating you exactly as they have treated me, ever since I
       brought them up out of Egypt, forsaking me and worshipping foreign gods. <verse eID="1Sam.8.8"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.8.9" osisID="1Sam.8.9"/> So listen to their voice; only, give them a solemn warning, and explain to
       them the methods of the king who shall reign over them.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.8.9"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eID="1Sam.8"/>
    <chapter osisID="1Sam.10" sID="1Sam.10"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.10.17" osisID="1Sam.10.17"/> Then Samuel called the people together to the Eternal at Mizpah <verse eID="1Sam.10.17"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.10.18" osisID="1Sam.10.18"/> and gave the Israelites this message from the Eternal, the God of
       Israel. <q>I brought up Israel from Egypt, I rescued you from the power of the Egyptians and from the power of all
       the realms that were oppressing you; <verse eID="1Sam.10.18"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.10.19" osisID="1Sam.10.19"/> and to-day you have rejected your God, who has himself saved you from
       all your calamities and distresses; you have said <q>no</q> to me and claimed a king.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.10.19"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eID="1Sam.10"/>
    <chapter osisID="1Sam.8" sID="1Sam.8"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.8.11" osisID="1Sam.8.11"/> Then he added, <q>Here are the methods of the king who shall reign over
       you; your sons he will take and place them in his chariots and among his horsemen and to run before his chariots;
      <verse eID="1Sam.8.11"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.8.12" osisID="1Sam.8.12"/> he will put them in command of his regiments and companies; some will
       have to plough his ground and reap his harvest, to make his arms and construct his char­iots; <verse eID="1Sam.8.12"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.8.13" osisID="1Sam.8.13"/> your daughters he will take for perfumers and cooks and bakers; <verse eID="1Sam.8.13"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.8.14" osisID="1Sam.8.14"/> he will take the pick of your fields and vine­yards and olive-yards and
       pre­sent them to his courtiers; <verse eID="1Sam.8.14"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.8.15" osisID="1Sam.8.15"/> a tenth part of your arable land and vineyards he will present to his
       officers and courtiers; <verse eID="1Sam.8.15"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.8.16" osisID="1Sam.8.16"/> your slaves, male and female, and the pick of your cattle and your
       asses, he will take and use for his own ends; <verse eID="1Sam.8.16"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.8.17" osisID="1Sam.8.17"/> a tenth part of your flocks he will take; and you yourselves shall be
       slaves to him. <verse eID="1Sam.8.17"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.8.18" osisID="1Sam.8.18"/> Then you will cry out on account of the king whom you have chosen for
       yourselves, but the Eternal will not answer you then.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.8.18"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.8.19" osisID="1Sam.8.19"/> However, the people would not listen to the voice of Samuel. <q>No,</q>
       they said, <q>we must have a king over us, <verse eID="1Sam.8.19"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.8.20" osisID="1Sam.8.20"/> to be like all the other nations, that our king may rule us and march in
       front of us and fight our battles.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.8.20"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.8.21" osisID="1Sam.8.21"/> When Samuel heard all that the people said, he repeated it in the
       hear­ing of the Eternal, <verse eID="1Sam.8.21"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.8.22" osisID="1Sam.8.22"/> and the Eternal said to Samuel, <q>Listen to their voice and make them a
       king.</q> So Samuel said to the men of Israel, <q>Well then, present yourselves before the Eternal in your clans
       and septs.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.8.22"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eID="1Sam.8"/>
    <chapter osisID="1Sam.10" sID="1Sam.10"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.10.20" osisID="1Sam.10.20"/> And Samuel made all the clans of Israel approach; the clan of Benjamin
       was selected by lot, <verse eID="1Sam.10.20"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.10.21" osisID="1Sam.10.21"/> and when he made the clan of Benjamin approach in their families, the
       family of the Matrites was selected by lot, and when he made the family of the Matrites approach man by man,
       <milestone type="pb" n="315"/>
       Saul the son of Kish was selected by lot. But when they looked for him, he was not to be found. <verse eID="1Sam.10.21"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.10.22" osisID="1Sam.10.22"/> So they asked the Eternal again, <q>Is the man here yet?</q> The
       Eternal answered, <q>He has hidden himself among the baggage.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.10.22"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.10.23" osisID="1Sam.10.23"/> Then they ran and brought him forward, and as he stood among the
       people he was a head taller than any of them. <verse eID="1Sam.10.23"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.10.24" osisID="1Sam.10.24"/> And Samuel told all the people, <q>Do you see whom the Eternal has
       chosen? There is not a man like him among all the people!</q> Then all the people shouted aloud, <q>Long live the
       king!</q> <verse eID="1Sam.10.24"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eID="1Sam.10"/>
    <chapter osisID="1Sam.12" sID="1Sam.12"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.12.1" osisID="1Sam.12.1"/>Then said Samuel to all Israel, <q>I have listened to your voice, to
       whatever you said to me, and I have put a king over you. <verse eID="1Sam.12.1"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.12.2" osisID="1Sam.12.2"/> There, the king marches in front of you; but as for me, I am old and
       grey­headed, and my sons are grown­up men among you. I have gone in front of you from my youth to this day. <verse eID="1Sam.12.2"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.12.3" osisID="1Sam.12.3"/> Here I am! Testify against me in presence of the Eternal and of his
      anointed king; whose ox have I seized, whose ass have I seized, whom have I maltreated, whom have I defrauded, from
      whom have I accepted a bribe or even a pair of sandals? Testify against me, and I will restore it to you.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.12.3"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.12.4" osisID="1Sam.12.4"/> They said, <q>You have never maltreated us, nor defrauded us, nor accepted
       any bribe from anyone.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.12.4"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.12.5" osisID="1Sam.12.5"/> So he said to them, <q>The Eternal is witness and his anointed king is
       witness this day against you, that you have found nothing to accuse me of!</q> <q>He is witness,</q> they replied.
      <verse eID="1Sam.12.5"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.12.6" osisID="1Sam.12.6"/> And Samuel said to the people, <q>The Eternal is witness, he who
       equipped Moses and Aaron, and brought up your fathers from the land of Egypt! <verse eID="1Sam.12.6"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.12.7" osisID="1Sam.12.7"/> Now stand there, that I may argue with you before the Eternal and
       recount all the saving deeds done by the Eternal for you and for your fathers. <verse eID="1Sam.12.7"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.12.8" osisID="1Sam.12.8"/> When Jacob went to Egypt, the Egyptians oppressed them, and your fathers
       cried to the Eternal; then the Eternal sent Moses and Aaron to bring your fathers out of Egypt, and settled them in
       this place. <verse eID="1Sam.12.8"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.12.9" osisID="1Sam.12.9"/> But they forgot the Eternal their God. So he sold them into the hand of
       Sisera, commander of the army of Jabin king of Hazor, and into the hand of the Philis­tines, and into the hand of
       the king of Moab, who fought against them. <verse eID="1Sam.12.9"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.12.10" osisID="1Sam.12.10"/> Then they cried to the Eternal, saying, <q>We have sinned, for we have
       for­saken the Eternal and wor­shipped the Baals and the Astartes; but rescue us from the power of our enemies, and we
       will worship thee.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.12.10"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.12.11" osisID="1Sam.12.11"/> So the Eternal sent Jerubbaal and Barak and Jephthah and Sam­uel, and
       rescued you from the power of your enemies on every side, till you lived in safety. <verse eID="1Sam.12.11"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.12.12" osisID="1Sam.12.12"/> Yet, when you saw Nahash king of Ammon coming to at­tack you, you said
       to me, <q>No, we must have a king to reign over us</q>--though the Eternal your God is your king. <verse eID="1Sam.12.12"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.12.13" osisID="1Sam.12.13"/> See, here is the king you have chosen! See, the Eternal has set a king
       over you! <verse eID="1Sam.12.13"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.12.14" osisID="1Sam.12.14"/> If you will reverence the Eternal and wor­ship him and listen to his
       voice and not rebel against the com­mand of the Eternal, if both you and the king who reigns over you are followers
       of the Eternal your God, well and good. <verse eID="1Sam.12.14"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.12.15" osisID="1Sam.12.15"/> But if you will not listen to the voice of the Eternal, if you rebel
       against the command of
       <milestone type="pb" n="316"/>
       the Eternal, then shall the hand of the Eternal be against you and your king.
      <verse eID="1Sam.12.15"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.12.16" osisID="1Sam.12.16"/> Now then, stand and see this wonder which the Eternal is about to
       perform before your eyes. <verse eID="1Sam.12.16"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.12.17" osisID="1Sam.12.17"/> Is it not wheat harvest to-day? Well, I will call upon the Eter­nal to
       send thunder and rain, and you shall know and see what a wicked thing you have done in the sight of the Eternal by
       asking a king.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.12.17"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.12.18" osisID="1Sam.12.18"/> So Samuel called to the Eter­nal, and that day the Eternal did send
       thunder and rain, till all the people were terrified of the Eternal and of Samuel. <verse eID="1Sam.12.18"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.12.19" osisID="1Sam.12.19"/> Then all the people said to Samuel, <q>Pray to the Eternal your God
       for your servants, lest we die; for, in addition to all our sins, we have wickedly asked a king.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.12.19"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.12.20" osisID="1Sam.12.20"/> Sam­uel said to the people, <q>Fear not; you have done this wrong
       indeed; only, do not swerve from following the Eternal, but worship the Eternal with all your heart, <verse eID="1Sam.12.20"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.12.21" osisID="1Sam.12.21"/> and never swerve in search of vain idols which cannot profit you nor
       save you--vain they are! <verse eID="1Sam.12.21"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.12.22" osisID="1Sam.12.22"/> For the sake of his own great credit, the Eternal will not abandon his
       people; for the Eternal has undertaken to make you a people for himself. <verse eID="1Sam.12.22"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.12.23" osisID="1Sam.12.23"/> Besides, for my part, far be it from me to sin against the Eternal by
       ceasing to pray for you; I will instruct you in the good and right path. <verse eID="1Sam.12.23"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.12.24" osisID="1Sam.12.24"/> Only reverence the Eternal and serve him loyally with all your heart;
       for you see what a wonder he has performed in your presence. <verse eID="1Sam.12.24"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.12.25" osisID="1Sam.12.25"/> But if you persist in doing wrong, both you and your king will be
       swept away.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.12.25"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eID="1Sam.12"/>
    <chapter osisID="1Sam.10" sID="1Sam.10"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.10.25" osisID="1Sam.10.25"/>Thus did Samuel explain to the people the methods of the kingdom; he
       wrote them on a scroll, which he deposited in the presence of the Eternal. Then Samuel dismissed all the people,
       every man to his house. <verse eID="1Sam.10.25"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.10.26" osisID="1Sam.10.26"/> Saul too went to his house at Gibeah, followed by the brave men of the
       nation, whose hearts God had touched. <verse eID="1Sam.10.26"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.10.27" osisID="1Sam.10.27"/> But a number of low characters said, <q>How can this fellow deliver
       us?</q> They despised him and they did not offer him any present. <verse eID="1Sam.10.27"/>
     </p>
     <p>* * *</p>
    <chapter eID="1Sam.10"/>
    <chapter osisID="1Sam.9" sID="1Sam.9"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.9.1" osisID="1Sam.9.1"/>There was a man belonging a to Gibeah in Benjamin, whose name was Kish,
       the son of Abiel, the son of Zeror, the son of Becorath, the son of Apliiah; he was a Benjamite, a man of
       substance, <verse eID="1Sam.9.1"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.9.2" osisID="1Sam.9.2"/> and he had a son whose name was Saul, a man in the prime of life and
       stalwart--there was not a man among the Israelites more stalwart than he was; he was a head taller than any of the
       people. <verse eID="1Sam.9.2"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.9.3" osisID="1Sam.9.3"/> Now some asses of Kish, Saul's father, were lost. So Kish told Saul his son
       to take one of the servants with him and go off in search of the asses. <verse eID="1Sam.9.3"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.9.4" osisID="1Sam.9.4"/> They made their way through the highlands of Ephraim and through the
       district of Shali-shah, but failed to find them; they made their way through the district of Shaalim, but the asses
       were not there; they made their way through the district of the Benjamites, but failed to find them. <verse eID="1Sam.9.4"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.9.5" osisID="1Sam.9.5"/> When they reached the district of Zuph, Saul said to his servant who was
       with him, <q>Come, let us go back, in case my father ceases to care about the asses and is anxious about us.</q>
      <verse eID="1Sam.9.5"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.9.6" osisID="1Sam.9.6"/> The servant said to him, <q>But there is a man of God in this town, a man
       who is highly respected; whatever he
       <milestone type="pb" n="317"/>
       says is sure to come true. Let us go there; perhaps he can tell us something about the errand we are on.</q>
      <verse eID="1Sam.9.6"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.9.7" osisID="1Sam.9.7"/><q>But suppose we go,</q> said Saul to his servant, <q>what shall we offer
       the man? Our sacks are empty of bread, and there is no present to offer the man. What have we got?</q> <verse eID="1Sam.9.7"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.9.8" osisID="1Sam.9.8"/> The servant answered Saul again, <q>I have ninepence here for you to give
       the man of God, that he may tell us about our errand.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.9.8"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.9.10" osisID="1Sam.9.10"/><q>Good,</q> said Saul to his servant, <q>come, let us go.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.9.10"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.9.11" osisID="1Sam.9.11"/> So they went to the town where the man of God lived. As they were
       climbing the as­cent to the town, they met some young girls coming out to draw water, and asked them, <q>Is the
       seer here?</q> <verse eID="1Sam.9.11"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.9.9" osisID="1Sam.9.9"/> (Formerly in Israel, when a man went to consult God, he said, <q>Come, let
       us go to the seer,</q> for the prophet of to-day used formerly to be called a <q>seer.</q>) <verse eID="1Sam.9.9"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.9.12" osisID="1Sam.9.12"/> The girls answered, <q>Yes, there he is in front of you: he has just
       come into the town this mo­ment, for the people are sacri­ficing to-day on the height. <verse eID="1Sam.9.12"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.9.13" osisID="1Sam.9.13"/> As soon as you enter the town you will find him, before he goes up to
       the height; for the people will not eat till he comes; he is to bless the sacrifice, and after that the guests
       partake. Go up, then, for you will meet him this moment.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.9.13"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.9.14" osisID="1Sam.9.14"/> So they went up to the town.
     </p>
     <p>
       They had just entered the gate-house, when there was Sam­uel, coming out in their direc­tion, on his way up to the
       height! <verse eID="1Sam.9.14"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.9.15" osisID="1Sam.9.15"/> (Now, the day before Saul ar­rived, the Eternal had whispered to Samuel,
      <verse eID="1Sam.9.15"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.9.16" osisID="1Sam.9.16"/><q>About this time to­morrow I will send you a man from the district of
       Benjamin, and you shall anoint him to be prince over my people Israel; he is to rescue them from the power of the
       Philistines, for I have seen the affliction of my people, and their cry has reached me.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.9.16"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.9.17" osisID="1Sam.9.17"/> So, when Samuel saw Saul, the Eternal reminded him, <q>Here is the man
      of whom I told you, <q>this man shall wield authority over my people.</q></q>) <verse eID="1Sam.9.17"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.9.18" osisID="1Sam.9.18"/> Saul went up to Samuel in the gate-house and said, <q>Pray tell me where
       the seer's house is.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.9.18"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.9.19" osisID="1Sam.9.19"/> And Samuel answered Saul, <q>I am the seer. Go up to the height in front
       of me, for you must eat with me to-day; in the morning I will let you go, telling you all that is in your mind. <verse eID="1Sam.9.19"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.9.20" osisID="1Sam.9.20"/> As for your asses that were lost three days ago, do not worry about
       them; they have been found. But the honours of Israel, to whom do they belong? Are they not for you and for all
       your father’s household?</q> <verse eID="1Sam.9.20"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.9.21" osisID="1Sam.9.21"/> Saul answered, <q>Am I not a Benjamite, a member of the smallest clan in
       Israel? Is not my fam­ily the humblest of all the septs in the clan of Benjamin? Why, then, do you talk to me in
       this way?</q> <verse eID="1Sam.9.21"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.9.22" osisID="1Sam.9.22"/> But Samuel took Saul and his servant and brought them into the
       dining-hall, where he seated them at the head of the guests (who were about thirty in number); <verse eID="1Sam.9.22"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.9.23" osisID="1Sam.9.23"/> then Samuel said to the cook, <q>Bring the portion I gave you, the
       portion I told you to put aside.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.9.23"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.9.24" osisID="1Sam.9.24"/> So the cook lifted the leg and the rump and put them before Saul, and
       Samuel said, <q>There, the flesh is put before you! Eat; it has been reserved for you till the hour appointed, that
       you might eat this among the guests.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.9.24"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.9.25" osisID="1Sam.9.25"/> So Saul ate with Samuel that day, and after they went down
       <milestone type="pb" n="318"/>
       from the height to the town, a couch was spread for Saul upon the house-top, and he lay down to sleep. <verse eID="1Sam.9.25"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.9.26" osisID="1Sam.9.26"/> At day-break Samuel called to Saul upon the house­top, <q>Arise, that I
       may speed you on your way.</q> So Saul got up, and he and Samuel went out into the street. <verse eID="1Sam.9.26"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.9.27" osisID="1Sam.9.27"/> They were walk­ing down to the outskirts of the town, when Samuel said
       to Saul, <q>Tell the servant to go on ahead; but stop here yourself, that I may unfold to you God's mesasage.</q>
      <verse eID="1Sam.9.27"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eID="1Sam.9"/>
    <chapter osisID="1Sam.10" sID="1Sam.10"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.10.1" osisID="1Sam.10.1"/>Then Samuel,taking a flask of oil, poured it over his head and kissed
       him, saying, <q>Has not the Eternal anointed you to be prince over his people Israel? You shall wield authority
       over the people of the Eternal and rescue them from the power of their enemies. And this shall be the sign that
       the Eternal has anointed you to be prince over his heritage; <verse eID="1Sam.10.1"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.10.2" osisID="1Sam.10.2"/>when you leave me to-day you will find two men near Rachel’s tomb on
       the frontier of Benjamin; they will tell you that the asses you went in search of have been found, and your father
       has ceased to care about the asses but is anxious about you; he says, <q>What am I to do about my son?</q> <verse eID="1Sam.10.2"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.10.3" osisID="1Sam.10.3"/> Then, as you pass forward and reach the oak at Tabor, you will be met by
       three men going up to God at Bethel, one carrying three kids, one carrying three loaves of bread, and one carrying
       a bottle of wine; <verse eID="1Sam.10.3"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.10.4" osisID="1Sam.10.4"/> they will salute you and give you two loaves of bread, which you must
       accept from them. <verse eID="1Sam.10.4"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.10.5" osisID="1Sam.10.5"/> After that you will reach God's Gibeah, where the prefect of the
       Philistines is stationed; and as you approach the town, you will meet a band of dervishes coming down from the
       height with lutes, drums, flutes, and lyres playing in front of them while they prophesy; <verse eID="1Sam.10.5"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.10.6" osisID="1Sam.10.6"/> the spirit of the Eternal will then inspire you till you proph­esy along
       with them and become a different man. <verse eID="1Sam.10.6"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.10.7" osisID="1Sam.10.7"/> Now, as these signs befall you, do whatever the occasion demands, for
       God is with you. <verse eID="1Sam.10.7"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.10.8" osisID="1Sam.10.8"/> [[You must go down to Gilgal before me, and I will come down to join
       you there, to offer burnt-offerings and sacrifice recompense-offer­ings; you must wait for seven days till I join
       you and tell you what to do.]]</q> <verse eID="1Sam.10.8"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.10.9" osisID="1Sam.10.9"/> And after he had turned to leave Samuel, God did change his nature. A1l
       these signs oc­curred, that day. <verse eID="1Sam.10.9"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.10.10" osisID="1Sam.10.10"/> Just as he reached Gibeah, a band of der­vishes met him; he prophesied
       along with them, <verse eID="1Sam.10.10"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.10.11" osisID="1Sam.10.11"/> and when people who knew him of old saw him prophesying along with the
       dervishes, they all said to each other, <q>Whatever has come over the son of Kish? Saul among the dervishes!</q>
      <verse eID="1Sam.10.11"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.10.12" osisID="1Sam.10.12"/> <q>Among men of no family!</q> as one local man ob­served. (So it
       passed into a proverb, <q>Saul among the der­vishes!</q>) <verse eID="1Sam.10.12"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.10.13" osisID="1Sam.10.13"/> When he had finished prophesying, he went home. <verse eID="1Sam.10.13"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.10.14" osisID="1Sam.10.14"/> Saul's uncle asked him and his servant, <q>Where have you been?</q>
       <q>In search of the asses,</q> said he, <q>and when we saw they were not to be found, we went to Samuel.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.10.14"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.10.15" osisID="1Sam.10.15"/> Then Saul's uncle asked, <q>Now tell me what Samuel said to you.</q>
      <verse eID="1Sam.10.15"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.10.16" osisID="1Sam.10.16"/> And Saul said to his uncle, <q>Why, he told us that the asses had been
       found!</q> He said noth­ing about the matter of the kingdom. <verse eID="1Sam.10.16"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eID="1Sam.10"/>
    <chapter osisID="1Sam.11" sID="1Sam.11"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.11.1" osisID="1Sam.11.1"/>About a month later, Nahash the Ammonite marched up and besieged
       <milestone type="pb" n="319"/>
       Jabesh-gilead, and the men of Jabesh-gilead all said to Nahash, <q>Make terms with us, and we will be your
       servants.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.11.1"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.11.2" osisID="1Sam.11.2"/> Nahash the Ammonite said to them, <q>I will make terms with you upon
       this condition, that I gouge out every man's right eye. So shall I stamp disgrace upon all Israel.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.11.2"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.11.3" osisID="1Sam.11.3"/> <q>Give us seven days' res­pite,</q> said the sheikhs of Jabesh, <q>that
       we may send messengers through all the territory of Is­rael. Then, if there is no one to rescue us, we will come
       out to you.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.11.3"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.11.4" osisID="1Sam.11.4"/> The messengers came to Saul's town of Gibeah and told their story to
       the people. All the people wept aloud. <verse eID="1Sam.11.4"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.11.5" osisID="1Sam.11.5"/> Saul, who was just coming home be­hind the oxen from the field, asked,
       <q>What is the matter with the people? Why are they weep­ing? So they told him what the men of Jabesh said.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.11.5"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.11.6" osisID="1Sam.11.6"/> The spirit of the Eternal inspired Saul mightily, when he heard this;
       his anger blazed up. <verse eID="1Sam.11.6"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.11.7" osisID="1Sam.11.7"/> He took a yoke of oxen, cut them in pieces, and sent them by the hand
       of messengers all over the territory of Israel, saying, <q>Who­ever does not come forward to follow Saul [[and
       Samuel]], so shall his oxen be treated!</q> The terror of the Eternal fell upon the people, and they gathered as
       one man. <verse eID="1Sam.11.7"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.11.8" osisID="1Sam.11.8"/> He numbered them at Bezek, three hundred thousand Israel­ites and thirty
       thousand men of Judah; <verse eID="1Sam.11.8"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.11.9" osisID="1Sam.11.9"/> then he told the mes­sengers to tell the men of Jabesh-gilead, <q>You
       will be delivered to­morrow, when the sun grows hot.</q> The messengers went and told the men of Jabesh, who were
       delighted; <verse eID="1Sam.11.9"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.11.10" osisID="1Sam.11.10"/> they said to Nahash, <q>We will come out to you to­morrow, and you can
       do whatever you like to us.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.11.10"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.11.11" osisID="1Sam.11.11"/> But on the morrow Saul arranged the peo­ple in three columns, and they
       made their way into the camp during the morning watch and routed the Ammonites till noon­day; the survivors were so
       scat­tered that no two men were left together. <verse eID="1Sam.11.11"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.11.12" osisID="1Sam.11.12"/> [[Then said the people to Samuel, <q>Who says Saul shall not reign
       over us? Bring such men, that we may put them to death.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.11.12"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.11.13" osisID="1Sam.11.13"/> But Saul said, <q>Not a man shall be put to death this day, for the
       Eternal has done a saving deed in Israel this day.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.11.13"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.11.14" osisID="1Sam.11.14"/> Then Samuel said to the people, <q>Come, let us go to Gilgal and
       ratify the kingdom there.</q>]] <verse eID="1Sam.11.14"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.11.15" osisID="1Sam.11.15"/> And all the people went to Gilgal, and at Gilgal they made Saul king
       in presence of the Eternal; there they sacrificed recompense-offerings in presence of the Eter­nal, and there Saul
       and all the men of Israel rejoiced exceeding­ly. <verse eID="1Sam.11.15"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eID="1Sam.11"/>
    <chapter osisID="1Sam.13" sID="1Sam.13"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.13.1" osisID="1Sam.13.1"/> [[Saul was . . . years old when he began to reign, and he reigned for
       . . . years over Israel.]] <verse eID="1Sam.13.1"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.13.2" osisID="1Sam.13.2"/> Saul picked three thousand men of Israel; two thousand were with Saul
       at Michmash and in the highlands of Bethel, one thousand were with Jonathan at Geba in Ben­jamin; the rest of the
       people he sent home, each man to his own tent. <verse eID="1Sam.13.2"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.13.3" osisID="1Sam.13.3"/> Jonathan defeated the prefect of the Philistines at Gibeah, and the
       Philistines heard a rumour that <q>the Hebrews had re­volted,</q> while Saul had the alarm sounded throughout all
       the land, <verse eID="1Sam.13.3"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.13.4" osisID="1Sam.13.4"/> till Israel heard a rumour that Saul had defeated the prefect of the
       Philistines and that Israel was in bad odour with the Philistines. Then the peo­ple rallied to Saul at Gilgal.
      <verse eID="1Sam.13.4"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.13.5" osisID="1Sam.13.5"/> The Philistines mustered to fight
       <milestone type="pb" n="320"/>
       against Israel with three thou­sand chariots, six thousand cav­alry, and infantry as numerous as the sand on the
       sea-shore: they marched up and camped at Michmash, east of Beth-aven. <verse eID="1Sam.13.5"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.13.6" osisID="1Sam.13.6"/> And when the men of Israel saw they were in straits (for the people
       were hard pressed), the people hid in caves and holes and rocks and tombs and pits; <verse eID="1Sam.13.6"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.13.7" osisID="1Sam.13.7"/> many crossed the Jordan into the land of Gad and Gilead. <verse eID="1Sam.13.7"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.13.8" osisID="1Sam.13.8"/> [[Saul was still at Gilgal, and the people were trembling and
     </p>
     <p>
      deserting him. <verse eID="1Sam.13.8"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.13.9" osisID="1Sam.13.9"/> He waited seven days, according to the time fixed by Samuel; but
       Samuel did not come to Gilgal, and meantime the people were scattering from him. <verse eID="1Sam.13.9"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.13.10" osisID="1Sam.13.10"/> So Saul said, <q>Bring the burnt-offering and the
       recompense-offerings here to me!</q> And he offered the burnt-offering. No sooner had he finished offering the
       burnt-offering than Samuel ar­rived. Saul went out to meet and greet him, <verse eID="1Sam.13.10"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.13.11" osisID="1Sam.13.11"/> but Samuel said, <q>What have you done?</q> Saul answered, <q>I saw
       the people were scattering from me, and you did not come at the time fixed, and the Philistines were massing at
       Michmash; <verse eID="1Sam.13.11"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.13.12" osisID="1Sam.13.12"/> so I thought, the Philistines will now pounce on us at Gilgal, and
       I have not appeased the Eternal. Hence I forced my­self to offer the burnt-offering.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.13.12"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.13.13" osisID="1Sam.13.13"/> <q>You have done a senseless thing,</q> said Samuel to Saul;
       <q>if you had obeyed the command of the Eternal your God, which he commanded you, then the Eternal would have
       established your kingdom over Israel forever. <verse eID="1Sam.13.13"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.13.14" osisID="1Sam.13.14"/> But now your kingdom shall not stand. The Eternal has discovered a
       man to his mind, and the Eternal has ap­pointed him to be prince over his people, because you have not obeyed
       what the Eternal commanded you.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.13.14"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.13.15" osisID="1Sam.13.15"/> Then Samuel went on his way from Gilgal.]]
     </p>
     <p>
       Saul numbered the people who were left with him, about six hundred men. <verse eID="1Sam.13.15"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.13.16" osisID="1Sam.13.16"/> Saul, Jonathan his son, and the people with them, remained at Geba
       in Benjamin, while the Philistines camped at Michmash. <verse eID="1Sam.13.16"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.13.17" osisID="1Sam.13.17"/> And raiders issued from the Philis­tine camp in three columns; one
       column took the road to Ophrah in the district of Shual, <verse eID="1Sam.13.17"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.13.18" osisID="1Sam.13.18"/> another column went in the direction of Beth-horon, and an­other
       column in the direction of the hill overlooking the wady of Hyaenas and facing the open country. <verse eID="1Sam.13.18"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.13.19" osisID="1Sam.13.19"/> [[No blacksmith was to be found anywhere in the land of Israel: for
       the Philistines were afraid of the Hebrews mak­ing swords or spears for them­selves. <verse eID="1Sam.13.19"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.13.20" osisID="1Sam.13.20"/> The Israelites all went down to the Philistines, each to get his
       ploughshare, his coulter, his axe, and his mattock sharp­ened . . . <verse eID="1Sam.13.20"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.13.22" osisID="1Sam.13.22"/> Thus, on the day of the battle of Michmash, none of the people with
       Saul and Jonathan had sword or spear--though Saul and Jonathan had weapons.]] <verse eID="1Sam.13.22"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.13.23" osisID="1Sam.13.23"/> The main body of the Philistines then moved to the pass of
       Michmash. <verse eID="1Sam.13.23"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eID="1Sam.13"/>
   </div>