   <div type="book" osisID="1Sam">
    <milestone type="pb" n="306"/>
    <chapter osisID="1Sam.1" sID="1Sam.1"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.1.1" osisID="1Sam.1.1"/>There was a man of Ramah, a Zuphite from the highlands of Ephraim, whose name
       was Elkanah---the son of Jeroham, the son of Elihu, the son of Tohu, the son of Zuph. He was an Ephraimite, <verse eID="1Sam.1.1"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.1.2" osisID="1Sam.1.2"/> and he had two wives, one called Hannah and the other Peninnah; Peninnah had
       children, but Hannah had no children. <verse eID="1Sam.1.2"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.1.3" osisID="1Sam.1.3"/> Now this man used to go up from his town, year by year, to worship and to
       sacrifice to the Lord of hosts at Shilo, where Eli and his two sons, Hophni and Phinehas, were priests to the
       Eternal. <verse eID="1Sam.1.3"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.1.4" osisID="1Sam.1.4"/> He used to give his wife Penin­nah and all her sons and daugh­ters shares of
       the sacrificial meat, <verse eID="1Sam.1.4"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.1.5" osisID="1Sam.1.5"/> but, though he loved Hannah, he gave her only a sin­gle share, because the
       Eternal had shut up her womb. <verse eID="1Sam.1.5"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.1.6" osisID="1Sam.1.6"/> Her rival used to taunt her bit­terly, to irritate her, because the Eternal
       had shut up her womb; <verse eID="1Sam.1.6"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.1.7" osisID="1Sam.1.7"/> and this went on year after year--whenever she went up to the house of the
       Eternal, she taunted Hannah. <verse eID="1Sam.1.7"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.1.4" osisID="1Sam.1.4"/> One day when Elkanah was sacrificing, Hannah wept and would not eat. <verse eID="1Sam.1.4"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.1.8" osisID="1Sam.1.8"/> So her husband Elkanah said to her, <q>Hannah, why are you weeping? Why are
       you not eating? Why is your heart sad? Am I not more to you than ten sons?</q> <verse eID="1Sam.1.8"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.1.9" osisID="1Sam.1.9"/> But after they had eaten the boiled flesh and had drunk, Hannah rose and
       stood before the Eternal where Eli the priest was sitting on his chair at the door­posts of the temple of the Eternal.
      <verse eID="1Sam.1.9"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.1.10" osisID="1Sam.1.10"/> With a sore heart she prayed to the Eternal, weeping bitterly, <verse eID="1Sam.1.10"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.1.11" osisID="1Sam.1.11"/> and she made this vow: <q>O Lord of hosts, if thou wilt in­deed look upon
       the plight of thy servant and remember me and not forget thy servant, but wilt give thy servant a son, then I will
       give him to the Eternal for the whole of his life; and no razor shall ever touch his head.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.1.11"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.1.12" osisID="1Sam.1.12"/> As she went on praying before the Eternal, Eli noticed her mouth--<verse eID="1Sam.1.12"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.1.13" osisID="1Sam.1.13"/> for Hannah was speaking to herself; only her lips moved, her voice was not
       heard. Eli thought she was drunk. <verse eID="1Sam.1.13"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.1.14" osisID="1Sam.1.14"/> So Eli said to her, <q>How long will you go on, you drunken creature? Away
       with you, go and sleep off your drunkenness!</q> <verse eID="1Sam.1.14"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.1.15" osisID="1Sam.1.15"/> But Hannah replied, <q>No, sir, I am a sorely tried woman, I have drunk
       neither wine nor liquor; I have been pouring out my soul be­fore the Eternal. <verse eID="1Sam.1.15"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.1.16" osisID="1Sam.1.16"/> Do not take your servant for a depraved woman; it is under my stress of
       grief and provocation that I have been speaking all the time.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.1.16"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.1.17" osisID="1Sam.1.17"/> Then Eli answered, <q>Go and prosper; may the God of Israel grant you what
       you have asked him!</q> <verse eID="1Sam.1.17"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.1.18" osisID="1Sam.1.18"/> And she said, <q>May your servant find favour in your eyes!</q> <verse eID="1Sam.1.18"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.1.19" osisID="1Sam.1.19"/> So the woman went away; she ate, and her face was sad no longer. In the
       morning they rose, worshipped before the Eternal, and returned home to Ramah. Elkanah had inter­course with Hannah his
       wife, and the Eternal remembered her; <verse eID="1Sam.1.19"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.1.20" osisID="1Sam.1.20"/> so Hannah conceived, and at the turn of the year she bore a son, calling
       his name Samuel or <q>God-asked.</q> <q>For,</q> she said, <q>I asked the Eternal for him.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.1.20"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.1.21" osisID="1Sam.1.21"/> Elkanah went up with all
       <milestone type="pb" n="307"/>
       his household to offer to the Eternal the yearly sacrifice and what he had vowed, but Han-
nah did not go up. “Once the child is weaned,” she told her husband, “then I will bring him; we shall appear before the Eternal, and he shall remain
there for ever.” Elkanah her husband said to her, “Do what­ever you think right; wait till you have weaned him, and may the Eternal let you carry out your purpose.” So Hannah waited and suckled her son till
she weaned him. Then, after weaning him, she took him with her, along with a three-year- old bullock, a bushel of flour, and a bottle of wine; she entered the house of the Eternal at Shilo, accompanied by the boy,
and, after the bullock had been slain, she brought the boy to
Eli. “As sure as you live, sir,” she said, “I am the woman who stood beside you here, praying
to the Eternal. I prayed about this boy, and the Eternal has
granted me what I asked. So I have lent him to the Eternal; as long as he lives he is loaned
to the Eternal.”
      <verse eID="1Sam.1.21"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.1.22" osisID="1Sam.1.22"/>
      <verse eID="1Sam.1.22"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.1.23" osisID="1Sam.1.23"/>
      <verse eID="1Sam.1.23"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.1.24" osisID="1Sam.1.24"/>
      <verse eID="1Sam.1.24"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.1.25" osisID="1Sam.1.25"/>
      <verse eID="1Sam.1.25"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.1.26" osisID="1Sam.1.26"/>
      <verse eID="1Sam.1.26"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.1.27" osisID="1Sam.1.27"/>
      <verse eID="1Sam.1.27"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.1.28" osisID="1Sam.1.28"/>
      <verse eID="1Sam.1.28"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eID="1Sam.1"/>
   </div>