   <div type="book" osisID="1Sam">
    <milestone type="pb" n="306"/>
    <chapter osisID="1Sam.1" sID="1Sam.1"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.1.1" osisID="1Sam.1.1"/>There was a man of Ramah, a Zuphite from the highlands of Ephraim, whose name
       was Elkanah---the son of Jeroham, the son of Elihu, the son of Tohu, the son of Zuph. He was an Ephraimite, <verse eID="1Sam.1.1"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.1.2" osisID="1Sam.1.2"/> and he had two wives, one called Hannah and the other Peninnah; Peninnah had
       children, but Hannah had no children. <verse eID="1Sam.1.2"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.1.3" osisID="1Sam.1.3"/> Now this man used to go up from his town, year by year, to worship and to
       sacrifice to the Lord of hosts at Shilo, where Eli and his two sons, Hophni and Phinehas, were priests to the
       Eternal. <verse eID="1Sam.1.3"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.1.4" osisID="1Sam.1.4"/> He used to give his wife Penin­nah and all her sons and daugh­ters shares of
       the sacrificial meat, <verse eID="1Sam.1.4"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.1.5" osisID="1Sam.1.5"/> but, though he loved Hannah, he gave her only a sin­gle share, because the
       Eternal had shut up her womb. <verse eID="1Sam.1.5"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.1.6" osisID="1Sam.1.6"/> Her rival used to taunt her bit­terly, to irritate her, because the Eternal
       had shut up her womb; <verse eID="1Sam.1.6"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.1.7" osisID="1Sam.1.7"/> and this went on year after year--whenever she went up to the house of the
       Eternal, she taunted Hannah. <verse eID="1Sam.1.7"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.1.4" osisID="1Sam.1.4"/> One day when Elkanah was sacrificing, Hannah wept and would not eat. <verse eID="1Sam.1.4"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.1.8" osisID="1Sam.1.8"/> So her husband Elkanah said to her, <q>Hannah, why are you weeping? Why are
       you not eating? Why is your heart sad? Am I not more to you than ten sons?</q> <verse eID="1Sam.1.8"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.1.9" osisID="1Sam.1.9"/> But after they had eaten the boiled flesh and had drunk, Hannah rose and
       stood before the Eternal where Eli the priest was sitting on his chair at the door­posts of the temple of the Eternal.
      <verse eID="1Sam.1.9"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.1.10" osisID="1Sam.1.10"/> With a sore heart she prayed to the Eternal, weeping bitterly, <verse eID="1Sam.1.10"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.1.11" osisID="1Sam.1.11"/> and she made this vow: <q>O Lord of hosts, if thou wilt in­deed look upon
       the plight of thy servant and remember me and not forget thy servant, but wilt give thy servant a son, then I will
       give him to the Eternal for the whole of his life; and no razor shall ever touch his head.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.1.11"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.1.12" osisID="1Sam.1.12"/> As she went on praying before the Eternal, Eli noticed her mouth--<verse eID="1Sam.1.12"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.1.13" osisID="1Sam.1.13"/> for Hannah was speaking to herself; only her lips moved, her voice was not
       heard. Eli thought she was drunk. <verse eID="1Sam.1.13"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.1.14" osisID="1Sam.1.14"/> So Eli said to her, <q>How long will you go on, you drunken creature? Away
       with you, go and sleep off your drunkenness!</q> <verse eID="1Sam.1.14"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.1.15" osisID="1Sam.1.15"/> But Hannah replied, <q>No, sir, I am a sorely tried woman, I have drunk
       neither wine nor liquor; I have been pouring out my soul be­fore the Eternal. <verse eID="1Sam.1.15"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.1.16" osisID="1Sam.1.16"/> Do not take your servant for a depraved woman; it is under my stress of
       grief and provocation that I have been speaking all the time.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.1.16"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.1.17" osisID="1Sam.1.17"/> Then Eli answered, <q>Go and prosper; may the God of Israel grant you what
       you have asked him!</q> <verse eID="1Sam.1.17"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.1.18" osisID="1Sam.1.18"/> And she said, <q>May your servant find favour in your eyes!</q> <verse eID="1Sam.1.18"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.1.19" osisID="1Sam.1.19"/> So the woman went away; she ate, and her face was sad no longer. In the
       morning they rose, worshipped before the Eternal, and returned home to Ramah. Elkanah had inter­course with Hannah his
       wife, and the Eternal remembered her; <verse eID="1Sam.1.19"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.1.20" osisID="1Sam.1.20"/> so Hannah conceived, and at the turn of the year she bore a son, calling
       his name Samuel or <q>God-asked.</q> <q>For,</q> she said, <q>I asked the Eternal for him.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.1.20"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.1.21" osisID="1Sam.1.21"/> Elkanah went up with all
       <milestone type="pb" n="307"/>
       his household to offer to the Eternal the yearly sacrifice and what he had vowed, <verse eID="1Sam.1.21"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.1.22" osisID="1Sam.1.22"/> but Hannah did not go up. <q>Once the child is weaned,</q> she told her
       husband, <q>then I will bring him; we shall appear before the Eternal, and he shall remain there for ever.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.1.22"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.1.23" osisID="1Sam.1.23"/> Elkanah her husband said to her, <q>Do what­ever you think right; wait
       till you have weaned him, and may the Eternal let you carry out your purpose.</q> So Hannah waited and suckled her son
       till she weaned him. <verse eID="1Sam.1.23"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.1.24" osisID="1Sam.1.24"/> Then, after weaning him, she took him with her, along with a
       three-year-old bullock, a bushel of flour, and a bottle of wine; she entered the house of the Eternal at Shilo,
       accompanied by the boy, <verse eID="1Sam.1.24"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.1.25" osisID="1Sam.1.25"/> and, after the bullock had been slain, she brought the boy to Eli. <verse eID="1Sam.1.25"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.1.26" osisID="1Sam.1.26"/> <q>As sure as you live, sir,</q> she said, <q>I am the woman who stood
       beside you here, praying to the Eternal. <verse eID="1Sam.1.26"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.1.27" osisID="1Sam.1.27"/> I prayed about this boy, and the Eternal has granted me what I asked. <verse eID="1Sam.1.27"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.1.28" osisID="1Sam.1.28"/> So I have lent him to the Eternal; as long as he lives he is loaned to the
       Eternal.</q><verse eID="1Sam.1.28"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eID="1Sam.1"/>
    <chapter osisID="1Sam.2" sID="1Sam.2"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.2.1" osisID="1Sam.2.1"/>[[Hannah sang this prayer:
      <lg>
       <l> My heart thrills to the Eternal, </l>
       <l> my powers are heightened by my God, </l>
       <l> my lips exult over my foes, </l>
       <l> for I joy in thy deliverance. </l>
      <verse eID="1Sam.2.1"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.2.2" osisID="1Sam.2.2"/>
       <l> None is divine like the Eternal, </l>
       <l> no Power is steadfast like our God. </l>
      <verse eID="1Sam.2.2"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.2.3" osisID="1Sam.2.3"/>
       <l> No more of your proud vaunts! </l>
       <l> No mouthing of your taunts! </l>
       <l> For the Eternal is a God who knows it all, </l>
       <l> and what men do he judges. </l>
      <verse eID="1Sam.2.3"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.2.4" osisID="1Sam.2.4"/>
       <l> The strong man’s bow is broken, </l>
       <l> and the stumbling are braced up; </l>
      <verse eID="1Sam.2.4"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.2.5" osisID="1Sam.2.5"/>
       <l> those who had plenty have to work for bread, </l>
       <l> and hungry people have to toil no more; </l>
       <l> the barren woman has seven chil­dren now, </l>
       <l> and the mother of many is pining. </l>
      <verse eID="1Sam.2.5"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.2.6" osisID="1Sam.2.6"/>
       <l> The Eternal kills, the Eternal life bestows, </l>
       <l> he lowers to death and he lifts up, </l>
      <verse eID="1Sam.2.6"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.2.7" osisID="1Sam.2.7"/>
       <l> the Eternal makes poor, the Eternal makes rich, </l>
       <l> he lays low and he raises, </l>
      <verse eID="1Sam.2.7"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.2.8" osisID="1Sam.2.8"/>
       <l> he lifts the poor out of the dust, </l>
       <l> he raises beggars from the rub­bish heap, </l>
       <l> seating them next to nobles, </l>
       <l> to give them thrones of splendour. </l>
       <l> [[For the pillars of the earth be­long to the Eternal, </l>
       <l> and on them he set the world.]] </l>
      <verse eID="1Sam.2.8"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.2.9" osisID="1Sam.2.9"/>
       <l> He will guard the steps of his godly folk, </l>
       <l> but evil men shall perish in the dark </l>
       <l> (for no man's strength makes him mighty).</l>
      <verse eID="1Sam.2.9"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.2.10" osisID="1Sam.2.10"/>
       <l> The Eternal will crush his enemies, </l>
       <l> the Most High in heaven will shatter them </l>
       <l> (the Eternal's judgments shall cover the wide world), </l>
       <l> to add power to his king, </l>
       <l> to heighten the strength of his anointed one.]]</l>
      </lg>
      <verse eID="1Sam.2.10"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.2.11" osisID="1Sam.2.11"/> Then Hannah left him there before the Eternal, and went to Hamah; but the
       boy ministered to the Eternal in presence of Eli the priest. <verse eID="1Sam.2.11"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.2.12" osisID="1Sam.2.12"/> Now the sons of Eli were depraved creatures; they cared nothing for the
       Eternal nor for the regular dues of a priest. <verse eID="1Sam.2.12"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.2.13" osisID="1Sam.2.13"/> Whenever a man offered sacrifice, the priest’s servant would come, as the
       flesh was being boiled, with a three-pronged fork in his hand, <verse eID="1Sam.2.13"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.2.14" osisID="1Sam.2.14"/> which he plunged into the pot or kettle or basin or dish; whatever the
       fork brought up, the priest took for himself. So they treated ail the Israelites who came to sac­rifice at Shilo to
       the Eternal. <verse eID="1Sam.2.14"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.2.15" osisID="1Sam.2.15"/> In fact, even before the fat was burned, the priest’s servant
       <milestone type="pb" n="308"/>
       would come and tell the man who was sacrificing, <q>Let the priest have some flesh for roast­ing; he wants raw flesh
       from you, not boiled.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.2.15"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.2.16" osisID="1Sam.2.16"/> If the man said to him, <q>First let the fat be burned, and then take as
       much as you want,</q> he would answer, <q>No, you must give it to me at once, or I will take it by force.</q> <verse eID="1Sam.2.16"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.2.17" osisID="1Sam.2.17"/> The sin of the young men was very great before the Eternal, for it meant
       disdain of what was offered to the Eternal. <verse eID="1Sam.2.17"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.2.18" osisID="1Sam.2.18"/> Samuel, a boy girt with a linen apron, ministered before the Eternal, <verse eID="1Sam.2.18"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.2.19" osisID="1Sam.2.19"/> and his mother used to make him a little robe, which she brought to him
       year by year when she came up with her husband to offer the yearly sacrifice. <verse eID="1Sam.2.19"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.2.20" osisID="1Sam.2.20"/> Eli would bless Elkanah and his wife, saying,<q>May the Eternal repay
       you with off­spring from this woman, for the loan she has made to the Eter­nal!</q> Then they would go home. <verse eID="1Sam.2.20"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.2.21" osisID="1Sam.2.21"/> And the Eternal re­membered Hannah, so that she conceived and bore three
       sons and two daughters. Meantime the boy Samuel grew up before the Eternal. <verse eID="1Sam.2.21"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.2.22" osisID="1Sam.2.22"/>
Now Eli was very old. When­ever he heard how his sons were behaving towards all Israel, and how they lay with the women caretakers at the door of the
Trysting tent, he said to them, “Why are you behaving like this? I hear of it from all the
people. No, my sons, it is no good report that I hear the peo-
pie of the Eternal repeating. If one man sins against another man, God will mediate for him, but if a man sins against the Eternal, who can intercede on Ms behalf?” However, they would not listen to what their father said, for the Eternal was
resolved to slay them. Mean- 26 time Samuel grew up to be a fine boy in the eyes of the Eter­nal and of men.
      <verse eID="1Sam.2.22"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.2.23" osisID="1Sam.2.23"/>
      <verse eID="1Sam.2.23"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.2.24" osisID="1Sam.2.24"/>
      <verse eID="1Sam.2.24"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.2.25" osisID="1Sam.2.25"/>
      <verse eID="1Sam.2.25"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.2.26" osisID="1Sam.2.26"/>
      <verse eID="1Sam.2.26"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="1Sam.2.27" osisID="1Sam.2.27"/>
Now a man of God came to 27 Eli and gave him this message from the Eternal. “Did I not reveal myself to your father’s household when they were in Egypt, slaves to the court of the Pharaoh? Did I not choose 28 him from all the clans of Israel to be my priest, to go up to my altar, to burn sacrifice, and to bear the ephod in my presence? Did I not assign to your father’s household as food all that the Israelites offer by fire? Why, 29 then, do you cast an envious eye upon my sacrifices and offer­ings, letting your sons override me and fattening yourselves under my very eyes upon the first-fruits of all that Israel my people offers? Therefore the 30 Eternal, the God of Israel, de­clares, I had meant your house­hold and your father’s house­hold to live in my favour for ever; but now, says the Eternal, far be that from me; those who honour me I will honour, and those who despise me shall be derided. The day is coming 31 when I will cut off your off­spring and the offspring of your father’s household till there is not an old man left in your household; then in your straits 32 you shall look enviously on all the prosperity I award to Is­rael. One of your family I will 33 not cut off from my altar, I will spare him to consume his eyes with longing and to wear out Ms heart; but the greater part of your household shall die by the sword of men. What is to 34 befall your two sons Hophni and Phinehas shall be an omen for you; both are to die on the
      <verse eID="1Sam.2.27"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.2.28" osisID="1Sam.2.28"/>
      <verse eID="1Sam.2.28"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.2.29" osisID="1Sam.2.29"/>
      <verse eID="1Sam.2.29"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.2.30" osisID="1Sam.2.30"/>
      <verse eID="1Sam.2.30"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.2.31" osisID="1Sam.2.31"/>
      <verse eID="1Sam.2.31"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.2.32" osisID="1Sam.2.32"/>
      <verse eID="1Sam.2.32"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.2.33" osisID="1Sam.2.33"/>
      <verse eID="1Sam.2.33"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.2.34" osisID="1Sam.2.34"/>
       <milestone type="pb" n="309"/>
same day. But I will raise up for myself a faithful priest, who is to do whatever I plan and desire; I will found a family for him that lasts; he shall live in the favour of my anointed king
for ever, and any survivor of your household shall come and do him obeisance for a pit­tance of money and a piece of bread, crying, ‘Do put me in some priestly position, that I may get a bite of food to eat.5 ”
      <verse eID="1Sam.2.34"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.2.35" osisID="1Sam.2.35"/>
      <verse eID="1Sam.2.35"/>
      <verse sID="1Sam.2.36" osisID="1Sam.2.36"/>
      <verse eID="1Sam.2.36"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eID="1Sam.2"/>
   </div>