   <div type="book" osisID="2Kgs">
     <chapter osisID="2Kgs.1" sID="2Kgs.1"/>
       <milestone type="pb" n="416"/>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.1.1" osisID="2Kgs.1.1"/> [[After Ahab's death Moab rebelled against Israel.]] <verse eID="2Kgs.1.1"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.1.2" osisID="2Kgs.1.2"/> Ahaziah, who had fallen through the lattice in his upper chamber
            in Samaria, was lying ill; so he sent messengers with orders to find out from Baal-zebub the god of Ekron
            whether he would recover from his illness. <verse eID="2Kgs.1.2"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.1.3" osisID="2Kgs.1.3"/> The angel of the Eternal told Elijah the Tishbite to go and
            meet the messengers of the king of Samaria and ask them, <q>Is it because there is no God in Israel that
            you are going to consult Baal-zebub the god of Ekron?</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.1.3"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.1.4" osisID="2Kgs.1.4"/> Elijah was to give them this answer from the Eternal for the
            king, <q>You shall never leave the bed to which you have taken; you must die.</q> Elijah then left them.
           <verse eID="2Kgs.1.4"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.1.5" osisID="2Kgs.1.5"/> And when the messengers returned to the king, he asked why they
            had come back. <verse eID="2Kgs.1.5"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.1.6" osisID="2Kgs.1.6"/> They told him that a man had come up to meet them and said,
            <q>Go back to the king who sent you and tell him this from the Eternal: <q>Is it because there is no God
            in Israel that you send to consult Baal-zebub the god of Ekron? For this you shall never leave the bed to
            which you have taken; you must die.</q></q> <verse eID="2Kgs.1.6"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.1.7" osisID="2Kgs.1.7"/> The king asked, <q>This man who came up to meet you and spoke
            to you, what was he like?</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.1.7"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.1.8" osisID="2Kgs.1.8"/> They said, <q>He wore a mantle of hair, with a waist-cloth of
            leather round his middle.</q> <q>It is Elijah the Tishbite,</q> said the king, <verse eID="2Kgs.1.8"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.1.9" osisID="2Kgs.1.9"/> and he despatched a captain with his fifty men to seize him.
            Elijah was sitting on the top of a hill; so the captain went up and said to him, <q>0 man of God, the
            king orders you to come down.</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.1.9"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.1.10" osisID="2Kgs.1.10"/> <q>If I am a man of God,</q> answered Elijah, <q>let fire fall
            from heaven and destroy you and your fifty men.</q> Down fell fire from heaven, destroying him and his fifty
            men. <verse eID="2Kgs.1.10"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.1.11" osisID="2Kgs.1.11"/> Once more the king despatched another captain with his fifty
            men. He went up and said, <q>O man of God, this is the king’s order: Come down at once.</q><verse eID="2Kgs.1.11"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.1.12" osisID="2Kgs.1.12"/> <q>If I am a man of God,</q> Elijah said to them, <q>let fire
            fall from heaven and destroy you and your fifty men.</q> Down fell God's fire from heaven, destroying him
            and his fifty men. <verse eID="2Kgs.1.12"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.1.13" osisID="2Kgs.1.13"/> Again the king sent a third captain with his fifty men. The
            third captain went up and fell on his knees before Elijah, beseeching him, <q>O man of God, pray spare my
            life and the lives of these fifty men, your servants. <verse eID="2Kgs.1.13"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.1.14" osisID="2Kgs.1.14"/> Fire fell from heaven, destroying the two former captains and
            their companies; now spare my life.</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.1.14"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.1.15" osisID="2Kgs.1.15"/> So the angel of the Eternal said to Elijah, <q>Go down along
            with him; have no fear of him.</q> He rose and went down along with him to the king, <verse eID="2Kgs.1.15"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.1.16" osisID="2Kgs.1.16"/> telling the king this message from the Eternal: <q>Since you
            sent messengers to consult Baal-zebub the god of Ekron, you shall never leave the bed to which you have
            taken; you must die.</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.1.16"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.1.17" osisID="2Kgs.1.17"/> And die he did, exactly as the Eternal had predicted by
            Elijah. <verse eID="2Kgs.1.17"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.1.18" osisID="2Kgs.1.18"/> The rest of the acts done by Ahaziah, are they not described
            in the book of the Annals of the Kings of Israel? <verse eID="2Kgs.1.18"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.1.17" osisID="2Kgs.1.17"/> Jehoram his brother began to reign instead of him, as he had
            no son (in the second year of Jehoram the son
            <milestone type="pb" n="417"/>
            of Jehoshaphat king of Judah).
           <verse eID="2Kgs.1.17"/>
       </p>
     <chapter eID="2Kgs.1"/>
     <chapter osisID="2Kgs.2" sID="2Kgs.2"/>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.2.1" osisID="2Kgs.2.1"/> Now when the Eternal was about to take up Elijah by a whirlwind
            into heaven, Elijah was leaving Gilgal along with Elisha; <verse eID="2Kgs.2.1"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.2.2" osisID="2Kgs.2.2"/> he said to Elisha, <q>Pray remain here, for the Eternal sends
            me as far as Bethel.</q> But Elisha answered, <q>As the Eternal lives and as you live, I will not leave
            you.</q> So down they went to Bethel. <verse eID="2Kgs.2.2"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.2.3" osisID="2Kgs.2.3"/> The guild of prophets at Bethel came out and asked Elisha,
           <q>Do you know that the Eternal is taking away your lord and master to­day?</q> <q>Yes,</q> he answered;
           <q>only hold your tongues.</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.2.3"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.2.4" osisID="2Kgs.2.4"/> Elijah said to him, <q>Pray remain here, Elisha, for the
            Eternal sends me to Jericho.</q> <q>As the Eternal lives, and as you live,</q> he said, <q>I will not
            leave you.</q>  So to Jericho they went.<verse eID="2Kgs.2.4"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.2.5" osisID="2Kgs.2.5"/> The guild of prophets at Jericho came out and asked Elisha,
            <q>Do you know that the Eternal is taking away your lord and master to-day?</q> <q>Yes,</q> he answered,
            <q>only hold your tongues.</q> Elijah said to him, <verse eID="2Kgs.2.5"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.2.6" osisID="2Kgs.2.6"/> <q>Pray remain here, for the Eternal sends me to the Jordan.</q>
            <q>As the Eternal lives and as you live,</q> he answered, <q>I will not leave you.</q> So the two of them went
            on. <verse eID="2Kgs.2.6"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.2.7" osisID="2Kgs.2.7"/> Fifty members of the guild went and stood opposite them at a
            distance, as the two of them were standing beside the Jordan; <verse eID="2Kgs.2.7"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.2.8" osisID="2Kgs.2.8"/> Elijah, rolling up his mantle, struck the water till it parted
            right and left, so that they could cross on dry ground. <verse eID="2Kgs.2.8"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.2.9" osisID="2Kgs.2.9"/> When they had crossed, Elijah said to Elisha, <q>Before I am taken
            from you, ask me for something.</q> Elisha answered, <q>Let me fall heir to your spirit.</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.2.9"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.2.10" osisID="2Kgs.2.10"/> <q>You have asked something hard,</q> said Elijah; <q>if you
            see me when I am being taken from you, it shall be yours, but not if you fail to see me.</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.2.10"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.2.11" osisID="2Kgs.2.11"/> Suddenly, as they walked and talked, a chariot of fire with
            horses of fire drove between them, and Elijah went up by a whirlwind into heaven. <verse eID="2Kgs.2.11"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.2.12" osisID="2Kgs.2.12"/> When Elisha saw this he cried, <q>My father, my father!
            worth chariots and horsemen to Israel!</q> Losing sight of him, Elisha seized his clothes and tore them
            in two. <verse eID="2Kgs.2.12"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.2.13" osisID="2Kgs.2.13"/> Then, lifting the mantle which had fallen from Elijah, he
            went back and stood on the bank of the Jordan; <verse eID="2Kgs.2.13"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.2.14" osisID="2Kgs.2.14"/> taking the mantle which had fallen from Elijah he struck the
            water, crying, <q>Where is the Eternal, the God of Elijah?</q> And, when he struck the water, it parted right
            and left, so that Elisha could cross. <verse eID="2Kgs.2.14"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.2.15" osisID="2Kgs.2.15"/> When the guild of prophets opposite saw him, they said, <q>The
            spirit of Elijah rests on Elisha!</q> They came forward to meet him and bowed before him to the ground. <verse eID="2Kgs.2.15"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.2.16" osisID="2Kgs.2.16"/> Then they said, <q>Your servants here have fifty stalwart
            men; pray let them go in search of your master, lest the spirit of the Eternal perhaps has caught him away and
            dropped him on some hill or in some valley.</q> Elisha refused. <verse eID="2Kgs.2.16"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.2.17" osisID="2Kgs.2.17"/> But, as they pressed him till he was ashamed, he agreed. So
            they sent fifty men, who searched for three days and failed to find him. <verse eID="2Kgs.2.17"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.2.18" osisID="2Kgs.2.18"/> When they came back to Elisha, who was still staying at
            Jericho, he said to them, <q>Did I not tell you not to go?</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.2.18"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.2.19" osisID="2Kgs.2.19"/> The townsmen said to Elisha, <q>The situation of this town is
            delightful, as my lord sees, but
            <milestone type="pb" n="418"/>
            the water is bad and it causes miscarriages.</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.2.19"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.2.20" osisID="2Kgs.2.20"/> <q>Bring me a new flask,</q> said Elisha, <q>and put in some
            salt.</q> They did so. <verse eID="2Kgs.2.20"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.2.21" osisID="2Kgs.2.21"/> Then he went to the source of their water-supply and,
            throwing salt in, he uttered this word from the Eternal, <q>I hereby heal these waters; never again
            shall they cause death or miscarriages.</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.2.21"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.2.22" osisID="2Kgs.2.22"/> To this day the waters remain healed, exactly as Elisha said.
           <verse eID="2Kgs.2.22"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.2.23" osisID="2Kgs.2.23"/> On his way to Bethel, as he was walking up the road, some
            small boys from the town mocked him, crying, <q>Walk up, baldhead! Walk up, baldhead!</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.2.23"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.2.24" osisID="2Kgs.2.24"/> When he looked round and saw them, he cursed them in the name
            of the Eternal; two she-bears came out of the wood and mangled forty-two of the boys. <verse eID="2Kgs.2.24"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.2.25" osisID="2Kgs.2.25"/> From Bethel he went on to mount Karmel, and then made his way
            back to Samaria. <verse eID="2Kgs.2.25"/>
       </p>
     <chapter eID="2Kgs.2"/>
     <chapter osisID="2Kgs.3" sID="2Kgs.3"/>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.1" osisID="2Kgs.3.1"/> In the eighteenth year of Jehoshaphat king of Judah, Jehoram
            the son of Ahab began to reign over Israel in Samaria, and he reigned for twelve years. <verse eID="2Kgs.3.1"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/> He did what was evil in the sight of the Eternal, though not
            like his father and his mother, for he removed the obelisk of Baal which his father had made. <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.3" osisID="2Kgs.3.3"/> Still, he adhered to the sin by which Jeroboam the son of
            Nebat had led Israel into sin; he never broke away from that. <verse eID="2Kgs.3.3"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.4" osisID="2Kgs.3.4"/> Mesha king of Moab was a sheep-master; he used to pay tribute
            to the king of Israel, the fleeces of a hundred thousand sheep and a hundred thousand rams. <verse eID="2Kgs.3.4"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.5" osisID="2Kgs.3.5"/> But after Ahab died, the king of Moab rebelled against the king
            of Israel. <verse eID="2Kgs.3.5"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.6" osisID="2Kgs.3.6"/> Then king Jehoram left Samaria to muster all Israel; <verse eID="2Kgs.3.6"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.7" osisID="2Kgs.3.7"/> he also sent this message to Jehoshaphat the king of Judah:
            <q>The king of Moab has rebelled against me; will you join me in making war upon Moab?</q> <q>I
            will,</q> he answered; <q>I am one with you, my people are one with your people, my horses with your
            horses.</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.3.7"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.8" osisID="2Kgs.3.8"/> He added, <q>And how are we to march?</q> <q>By the desert of
            Edom,</q> said Jehoram. <verse eID="2Kgs.3.8"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.9" osisID="2Kgs.3.9"/> So the king of Israel started, with the king of Judah and the
            king of Edom, marching for seven days along a roundabout route, till the army and its train of beasts
            had no water. <verse eID="2Kgs.3.9"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.10" osisID="2Kgs.3.10"/> <q>Alas!</q> said the king of Israel, <q>here has the Eternal
           gathered three kings, only to put them into the hands of Moab!</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.3.10"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.11" osisID="2Kgs.3.11"/> Jehoshaphat said, <q>Is there no prophet of the Eternal here,
            by whom we may consult the Eternal?</q> An officer of the king of Israel replied, <q>Elisha the son of
            Shaphat is here, who used to be servant to Elijah.</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.3.11"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.12" osisID="2Kgs.3.12"/> Said Jehoshaphat, <q>The word of the Eternal is with him.</q>
            So the king of Israel and Jehoshaphat and the king of Edom went to him. <verse eID="2Kgs.3.12"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.13" osisID="2Kgs.3.13"/> Elisha said to the king of Israel, <q>What have you to do
            with me? Away to the prophets of your father and the prophets of your mother!</q> The king of Israel
            protested, <q>No, it is the Eternal who has gathered us three kings, only to put us into the hands of
            Moab.</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.3.13"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.14" osisID="2Kgs.3.14"/> <q>As surely as the Eternal lives, whom I serve,</q> said
            Elisha, <q>were it not that I have some respect for Jehoshaphat the king of Judah here, I would not look
            your way, I would never notice you. <verse eID="2Kgs.3.14"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.15" osisID="2Kgs.3.15"/> However, bring me a minstrel</q> (for, whenever a minstrel
            played, he would fall into a trance from the Eternal). <verse eID="2Kgs.3.15"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.16" osisID="2Kgs.3.16"/> Then he uttered this word from the Eternal: <q>I will
            <milestone type="pb" n="419"/>
            make this dry ravine pool after pool of water. <verse eID="2Kgs.3.16"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.17" osisID="2Kgs.3.17"/> For, the Eternal declares, though you see neither wind nor
            rain, this dry ravine shall be so full of water that you and your armies and your beasts shall all
            drink. <verse eID="2Kgs.3.17"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.18" osisID="2Kgs.3.18"/> So little is this to the Eternal, that he will also put the
            Moabites into your power; <verse eID="2Kgs.3.18"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.19" osisID="2Kgs.3.19"/> you shall storm every fortified town and fell every
            fruitful tree and stop every fountain and spoil every good field with stones.</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.3.19"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.20" osisID="2Kgs.3.20"/> Next morning, about the hour for the morning sacrifice,
            water did come from the direction of Edom, till the country was full of water. <verse eID="2Kgs.3.20"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.21" osisID="2Kgs.3.21"/> Now, on hearing that the kings had marched to attack them,
            all the Moabites had been mustered, all at and above the age of bearing arms; they were posted on the
            frontier. <verse eID="2Kgs.3.21"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.22" osisID="2Kgs.3.22"/> When they rose in the morning, the sun was shining on the
            water, and, seeing the water in front of them as red as blood, <verse eID="2Kgs.3.22"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.23" osisID="2Kgs.3.23"/> the Moabites said, <q>This is blood! The kings must have been
            fighting among themselves, they have killed one another! Now then, Moab to the spoil!</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.3.23"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.24" osisID="2Kgs.3.24"/> But when they reached the camp of Israel, the Israelites
            started an attack, till the Moabites fled before them; they pressed forward, cutting down the Moabites
            as they went; <verse eID="2Kgs.3.24"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.25" osisID="2Kgs.3.25"/> they demolished the towns, every man threw a stone on every
            good field till it was covered, they stopped every fountain, and they felled every fruitful tree,
            harrying Moab till no Moabites wrere left except in Kirhareseth, which the shngers surrounded and laid
            low. <verse eID="2Kgs.3.25"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.26" osisID="2Kgs.3.26"/> The king of Moab, when he saw that the battle was too hot for
            him, took seven hundred swordsmen to cut his way through to the king of Edom. This failed. <verse eID="2Kgs.3.26"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.27" osisID="2Kgs.3.27"/> So he took his eldest son, the heir to the throne, and
            sacrificed him on the wall. It brought such a storm of indignation against Israel, that the Israelites
            had to leave him alone and return home. <verse eID="2Kgs.3.27"/>
       </p>
     <chapter eID="2Kgs.3"/>
     <chapter osisID="2Kgs.4" sID="2Kgs.4"/>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.4.1" osisID="2Kgs.4.1"/> The wife of a member of the prophets' guild once made an
            appeal to Elisha. <q>Your serv­ant my husband is dead,</q> she cried, <q>and you know that your servant
           reverenced the Eternal. Now a creditor has come to seize my two children and make them his slaves.</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.4.1"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.4.2" osisID="2Kgs.4.2"/> <q>What can I do for you?</q> said Elisha. <q>Tell me what you
            have in the house.</q> She replied, <q>Your humble servant has nothing in the house at all, except a
            flask of olive-oil.</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.4.2"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.4.3" osisID="2Kgs.4.3"/> <q>Then borrow vessels here and there,</q> he said, <q>from all
            your neighbours, empty vessels, plenty of them; <verse eID="2Kgs.4.3"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.4.4" osisID="2Kgs.4.4"/> shut yourself into the house, you and your sons; pour the oil
            into all these vessels; and, whenever one is full, set it aside.</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.4.4"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.4.5" osisID="2Kgs.4.5"/> She went away and did so, shutting herself and her sons inside the
            house. They brought the vessels, while she poured out the oil. <verse eID="2Kgs.4.5"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.4.6" osisID="2Kgs.4.6"/> When the vessels had been filled, she said to her boy, <q>Bring
            another.</q> He said to her, <q>There is not one more.</q> Whereupon the oil stopped flowing. <verse eID="2Kgs.4.6"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.4.7" osisID="2Kgs.4.7"/> When she went and told the man of God, he bade her sell some of
            the oil to pay her debts, and then live, herself and her sons, off the rest. <verse eID="2Kgs.4.7"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.4.8" osisID="2Kgs.4.8"/> One day Elisha went over to Shunem, and a rich lady who lived
            there made him take some food. After this he used to turn in for a meal whenever he was passing. <verse eID="2Kgs.4.8"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.4.9" osisID="2Kgs.4.9"/> So she said to her husband,
            <milestone type="pb" n="420"/>
            <q>This is a holy man of God, I see, who is constantly passing. <verse eID="2Kgs.4.9"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.4.10" osisID="2Kgs.4.10"/> Come and let us build a small guest-chamber for him, with a
            bed and a table and a seat and a lamp, so that whenever he comes to us he can turn in.</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.4.10"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.4.11" osisID="2Kgs.4.11"/> One day he came, and he did turn in to the chamber and rested
            there. <verse eID="2Kgs.4.11"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.4.12" osisID="2Kgs.4.12"/> <q>Call this Shunammite,</q> he said to his servant Gehazi.
            And when she stood before him, at his bidding, <verse eID="2Kgs.4.12"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.4.13" osisID="2Kgs.4.13"/> he told Gehazi to ask her, <q>What is to be done for you,
            after all this thought and trouble you have taken for us? Shall we say a word for you to the king or to
            the commander-in-chief?</q> <q>No,</q> she answered, <q>I am quite safe, among my own kinsmen.</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.4.13"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.4.14" osisID="2Kgs.4.14"/> So he asked Gehazi what was to be done for her, and Gehazi
            replied, <q>She has not a son, and her husband is an old man.</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.4.14"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.4.15" osisID="2Kgs.4.15"/> <q>Call her back,</q> said Elisha. And as she stood at the
            door, in reply to his summons, <verse eID="2Kgs.4.15"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.4.16" osisID="2Kgs.4.16"/> he said, <q>This time next year you will be embracing a
            son.</q> <q>No, no, my lord,</q> she answered, <q>you are a man of God, do not deceive your humble
            servant!</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.4.16"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.4.17" osisID="2Kgs.4.17"/> But the woman did conceive, and next year, when the time came
            round, she bore a son, as Elisha had told her. <verse eID="2Kgs.4.17"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.4.18" osisID="2Kgs.4.18"/> When the boy grew up, he went out one day to his father among
            the reapers. <verse eID="2Kgs.4.18"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.4.19" osisID="2Kgs.4.19"/> He called to his father, <q>Oh, my head! my head!</q> The
            father told his servant to carry the boy to his mother, <verse eID="2Kgs.4.19"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.4.20" osisID="2Kgs.4.20"/> and when he was brought to his mother he sat on her lap till
            noon; then he died. <verse eID="2Kgs.4.20"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.4.21" osisID="2Kgs.4.21"/> She carried him up and laid him on the bed of the man of God,
            closed the door, <verse eID="2Kgs.4.21"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.4.22" osisID="2Kgs.4.22"/> and went away to her husband, saying, <q>Pray let me have one
            of the servants and one of the asses, that I may hurry to the man of God and then get back again.</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.4.22"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.4.23" osisID="2Kgs.4.23"/> <q>Why go to him today?</q> he asked; <q>it is not the
            new-moon festival or the sabbath.</q> <q>Never mind,</q> she said; <verse eID="2Kgs.4.23"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.4.24" osisID="2Kgs.4.24"/> and saddling an ass she told her servant, <q>Drive ahead,
            never check the pace for me till I tell you.</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.4.24"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.4.25" osisID="2Kgs.4.25"/> So on she went to the man of God at mount Karmel.
       </p>
       <p>
            When the man of God spied her at a distance, he said to his servant Gehazi, <q>Look, there is the
            Shunammite!
           <verse eID="2Kgs.4.25"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.4.26" osisID="2Kgs.4.26"/> Now run to meet her and ask her if she is well, if her
            husband is well, and if the child is well.</q> She answered, <q>Yes,</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.4.26"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.4.27" osisID="2Kgs.4.27"/> and went on to the man of God upon the hill, grasping his
            feet. Gehazi went up to push her away, but the man of God said, <q>Let her alone; she has a sore heart,
            and the Eternal has not told me, he has hidden it from me.</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.4.27"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.4.28" osisID="2Kgs.4.28"/> Then she cried, <q>Did I ask my lord for a son? Did I not
            say, <q>Do not deceive me</q>?</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.4.28"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.4.29" osisID="2Kgs.4.29"/> So he told Gehazi, <q>Gird up your loins, take my staff in
            your hand, and be off; if you meet anyone, do not stop to salute him, and if anyone salutes you, do not
            stop to reply; lay my staff on the face of the child.</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.4.29"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.4.30" osisID="2Kgs.4.30"/> The mother said to Elisha, <q>As surely as the Eternal lives
            and you live, I will not go home without you.</q> So he rose and went with her. <verse eID="2Kgs.4.30"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.4.31" osisID="2Kgs.4.31"/> Gehazi had gone in front of them and laid the staff on the
            face of the child; but, as there was not a sound or sign of life, he came back to tell Elisha that the
            child had not wakened. <verse eID="2Kgs.4.31"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.4.32" osisID="2Kgs.4.32"/> When Elisha entered the house, there was the child lying dead
            upon his bed! <verse eID="2Kgs.4.32"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.4.33" osisID="2Kgs.4.33"/> He went in and shut the door upon the two of
            <milestone type="pb" n="421"/>
            them, praying to the Eternal. <verse eID="2Kgs.4.33"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.4.34" osisID="2Kgs.4.34"/> Then he stretched himself over the child, putting his mouth
            on the child's mouth, his eyes on the child's eyes, and his hands on the child's hands, till, as he
            crouched over the child, its flesh grew warm. <verse eID="2Kgs.4.34"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.4.35" osisID="2Kgs.4.35"/> Rising up, he walked to and fro, and then went and stretched
            himself seven times over the child, till it opened its eyes. <verse eID="2Kgs.4.35"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.4.36" osisID="2Kgs.4.36"/> Calling Gehazi, he ordered him to summon the Shunammite. When
            she came in, at his bidding, he said, <q>Lift your son.</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.4.36"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.4.37" osisID="2Kgs.4.37"/> She fell at his feet, bowing herself to the ground; then
            lifting her son she went away. <verse eID="2Kgs.4.37"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.4.38" osisID="2Kgs.4.38"/> Elisha once came to Gilgal when there was a famine in the
            land. As the guild of prophets was sitting in front of him, he told his servant to put the large pot on
            the fire and boil some pottage for the prophets. <verse eID="2Kgs.4.38"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.4.39" osisID="2Kgs.4.39"/> One man went to gather herbs in the field, and finding a wild
            vine he gathered a lapful of wild gourds, which he cut up for the pot of pottage, not knowing what they
            were. <verse eID="2Kgs.4.39"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.4.40" osisID="2Kgs.4.40"/> The pottage was then poured out for the men. But as they were
            eating they cried out, <q>0 man of God, there is death in the pot!</q> They could not eat the pottage. <verse eID="2Kgs.4.40"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.4.41" osisID="2Kgs.4.41"/> So he said, <q>Bring some meal.</q> This he threw into the
            pot, saying, <q>Now pour out for the men to eat.</q> And now there was nothing wrong with the pot. <verse eID="2Kgs.4.41"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.4.42" osisID="2Kgs.4.42"/> A man once came from Baalshalisha, bringing the man of God
            some first-fruits as food, twenty barley loaves and fresh vegetables in a basket. Elisha said, <q>Give
            the folk something to eat.</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.4.42"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.4.43" osisID="2Kgs.4.43"/> <q>What,</q> said his servant, <q>am I to set this before a
            hundred men?</q> <q>Give the folk something to eat,</q> said Elisha, <q>for the Eternal declares that
            they shall eat and leave some over.</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.4.43"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.4.44" osisID="2Kgs.4.44"/> So he did set it before them, and, as the Eternal had
            predicted, they ate and some was left over. <verse eID="2Kgs.4.44"/>
       </p>
     <chapter eID="2Kgs.4"/>
     <chapter osisID="2Kgs.5" sID="2Kgs.5"/>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.5.1" osisID="2Kgs.5.1"/> Naaman, who commanded cf the army of the king of Aram, was
            highly regarded by his lord and famous, since the Eternal had used him to make Aram victorious; only, he was a
            leper. <verse eID="2Kgs.5.1"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.5.2" osisID="2Kgs.5.2"/> Now on one of their raids the Aramaeans had carried off a
            little girl as a prisoner from the land of Israel, who waited on Naaman's wife. <verse eID="2Kgs.5.2"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.5.3" osisID="2Kgs.5.3"/> She said to her mistress, <q>Would that my lord saw the
            prophet who lives at Samaria! He would relieve my lord of his leprosy.</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.5.3"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.5.4" osisID="2Kgs.5.4"/> Someone told his lord what the Israelite girl had said. <verse eID="2Kgs.5.4"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.5.5" osisID="2Kgs.5.5"/> Whereupon the king of Aram said, <q>Come, I will send a
            letter to the king of Israel.</q>
       </p>
       <p>
            So Naaman started off, taking over four thousand pounds in silver and over twelve thousand pounds in gold,
            with ten festal robes: <verse eID="2Kgs.5.5"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.5.6" osisID="2Kgs.5.6"/> he brought the king of Israel the letter, which ran: <q>And
           now, with this letter, I send you my servant Naaman, that you may get him relief from his leprosy.</q>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.5.6"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.5.7" osisID="2Kgs.5.7"/> When the king of Israel read the letter he tore his clothes,
           crying, <q>Am I a god, able to kill and to make men live, that this man sends to me to get a man relief
           from leprosy? Just think; see how he is trying to pick a quarrel with me!</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.5.7"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.5.8" osisID="2Kgs.5.8"/> When Elisha the man of God heard about the king of Israel
            tearing his clothes in despair, he sent this message to the king of Israel:	<q>Why tear your clothes? Let the
            man come to me now, and he shall find there
            <milestone type="pb" n="422"/>
            is a prophet in Israel.</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.5.8"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.5.9" osisID="2Kgs.5.9"/> So Naaman drove up with his horses and his chariots and stopped
            at the door of Elisha's house. <verse eID="2Kgs.5.9"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.5.10" osisID="2Kgs.5.10"/> Elisha sent out word to him, <q>Go and wash seven times in
            the Jordan, and your body shall once more be well and clean.</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.5.10"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.5.11" osisID="2Kgs.5.11"/> Naaman went off in a rage, muttering, <q>I expected he would
            come outside to me and invoke the Eternal his God, waving his hand over the place and relieving the leper.
           <verse eID="2Kgs.5.11"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.5.12" osisID="2Kgs.5.12"/> Surely Amana and Pharpar, the rivers of Damascus, are better than
            any water in Israel! Could I not wash in them and be clean?</q> So he drove away in a fit of anger. <verse eID="2Kgs.5.12"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.5.13" osisID="2Kgs.5.13"/> But his servants went up to him and said, <q>If the prophet
            had told you to do something great, would you not have done it? How much rather, then, when he tells you
            only to wash and be clean?</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.5.13"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.5.14" osisID="2Kgs.5.14"/> At this he went down and dipped seven times in the Jordan, as
            the man of God had ordered; his body became once more like a child's body, and he was clean. <verse eID="2Kgs.5.14"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.5.15" osisID="2Kgs.5.15"/> Then, returning to the man of God, he and all his retinue, he
            stood in his presence, saying, <q>Now indeed I know there is no God in all the earth except in Israel! Pray
            accept a present from your humble servant.</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.5.15"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.5.16" osisID="2Kgs.5.16"/> <q>As sure as the Eternal lives, whom I serve,</q> said Elisha,
            <q>I will not take a single thing.</q> Naaman pressed him, but he refused. <verse eID="2Kgs.5.16"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.5.17" osisID="2Kgs.5.17"/> Then said Naaman, <q>Well, let your servant at least have two
            mules' load of earth, for after this your servant will offer neither victim nor sacrifice to any god except the
            Eternal. <verse eID="2Kgs.5.17"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.5.18" osisID="2Kgs.5.18"/> But may the Eternal pardon me this: when my lord enters the
            temple of Rimmon to worship there, leaning on my arm, and I bow in the house of Rimmon when he bows in
            the house of Rimmon--may the Eternal pardon your servant then!</q>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.5.18"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.5.19" osisID="2Kgs.5.19"/>
            <q>Farewell,</q> said Elisha.
       </p>
       <p>
            He had gone only a short distance,
           <verse eID="2Kgs.5.19"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.5.20" osisID="2Kgs.5.20"/> when Gehazi said to himself, <q>Here has my master spared
            this Naaman the Aramaean, declining to accept his present! By the Eternal, I will run after him and get
            something out of him!</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.5.20"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.5.21" osisID="2Kgs.5.21"/> So Gehazi followed up Naaman. When Naaman saw him running
            behind, he alighted from the chariot to meet him, saying, <q>Is all well?</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.5.21"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.5.22" osisID="2Kgs.5.22"/> <q>All is well,</q> said Gehazi. <q>My master sends me to
           say that two young members of the prophets' guild from the uplands of Ephraim have just come to him;
           will you give them four hundred pounds in silver and two festal robes?</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.5.22"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.5.23" osisID="2Kgs.5.23"/> <q>Allow me to give you eight hundred pounds,</q> said
            Naaman. He urged this, tying up eight hundred pounds in silver inside two bags and also two festal robes;
            these he laid on Gehazi's two servants, who carried them in front of him. <verse eID="2Kgs.5.23"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.5.24" osisID="2Kgs.5.24"/> When he reached the Mound, he took them from the servants and
            put them away inside the house, letting the servants go their way. <verse eID="2Kgs.5.24"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.5.25" osisID="2Kgs.5.25"/> Then he went in to wait upon Elisha. Elisha said to him,
            <q>Where have you been, Gehazi?</q> <q>Your servant has not been anywhere,</q> he answered. <verse eID="2Kgs.5.25"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.5.26" osisID="2Kgs.5.26"/> But Elisha said to him, <q>Was I not with you in spirit when
            someone came back from his chariot to meet you? You have taken money, and you mean to get garments, oliveyards,
            vineyards, sheep, oxen, and slaves, male and female? <verse eID="2Kgs.5.26"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.5.27" osisID="2Kgs.5.27"/> Yes, and the leprosy of Naaman
            <milestone type="pb" n="423"/>
            for yourself and your descendants ever after this!</q> Then he left Elisha's presence a leper, white as
            snow. <verse eID="2Kgs.5.27"/>
       </p>
     <chapter eID="2Kgs.5"/>
     <chapter osisID="2Kgs.6" sID="2Kgs.6"/>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.6.1" osisID="2Kgs.6.1"/> The prophets' guild once said to Elisha, <q>This dwelling of
            ours, as you see for yourself, is too small for us. <verse eID="2Kgs.6.1"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.6.2" osisID="2Kgs.6.2"/> Pray let us go to the Jordan and get each of us a log, to build
            a dwelling-house for ourselves there.</q> Elisha told them to go; <verse eID="2Kgs.6.2"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.6.3" osisID="2Kgs.6.3"/> and, when one of them said, <q>Pray agree to go along with
            your servants,</q> he answered, <q>I will go,</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.6.3"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.6.4" osisID="2Kgs.6.4"/> and went. On reaching the Jordan they cut down some timber. <verse eID="2Kgs.6.4"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.6.5" osisID="2Kgs.6.5"/> But as one man was swinging his axe, the head of the axe fell
            into the water. <q>Alas, my master!</q> cried the man, <q>it was borrowed.</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.6.5"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.6.6" osisID="2Kgs.6.6"/> <q>Where did it fall?</q> said the man of God. The man showed
            him the spot. Then, cutting a stick, Elisha threw it in, and so made the iron swim. <verse eID="2Kgs.6.6"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.6.7" osisID="2Kgs.6.7"/> <q>Lift it,</q> he told the man. And the man put out his hand
            and lifted it. <verse eID="2Kgs.6.7"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.6.8" osisID="2Kgs.6.8"/> The king of Aram was fighting Israel. He planned with his
            officers to lay an ambush at a certain spot. <verse eID="2Kgs.6.8"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.6.9" osisID="2Kgs.6.9"/> But the man of God sent a warning to the king of Israel not to
            pass that spot, because the Aramaeans were lying hidden there; <verse eID="2Kgs.6.9"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.6.10" osisID="2Kgs.6.10"/> so the king of Israel, sending to the spot about which the
            man of God had warned him, saved himself. This happened more than once. <verse eID="2Kgs.6.10"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.6.11" osisID="2Kgs.6.11"/> It greatly upset the mind of the king of Aram. He summoned
            his officers and asked them, <q>Can you not show me who is betraying us to the king of Israel?</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.6.11"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.6.12" osisID="2Kgs.6.12"/> <q>None of us, my lord king!</q> said an officer. <q>It is
            Elisha the prophet in Israel; he tells the king of Israel the very words you breathe in your
            bedchamber.</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.6.12"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.6.13" osisID="2Kgs.6.13"/> So he gave orders to find out where Elisha stayed, that he
            might send and fetch him. On being told that he was at Dothan, <verse eID="2Kgs.6.13"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.6.14" osisID="2Kgs.6.14"/> the king sent cavairy, chariots, and a large force, which
            marching over-night surrounded the town. <verse eID="2Kgs.6.14"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.6.15" osisID="2Kgs.6.15"/> Early on the morning of the next day, Elisha the man of God
            rose and went outside; and there was an armed force with cavalry and chariots round the town! <q>Alas,
            my master!</q> said his servant, <q>whatever are we to do?</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.6.15"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.6.16" osisID="2Kgs.6.16"/> <q>Fear not,</q> he answered; <q>those on our side are more
            than those on their side.</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.6.16"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.6.17" osisID="2Kgs.6.17"/> Then Elisha prayed, <q>0 Eternal, open his eyes, that he may
            see.</q> The Eternal did open the young man's eyes; and what he saw was the hill covered with horses and
            chariots of fire around Elisha! <verse eID="2Kgs.6.17"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.6.18" osisID="2Kgs.6.18"/> When the enemy came down upon him, Elisha prayed to the
            Eternal, <q>Punish this host with blindness.</q> He punished them with blindness, as Elisha had asked.
           <verse eID="2Kgs.6.18"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.6.19" osisID="2Kgs.6.19"/> Whereupon Elisha said to them, <q>This is not the road, this
            is not the town; follow me and I will take you to the man you are after.</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.6.19"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.6.20" osisID="2Kgs.6.20"/> He led them to Samaria, and, once they were at Samaria,
            Elisha said, <q>0 Eternal, open the eyes of these men, that they may see.</q> When the Eternal opened
            their eyes, they looked--and there they were, inside Samaria! <verse eID="2Kgs.6.20"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.6.21" osisID="2Kgs.6.21"/> When the king of Israel saw them, he asked Elisha, <q>My
           father, shall I cut them down? Shall I cut them down?</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.6.21"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.6.22" osisID="2Kgs.6.22"/> <q>No,</q> said Elisha; <q>would you cut down prisoners you
            never captured with your own sword and bow? Set bread and water
            <milestone type="pb" n="424"/>
            before them, that they may eat and drink before returning to their master.</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.6.22"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.6.23" osisID="2Kgs.6.23"/> So he had a great feast spread for them, and after they had
            eaten and drunk he sent them away back to their master. The Aramaean raiders no longer invaded the land
            of Israel. <verse eID="2Kgs.6.23"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.6.24" osisID="2Kgs.6.24"/> It was after this that Benhadad the king of Aram mustered all his
            forces and marched to besiege Samaria. <verse eID="2Kgs.6.24"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.6.25" osisID="2Kgs.6.25"/> A severe famine raged in Samaria, as the siege went on, till
            ten pounds in silver was paid for the head of an ass and twelve shillings for a pint of doves' dung. <verse eID="2Kgs.6.25"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.6.26" osisID="2Kgs.6.26"/> As the king was passing along the wall, a woman cried out to
            him, <q>Help, my lord king!</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.6.26"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.6.27" osisID="2Kgs.6.27"/> <q>No,</q> he answered, <q>may the Eternal help you! How can
            I? Can I help you from threshing-floor or winepress?</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.6.27"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.6.28" osisID="2Kgs.6.28"/> Then the king asked, <q>What ails you?</q> She replied,
            <q>This woman here said to me, <q>Let us have your boy to eat to-day, and to-morrow we will eat my
            boy.</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.6.28"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.6.29" osisID="2Kgs.6.29"/> So we boiled my boy and ate him. Next day when I said, <q>Now
            let us have your son to eat,</q> she had hid the boy.</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.6.29"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.6.30" osisID="2Kgs.6.30"/> When the king heard what the woman said, he tore his clothes,
            as he stood on the wall. (The people noticed that he was wearing sackcloth next his skin.) <verse eID="2Kgs.6.30"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.6.31" osisID="2Kgs.6.31"/> <q>God kill me and worse,</q> he cried, <q>if the head of
            Elisha the son of Shaphat remain on his shoulders to-day!</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.6.31"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.6.32" osisID="2Kgs.6.32"/> Elisha was sitting at home with the sheikhs of Israel.
            Before ever the king's messenger arrived, he said to the sheikhs, <q>Do you see that this murderous
            creature has given orders to cut off my head? Look to it. When the messenger arrives, close the door,
            shut it in his face: is not the sound of his master’s feet behind him?</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.6.32"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.6.33" osisID="2Kgs.6.33"/> He was still talking to them when the king himself arrived,
            saying, <q>This trouble comes from the Eternal; why should I wait for the Eternal's help any longer?</q>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.6.33"/>
       </p>
     <chapter eID="2Kgs.6"/>
     <chapter osisID="2Kgs.7" sID="2Kgs.7"/>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.7.1" osisID="2Kgs.7.1"/> Elisha answered, <q>Listen to this  promise from the Eternal;
            the Eternal declares that this time to-morrow a peck of fine flour will be sold for only half-a-crown
            and two pecks of barley for only half-a-crown, at the gate of Samaria.</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.7.1"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.7.2" osisID="2Kgs.7.2"/> The adjutant, on whose arm the king leant, replied to the man
            of God, <q>Could that be, even if the Eternal were to open sluices in the sky?</q> Said Elisha,
            <q>You shall see that sight, but you shall not eat the food.</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.7.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.7.3" osisID="2Kgs.7.3"/> Now four lepers were sitting in the entry at the gates.
            <q>Why sit here till we die?</q> they said to themselves. <verse eID="2Kgs.7.3"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.7.4" osisID="2Kgs.7.4"/> <q>If we propose to enter the town, the famine is in the
            town, and we shall die there; if we remain here, we die also. Come along, let us go over to the Aramaean
            army. If they let us live, we shall live; if they kill us, we shall only die.</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.7.4"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.7.5" osisID="2Kgs.7.5"/> So in the twilight they started for the Aramaean camp. When
            they reached the fringes of the Aramaean camp, not a man was to be found! <verse eID="2Kgs.7.5"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.7.6" osisID="2Kgs.7.6"/> The Lord had made the Aramaean army hear a noise of chariots
            and a noise of cavalry, the noise of a large army, till they thought, <q>The king of Israel must have
            hired the kings of the Hittites and the kings of Muzri to attack us.</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.7.6"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.7.7" osisID="2Kgs.7.7"/> So they had fled away for their lives in the twilight, leaving
            their tents, their horses, and their asses, just as they were, in the camp. <verse eID="2Kgs.7.7"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.7.8" osisID="2Kgs.7.8"/> When the lepers reached the fringes of the camp,
            <milestone type="pb" n="425"/>
            they entered one tent, ate and drank, carried off the silver, the gold, and the clothes, and after
            hiding them came back to another tent which they also stripped, hiding its contents. <verse eID="2Kgs.7.8"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.7.9" osisID="2Kgs.7.9"/> Then they said to themselves, <q>We are not doing right. This
            is a day of good news, and we are not spreading it. If we wait till morning dawns, punishment will
            overtake us. Come along, let us go and inform the royal household.</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.7.9"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.7.10" osisID="2Kgs.7.10"/> So they went and called to the warders of the town, <q>We
            have been to the Aramaean camp, and not a man is to be found there! There is not a human sound, only
            horses tethered, asses tethered, and the tents as they were!</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.7.10"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.7.11" osisID="2Kgs.7.11"/> When the warders informed the royal household, <verse eID="2Kgs.7.11"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.7.12" osisID="2Kgs.7.12"/> the king rose in the night and said to his officers, <q>I
            will tell you what the Aramaeans have done about us. They know we are starving, and so they have left
            the camp to hide themselves in the open country, thinking that once we leave the town, they will capture
            us alive and get into the town!</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.7.12"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.7.13" osisID="2Kgs.7.13"/> One of the officers replied, <q>Pray send some men, with five
            of the horses that are left; if they live, they will fare like all the multitude of Israel who survive here,
            and if they die, they die like all the multitude of Israel that perish here. Let us send and see!</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.7.13"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.7.14" osisID="2Kgs.7.14"/> So two men on horseback were chosen, and sent by the king
            after the Aramaean army with orders to go and see. <verse eID="2Kgs.7.14"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.7.15" osisID="2Kgs.7.15"/> They followed the track as far as the Jordan, finding the
            road all littered with the garments and the weapons which the Aramaeans had thrown away in their
            hurried flight. When the messengers came back and told the king, <verse eID="2Kgs.7.15"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.7.16" osisID="2Kgs.7.16"/> the people went out and plundered the Aramaeans' camp. And a
            peck of fine flour was sold for only half-a-crown, two pecks of barley were sold for only half-a-crown,
            as the Eternal had foretold. <verse eID="2Kgs.7.16"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.7.17" osisID="2Kgs.7.17"/> The king had put the gate in charge of the adjutant on whose
            arm he was accustomed to lean; and the crowd trod on him at the gate till he died--also as the man of God had
            predicted when the king visited him. <verse eID="2Kgs.7.17"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.7.18" osisID="2Kgs.7.18"/> As the man of God had told the king that two pecks of barley
            would be sold for half-a-crown and a peck of fine flour for half-a-crown by that time next day, <verse eID="2Kgs.7.18"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.7.19" osisID="2Kgs.7.19"/> and as the man of God had said, <q>You shall see that sight,
            but you shall not eat the food,</q> to the adjutant who had said, <q>Could that be, even if the
            Eternal were to open sluices in the sky?</q>--<verse eID="2Kgs.7.19"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.7.20" osisID="2Kgs.7.20"/>so it happened to him; the crowd at the gate trod on him till
            he died. <verse eID="2Kgs.7.20"/>
       </p>
     <chapter eID="2Kgs.7"/>
     <chapter osisID="2Kgs.8" sID="2Kgs.8"/>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.8.1" osisID="2Kgs.8.1"/> Elisha said to the woman whose boy he had restored to life,
            <q>Move away, you and your household, and stay abroad wherever you can, for the Eternal has called for a
             famine.</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.8.1"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.8.2" osisID="2Kgs.8.2"/> The famine did come upon the land for seven years. But the
            woman started off, at the bidding of the man of God; she and her household went and stayed in the land
            of the Philistines for seven years. <verse eID="2Kgs.8.2"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.8.3" osisID="2Kgs.8.3"/> At the end of the seven years, when the woman came back from
            the land of the Philistines, she went to appeal to the king for her house and land. <verse eID="2Kgs.8.3"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.8.4" osisID="2Kgs.8.4"/> The king was talking to Gehazi the servant of the man of God,
            asking him to tell him about all the great deeds of Elisha; <verse eID="2Kgs.8.4"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.8.5" osisID="2Kgs.8.5"/> and just as he was telling the king how Elisha had
            <milestone type="pb" n="426"/>
            restored a boy to life, the very woman whose boy had been restored to life made her appeal to the king
            for her house and land. <q>My lord king,</q> said Gehazi, <q>this is the woman, and this is her boy whom
            Elisha restored to life!</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.8.5"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.8.6" osisID="2Kgs.8.6"/> When the king asked the woman, she told him the story. So the
            king appointed a eunuch to see that she got back all her property and all the produce that her farm had
            yielded ever since she left the country. <verse eID="2Kgs.8.6"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.8.7" osisID="2Kgs.8.7"/> Once, when Elisha came to Damascus, Benhadad king of Aram was
            ill; he was told that the man of God had arrived, <verse eID="2Kgs.8.7"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.8.8" osisID="2Kgs.8.8"/> and so the king said to Hazael, <q>Take a present with you and
            go to see the man of God; ask the Eternal through him whether I shall recover from this illness.</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.8.8"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.8.9" osisID="2Kgs.8.9"/> Hazael went to see him, taking as a present specimens of all
            the rare wares of Damascus, as much as forty camels could carry. When he reached Elisha, he stood in
            front of him and said, <q>Your son Benhadad king of Aram has sent me to ask you whether he will recover
            from this illness.</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.8.9"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.8.10" osisID="2Kgs.8.10"/> Elisha answered, <q>Go and tell him that he will certainly
            recover--though the Eternal has revealed to me that he will certainly die.</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.8.10"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.8.11" osisID="2Kgs.8.11"/> As he spoke, the man of God's face became rigid with horror,
            absolute horror. Then he burst into tears. <verse eID="2Kgs.8.11"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.8.12" osisID="2Kgs.8.12"/> <q>Why does my lord weep?</q> said Hazael. <q>Because,</q>
            he answered, <q>I know the cruelties you will practise on the Israelites, setting fortresses ablaze,
            murdering young men, dashing children to pieces, and ripping up pregnant women!</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.8.12"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.8.13" osisID="2Kgs.8.13"/> <q>Your humble servant is but a cur,</q> said Hazael; <q>how
            can he achieve all this?</q> Elisha answered, <q>The Eternal has let me see you reigning over Aram!</q>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.8.13"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.8.14" osisID="2Kgs.8.14"/> Leaving Elisha, he went back to his master, who asked,
            <q>What did Elisha say to you?</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.8.14"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.8.15" osisID="2Kgs.8.15"/> Hazael replied, <q>He told me that you would certainly
            recover.</q> Next day he took the bath-towel, soaked it and then spread it over the king's face till he was
            dead. Then Hazael reigned instead of him. <verse eID="2Kgs.8.15"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.8.16" osisID="2Kgs.8.16"/>In the fifth year of Jehoram the son of Ahab king of Israel, Jehoram
            the son of Jehoshaphat king of Judah began to reign; <verse eID="2Kgs.8.16"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.8.17" osisID="2Kgs.8.17"/> he was thirty-two years old when he began to reign, and he
            reigned in Jerusalem for eight years. <verse eID="2Kgs.8.17"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.8.18" osisID="2Kgs.8.18"/> He lived on the lines of the kings of Israel, following the
            dynasty of Ahab--for he was married to Ahab's daughter. He did what was evil in the eyes of the
            Eternal, <verse eID="2Kgs.8.18"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.8.19" osisID="2Kgs.8.19"/> but for the sake of David his servant the Eter­nal would not
            destroy Judah, since he had promised David a dynasty before the Eternal for all time. <verse eID="2Kgs.8.19"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.8.20" osisID="2Kgs.8.20"/> (It was during his reign that Edom revolted from Judah and
            set up a king for itself. <verse eID="2Kgs.8.20"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.8.21" osisID="2Kgs.8.21"/> Whereupon Jehoram went across to Zair, with all his
            chariots . . . However, Jehoram and the captains of his chariots with him rose by night and raided the
            Edomites, who hemmed them in. The rank and file scurried home. <verse eID="2Kgs.8.21"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.8.22" osisID="2Kgs.8.22"/> So Edom revolted from Judah to this day; and Libnah revolted
            at the same time.) <verse eID="2Kgs.8.22"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.8.23" osisID="2Kgs.8.23"/> The rest of the acts of Jehoram and all his deeds, are they
            not described in the book of the Annals of the Kings of Judah? <verse eID="2Kgs.8.23"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.8.24" osisID="2Kgs.8.24"/> Jehoram slept with his fathers, and was buried with his
            fathers in David's burg;
            <milestone type="pb" n="427"/>
           Ahaziah his son reigned instead of him. <verse eID="2Kgs.8.24"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.8.25" osisID="2Kgs.8.25"/> In the twelfth year of Jehoram the son of Ahab king of
            Israel, Ahaziah the son of Jehoram king of Judah began to reign; <verse eID="2Kgs.8.25"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.8.26" osisID="2Kgs.8.26"/> Ahaziah was twenty-two years old when he began to reign, and
            he reigned in Jerusalem for one year. His mother's name was Athallah, a grand­daughter of Omri king of
            Israel. <verse eID="2Kgs.8.26"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.8.27" osisID="2Kgs.8.27"/> He lived on the lines of the dynasty of Ahab, doing what was
            evil in the eyes of the Eternal as Ahab s dynasty did--for he had married a wife of that family. <verse eID="2Kgs.8.27"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.8.28" osisID="2Kgs.8.28"/> He accompanied Jehoram the son of Ahab to attack Hazael king
            of Aram at Ramoth-gilead, where the archers wounded Jehoram,
           <verse eID="2Kgs.8.28"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.8.29" osisID="2Kgs.8.29"/> who returned to Jezreel to recover from the wounds inflicted
            by the Aramaeans at Hamah, as he had fought against Hazael king of Aram.
       </p>
       <p>
            Ahaziah the son of Jehoram king of Judah went down to visit Jehoram the son of Ahab at Jezreel, where he
            lay ill. <verse eID="2Kgs.8.29"/>
     <chapter eID="2Kgs.8"/>
     <chapter osisID="2Kgs.9" sID="2Kgs.9"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.9.1" osisID="2Kgs.9.1"/> Then Elisha the prophet called a member of the prophets'
            guild and told him, <q>Gird up your loins and go to Ramoth-gilead, carrying this flask of oil. <verse eID="2Kgs.9.1"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.9.2" osisID="2Kgs.9.2"/> When you get there, look for Jehu the son of Jehoshaphat the
            son of Nimshi; get access to him and take him away from his kinsfolk to an inner chamber apart; <verse eID="2Kgs.9.9"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.9.3" osisID="2Kgs.9.3"/> then take the flask and pour the oil over his head, saying,
            <q>The Eternal hereby declares, I anoint you king over Israel.</q> Then open the door and fly; do not
            linger.</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.9.3"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.9.4" osisID="2Kgs.9.4"/> So the youthful prophet went to Ramoth-gilead. <verse eID="2Kgs.9.4"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.9.5" osisID="2Kgs.9.5"/> When he arrived, he found the generals of the army at a
            war-council. <q>I have an errand to you, 0 general,</q> he cried. <q>To which of us?</q> said Jehu.
            <q>To you, 0 general,</q> said the youth. <verse eID="2Kgs.9.5"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.9.6" osisID="2Kgs.9.6"/> So Jehu rose and went indoors. Then the prophet poured the oil
            on his head, saying, <q>The Eternal, the God of Israel, hereby declares, <q>I anoint you king over the
            Eternal's people, over Israel. <verse eID="2Kgs.9.6"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.9.7" osisID="2Kgs.9.7"/> [[You shall destroy the house of your master Ahab, that I may
            avenge on Jezebel the blood of my servants the prophets and the blood of all the servants of the
            Eternal. <verse eID="2Kgs.9.7"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.9.8" osisID="2Kgs.9.8"/> For the whole house of Ahab shall perish; I will cut off from
            Ahab every male child, and the fettered and free alike in Israel; <verse eID="2Kgs.9.8"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.9.9" osisID="2Kgs.9.9"/> I will make Ahab's house like the house of Jeroboam the son of
            Nebat, and like the house of Baasha the son of Ahijah. <verse eID="2Kgs.9.9"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.9.10" osisID="2Kgs.9.10"/> Dogs shall eat Jezebel in the district of Jezreel, and none
            shall bury her.]]</q></q> Then, opening the door, he fled. <verse eID="2Kgs.9.10"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.9.11" osisID="2Kgs.9.11"/> When Jehu came out to the officers of his lord, they asked
            him, <q>Is all well? Why did that mad creature come to you?</q> <q>Oh you know how a fellow like that
            talks!</q> he replied. <verse eID="2Kgs.9.11"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.9.12" osisID="2Kgs.9.12"/> <q>You are lying,</q> they said; <q>come, tell us what it
            was.</q> So he told them that the man had said to him, <q>The Eternal hereby declares, I anoint you
            king over Israel.</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.9.12"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.9.13" osisID="2Kgs.9.13"/> Then every man of them rushed to lay his robe under Jehu's
            feet on the bare steps, and they blew a trumpet blast proclaiming, <q>Jehu is king!</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.9.13"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.9.14" osisID="2Kgs.9.14"/> This was how Jehu the grandson of Nimshi conspired against
            Jehoram. (Jehu was holding Ramoth-gilead, along with all Israel, against Hazael the king of Aram, <verse eID="2Kgs.9.14"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.9.15" osisID="2Kgs.9.15"/> while king Jehoram had returned to Jezreel to be cured of
            the wounds he had received
            <milestone type="pb" n="428"/>
            from the Aramaeans in fighting against Hazael king of Aram.) <q>Well,</q> said Jehu, <q>if you are on my
            side, let no one escape from the town to take word to Jezreel.</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.9.15"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.9.16" osisID="2Kgs.9.16"/> Then Jehu drove off in a chariot to Jezreel, where Jehoram
            lay, whom Ahaziah king of Judah had come down to visit. <verse eID="2Kgs.9.16"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.9.17" osisID="2Kgs.9.17"/> A sentinel posted on the tower of Jezreel caught sight of
            Jehu's company and called out, <q>I see a company.</q> Jehoram gave orders for a mounted man to ride
            out and meet them, to ask if all was well. <verse eID="2Kgs.9.17"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.9.18" osisID="2Kgs.9.18"/> So a mounted man rode out with the king's message, <q>Is all
           well?</q> <q>What have you to do with welfare?</q> said Jehu: <q>fall in behind me.</q> When the sentinel
            reported that the messenger had reached them but was not returning, <verse eID="2Kgs.9.18"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.9.19" osisID="2Kgs.9.19"/> the king sent out a second mounted man who also gave the
            king's message, <q>Is all well?</q> <q>What have you to do with welfare?</q> said Jehu: <q>fall
            in behind me.</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.9.19"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.9.20" osisID="2Kgs.9.20"/> The sentinel reported, <q>He reached them, but he is not
            returning, and the driving is like the driving of Jehu the grandson of Nimshi, for he drives like a
            madman.</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.9.20"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.9.21" osisID="2Kgs.9.21"/> <q>Harness my chariot,</q> said Jehoram. They did so, and
            Jehoram king of Israel drove out to meet him, with Ahaziah king of Judah, each in his own chariot. They
            came upon him in the field of Naboth the Jezreelite. <verse eID="2Kgs.9.21"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.9.22" osisID="2Kgs.9.22"/> On seeing Jehu, Jehoram said, <q>Is all well, Jehu?</q>
            <q>Well?</q> he retorted. <q>How can it be well, so long as your mother Jezebel goes on with all her
            seductions and wiles?</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.9.22"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.9.23" osisID="2Kgs.9.23"/> Jehoram wheeled round and fled, shouting, <q>Treachery,
            Ahaziah!</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.9.23"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.9.24" osisID="2Kgs.9.24"/> But Jehu had his bow drawn, and he struck Jehoram between
            the arms, till the arrow went through his heart, and he sank in his chariot. <verse eID="2Kgs.9.24"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.9.25" osisID="2Kgs.9.25"/> <q>Fling him out on the ancestral field of Naboth the
            Jezreelite,</q> said Jehu to his adjutant Bidkar; <q>for I remember, when I and you rode side by side
            behind his father Ahab, how the Eternal uttered this oracle of doom upon him: <verse eID="2Kgs.9.25"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.9.26" osisID="2Kgs.9.26"/> <q>Yesterday I saw Naboth's blood and the blood of Naboth's
            sons, the Eternal declares, and I will punish you in this plot of ground, the Eternal declares.</q> So
            fling him on this plot of ground, as the Eternal declared.</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.9.26"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.9.27" osisID="2Kgs.9.27"/> When Ahaziah king of Judah saw this, he fled in the
            direction of Beth-haggan, pursued by Jehu, who shouted, <q>Kill him too! Kill him in the chariot!</q>
            They struck him at the ascent of Gur near Ibleam, but he got away to Megiddo, where he died. <verse eID="2Kgs.9.27"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.9.28" osisID="2Kgs.9.28"/> His men carried him in a chariot to Jerusalem, and buried
            him in his tomb beside his fathers in David's burg. <verse eID="2Kgs.9.28"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.9.29" osisID="2Kgs.9.29"/> [[In the eleventh year of Jehoram the son of Ahab, Ahaziah
            began to reign over Judah.]] <verse eID="2Kgs.9.29"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.9.30" osisID="2Kgs.9.30"/> When Jehu reached Jezreel, Jezebel heard of it, and,
            painting her eyes and adorning her head, she looked out of the window. <verse eID="2Kgs.9.30"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.9.31" osisID="2Kgs.9.31"/> As Jehu came in through the gateway, she cried, <q>How are
            you, you Zimri, murderer of your master?</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.9.31"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.9.32" osisID="2Kgs.9.32"/> Jehu looked up to the window. <q>Who is on my side?</q> he
            asked, <q>which of you?</q> Two or three eunuchs looked out. <verse eID="2Kgs.9.32"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.9.33" osisID="2Kgs.9.33"/> <q>Throw her down,</q> he cried, and they threw her down,
            some of her blood spurting on the wall and on the horses, who trampled her under foot. <verse eID="2Kgs.9.33"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.9.34" osisID="2Kgs.9.34"/> Jehu went inside and dined.
            <milestone type="pb" n="429"/>
            Then he said, <q>See to that accursed woman; have her buried, for she was a king’s daughter.</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.9.34"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.35" osisID="2Kgs.3.35"/> But when they went to bury her, they found nothing but her
            skull, her feet, and her hands. <verse eID="2Kgs.3.35"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.36" osisID="2Kgs.3.36"/> When they reported this to Jehu, he said, <q>It is as the
            Eternal predicted by his servant Elijah the Tishbite, when he said: <q>In the district of Jezreel
            shall dogs devour the flesh of Jezebel; <verse eID="2Kgs.3.36"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.37" osisID="2Kgs.3.37"/> the corpse of Jezebel shall be like the corpse of Naboth,
            and there shall be none to say, Alas, alas!</q></q> <verse eID="2Kgs.3.37"/>
       </p>
     <chapter eID="2Kgs.9"/>
     <chapter osisID="2Kgs.10" sID="2Kgs.10"/>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.10.1" osisID="2Kgs.10.1"/> Ahab had seventy kinsmen at Samaria. So Jehu wrote a letter
            which he sent to the sheikhs, the authorities of the town, and those in charge of Ahab's kinsmen, and in which
            he said, <verse eID="2Kgs.10.1"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.10.2" osisID="2Kgs.10.2"/> <q>As soon as this letter reaches you, since you have with
            you the descendants of your master and also chariots, horses, fortified towns, and weapons, <verse eID="2Kgs.10.2"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.10.3" osisID="2Kgs.10.3"/> choose the best and bravest of your master's descendants,
            put him on his father's throne and fight for your master’s house.</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.10.3"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.10.4" osisID="2Kgs.10.4"/> But they were terribly afraid. <q>Two kings could not stand
            before him,</q> they said, <q>and how can we?</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.10.4"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.10.5" osisID="2Kgs.10.5"/> So the head of the palace and the provost of the town, along
            with the sheikhs and those in charge of the royal family, sent this message to Jehu: <q>We are at your
            service, we will do anything you bid us, we will not make anyone king. Act as you think best.</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.10.5"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.10.6" osisID="2Kgs.10.6"/> So he wrote them a second letter, saying, <q>If you are on
            my side and if you will listen to me, take the heads of your master's descendants and bring them to me
            at Jezreel by this time to-morrow.</q>
       </p>
       <p>
           The king's descendants, numbering seventy, were living with the chief men of the town, who were in
            charge of them; <verse eID="2Kgs.10.6"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.10.7" osisID="2Kgs.10.7"/> and, as soon as this letter came, they murdered the king's
           descendants, seventy in all, put their heads in a basket, and forwarded them to Jehu at Jezreel. <verse eID="2Kgs.10.7"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.10.8" osisID="2Kgs.10.8"/> A messenger reached him with the news that the heads of the
            king's descendants had been brought in. He said, <q>Lay them in two heaps at the entrance to the gate,
            till to-morrow morning.</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.10.8"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.10.9" osisID="2Kgs.10.9"/> In the morning he went out and stood before all the people,
            saying, <q>You are fair-minded men; I did conspire against my master and I killed him, but who murdered
            all these? <verse eID="2Kgs.10.9"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.10.10" osisID="2Kgs.10.10"/> Be sure of this, that every word of the Eternal about the
            house of Ahab shall be fulfilled; the Eternal has done what he predicted by his servant Elijah.</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.10.10"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.10.11" osisID="2Kgs.10.11"/> Whereupon Jehu killed every survivor of Ahab's house at
            Jezreel, all his kinsfolk as well as his priests, till he left Ahab with not a man. <verse eID="2Kgs.10.11"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.10.12" osisID="2Kgs.10.12"/> Jehu then started for Samaria. On his way there, at
            Beth-eked, <verse eID="2Kgs.10.12"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.10.13" osisID="2Kgs.10.13"/> he met the kinsmen of Ahaziah king of Judah. <q>Who are
            you?</q> said Jehu. <q>We are Ahaziah's kinsmen,</q> they answered; <q>we came down to visit the sons
            of the king and the sons of the queen.</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.10.13"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.10.14" osisID="2Kgs.10.14"/> <q>Take them alive,</q> he ordered; his men took them
            alive and murdered them at the pit of Beth-eked, forty-two of them, not one being spared. <verse eID="2Kgs.10.14"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.10.15" osisID="2Kgs.10.15"/> Leaving that place, he met Jehonadab the son of Rechab,
            who was coming to meet him. Jehu saluted him, asking, <q>Are you honestly with me, as I am honestly
            with you?</q> <q>I am,</q> said Jehonadab. <q>Then give me your hand,</q> said Jehu. Jehonadab gave
            him his hand, and
            <milestone type="pb" n="430"/>
            Jehu took him up into his chariot, <verse eID="2Kgs.10.15"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.10.16" osisID="2Kgs.10.16"/> saying, <q>Come and see my zeal for the Eternal.</q> Jehu
            made him ride in his chariot, <verse eID="2Kgs.10.16"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.10.17" osisID="2Kgs.10.17"/> and when he reached Samaria he murdered all the survivors
            of Ahab in Samaria, till Ahab's house was wiped out, as the Eternal had given orders by Elijah. <verse eID="2Kgs.10.17"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.10.18" osisID="2Kgs.10.18"/> Then Jehu collected all the people. <q>Ahab served Baal a
            little,</q> he cried, <q>but Jehu will serve him largely! <verse eID="2Kgs.10.18"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.10.19" osisID="2Kgs.10.19"/> Come, summon all the prophets of Baal and all his priests;
            let none be absent; for I have a great sacrifice for Baal, and anyone who is absent shall lose his
            life.</q> (Jehu was acting cunningly; he meant to destroy the worshippers of Baal.) <verse eID="2Kgs.10.19"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.10.20" osisID="2Kgs.10.20"/> Then Jehu ordered a sacred gathering in honour of Baal to
            be proclaimed. This was done. <verse eID="2Kgs.10.20"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.10.21" osisID="2Kgs.10.21"/> Jehu sent throughout all Israel, till all the worshippers
            of Baal came; not a man was left who did not attend. They entered the temple of Baal, till the temple
            was filled from end to end. <verse eID="2Kgs.10.21"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.10.22" osisID="2Kgs.10.22"/> Then he said to the keeper of the wardrobe, <q>Bring out
            vestments for all the worshippers of Baal.</q> Vestments were brought out. <verse eID="2Kgs.10.22"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.10.23" osisID="2Kgs.10.23"/> Jehu then entered the temple of Baal along with Jehonadab
            the son of Bechab, and told the worshippers of Baal, <q>Search and see that there is no servant of the Eternal
            among you, but only worshippers of Baal.</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.10.23"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.10.24" osisID="2Kgs.10.24"/> He then proceeded to offer sacrifices and burnt-offerings.
            Now outside he had posted eighty men, telling them, <q>The man who lets anyone escape of those I put into your
            hands, that man shall answer for it with his life.</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.10.24"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.10.25" osisID="2Kgs.10.25"/> So, as soon as he had finished the sacrifice, Jehu told
            the guard and their officers, <q>Go inside and slay them; let no one out.</q> The guard and their
            officers cut them down, flung them outside, and then made their way inside the shrine of the temple of
            Baal, <verse eID="2Kgs.10.25"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.10.26" osisID="2Kgs.10.26"/> bringing out the image of Astarte from the temple of Baal and
            burning it, <verse eID="2Kgs.10.26"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.10.27" osisID="2Kgs.10.27"/> demolishing the pillar of Baal, and destroying the temple
            of Baal till it became a latrine, as it is to this day. <verse eID="2Kgs.10.27"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.10.28" osisID="2Kgs.10.28"/> But though Jehu rooted Baal out of Israel, <verse eID="2Kgs.10.28"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.10.29" osisID="2Kgs.10.29"/> Jehu did not give up the sins by which Jeroboam the son of
            Nebat led Israel into sin, that is, the golden calves at Bethel and at Dan. <verse eID="2Kgs.10.29"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.10.30" osisID="2Kgs.10.30"/> The Eternal said to Jehu, <q>Since you have done well in
            carrying out my will, punishing the house of Ahab exactly as I intended, your sons shall sit on the
            throne of Israel down to the fourth generation.</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.10.30"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.10.31" osisID="2Kgs.10.31"/> But Jehu was careless about following strictly the
            directions of the Eternal, the God of Israel; he did not give up the sins by which Jeroboam the son of
            Nebat led Israel into sin. <verse eID="2Kgs.10.31"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.10.32" osisID="2Kgs.10.32"/> In those days the Eternal began to loathe Israel; Hazael
            defeated them everywhere, all over the territory of Israel, <verse eID="2Kgs.10.32"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.10.33" osisID="2Kgs.10.33"/> from the Jordan to the East, over the whole of Gilead, all
            the land of the Gadites, the Reubenites, and the Manassites, and from Aider at the valley of Arnon, over
            Gilead and Bashan. <verse eID="2Kgs.10.33"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.10.34" osisID="2Kgs.10.34"/> The rest of the acts of Jehu, all his deeds and all his prowess,
            are they not all described in the book of the Annals of the Kings of Israel? <verse eID="2Kgs.10.34"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.10.35" osisID="2Kgs.10.35"/> Jehu slept with his fathers, and was buried in Samaria;
            Jehoahaz his son reigned instead of him. <verse eID="2Kgs.10.35"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.10.36" osisID="2Kgs.10.36"/> Jehu had reigned over Israel in Samaria for twenty-eight
            years. <verse eID="2Kgs.10.36"/>
       </p>
       <milestone type="pb" n="431"/>
     <chapter eID="2Kgs.10"/>
     <chapter osisID="2Kgs.11" sID="2Kgs.11"/>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.11.1" osisID="2Kgs.11.1"/> When Athaliah the mother of Ahaziah found that her son was
            dead, she went and murdered all the royal children. <verse eID="2Kgs.11.1"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.11.2" osisID="2Kgs.11.2"/> But Jehosheba the daughter of king Jehoram, a sister of
            Ahaziah, caught up Joash the son of Ahaziah from the king's sons who were being killed in the
            bed­chamber, hiding him from Athaliah, so that he was not killed. <verse eID="2Kgs.11.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.11.3" osisID="2Kgs.11.3"/> For six years the boy lay concealed with her inside the
            temple of the Eternal, while Athaliah ruled the land. <verse eID="2Kgs.11.3"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.11.4" osisID="2Kgs.11.4"/> In the seventh year Jehoiada sent for the captains of the
            Carians and the guards and had them brought to him in the temple of the Eternal, where he made a
            compact with them, obliging them to swear by the temple of the Eternal, and then showing them the
            king's son. <verse eID="2Kgs.11.4"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.11.5" osisID="2Kgs.11.5"/> He issued this order: <q>What you must do is this: third of
            you, those who go on sabbath to guard the palace, <verse eID="2Kgs.11.5"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.11.7" osisID="2Kgs.11.7"/> along with the two other divisions who go on sabbath to
            guard the temple of the Eternal round the king, <verse eID="2Kgs.11.7"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.11.8" osisID="2Kgs.11.8"/> shall all surround the king, every man carrying his
            weapons. Any intruder is to be slain. You must accompany the king as he leaves the temple and enters the
            palace.</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.11.8"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.11.9" osisID="2Kgs.11.9"/> The captains carried out all the orders of Jehoiada; each
            brought his men to Jehoiada the priest, those who were to go off duty on sabbath and those who were to
            come on duty. <verse eID="2Kgs.11.9"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.11.10" osisID="2Kgs.11.10"/> The priest handed the captains the spears and shields
            belonging to king David, which had lain in the temple of the Eternal; <verse eID="2Kgs.11.10"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.11.11" osisID="2Kgs.11.11"/> and the guards stood, each carrying his weapons, from the
            south side of the temple to the north side of the temple, facing the altar and the temple. <verse eID="2Kgs.11.11"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.11.12" osisID="2Kgs.11.12"/> Then, bringing out the king’s son, he put the crown and
            the royal bracelets on him. They proclaimed him king and anointed him, clapping their hands and
            shouting, <q>Long live the king!</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.11.12"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.11.13" osisID="2Kgs.11.13"/> [[When Athaliah heard the cheers of the troops, she came
            out to them in the temple of the Eternal. <verse eID="2Kgs.11.13"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.11.14" osisID="2Kgs.11.14"/> When she looked, there she saw the king standing on the
            platform, as was the custom, with the captains and trumpeters beside him, and all the people of the
            land rejoicing and blowing trumpets! <q>Treason! Treason!</q> cried Athaliah, tearing her robes. <verse eID="2Kgs.11.14"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.11.15" osisID="2Kgs.11.15"/> But Jehoiada the priest ordered the captains and the army
            commanders, <q>Bring her out between the ranks, and slay anyone who follows her</q> {the priest forbade her
            to be killed inside the temple of the Eternal). <verse eID="2Kgs.11.15"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.11.16" osisID="2Kgs.11.16"/> So they caught hold of her; she came out by the horses'
            entry to the royal palace, and there she was put to death. <verse eID="2Kgs.11.16"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.11.17" osisID="2Kgs.11.17"/> Jehoiada then made a compact between the Eternal and the
            king and people, that they were to be the Eternal's people, as also between the king and the people.
           <verse eID="2Kgs.11.17"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.11.18" osisID="2Kgs.11.18"/> All the people of the land went to the temple of Baal and
            demolished it, smashing his altars and images to pieces, and killing Mattan the priest of Baal in front of
            the altars.]] The priest appointed guards over the temple of the Eternal. <verse eID="2Kgs.11.18"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.11.19" osisID="2Kgs.11.19"/> Then, taking the captains, the Carians, the guards, and
            all the people of the land, he had the king brought down from the temple of the Eternal by the gate of the
            footguards into the royal palace, where he took his seat upon the royal throne. <verse eID="2Kgs.11.19"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.11.20" osisID="2Kgs.11.20"/> The people of the land all rejoiced; the town was
            <milestone type="pb" n="432"/>
           quiet; and Athaliah they cut down at the palace. <verse eID="2Kgs.11.20"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.11.21" osisID="2Kgs.11.21"/> Jehoash was seven years old when he began to reign. <verse eID="2Kgs.11.21"/>
       </p>
     <chapter eID="2Kgs.11"/>
     <chapter osisID="2Kgs.12" sID="2Kgs.12"/>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.12.1" osisID="2Kgs.12.1"/> It was in the seventh year of Jehu that Jehoash began to
            reign, and he reigned in Jerusalem for forty years. His mother's name was Zibiah of a Beersheba. <verse eID="2Kgs.12.1"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.12.2" osisID="2Kgs.12.2"/> Jehoash did what was right in the eyes of the Eternal all
            his life, since Jehoiada the priest gave him instruction. <verse eID="2Kgs.12.2"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.12.3" osisID="2Kgs.12.3"/> However, the shrines were not removed; the people still
            sacrificed and burnt incense at the shrines. <verse eID="2Kgs.12.3"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.12.4" osisID="2Kgs.12.4"/> Jehoash had ordered the priests that <q>all sacred monies
            paid into the temple of the Eternal, <verse eID="2Kgs.12.4"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.12.5" osisID="2Kgs.12.5"/> the money each man was assessed to pay, and the money which
            he contributed of his own accord, all must be taken by the priests, by each priest from his own
            customers, and devoted to the repair of any dilapidations to be found in the temple.</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.12.5"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.12.6" osisID="2Kgs.12.6"/> But even when king Jehoash had reached his twenty-third
            year, the priests had not repaired the dilapidations of the temple. <verse eID="2Kgs.12.6"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.12.7" osisID="2Kgs.12.7"/> So king Jehoash summoned Jehoiada and the other priests.
            <q>Why have you not repaired the dilapidations of the temple?</q> he asked them. <q>In­stead of
            accepting money from your customers, hand it over for the repair of the temple.</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.12.7"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.12.8" osisID="2Kgs.12.8"/> The priests agreed to this, that they were neither to take
            money from their customers nor to re­pair the dilapidations of the temple; <verse eID="2Kgs.12.8"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.12.9" osisID="2Kgs.12.9"/> Jehoiada the priest took a box, bored a hole in the lid of
            it, and placed it near the southern door-post, on the right hand of anyone entering the temple of
            the Eternal, and the priests who were warders of the entry put into it all the money brought into the
            temple of the Eternal. <verse eID="2Kgs.12.9"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.12.10" osisID="2Kgs.12.10"/> Whenever they saw that there was a large amount of money
            in the box, the king's secretary and the high priest came and put this money into bags, counting it.
           <verse eID="2Kgs.12.10"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.12.11" osisID="2Kgs.12.11"/> Dealing out the money, they put it into the hands of the
            overseers of the temple of the Eternal, who paid the joiners and builders at work on the temple of th
            Eternal, <verse eID="2Kgs.12.11"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.12.12" osisID="2Kgs.12.12"/> also the masons and the stone-cutters, besides buying
            timber and dressed stone to repair the dilapidations of the temple of the Eternal, and anything in the
            shape of repairs which required an outlay. <verse eID="2Kgs.12.12"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.12.13" osisID="2Kgs.12.13"/> The money brought into the temple of the Eternal did not
            go to silver cups, snuffers, basins, trumpets, or any article of gold or silver; <verse eID="2Kgs.12.13"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.12.14" osisID="2Kgs.12.14"/> it was given to the workmen for the repairs on the temple
            of the Eternal. <verse eID="2Kgs.12.14"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.12.15" osisID="2Kgs.12.15"/> No check was taken of the men who were given the money to
            pay the labourers, for they did their work honestly. <verse eID="2Kgs.12.15"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.12.16" osisID="2Kgs.12.16"/> (The monies for sin-offerings and guilt-offerings were
            not brought into the temple of the Eternal; they belonged to the priests.) <verse eID="2Kgs.12.16"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.12.17" osisID="2Kgs.12.17"/> Now Hazael king of Aram marched to attack Gath and
            captured it. Hazael then turned to Jerusalem. <verse eID="2Kgs.12.17"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.12.18" osisID="2Kgs.12.18"/> But Jehoash king of Judah took all the votive offerings
            of Jehoshaphat, Jehoram, and Ahaziah, his ancestors, the kings of Judah, along with his own votive
            offerings and all the gold to be found in the treasures of the temple of the Eternal and of the
            palace, and this he sent to Hazael king of Aram, who left Jerusalem alone. <verse eID="2Kgs.12.18"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.12.19" osisID="2Kgs.12.19"/> The rest of the acts of Jehoash and all his deeds, are
            they not
            <milestone type="pb" n="433"/>
            described in the book of the Annals of the Kings of Judah? <verse eID="2Kgs.12.19"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.12.20" osisID="2Kgs.12.20"/> His officers started a conspiracy, felling Jehoash as he
            was going down to the house of Millo; <verse eID="2Kgs.12.20"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.12.21" osisID="2Kgs.12.21"/> it was Jozkar the son of Shimeath and Jehozabad the son
            of Shomer, both officers of his, who felled him. He died and was buried with his fathers in David's
            burg. Amazlah his son reigned instead of him. <verse eID="2Kgs.12.21"/>
       </p>
     <chapter eID="2Kgs.12"/>
     <chapter osisID="2Kgs.13" sID="2Kgs.13"/>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.13.1" osisID="2Kgs.13.1"/> It was in the twenty-third year of Jehoash the son of
            Ahaziah, king of Judah, that Jehoahaz the son of Jehu began his seventeen years' reign over Israel in
            Samaria. <verse eID="2Kgs.13.1"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.13.2" osisID="2Kgs.13.2"/> He did what was evil in the eyes of the Eternal, following
            the sins by winch Jeroboam the son of Nebat led Israel into sin; he did not abandon these sinful
            practices. <verse eID="2Kgs.13.2"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.13.3" osisID="2Kgs.13.3"/> So the anger of the Eternal blazed against Israel, till he
            let them lie, without a break, in the power of Hazael the king of Aram and of Hazael's son Benhadad.
           <verse eID="2Kgs.13.3"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.13.4" osisID="2Kgs.13.4"/> (Jehoahaz besought the Eternal, and the Eternal listened to
            him, for he saw how the king of Aram was oppressing Israel; <verse eID="2Kgs.13.4"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.13.5" osisID="2Kgs.13.5"/> the Eternal gave Israel a hero to deliver them, so that
            they got free from the grip of the Aramseans, and the Israelites lived in their own homes as before.
           <verse eID="2Kgs.13.5"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.13.6" osisID="2Kgs.13.6"/> Yet they would not abandon the sins by which Jeroboam the
            son of Nebat led Israel into sin; they practised their sins. And the Astarte image still remained in
            Samaria.) <verse eID="2Kgs.13.6"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.13.7" osisID="2Kgs.13.7"/> For all that was left him of an army was fifty cavalry, ten
            chariots, and ten thousand infantry; the king of Aram had reduced the army till it was weak as dust upon a
            threshing-floor. <verse eID="2Kgs.13.7"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.13.23" osisID="2Kgs.13.23"/> But the Eternal was gracious to them, he had pity on
            them and turned to them again, because of his compact with Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob; he would not
            destroy them nor drive them from his presence. <verse eID="2Kgs.13.23"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.13.8" osisID="2Kgs.13.8"/> The rest of the acts of Jehoahaz, with all his deeds and
            his prowess, are they not described in the book of the Annals of the Kings of Israel? <verse eID="2Kgs.13.8"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.13.9" osisID="2Kgs.13.9"/> Jehoahaz slept with his fathers and was buried in Samaria;
            Jehoash his son reigned instead of him. <verse eID="2Kgs.13.9"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.13.10" osisID="2Kgs.13.10"/> It was in the thirty-ninth year of Jehoash king of
            Judah that Jehoash the son of Jehoahaz began his sixteen years' reign over Israel in Samaria. <verse eID="2Kgs.13.10"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.13.11" osisID="2Kgs.13.11"/> He did what was evil in the eyes of the Eternal, he did
            not abandon any of the sins by which Jeroboam the son of Nebat had led Israel into sin, but followed
            their sinful practices. <verse eID="2Kgs.13.11"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.13.14" osisID="2Kgs.13.14"/> Now when Elisha had fallen ill with the disease of which
            he was to die, Jehoash king of Israel went dowrn to him and wept over him, crying, <q>My father, my
            father, you are worth chariots and horsemen to Israel!</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.13.14"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.13.15" osisID="2Kgs.13.15"/> Elisha told him to take his bow and arrows. He took his
            bow and arrows. <verse eID="2Kgs.13.15"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.13.16" osisID="2Kgs.13.16"/> Then said Elisha to the king of Israel, <q>Draw the
            bow.</q> So he drew the bow; Elisha rested his hands on the king's hands, <verse eID="2Kgs.13.16"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.13.17" osisID="2Kgs.13.17"/> and told him to open the window towards the east. When he
            opened it, Elisha said, <q>Shoot.</q> As he shot his arrow, Elisha cried, <q>It is the Eternal's own
            arrow of victory! Victory over Aram! You shall defeat the Aramseans at Aphek, and wipe them out.</q>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.13.17"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.13.18" osisID="2Kgs.13.18"/> Then he told the king of Israel to take some arrows; he
            did so, and Elisha said, <q>Strike them into the ground.</q> He struck them into
            <milestone type="pb" n="434"/>
            the ground, and then, stopped. <verse eID="2Kgs.13.18"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.13.19" osisID="2Kgs.13.19"/> The man of God was angry with him; <q>You should have
            struck five or six times,</q> he said, <q>and then you would have struck down Aram and destroyed it.
            As it is, you will defeat Aram only three times.</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.13.19"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.13.20" osisID="2Kgs.13.20"/> Elisha died and was buried. Now parties of Moabites used
            to raid the country year by year; <verse eID="2Kgs.13.20"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.13.21" osisID="2Kgs.13.21"/> once, when they were burying a man, they suddenly spied a
            band of the enemy; so, flinging the man into the tomb of Misha, they made off. No sooner did the man touch
            the bones of Elisha than he revived and stood up on his feet. <verse eID="2Kgs.13.21"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.13.22" osisID="2Kgs.13.22"/> During all the reign of Jehoahaz, Hazael king of Aram
            oppressed Israel; <verse eID="2Kgs.13.22"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.13.24" osisID="2Kgs.13.24"/> but when Hazael died and was succeeded by his son
            Benhadad, <verse eID="2Kgs.13.24"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.13.25" osisID="2Kgs.13.25"/> Jehoash the son of Jehoahaz recovered from Benhadad the
            son of Hazael the towns which had been captured from his father Jehoahaz. Three times did Jehoash
            defeat him, regaining the towns of Israel. <verse eID="2Kgs.13.25"/>
       </p>
     <chapter eID="2Kgs.13"/>
     <chapter osisID="2Kgs.14" sID="2Kgs.14"/>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.14.8" osisID="2Kgs.14.8"/> Then Amazlah sent messengers to Jehoash the son of Jehoahaz
            (the son of Jehu), king of Israel, challenging him to an encounter. <verse eID="2Kgs.14.8"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.14.9" osisID="2Kgs.14.9"/> Jehoash king of Israel sent this answer to Amazlah king of
            Judah. <q>The thistle at Lebanon sent word to the cedar at Lebanon, saying, <q>Give your daughter to
            my son in marriage</q>--when a wild animal at Lebanon trampled down the thistle as it passed! <verse eID="2Kgs.14.9"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.14.10" osisID="2Kgs.14.10"/> You are proud of having defeated Edom? Stay at home with
            your pride; why should you provoke trouble, to the ruin of yourself and Judah with you?</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.14.10"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.14.11" osisID="2Kgs.14.11"/> But Amazlah would not listen to him. So Jehoash king of
            Israel sallied out; he and Amazlah king of Judah had an encounter at Bethshemesh, which belongs to
            Judah; <verse eID="2Kgs.14.11"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.14.12" osisID="2Kgs.14.12"/> Judah was overthrown by Israel, and every man scurried
            home. <verse eID="2Kgs.14.12"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.14.13" osisID="2Kgs.14.13"/> At Beth-shemesh Jehoash king of Israel captured Amazlah
            king of Judah, the son of Jehoash, the grandson of Ahaziah; he took him down to Jerusalem, demolished
            the wall of Jerusalem for two hundred yards from the gate of Ephraim to the Corner Gate, <verse eID="2Kgs.14.13"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.14.14" osisID="2Kgs.14.14"/> seized all the gold and silver and all the articles to be
            found in the temple of the Eternal and in the treasures of the palace, and then returned to Samaria, carrying
            hostages with him. <verse eID="2Kgs.14.14"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.14.15" osisID="2Kgs.14.15"/> The rest of the acts done by Jehoash, his prowess, and
            his fight against Amazlah king of Judah, are they not described in the book of the Annals of the Kings
            of Israel? <verse eID="2Kgs.14.15"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.14.16" osisID="2Kgs.14.16"/> Jehoash slept with his fathers and was buried at Samaria
            beside the kings of Israel. Jeroboam his son reigned instead of him. <verse eID="2Kgs.14.16"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.14.1" osisID="2Kgs.14.1"/> It was in the second year of Jehoash son of Jehoahaz king
            of Israel that Amazlah the son of Jehoash king of Judah began to reign. <verse eID="2Kgs.14.1"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.14.2" osisID="2Kgs.14.2"/> He was twenty-five years old when he began to reign, and he
            reigned in Jerusalem for twenty-nine years. His mother's name was Jehoaddin of Jerusalem. <verse eID="2Kgs.14.2"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.14.3" osisID="2Kgs.14.3"/> He did what was right in the eyes of the Eternal, though
            not so well as David his ancestor; he did exactly as Jehoash his father had done. <verse eID="2Kgs.14.3"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.14.4" osisID="2Kgs.14.4"/> However, the shrines were not removed; the people still
            sacrificed and burnt incense at the shrines, <verse eID="2Kgs.14.4"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.14.5" osisID="2Kgs.14.5"/> Once he had the kingdom firmly in hand, he killed the
            officers who had
            <milestone type="pb" n="435"/>
            killed the king his father, <verse eID="2Kgs.14.5"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.14.6" osisID="2Kgs.14.6"/> but he did not put to death the children of the murderers,
            following the injunction in the law-book of Moses, the Eternal's order that fathers are not to be put
            to death for children, nor children for fathers, but that everyone must be put to death for his own
            sin. <verse eID="2Kgs.14.6"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.14.7" osisID="2Kgs.14.7"/> He slaughtered ten thousand Edomites in the wady of Salt
            and stormed Sela, which he renamed Joktheel--as it is called to this day. <verse eID="2Kgs.14.7"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.14.17" osisID="2Kgs.14.17"/> Amaziah the son of Jehoash king of Judah lived for
            fifteen years after the death of Jehoash son of Jehoahaz, king of Israel. <verse eID="2Kgs.14.17"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.14.18" osisID="2Kgs.14.18"/> As for the rest of the acts of Amaziah, are they not
            described in the book of the Annals of Kings of Judah? <verse eID="2Kgs.14.18"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.14.19" osisID="2Kgs.14.19"/> There was a conspiracy formed against him in Jerusalem;
            he fled to Lakhish, but the conspirators sent men after him and murdered him at Lakhish; <verse eID="2Kgs.14.19"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.14.20" osisID="2Kgs.14.20"/> he was then brought on horses to Jerusalem, where he was
            buried with his fathers in David's burg. <verse eID="2Kgs.14.20"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.14.21" osisID="2Kgs.14.21"/> The people of Judah all took Azarlah, who was sixteen,
            and made him king instead of his father Amaziah. <verse eID="2Kgs.14.21"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.14.22" osisID="2Kgs.14.22"/> (It was he who rebuilt Elath and restored it to Judah,
            after king Amaziah slept with his fathers!) <verse eID="2Kgs.14.22"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.14.23" osisID="2Kgs.14.23"/> In the fifteenth year of Amaziah the son of Jehoash king
            of Judah, Jeroboam the son of Jehoash king of Israel began his forty-one years' reign in Samaria. <verse eID="2Kgs.14.23"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.14.24" osisID="2Kgs.14.24"/> He did what was evil in the sight of the Eternal; he did
            not abandon any of the sins by which Jeroboam the son of Nebat had led Israel into sin. <verse eID="2Kgs.14.24"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.14.25" osisID="2Kgs.14.25"/> He restored the frontier of Israel from the pass of
            Hamath as far as to the sea of Arabah, as enjoined by the Eternal the God of Israel speaking by his
            servant the prophet Jonah the son of Amittai, who belonged to Gathhepher. <verse eID="2Kgs.14.25"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.14.26" osisID="2Kgs.14.26"/> For the Eternal saw how bitterly Israel was suffering,
            stripped of fettered and free alike, and with no one to help her; <verse eID="2Kgs.14.26"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.14.27" osisID="2Kgs.14.27"/> it was not the Eternal's purpose to blot out the very
            name of Israel from under heaven, and so he rescued them by means of Jeroboam the son of Jehoash.
           <verse eID="2Kgs.14.27"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.14.28" osisID="2Kgs.14.28"/> The rest of the acts of Jeroboam, all his deeds and his
            prowess, how he fought Damascus and averted the Eternal's anger from Israel--is not all this described
            in the book of the Annals of the Kings of Israel? <verse eID="2Kgs.14.28"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.14.29" osisID="2Kgs.14.29"/> Jeroboam slept with his fathers the kings of Israel, and
            Zecharlah his son reigned instead of him. <verse eID="2Kgs.14.29"/>
       </p>
     <chapter eID="2Kgs.14"/>
     <chapter osisID="2Kgs.15" sID="2Kgs.15"/>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.15.1" osisID="2Kgs.15.1"/> It was in the twenty-seventh year of Jeroboam king of
            Israel that Azarlah son of Amaziah king of Judah began to reign, <verse eID="2Kgs.15.1"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.15.2" osisID="2Kgs.15.2"/> and he reigned in Jerusalem for fifty-two years. His
            mother's name was Jekollah of Jerusalem. <verse eID="2Kgs.15.2"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.15.3" osisID="2Kgs.15.3"/> He did what was right in the eyes of the Eternal,
            exactly as his father Amaziah had done. <verse eID="2Kgs.15.3"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.15.4" osisID="2Kgs.15.4"/> However, the shrines were not removed; the people still
            sacrificed and burnt incense at the shrines. <verse eID="2Kgs.15.4"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.15.5" osisID="2Kgs.15.5"/> But the Eternal struck the king, till he became a leper to
            the day of his death; he was allowed to stay in his palace unmolested, but prince Jotham managed the
            royal household and ruled the nation. <verse eID="2Kgs.15.5"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.15.6" osisID="2Kgs.15.6"/> The rest of the acts of Azarlah and all he did, are they
            not described in the book of the Annals of the Kings of Judah? <verse eID="2Kgs.15.6"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.15.7" osisID="2Kgs.15.7"/> Azariah slept with his fathers, and was buried with his
            fathers in
            <milestone type="pb" n="436"/>
            David’s burg. Jotham his son reigned instead of him. <verse eID="2Kgs.15.7"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.15.8" osisID="2Kgs.15.8"/> It was in the thirty-eighth year of Azariah king of Judah
            that Zechariah the son of Jeroboam began his six months' reign over Israel in Samaria. <verse eID="2Kgs.15.8"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.15.9" osisID="2Kgs.15.9"/> He did what was evil in the eyes of the Eternal, as his
            fathers had done; he would not abandon the sins by which Jeroboam the son of Nebat had led Israel into
            sin. <verse eID="2Kgs.15.9"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.15.10" osisID="2Kgs.15.10"/> Shallum the son of Jabesh conspired against him, and
            struck him down dead at Ibleam; then he succeeded him. <verse eID="2Kgs.15.10"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.15.11" osisID="2Kgs.15.11"/> The rest of the acts of Zechariah are described in the
            book of the Annals of the Kings of Israel. <verse eID="2Kgs.15.11"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.15.12" osisID="2Kgs.15.12"/> (This was the promise made by the Eternal to Jehu,
            <q>Your sons shall sit on the throne of Israel to the fourth generation.</q> And so it was.) <verse eID="2Kgs.15.12"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.15.13" osisID="2Kgs.15.13"/> Shallum the son of Jabesh began to reign in the
            thirty-ninth year of Azariah king of Judah; he reigned for one month in Samaria. <verse eID="2Kgs.15.13"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.15.14" osisID="2Kgs.15.14"/> Then Menahem the son of Gadi came up from Tirzah to
            Samaria and struck down Shallum son of Jabesh dead in Samaria; he succeeded him. <verse eID="2Kgs.15.14"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.15.15" osisID="2Kgs.15.15"/> The rest of the acts of Shallum and his conspiracy are
            described in the book of the Annals of the Kings of Israel. <verse eID="2Kgs.15.15"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.15.17" osisID="2Kgs.15.17"/> It was in the thirty-ninth year of Azariah king of Judah
            that Menahem the son of Gadi began his ten years' reign over Israel in Samaria. <verse eID="2Kgs.15.17"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.15.18" osisID="2Kgs.15.18"/> He did what was evil in the eyes of the Eternal; he would
            not abandon the sins by which Jeroboam the son of Nebat had led Israel into sin. <verse eID="2Kgs.15.18"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.15.16" osisID="2Kgs.15.16"/> From Tirzah Menahem sacked Tappuah with all its citizens
            and all within its territory; as the town would not open to him, he sacked it, ripping up all the pregnant
            women. <verse eID="2Kgs.15.16"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.15.19" osisID="2Kgs.15.19"/> During his reign Pulu the Assyrian king invaded the
            country; but Menahem gave Pulu over four hundred thousand pounds in silver, to gain his help in
            confirming his royal power. <verse eID="2Kgs.15.19"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.15.20" osisID="2Kgs.15.20"/> Menahem assessed all the wealthy men of Israel, taking
            nearly four hundred pounds in silver from each, for this present to the Assyrian king. So the Assyrian
            king turned back, instead of remaining in the country. <verse eID="2Kgs.15.20"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.15.21" osisID="2Kgs.15.21"/> As for the rest of the acts of Menahem and all he did,
            are they not described in the book of the Annals of the Kings of Israel? <verse eID="2Kgs.15.21"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.15.22" osisID="2Kgs.15.22"/> Menahem slept with his fathers, and Pekahiah his son
            reigned instead of him. <verse eID="2Kgs.15.22"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.15.23" osisID="2Kgs.15.23"/> It was in the fiftieth year of Azariah king of Judah that
            Pekahiah the son of Menahem began his two years' reign over Israel in Samaria. <verse eID="2Kgs.15.23"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.15.24" osisID="2Kgs.15.24"/> He did what was evil in the eyes of the Eternal; he would
            not abandon the sins by which Jeroboam the son of Nebat had led Israel into sin. <verse eID="2Kgs.15.24"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.15.25" osisID="2Kgs.15.25"/> His adjutant, Pekah the son of Remaliah, conspired
            against him, and, with fifty men from Gilead, struck him down in Samaria, inside the citadel of the
            royal palace; having killed him, Pekab reigned instead of him. <verse eID="2Kgs.15.25"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.15.26" osisID="2Kgs.15.26"/> The rest of the acts of Pekahiah and all he did are
            described in the book of the Annals of the Kings of Israel. <verse eID="2Kgs.15.26"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.15.27" osisID="2Kgs.15.27"/> It was in the fifty-second year of Azariah king of Judah
            that Pekah the son of Remaliah began his twenty years' reign over Israel in Samaria. <verse eID="2Kgs.15.27"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.15.28" osisID="2Kgs.15.28"/> He did what was evil in the eyes of the Eternal; he would
            not abandon the sins by which Jeroboam the son of Nebat had led Israel into sin. <verse eID="2Kgs.15.28"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.15.29" osisID="2Kgs.15.29"/> During the reign of Pekah
            <milestone type="pb" n="437"/>
            king of Israel, the Assyrian king Tiglath-pileser came and captured Ijon, Abel-beth-maaeah, Janoah,
            Kedesh, Hazor, Argob, and Havoth-jair (Gilead and Galilee), indeed the whole territory of Naphtali,
            carrying off the inhabitants into exile in Assyria. <verse eID="2Kgs.15.29"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.15.30" osisID="2Kgs.15.30"/> Hoshea the son of Elah started a conspiracy against Pekah
            the son of Remaliah, striking him down dead and reigning instead of him, in the twentieth year of Jotham the
            son of Azariah. <verse eID="2Kgs.15.30"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.15.31" osisID="2Kgs.15.31"/> The rest of the acts of Pekah and all he did are
            described in the book of the Annals of the Kings of Israel. <verse eID="2Kgs.15.31"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.15.32" osisID="2Kgs.15.32"/> It was in the second year of Pekah the son of Remaliah
            king of Israel that Jotham the son of Azariah king of Judah began to reign. <verse eID="2Kgs.15.32"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.15.33" osisID="2Kgs.15.33"/> He was twenty-five years old when he began to reign, and
            he reigned in Jerusalem for sixteen years. His mother's name was Jerusha the daughter of Zadok. <verse eID="2Kgs.15.33"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.15.34" osisID="2Kgs.15.34"/> He did what was right in the eyes of the Eternal; he did
            exactly as his father Azariah had done. <verse eID="2Kgs.15.34"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.15.35" osisID="2Kgs.15.35"/> However, the shrines were not removed; the people still
            sacrificed and burnt incense at the shrines. He built the upper gateway to the temple of the Eternal.
           <verse eID="2Kgs.15.35"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.15.36" osisID="2Kgs.15.36"/> The rest of the acts of Jotham and all he did, are they
            not all described in the book of the Annals of the Kings of Judah? <verse eID="2Kgs.15.36"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.15.37" osisID="2Kgs.15.37"/> (It was in those days that the Eternal began to send
            Rezin the king of Aram and Pekah the son of Remaliah to attack Judah.) <verse eID="2Kgs.15.37"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.15.38" osisID="2Kgs.15.38"/> Jotham slept with his fathers, and was buried with his
            fathers in his father David's burg. Ahaz his son reigned instead of him. <verse eID="2Kgs.15.38"/>
       </p>
     <chapter eID="2Kgs.15"/>
     <chapter osisID="2Kgs.16" sID="2Kgs.16"/>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.16.1" osisID="2Kgs.16.1"/> It was in the seventeenth year of Pekah the son of
            Remaliah that Ahaz the son of Jotham king of Judah began to reign. <verse eID="2Kgs.16.1"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.16.2" osisID="2Kgs.16.2"/> Ahaz was twenty years old when he began to reign, and he
            reigned in Jerusalem for sixteen years. He did not do what was right in the eyes of the Eternal his
            God, as his ancestor David had done; <verse eID="2Kgs.16.2"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.16.3" osisID="2Kgs.16.3"/> he lived on the lines of the kings of Israel, and he
            actually burnt his son alive in sacrifice, following the abominable practice of the nations whom the
            Eternal had dispossessed to make room for Israel. <verse eID="2Kgs.16.3"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.16.4" osisID="2Kgs.16.4"/> He sacrificed and burnt incense at the shrines, on the
            hilltops, and under every spreading tree. <verse eID="2Kgs.16.4"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.16.5" osisID="2Kgs.16.5"/> Now Rezin the king of Aram and Pekah the son of Remaliah
            king of Israel marched up to attack Jerusalem; they besieged Ahaz, though they could not conquer him.
           <verse eID="2Kgs.16.5"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.16.6" osisID="2Kgs.16.6"/> (It was then that the king of Edom regained Elath for Edom;
            he cleared out the Judahites from Elath, and the Edomites entered Elath, where they dwell to this day.)
           <verse eID="2Kgs.16.6"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.16.7" osisID="2Kgs.16.7"/> So Ahaz sent messengers to Tig­lath-pileser king of
            Assyria, to say: <q>I am your servant and your son; march up and rescue me from the king of Aram and
            from the king of Israel, who are attacking me.</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.16.7"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.16.8" osisID="2Kgs.16.8"/> Ahaz also took all the silver and the gold that were to be
            found in the temple of the Eternal and in the treasures of the royal palace, and sent it as tribute to the
            king of Assyria. <verse eID="2Kgs.16.8"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.16.9" osisID="2Kgs.16.9"/> The king of Assyria listened to his plea. The king of
            Assyria marched on Damascus, captured it, and carried off the inhabitants as prisoners to Kir,
            putting Rezin to death. <verse eID="2Kgs.16.9"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.16.10" osisID="2Kgs.16.10"/> When king Ahaz went to Damascus to meet Tiglath-pileser
            <milestone type="pb" n="438"/>
            the king of Assyria and saw the altar at Damascus, he sent a model of it, a pattern exact in every
            detail, <verse eID="2Kgs.16.10"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.16.11" osisID="2Kgs.16.11"/> to the priest Urijah, who built an altar; Urijah the
            priest followed all the instructions sent by king Ahaz from Damascus, and had it ready for king Ahaz
            when he returned from Damascus. <verse eID="2Kgs.16.11"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.16.12" osisID="2Kgs.16.12"/> On his return from Damascus, the king inspected the
            altar and then went up to it to sacrifice; <verse eID="2Kgs.16.12"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.16.13" osisID="2Kgs.16.13"/> he burnt his burnt-offering and his cereal-offering, he
            poured out his libation, and he splashed the blood of his recompense-offerings on the altar of bronze
            in front of the Eternal; <verse eID="2Kgs.16.13"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.16.14" osisID="2Kgs.16.14"/> coming forward between the temple and the new altar, he
            applied the blood to the new altar. <verse eID="2Kgs.16.14"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.16.15" osisID="2Kgs.16.15"/> Then king Ahaz ordered Urijah the priest to use the new
            large altar for the morning burnt-offering, the evening cereal-offering, the king's burnt-offering, and the
            king's cereal­offering, as well as the nation's burnt-offering and cereal-offering and their libations;
            he was to splash on it the blood of the burnt-offering and all the sacrificial blood, while the
            bronze altar was to serve for the king's divination. <verse eID="2Kgs.16.15"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.16.16" osisID="2Kgs.16.16"/> Urijah the priest followed all the instructions of king
            Ahaz. <verse eID="2Kgs.16.16"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.16.17" osisID="2Kgs.16.17"/> King Ahaz also cut off the panels from the trolleys, and
            removed the bronze pots from them, he removed the tank from the bronze bulls on which it rested, and
            placed it on a stone pediment <verse eID="2Kgs.16.17"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.16.18" osisID="2Kgs.16.18"/> ... all owing to the king of Assyria.<verse eID="2Kgs.16.18"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.16.19" osisID="2Kgs.16.19"/> As for the rest of the acts done by Ahaz, are they not
            described in the book of the Annals of the Kings of Judah? <verse eID="2Kgs.16.19"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.16.20" osisID="2Kgs.16.20"/> Ahaz slept with his fathers, and was buried with his
            fathers in David's burg. Hezekiah his son reigned instead of him. <verse eID="2Kgs.16.20"/>
       </p>
     <chapter eID="2Kgs.16"/>
     <chapter osisID="2Kgs.17" sID="2Kgs.17"/>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.17.1" osisID="2Kgs.17.1"/>
            It was in the twelfth year of Ahaz king of Judah that Hoshea the son of Elah began his nine years'
            reign over Israel in Samaria. <verse eID="2Kgs.17.1"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.17.2" osisID="2Kgs.17.2"/> He did what was evil in the eyes of the Eternal, though
            not like the previous kings of Israel. <verse eID="2Kgs.17.2"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.17.3" osisID="2Kgs.17.3"/> When Shalmaneser the king of Assyria marched against him,
            Hoshea submitted to him and offered tribute. <verse eID="2Kgs.17.3"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.17.4" osisID="2Kgs.17.4"/> But when the king of Assyria discovered Hoshea conspiring
            (for he had sent envoys to Seve the Egyptian king, instead of bringing his annual tribute as usual
            to the king of Assyria), the king of Assyria kept him in custody as a prisoner. <verse eID="2Kgs.17.4"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.17.5" osisID="2Kgs.17.5"/> Then the king of Assyria marched right through the
            country, laying siege to Samaria for three years. <verse eID="2Kgs.17.5"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.17.6" osisID="2Kgs.17.6"/> In the ninth year of Hoshea the king of Assyria captured
            Samaria and carried Israel off to Assyria, settling them in Halah and on the Habor, the river of
            Gozan, and throughout the cities of Media. <verse eID="2Kgs.17.6"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.17.7" osisID="2Kgs.17.7"/> The wrath of God was upon Israel, because the Israelites
            had sinned against the Eternal their God, who had brought them out of the land of Egypt from the grip of
            the Pharaoh king of Egypt; they had reverenced other gods <verse eID="2Kgs.17.7"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.17.8" osisID="2Kgs.17.8"/> and followed the customs of the nations whom the Eternal
            had dispossessed to make room for the Israelites. <verse eID="2Kgs.17.8"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.17.9" osisID="2Kgs.17.9"/> The Israelites devised what was evil against the Eternal
            their God, erecting shrines in all their settlements, from villages to large towns, <verse eID="2Kgs.17.9"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.17.10" osisID="2Kgs.17.10"/> setting up obelisks and sacred poles on every hill and
            under every spreading tree, <verse eID="2Kgs.17.10"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.17.11" osisID="2Kgs.17.11"/> and sacrificing there (at all the
            <milestone type="pb" n="439"/>
            shrines) like the nations whom the Eternal had ejected before them, practising wickedness to vex the
            Eternal, <verse eID="2Kgs.17.11"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.17.12" osisID="2Kgs.17.12"/> and worshipping fetishes, which the Eternal had
            forbidden them to do. <verse eID="2Kgs.17.12"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.17.13" osisID="2Kgs.17.13"/> Yet the Eternal warned Israel and Judah by all his
            prophets and seers, saying, <q>Turn from your evil ways and obey my commands and rules, in terms of
            all the law which I enjoined upon your fathers and imparted to you by my servants the prophets.</q>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.17.13"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.17.14" osisID="2Kgs.17.14"/> However, they would not listen; they were as wilful as
            their fathers, who would not believe in the Eternal their God; <verse eID="2Kgs.17.14"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.17.15" osisID="2Kgs.17.15"/> they rejected his rules and the compact he had made
            with their fathers and the warnings he had given them; they went after false gods to become false
            like them, following the surrounding nations whom the Eternal had ordered them not to copy; <verse eID="2Kgs.17.15"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.17.16" osisID="2Kgs.17.16"/> they abandoned all the commands of the Eternal their
            God and manufactured metal idols, making an image of Astarte, worshipping all the stars, and
            honouring Baal; <verse eID="2Kgs.17.16"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.17.17" osisID="2Kgs.17.17"/> they burned their sons and daughters alive in
            sacrifice, they practised divination and sorcery, selling themselves to do evil in the eyes of the
            Eternal, to vex him. <verse eID="2Kgs.17.17"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.17.18" osisID="2Kgs.17.18"/> So the Eternal was furious with Israel and removed them
            from his sight; all that was left was the clan of Judah. <verse eID="2Kgs.17.18"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.17.19" osisID="2Kgs.17.19"/> [[Judah also followed the customs introduced by Israel,
            instead of obeying the commands of the Eternal their God; <verse eID="2Kgs.17.19"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.17.20" osisID="2Kgs.17.20"/> and so the Eternal rejected the whole race of Israel,
            afflicting them and handing them over to plunderers, till he had cleared them out of his sight.]]
           <verse eID="2Kgs.17.20"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.17.21" osisID="2Kgs.17.21"/> For after he tore Israel from the dynasty of David,
            Israel made Jeroboam the son of Nebat king, and Jeroboam drove Israel from its loyalty to the
            Eternal, making it commit a great sin. <verse eID="2Kgs.17.21"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.17.22" osisID="2Kgs.17.22"/> The Israelites adhered to all the sins committed by
            Jeroboam; they would not give them up, <verse eID="2Kgs.17.22"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.17.23" osisID="2Kgs.17.23"/> till at last the Eternal removed Israel from his sight,
            as he had threatened by all his servants the prophets. Israel was carried off from their own land to
            Assyria, where they are to this day. <verse eID="2Kgs.17.23"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.17.24" osisID="2Kgs.17.24"/> The king of Assyria then brought people from Babylon, Kutu,
            Ivvah, Hamath, and Seph- arvaim, and settled them in Samaria in place of the Israelites. These people took
            possession of Samaria and lived in its towns. <verse eID="2Kgs.17.24"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.17.25" osisID="2Kgs.17.25"/> When they began to live there, they did not worship the
            Eternal; so the Eternal sent lions among them, which used to kill some of them. <verse eID="2Kgs.17.25"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.17.26" osisID="2Kgs.17.26"/> The king of Assyria was told that as the nations he had
            deported to settle in the towns of Samaria did not know the religion of the local god, he had sent lions
            among them, and that they were being killed because they did not know the religion of the local god.
           <verse eID="2Kgs.17.26"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.17.27" osisID="2Kgs.17.27"/> So the king of Assyria issued orders that one of the
            priests whom he had carried off should be taken back and allowed to live in the country, to teach
            them the religion of the local god. <verse eID="2Kgs.17.27"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.17.28" osisID="2Kgs.17.28"/> One of the priests who had been carried off from
            Samaria did return to live at Bethel, where he taught them how to worship the Eternal; <verse eID="2Kgs.17.28"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.17.29" osisID="2Kgs.17.29"/> but the nations had all made gods of their own, setting
            up their worship in the shrines made by the Samaritans, each nation in its own towns, <verse eID="2Kgs.17.29"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.17.30" osisID="2Kgs.17.30"/> the
            <milestone type="pb" n="440"/>
            Babylonians making an image of Sukkoth-Benoth, the men of Kutu choosing Nergal, the men of Hamath
            Ashima, <verse eID="2Kgs.17.30"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.17.31" osisID="2Kgs.17.31"/> the Ivvites Nibhaz and Tartak, while the Sepharvites
            burnt their children alive in sacrifice to Adrammalek and Anammelek, the Sepharvite gods. <verse eID="2Kgs.17.31"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.17.32" osisID="2Kgs.17.32"/> In worshipping the Eternal, they chose men from the
            masses to be priests for their shrines, who officiated for them at the sacred shrines. <verse eID="2Kgs.17.32"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.17.33" osisID="2Kgs.17.33"/> They worshipped the Eternal and they also served their
            own gods, after the religious customs of the nations from which they had been deported. <verse eID="2Kgs.17.33"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.17.34" osisID="2Kgs.17.34"/> To this day they follow these primitive religious
            customs. [[They neither worship the Eternal nor follow the rules, the rites, the directions, and the
            commands laid dowrn by the Eternal for the children of Jacob whom he named Israel, <verse eID="2Kgs.17.34"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.17.35" osisID="2Kgs.17.35"/> and with whom the Eternal made this compact, charging
            them, <q>You must never worship other gods, never bow down to them, nor serve them, nor sacrifice to
            them; <verse eID="2Kgs.17.35"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.17.36" osisID="2Kgs.17.36"/> it is the Eternal who brought you from the land of
            Egypt by sheer strength and main force, it is the Eternal you must worship, to him you must bow down
            and sacrifice; <verse eID="2Kgs.17.36"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.17.37" osisID="2Kgs.17.37"/> you must be mindful always to keep the rules, the
            rites, the law, and the commands he has written for you; you must never worship other gods, <verse eID="2Kgs.17.37"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.17.38" osisID="2Kgs.17.38"/> and never forget the compact I have made with you; you
            must never worship other gods, <verse eID="2Kgs.17.38"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.17.39" osisID="2Kgs.17.39"/> but worship the Eternal your God, and he will rescue
            you from all your foes. <verse eID="2Kgs.17.39"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.17.40" osisID="2Kgs.17.40"/> However, they would not listen, they followed their
            primitive religious customs.]] <verse eID="2Kgs.17.40"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.17.41" osisID="2Kgs.17.41"/> So these nations worshipped the Eternal and also
            served carved idols of their own, as did their children and their children's children, following
            their fathers as they do to this day. <verse eID="2Kgs.17.41"/>
       </p>
     <chapter eID="2Kgs.17"/>
     <chapter osisID="2Kgs.18" sID="2Kgs.18"/>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.18.1" osisID="2Kgs.18.1"/> It was in the third year of Hoshea son of Elah king of
            Israel that Hezekiah the son of Ahaz king of Judah began to reign; <verse eID="2Kgs.18.1"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.18.2" osisID="2Kgs.18.2"/> he was twenty-five years old when he began to reign, and
            he reigned in Jerusalem for twenty-nine years. His mother's name was Abijah the daughter of
            Zechariah. <verse eID="2Kgs.18.2"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.18.3" osisID="2Kgs.18.3"/> He did what was right in the eyes of the Eternal, exactly
            as David his ancestor had done. <verse eID="2Kgs.18.3"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.18.4" osisID="2Kgs.18.4"/> He removed the shrines, broke the obelisks, and cut down
            the sacred poles; he demolished the bronze serpent made by Moses (Nehushtan, it was called), as the
            Israelites in those days sacrificed to it. <verse eID="2Kgs.18.4"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.18.5" osisID="2Kgs.18.5"/> His trust was in the Eternal, the God of Israel, so that
            there was no king of Judah like him, before or afterwards; <verse eID="2Kgs.18.5"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.18.6" osisID="2Kgs.18.6"/> for he adhered to the Eternal, he never gave up following
            him, but obeyed the commands given by the Eternal to Moses. <verse eID="2Kgs.18.6"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.18.7" osisID="2Kgs.18.7"/> And the Eternal was on his side; wherever he made an
            expedition, he succeeded. He rebelled against the king of Assyria and refused to serve him, <verse eID="2Kgs.18.7"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.18.8" osisID="2Kgs.18.8"/> and he also drove the Philistines back to Gaza,
            conquering its district, villages and large towns and all. <verse eID="2Kgs.18.8"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.18.9" osisID="2Kgs.18.9"/> In the fourth year of king Hezekiah--that is, the
            seventh year of Hoshea son of Elah king of Israel--Shalmaneser king of Assyria marched against
            Samaria and besieged it. <verse eID="2Kgs.18.9"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.18.10" osisID="2Kgs.18.10"/> After two years it fell; in the sixth year of Hezekiah,
            the ninth year of Hoshea king of Israel, Samaria was captured. <verse eID="2Kgs.18.10"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.18.11" osisID="2Kgs.18.11"/> The king of Assyria carried off Israel to
            <milestone type="pb" n="441"/>
            Assyria, settling them in Halah and on the Habor, the river of Gozan, and throughout the
            cities of Media, <verse eID="2Kgs.18.11"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.18.12" osisID="2Kgs.18.12"/> because they had not listened to the Eternal their God
           but had broken his compact, refusing to heed or to obey anything that Moses the servant of the Eternal had
           laid down. <verse eID="2Kgs.18.12"/>
       </p>
     <chapter eID="2Kgs.18"/>
     <chapter osisID="2Kgs.20" sID="2Kgs.20"/>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.20.1" osisID="2Kgs.20.1"/> Now Hezekiah fell ill, and was at the point of death; the
            prophet Isaiah, the son of Amoz, went and gave him this message from the Eternal, <q>Put your affairs in
            order, for you are to die, not to recover.</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.20.1"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.20.2" osisID="2Kgs.20.2"/> Then Hezekiah turned his face to the wall and prayed to
            the Eternal, <verse eID="2Kgs.20.2"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.20.3" osisID="2Kgs.20.3"/> <q>0 Eternal, pray remember how loyal and whole-hearted
            my life has been in thy presence, and how I have done right in thy sight!</q> Hezekiah wept aloud.
           <verse eID="2Kgs.20.3"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.20.4" osisID="2Kgs.20.4"/> Before Isaiah had left the courtyard, this word of the
           Eternal came to him, <verse eID="2Kgs.20.4"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.20.5" osisID="2Kgs.20.5"/> <q>Go back and tell Hezekiah, the prince of my people,
            that the Eternal, the God of his father David, declares, <q>I have heard your prayers, I have seen
            your tears, and now I heal you; the day after tomorrow you will be able to go up to the temple of
            the Eternal. <verse eID="2Kgs.20.5"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.20.6" osisID="2Kgs.20.6"/> I will add fifteen years to your life; I will rescue both
            you and this city from the king of Assyria, I will defend this city for my own sake and for the sake
            of my servant David.</q></q> <verse eID="2Kgs.20.6"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.20.7" osisID="2Kgs.20.7"/> Isaiah ordered a poultice of figs to be applied to the
            eruption, that he might recover. <verse eID="2Kgs.20.7"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.20.8" osisID="2Kgs.20.8"/> And when Hezekiah asked Isaiah, <q>What is the sign that
            the Eternal will heal me and let me go up to the temple of the Eternal the day after to-morrow?</q>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.20.8"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.20.9" osisID="2Kgs.20.9"/> Isaiah replied, <q>Here is a sign for you from the
            Eternal, that the Eternal will do as he has promised; choose, shall the shadow move forward or
            back­ward ten steps?</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.20.9"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.20.10" osisID="2Kgs.20.10"/> Hezekiah io said, <q>It is easy for yonder shadow to
            move forward ten steps; rather let the shadow move back ten steps.</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.20.10"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.20.11" osisID="2Kgs.20.11"/> Then the prophet Isaiah called to the Eternal, who
            brought the shadow back for ten steps which it had advanced on the sundial of Ahaz. <verse eID="2Kgs.20.11"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.20.12" osisID="2Kgs.20.12"/> It was then that Merodachbaladan, son of Baladan, king
            of Babylon, sent eunuchs with a present to Hezekiah, for he heard that Hezekiah had been ill. <verse eID="2Kgs.20.12"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.20.13" osisID="2Kgs.20.13"/> Hezekiah was delighted and displayed all his
            treasures, the silver, the gold, the spices, and the precious oil in his stores, besides his armoury;
            there was nothing in his palace or indeed in all his realm that he did not display to them. <verse eID="2Kgs.20.13"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.20.14" osisID="2Kgs.20.14"/> But the prophet Isaiah went to king Hezekiah and
            asked, <q>What did these men say? Where may they have come from?</q> Hezekiah replied, <q>They have come
            from a far country, from Babylon.</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.20.14"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.20.15" osisID="2Kgs.20.15"/> <q>And what did they see in your palace?</q> Hezekiah
            answered, <q>They saw everything in my palace; there is nothing of all my treasure that I did not show to
            them.</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.20.15"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.20.16" osisID="2Kgs.20.16"/> Then said Isaiah to Hezekiah, <verse eID="2Kgs.20.16"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.20.17" osisID="2Kgs.20.17"/> <q>Listen to this word from the Eternal: <q>The day is coming when all in your
            palace, with all that your fathers have ever stored up, shall be carried off to Babylon: nothing shall be left,</q> says the
            Eternal. <verse eID="2Kgs.20.17"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.20.18" osisID="2Kgs.20.18"/> <q>The sons born to you, born of your body, shall be taken away to be eunuchs in the
            palace of the king of Babylon.</q></q>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.20.18"/>
           <milestone type="pb" n="442"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.20.19" osisID="2Kgs.20.19"/>
            <q>Very good,</q> said Hezekiah; <q>it is the word of the Eternal you utter!</q> (thinking to himself that there would be no trouble
            or change at least so long as he was alive).
           <verse eID="2Kgs.20.19"/>
       </p>
     <chapter eID="2Kgs.20"/>
     <chapter osisID="2Kgs.18" sID="2Kgs.18"/>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.18.13" osisID="2Kgs.18.13"/> In the fourteenth year of Hezekiah, Sancherib king of Assyria marched against all
            the fortified towns of Judah and captured them. <verse eID="2Kgs.18.13"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.18.14" osisID="2Kgs.18.14"/> So Hezekiah king of Judah sent this message to the king of Assyria at Lakhish:
            <q>I have done wrong; withdraw, and I will pay any fine you choose to inflict.</q> The king of Assyria fixed Hezekiah king of
            Judah's fine at a hundred and twenty-four thousand pounds in silver and a hundred and seventy-four thousand pounds in gold;
           <verse eID="2Kgs.18.14"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.18.15" osisID="2Kgs.18.15"/> Hezekiah gave him all the silver to be found in the temple of the Eternal and in
            the treasures of the royal palace. <verse eID="2Kgs.18.15"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.18.16" osisID="2Kgs.18.16"/> Then it was that Hezekiah had to strip the gold from the doors of the temple of the
            Eternal and from the door-posts overlaid by Hezekiah king of Judah, to give it to the king of Assyria. <verse eID="2Kgs.18.16"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.18.17" osisID="2Kgs.18.17"/> The king of Assyria then sent the field-marshal, the comptroller, and the
            staff-commander, with a large army from Lakhish to king Hezekiah at Jerusalem. They marched up to Jerusalem, and on arriving there
            they went and took up a position beside the conduit of the upper pool on the way to the Fuller's Field, <verse eID="2Kgs.18.17"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.18.18" osisID="2Kgs.18.18"/> calling for the king. When Ellakim the son of Hilkiah, who was prefect of the
            palace, with Shebna the secretary and Joab the son of Asaph the chancellor, came forward, <verse eID="2Kgs.18.18"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.18.19" osisID="2Kgs.18.19"/> the staff-commander gave them this message for Hezekiah: <q>The great monarch, the
            king of Assyria, asks Hezekiah, <q>On what are you resting your confidence? <verse eID="2Kgs.18.19"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.18.20" osisID="2Kgs.18.20"/> You think mere words will do, as policy and power in war! Whom are you trusting to,
            that you rebel against me? <verse eID="2Kgs.18.20"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.18.21" osisID="2Kgs.18.21"/> You trust to this broken reed of a staff, Egypt, that will pierce the hand of any
            man who leans upon it! That is all the Pharaoh king of Egypt does for anyone who trusts to him! <verse eID="2Kgs.18.21"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.18.22" osisID="2Kgs.18.22"/> If you tell me that you trust in the Eternal your God, is this not the very Eternal
            whose shrines and altars Hezekiah has removed, telling Judah and Jerusalem that they are to worship at this altar in Jerusalem?</q>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.18.22"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.18.23" osisID="2Kgs.18.23"/> Come,</q> added the staff-commander, <q>make this wager with my master the king of
            Assyria: I will give you two thousand horses, if you can put as many riders on their backs! <verse eID="2Kgs.18.23"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.18.24" osisID="2Kgs.18.24"/> How, then, can you repulse even the weakest of my master's officers, trusting to
            Egypt for chariots and cavalry? <verse eID="2Kgs.18.24"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.18.25" osisID="2Kgs.18.25"/> Have I marched against this place to destroy it, wdthout the Eternal's sanction?
            No, the Eternal told me to march against this country and destroy it.</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.18.25"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.18.26" osisID="2Kgs.18.26"/> Eliakim the son of Hilkiah and Shebna and Joab said to the staff-commander,
            <q>Pray speak to your servants in Aramaic, for we understand it; do not speak to us in the Jews' language, with the people
            listening on the wall.</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.18.26"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.18.27" osisID="2Kgs.18.27"/> But the staff-commander replied, <q>Did my master send me with this menace for
            your master and for you, and not for the men sitting on the wall--doomed along with you to eat their own dung and drink their
            own urine?</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.18.27"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.18.28" osisID="2Kgs.18.28"/> And the staff-commander stepped forward, shouting aloud in the Jews' language,
            <q>Listen to this
            <milestone type="pb" n="443"/>
            word from the great monarch, the king of Assyria! <verse eID="2Kgs.18.28"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.18.29" osisID="2Kgs.18.29"/> The king warns you not to let Hezekiah delude you; he will never be able to save
            you from my hand. <verse eID="2Kgs.18.29"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.18.30" osisID="2Kgs.18.30"/> Nor let Hezekiah induce you to trust in the Eternal by telling you that the Eternal
            will be sure to save you and prevent this town from falling into the hands of the king of Assyria. <verse eID="2Kgs.18.30"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.18.31" osisID="2Kgs.18.31"/> Never heed Hezekiah. The king of Assyria's advice to you is <q>Make your peace with
            me, surrender to me, and then you can each eat the fruit of your vine and your fig-tree and drink from your own water-supply,
           <verse eID="2Kgs.18.31"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.18.32" osisID="2Kgs.18.32"/> until I come to deport you to a land like your own land, a land of com and wine, a
            land of bread and vineyards, a land of olive-oil and honey, that you may live and not die. Never heed Hezekiah, when he
            persuades you that the Eternal will save you. <verse eID="2Kgs.18.32"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.18.33" osisID="2Kgs.18.33"/> Has any god of any nation ever yet saved his land from the hands of the king of
            Assyria? <verse eID="2Kgs.18.33"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.18.34" osisID="2Kgs.18.34"/> Where are the gods of Hamath and Arpad? Where are the gods of Sepharvaim, of Hena,
            of Ivvah? Where are the gods of Samaria? Have they saved Samaria from me? <verse eID="2Kgs.18.34"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.18.35" osisID="2Kgs.18.35"/> What gods, of all the gods of these lands, have saved these lands from me, that the
            Eternal should now save Jerusalem from me?</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.18.35"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.18.36" osisID="2Kgs.18.36"/> The people said nothing, they made no reply, for the king had ordered them to make no
            answer. <verse eID="2Kgs.18.36"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.18.37" osisID="2Kgs.18.37"/> Then Eliakim the son of Hilkiah, who was prefect of the palace, Shebna the
            secretary, and Joab the son of Asaph the chancellor, went, tearing their clothes, to Hezekiah, to report what the
            staff-commander had said. <verse eID="2Kgs.18.37"/>
       </p>
     <chapter eID="2Kgs.18"/>
     <chapter osisID="2Kgs.18" sID="2Kgs.18"/>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.18.12" osisID="2Kgs.18.12"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.18.12"/>
       </p>
       <chapter eID="2Kgs.18"/>
       <chapter osisID="2Kgs.18" sID="2Kgs.18"/>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.18.12" osisID="2Kgs.18.12"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.18.12"/>
       </p>
       <chapter eID="2Kgs.18"/>
       <chapter osisID="2Kgs.18" sID="2Kgs.18"/>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.18.12" osisID="2Kgs.18.12"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.18.12"/>
       </p>
       <chapter eID="2Kgs.18"/>
       <chapter osisID="2Kgs.18" sID="2Kgs.18"/>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.18.12" osisID="2Kgs.18.12"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.18.12"/>
       </p>
       <chapter eID="2Kgs.18"/>
     <chapter osisID="2Kgs.18" sID="2Kgs.18"/>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.18.12" osisID="2Kgs.18.12"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.18.12"/>
       </p>
     <chapter eID="2Kgs.18"/>
   </div>