   <div type="book" osisID="2Kgs">
     <chapter osisID="2Kgs.1" sID="2Kgs.1"/>
       <milestone type="pb" n="416"/>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.1.1" osisID="2Kgs.1.1"/> [[After Ahab's death Moab rebelled against Israel.]] <verse eID="2Kgs.1.1"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.1.2" osisID="2Kgs.1.2"/> Ahaziah, who had fallen through the lattice in his upper chamber
            in Samaria, was lying ill; so he sent messengers with orders to find out from Baal-zebub the god of Ekron
            whether he would recover from his illness. <verse eID="2Kgs.1.2"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.1.3" osisID="2Kgs.1.3"/> The angel of the Eternal told Elijah the Tishbite to go and
            meet the messengers of the king of Samaria and ask them, <q>Is it because there is no God in Israel that
            you are going to consult Baal-zebub the god of Ekron?</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.1.3"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.1.4" osisID="2Kgs.1.4"/> Elijah was to give them this answer from the Eternal for the
            king, <q>You shall never leave the bed to which you have taken; you must die.</q> Elijah then left them.
           <verse eID="2Kgs.1.4"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.1.5" osisID="2Kgs.1.5"/> And when the messengers returned to the king, he asked why they
            had come back. <verse eID="2Kgs.1.5"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.1.6" osisID="2Kgs.1.6"/> They told him that a man had come up to meet them and said,
            <q>Go back to the king who sent you and tell him this from the Eternal: <q>Is it because there is no God
            in Israel that you send to consult Baal-zebub the god of Ekron? For this you shall never leave the bed to
            which you have taken; you must die.</q></q> <verse eID="2Kgs.1.6"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.1.7" osisID="2Kgs.1.7"/> The king asked, <q>This man who came up to meet you and spoke
            to you, what was he like?</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.1.7"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.1.8" osisID="2Kgs.1.8"/> They said, <q>He wore a mantle of hair, with a waist-cloth of
            leather round his middle.</q> <q>It is Elijah the Tishbite,</q> said the king, <verse eID="2Kgs.1.8"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.1.9" osisID="2Kgs.1.9"/> and he despatched a captain with his fifty men to seize him.
            Elijah was sitting on the top of a hill; so the captain went up and said to him, <q>0 man of God, the
            king orders you to come down.</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.1.9"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.1.10" osisID="2Kgs.1.10"/> <q>If I am a man of God,</q> answered Elijah, <q>let fire fall
            from heaven and destroy you and your fifty men.</q> Down fell fire from heaven, destroying him and his fifty
            men. <verse eID="2Kgs.1.10"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.1.11" osisID="2Kgs.1.11"/> Once more the king despatched another captain with his fifty
            men. He went up and said, <q>O man of God, this is the king’s order: Come down at once.</q><verse eID="2Kgs.1.11"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.1.12" osisID="2Kgs.1.12"/> <q>If I am a man of God,</q> Elijah said to them, <q>let fire
            fall from heaven and destroy you and your fifty men.</q> Down fell God's fire from heaven, destroying him
            and his fifty men. <verse eID="2Kgs.1.12"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.1.13" osisID="2Kgs.1.13"/> Again the king sent a third captain with his fifty men. The
            third captain went up and fell on his knees before Elijah, beseeching him, <q>O man of God, pray spare my
            life and the lives of these fifty men, your servants. <verse eID="2Kgs.1.13"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.1.14" osisID="2Kgs.1.14"/> Fire fell from heaven, destroying the two former captains and
            their companies; now spare my life.</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.1.14"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.1.15" osisID="2Kgs.1.15"/> So the angel of the Eternal said to Elijah, <q>Go down along
            with him; have no fear of him.</q> He rose and went down along with him to the king, <verse eID="2Kgs.1.15"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.1.16" osisID="2Kgs.1.16"/> telling the king this message from the Eternal: <q>Since you
            sent messengers to consult Baal-zebub the god of Ekron, you shall never leave the bed to which you have
            taken; you must die.</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.1.16"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.1.17" osisID="2Kgs.1.17"/> And die he did, exactly as the Eternal had predicted by
            Elijah. <verse eID="2Kgs.1.17"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.1.18" osisID="2Kgs.1.18"/> The rest of the acts done by Ahaziah, are they not described
            in the book of the Annals of the Kings of Israel? <verse eID="2Kgs.1.18"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.1.17" osisID="2Kgs.1.17"/> Jehoram his brother began to reign instead of him, as he had
            no son (in the second year of Jehoram the son
            <milestone type="pb" n="417"/>
            of Jehoshaphat king of Judah).
           <verse eID="2Kgs.1.17"/>
       </p>
     <chapter eID="2Kgs.1"/>
     <chapter osisID="2Kgs.2" sID="2Kgs.2"/>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.2.1" osisID="2Kgs.2.1"/> Now when the Eternal was about to take up Elijah by a whirlwind
            into heaven, Elijah was leaving Gilgal along with Elisha; <verse eID="2Kgs.2.1"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.2.2" osisID="2Kgs.2.2"/> he said to Elisha, <q>Pray remain here, for the Eternal sends
            me as far as Bethel.</q> But Elisha answered, <q>As the Eternal lives and as you live, I will not leave
            you.</q> So down they went to Bethel. <verse eID="2Kgs.2.2"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.2.3" osisID="2Kgs.2.3"/> The guild of prophets at Bethel came out and asked Elisha,
           <q>Do you know that the Eternal is taking away your lord and master to­day?</q> <q>Yes,</q> he answered;
           <q>only hold your tongues.</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.2.3"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.2.4" osisID="2Kgs.2.4"/> Elijah said to him, <q>Pray remain here, Elisha, for the
            Eternal sends me to Jericho.</q> <q>As the Eternal lives, and as you live,</q> he said, <q>I will not
            leave you.</q>  So to Jericho they went.<verse eID="2Kgs.2.4"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.2.5" osisID="2Kgs.2.5"/> The guild of prophets at Jericho came out and asked Elisha,
            <q>Do you know that the Eternal is taking away your lord and master to-day?</q> <q>Yes,</q> he answered,
            <q>only hold your tongues.</q> Elijah said to him, <verse eID="2Kgs.2.5"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.2.6" osisID="2Kgs.2.6"/> <q>Pray remain here, for the Eternal sends me to the Jordan.</q>
            <q>As the Eternal lives and as you live,</q> he answered, <q>I will not leave you.</q> So the two of them went
            on. <verse eID="2Kgs.2.6"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.2.7" osisID="2Kgs.2.7"/> Fifty members of the guild went and stood opposite them at a
            distance, as the two of them were standing beside the Jordan; <verse eID="2Kgs.2.7"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.2.8" osisID="2Kgs.2.8"/> Elijah, rolling up his mantle, struck the water till it parted
            right and left, so that they could cross on dry ground. <verse eID="2Kgs.2.8"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.2.9" osisID="2Kgs.2.9"/> When they had crossed, Elijah said to Elisha, <q>Before I am taken
            from you, ask me for something.</q> Elisha answered, <q>Let me fall heir to your spirit.</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.2.9"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.2.10" osisID="2Kgs.2.10"/> <q>You have asked something hard,</q> said Elijah; <q>if you
            see me when I am being taken from you, it shall be yours, but not if you fail to see me.</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.2.10"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.2.11" osisID="2Kgs.2.11"/> Suddenly, as they walked and talked, a chariot of fire with
            horses of fire drove between them, and Elijah went up by a whirlwind into heaven. <verse eID="2Kgs.2.11"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.2.12" osisID="2Kgs.2.12"/> When Elisha saw this he cried, <q>My father, my father!
            worth chariots and horsemen to Israel!</q> Losing sight of him, Elisha seized his clothes and tore them
            in two. <verse eID="2Kgs.2.12"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.2.13" osisID="2Kgs.2.13"/> Then, lifting the mantle which had fallen from Elijah, he
            went back and stood on the bank of the Jordan; <verse eID="2Kgs.2.13"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.2.14" osisID="2Kgs.2.14"/> taking the mantle which had fallen from Elijah he struck the
            water, crying, <q>Where is the Eternal, the God of Elijah?</q> And, when he struck the water, it parted right
            and left, so that Elisha could cross. <verse eID="2Kgs.2.14"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.2.15" osisID="2Kgs.2.15"/> When the guild of prophets opposite saw him, they said, <q>The
            spirit of Elijah rests on Elisha!</q> They came forward to meet him and bowed before him to the ground. <verse eID="2Kgs.2.15"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.2.16" osisID="2Kgs.2.16"/> Then they said, <q>Your servants here have fifty stalwart
            men; pray let them go in search of your master, lest the spirit of the Eternal perhaps has caught him away and
            dropped him on some hill or in some valley.</q> Elisha refused. <verse eID="2Kgs.2.16"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.2.17" osisID="2Kgs.2.17"/> But, as they pressed him till he was ashamed, he agreed. So
            they sent fifty men, who searched for three days and failed to find him. <verse eID="2Kgs.2.17"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.2.18" osisID="2Kgs.2.18"/> When they came back to Elisha, who was still staying at
            Jericho, he said to them, <q>Did I not tell you not to go?</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.2.18"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.2.19" osisID="2Kgs.2.19"/> The townsmen said to Elisha, <q>The situation of this town is
            delightful, as my lord sees, but
            <milestone type="pb" n="418"/>
            the water is bad and it causes miscarriages.</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.2.19"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.2.20" osisID="2Kgs.2.20"/> <q>Bring me a new flask,</q> said Elisha, <q>and put in some
            salt.</q> They did so. <verse eID="2Kgs.2.20"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.2.21" osisID="2Kgs.2.21"/> Then he went to the source of their water-supply and,
            throwing salt in, he uttered this word from the Eternal, <q>I hereby heal these waters; never again
            shall they cause death or miscarriages.</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.2.21"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.2.22" osisID="2Kgs.2.22"/> To this day the waters remain healed, exactly as Elisha said.
           <verse eID="2Kgs.2.22"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.2.23" osisID="2Kgs.2.23"/> On his way to Bethel, as he was walking up the road, some
            small boys from the town mocked him, crying, <q>Walk up, baldhead! Walk up, baldhead!</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.2.23"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.2.24" osisID="2Kgs.2.24"/> When he looked round and saw them, he cursed them in the name
            of the Eternal; two she-bears came out of the wood and mangled forty-two of the boys. <verse eID="2Kgs.2.24"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.2.25" osisID="2Kgs.2.25"/> From Bethel he went on to mount Karmel, and then made his way
            back to Samaria. <verse eID="2Kgs.2.25"/>
       </p>
     <chapter eID="2Kgs.2"/>
     <chapter osisID="2Kgs.3" sID="2Kgs.3"/>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.1" osisID="2Kgs.3.1"/> In the eighteenth year of Jehoshaphat king of Judah, Jehoram
            the son of Ahab began to reign over Israel in Samaria, and he reigned for twelve years. <verse eID="2Kgs.3.1"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/> He did what was evil in the sight of the Eternal, though not
            like his father and his mother, for he removed the obelisk of Baal which his father had made. <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.3" osisID="2Kgs.3.3"/> Still, he adhered to the sin by which Jeroboam the son of
            Nebat had led Israel into sin; he never broke away from that. <verse eID="2Kgs.3.3"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.4" osisID="2Kgs.3.4"/> Mesha king of Moab was a sheep-master; he used to pay tribute
            to the king of Israel, the fleeces of a hundred thousand sheep and a hundred thousand rams. <verse eID="2Kgs.3.4"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.5" osisID="2Kgs.3.5"/> But after Ahab died, the king of Moab rebelled against the king
            of Israel. <verse eID="2Kgs.3.5"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.6" osisID="2Kgs.3.6"/> Then king Jehoram left Samaria to muster all Israel; <verse eID="2Kgs.3.6"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.7" osisID="2Kgs.3.7"/> he also sent this message to Jehoshaphat the king of Judah:
            <q>The king of Moab has rebelled against me; will you join me in making war upon Moab?</q> <q>I
            will,</q> he answered; <q>I am one with you, my people are one with your people, my horses with your
            horses.</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.3.7"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.8" osisID="2Kgs.3.8"/> He added, <q>And how are we to march?</q> <q>By the desert of
            Edom,</q> said Jehoram. <verse eID="2Kgs.3.8"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.9" osisID="2Kgs.3.9"/> So the king of Israel started, with the king of Judah and the
            king of Edom, marching for seven days along a roundabout route, till the army and its train of beasts
            had no water. <verse eID="2Kgs.3.9"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.10" osisID="2Kgs.3.10"/> <q>Alas!</q> said the king of Israel, <q>here has the Eternal
           gathered three kings, only to put them into the hands of Moab!</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.3.10"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.11" osisID="2Kgs.3.11"/> Jehoshaphat said, <q>Is there no prophet of the Eternal here,
            by whom we may consult the Eternal?</q> An officer of the king of Israel replied, <q>Elisha the son of
            Shaphat is here, who used to be servant to Elijah.</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.3.11"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.12" osisID="2Kgs.3.12"/> Said Jehoshaphat, <q>The word of the Eternal is with him.</q>
            So the king of Israel and Jehoshaphat and the king of Edom went to him. <verse eID="2Kgs.3.12"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.13" osisID="2Kgs.3.13"/> Elisha said to the king of Israel, <q>What have you to do
            with me? Away to the prophets of your father and the prophets of your mother!</q> The king of Israel
            protested, <q>No, it is the Eternal who has gathered us three kings, only to put us into the hands of
            Moab.</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.3.13"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.14" osisID="2Kgs.3.14"/> <q>As surely as the Eternal lives, whom I serve,</q> said
            Elisha, <q>were it not that I have some respect for Jehoshaphat the king of Judah here, I would not look
            your way, I would never notice you. <verse eID="2Kgs.3.14"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.15" osisID="2Kgs.3.15"/> However, bring me a minstrel</q> (for, whenever a minstrel
            played, he would fall into a trance from the Eternal). <verse eID="2Kgs.3.15"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.16" osisID="2Kgs.3.16"/> Then he uttered this word from the Eternal: <q>I will
            <milestone type="pb" n="419"/>
            make this dry ravine pool after pool of water. <verse eID="2Kgs.3.16"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.17" osisID="2Kgs.3.17"/> For, the Eternal declares, though you see neither wind nor
            rain, this dry ravine shall be so full of water that you and your armies and your beasts shall all
            drink. <verse eID="2Kgs.3.17"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.18" osisID="2Kgs.3.18"/> So little is this to the Eternal, that he will also put the
            Moabites into your power; <verse eID="2Kgs.3.18"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.19" osisID="2Kgs.3.19"/> you shall storm every fortified town and fell every
            fruitful tree and stop every fountain and spoil every good field with stones.</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.3.19"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.20" osisID="2Kgs.3.20"/> Next morning, about the hour for the morning sacrifice,
            water did come from the direction of Edom, till the country was full of water. <verse eID="2Kgs.3.20"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.21" osisID="2Kgs.3.21"/> Now, on hearing that the kings had marched to attack them,
            all the Moabites had been mustered, all at and above the age of bearing arms; they were posted on the
            frontier. <verse eID="2Kgs.3.21"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.22" osisID="2Kgs.3.22"/> When they rose in the morning, the sun was shining on the
            water, and, seeing the water in front of them as red as blood, <verse eID="2Kgs.3.22"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.23" osisID="2Kgs.3.23"/> the Moabites said, <q>This is blood! The kings must have been
            fighting among themselves, they have killed one another! Now then, Moab to the spoil!</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.3.23"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.24" osisID="2Kgs.3.24"/> But when they reached the camp of Israel, the Israelites
            started an attack, till the Moabites fled before them; they pressed forward, cutting down the Moabites
            as they went; <verse eID="2Kgs.3.24"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.25" osisID="2Kgs.3.25"/> they demolished the towns, every man threw a stone on every
            good field till it was covered, they stopped every fountain, and they felled every fruitful tree,
            harrying Moab till no Moabites wrere left except in Kirhareseth, which the shngers surrounded and laid
            low. <verse eID="2Kgs.3.25"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.26" osisID="2Kgs.3.26"/> The king of Moab, when he saw that the battle was too hot for
            him, took seven hundred swordsmen to cut his way through to the king of Edom. This failed. <verse eID="2Kgs.3.26"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.27" osisID="2Kgs.3.27"/> So he took his eldest son, the heir to the throne, and
            sacrificed him on the wall. It brought such a storm of indignation against Israel, that the Israelites
            had to leave him alone and return home. <verse eID="2Kgs.3.27"/>
       </p>
     <chapter eID="2Kgs.3"/>
     <chapter osisID="2Kgs.3" sID="2Kgs.3"/>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
     <chapter eID="2Kgs.3"/>
     <chapter osisID="2Kgs.3" sID="2Kgs.3"/>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
     <chapter eID="2Kgs.3"/>
     <chapter osisID="2Kgs.3" sID="2Kgs.3"/>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
     <chapter eID="2Kgs.3"/>
     <chapter osisID="2Kgs.3" sID="2Kgs.3"/>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
     <chapter eID="2Kgs.3"/>
     <chapter osisID="2Kgs.3" sID="2Kgs.3"/>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
     <chapter eID="2Kgs.3"/>
     <chapter osisID="2Kgs.3" sID="2Kgs.3"/>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
     <chapter eID="2Kgs.3"/>
     <chapter osisID="2Kgs.3" sID="2Kgs.3"/>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
     <chapter eID="2Kgs.3"/>
     <chapter osisID="2Kgs.3" sID="2Kgs.3"/>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
     <chapter eID="2Kgs.3"/>
     <chapter osisID="2Kgs.3" sID="2Kgs.3"/>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
     <chapter eID="2Kgs.3"/>
     <chapter osisID="2Kgs.3" sID="2Kgs.3"/>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
     <chapter eID="2Kgs.3"/>
     <chapter osisID="2Kgs.3" sID="2Kgs.3"/>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
     <chapter eID="2Kgs.3"/>
     <chapter osisID="2Kgs.3" sID="2Kgs.3"/>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
     <chapter eID="2Kgs.3"/>
     <chapter osisID="2Kgs.3" sID="2Kgs.3"/>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
     <chapter eID="2Kgs.3"/>
     <chapter osisID="2Kgs.3" sID="2Kgs.3"/>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
     <chapter eID="2Kgs.3"/>
     <chapter osisID="2Kgs.3" sID="2Kgs.3"/>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
     <chapter eID="2Kgs.3"/>
   </div>