   <div type="book" osisID="2Kgs">
     <chapter osisID="2Kgs.1" sID="2Kgs.1"/>
       <milestone type="pb" n="416"/>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.1.1" osisID="2Kgs.1.1"/> [[After Ahab's death Moab rebelled against Israel.]] <verse eID="2Kgs.1.1"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.1.2" osisID="2Kgs.1.2"/> Ahaziah, who had fallen through the lattice in his upper chamber
            in Samaria, was lying ill; so he sent messengers with orders to find out from Baal-zebub the god of Ekron
            whether he would recover from his illness. <verse eID="2Kgs.1.2"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.1.3" osisID="2Kgs.1.3"/> The angel of the Eternal told Elijah the Tishbite to go and
            meet the messengers of the king of Samaria and ask them, <q>Is it because there is no God in Israel that
            you are going to consult Baal-zebub the god of Ekron?</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.1.3"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.1.4" osisID="2Kgs.1.4"/> Elijah was to give them this answer from the Eternal for the
            king, <q>You shall never leave the bed to which you have taken; you must die.</q> Elijah then left them.
           <verse eID="2Kgs.1.4"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.1.5" osisID="2Kgs.1.5"/> And when the messengers returned to the king, he asked why they
            had come back. <verse eID="2Kgs.1.5"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.1.6" osisID="2Kgs.1.6"/> They told him that a man had come up to meet them and said,
            <q>Go back to the king who sent you and tell him this from the Eternal: <q>Is it because there is no God
            in Israel that you send to consult Baal-zebub the god of Ekron? For this you shall never leave the bed to
            which you have taken; you must die.</q></q> <verse eID="2Kgs.1.6"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.1.7" osisID="2Kgs.1.7"/> The king asked, <q>This man who came up to meet you and spoke
            to you, what was he like?</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.1.7"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.1.8" osisID="2Kgs.1.8"/> They said, <q>He wore a mantle of hair, with a waist-cloth of
            leather round his middle.</q> <q>It is Elijah the Tishbite,</q> said the king, <verse eID="2Kgs.1.8"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.1.9" osisID="2Kgs.1.9"/> and he despatched a captain with his fifty men to seize him.
            Elijah was sitting on the top of a hill; so the captain went up and said to him, <q>0 man of God, the
            king orders you to come down.</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.1.9"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.1.10" osisID="2Kgs.1.10"/> <q>If I am a man of God,</q> answered Elijah, <q>let fire fall
            from heaven and destroy you and your fifty men.</q> Down fell fire from heaven, destroying him and his fifty
            men. <verse eID="2Kgs.1.10"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.1.11" osisID="2Kgs.1.11"/> Once more the king despatched another captain with his fifty
            men. He went up and said, <q>O man of God, this is the king’s order: Come down at once.</q><verse eID="2Kgs.1.11"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.1.12" osisID="2Kgs.1.12"/> <q>If I am a man of God,</q> Elijah said to them, <q>let fire
            fall from heaven and destroy you and your fifty men.</q> Down fell God's fire from heaven, destroying him
            and his fifty men. <verse eID="2Kgs.1.12"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.1.13" osisID="2Kgs.1.13"/> Again the king sent a third captain with his fifty men. The
            third captain went up and fell on his knees before Elijah, beseeching him, <q>O man of God, pray spare my
            life and the lives of these fifty men, your servants. <verse eID="2Kgs.1.13"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.1.14" osisID="2Kgs.1.14"/> Fire fell from heaven, destroying the two former captains and
            their companies; now spare my life.</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.1.14"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.1.15" osisID="2Kgs.1.15"/> So the angel of the Eternal said to Elijah, <q>Go down along
            with him; have no fear of him.</q> He rose and went down along with him to the king, <verse eID="2Kgs.1.15"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.1.16" osisID="2Kgs.1.16"/> telling the king this message from the Eternal: <q>Since you
            sent messengers to consult Baal-zebub the god of Ekron, you shall never leave the bed to which you have
            taken; you must die.</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.1.16"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.1.17" osisID="2Kgs.1.17"/> And die he did, exactly as the Eternal had predicted by
            Elijah. <verse eID="2Kgs.1.17"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.1.18" osisID="2Kgs.1.18"/> The rest of the acts done by Ahaziah, are they not described
            in the book of the Annals of the Kings of Israel? <verse eID="2Kgs.1.18"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.1.17" osisID="2Kgs.1.17"/> Jehoram his brother began to reign instead of him, as he had
            no son (in the second year of Jehoram the son
            <milestone type="pb" n="417"/>
            of Jehoshaphat king of Judah).
           <verse eID="2Kgs.1.17"/>
       </p>
     <chapter eID="2Kgs.1"/>
     <chapter osisID="2Kgs.2" sID="2Kgs.2"/>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.2.1" osisID="2Kgs.2.1"/> Now when the Eternal was about to take up Elijah by a whirlwind
            into heaven, Elijah was leaving Gilgal along with Elisha; <verse eID="2Kgs.2.1"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.2.2" osisID="2Kgs.2.2"/> he said to Elisha, <q>Pray remain here, for the Eternal sends
            me as far as Bethel.</q> But Elisha answered, <q>As the Eternal lives and as you live, I will not leave
            you.</q> So down they went to Bethel. <verse eID="2Kgs.2.2"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.2.3" osisID="2Kgs.2.3"/> The guild of prophets at Bethel came out and asked Elisha,
           <q>Do you know that the Eternal is taking away your lord and master to­day?</q> <q>Yes,</q> he answered;
           <q>only hold your tongues.</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.2.3"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.2.4" osisID="2Kgs.2.4"/> Elijah said to him, <q>Pray remain here, Elisha, for the
            Eternal sends me to Jericho.</q> <q>As the Eternal lives, and as you live,</q> he said, <q>I will not
            leave you.</q>  So to Jericho they went.<verse eID="2Kgs.2.4"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.2.5" osisID="2Kgs.2.5"/> The guild of prophets at Jericho came out and asked Elisha,
            <q>Do you know that the Eternal is taking away your lord and master to-day?</q> <q>Yes,</q> he answered,
            <q>only hold your tongues.</q> Elijah said to him, <verse eID="2Kgs.2.5"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.2.6" osisID="2Kgs.2.6"/> <q>Pray remain here, for the Eternal sends me to the Jordan.</q>
            <q>As the Eternal lives and as you live,</q> he answered, <q>I will not leave you.</q> So the two of them went
            on. <verse eID="2Kgs.2.6"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.2.7" osisID="2Kgs.2.7"/> Fifty members of the guild went and stood opposite them at a
            distance, as the two of them were standing beside the Jordan; <verse eID="2Kgs.2.7"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.2.8" osisID="2Kgs.2.8"/> Elijah, rolling up his mantle, struck the water till it parted
            right and left, so that they could cross on dry ground. <verse eID="2Kgs.2.8"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.2.9" osisID="2Kgs.2.9"/> When they had crossed, Elijah said to Elisha, <q>Before I am taken
            from you, ask me for something.</q> Elisha answered, <q>Let me fall heir to your spirit.</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.2.9"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.2.10" osisID="2Kgs.2.10"/> <q>You have asked something hard,</q> said Elijah; <q>if you
            see me when I am being taken from you, it shall be yours, but not if you fail to see me.</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.2.10"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.2.11" osisID="2Kgs.2.11"/> Suddenly, as they walked and talked, a chariot of fire with
            horses of fire drove between them, and Elijah went up by a whirlwind into heaven. <verse eID="2Kgs.2.11"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.2.12" osisID="2Kgs.2.12"/> When Elisha saw this he cried, <q>My father, my father!
            worth chariots and horsemen to Israel!</q> Losing sight of him, Elisha seized his clothes and tore them
            in two. <verse eID="2Kgs.2.12"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.2.13" osisID="2Kgs.2.13"/> Then, lifting the mantle which had fallen from Elijah, he
            went back and stood on the bank of the Jordan; <verse eID="2Kgs.2.13"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.2.14" osisID="2Kgs.2.14"/> taking the mantle which had fallen from Elijah he struck the
            water, crying, <q>Where is the Eternal, the God of Elijah?</q> And, when he struck the water, it parted right
            and left, so that Elisha could cross. <verse eID="2Kgs.2.14"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.2.15" osisID="2Kgs.2.15"/> When the guild of prophets opposite saw him, they said, <q>The
            spirit of Elijah rests on Elisha!</q> They came forward to meet him and bowed before him to the ground. <verse eID="2Kgs.2.15"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.2.16" osisID="2Kgs.2.16"/> Then they said, <q>Your servants here have fifty stalwart
            men; pray let them go in search of your master, lest the spirit of the Eternal perhaps has caught him away and
            dropped him on some hill or in some valley.</q> Elisha refused. <verse eID="2Kgs.2.16"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.2.17" osisID="2Kgs.2.17"/> But, as they pressed him till he was ashamed, he agreed. So
            they sent fifty men, who searched for three days and failed to find him. <verse eID="2Kgs.2.17"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.2.18" osisID="2Kgs.2.18"/> When they came back to Elisha, who was still staying at
            Jericho, he said to them, <q>Did I not tell you not to go?</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.2.18"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.2.19" osisID="2Kgs.2.19"/> The townsmen said to Elisha, <q>The situation of this town is
            delightful, as my lord sees, but
            <milestone type="pb" n="418"/>
            the water is bad and it causes miscarriages.</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.2.19"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.2.20" osisID="2Kgs.2.20"/> <q>Bring me a new flask,</q> said Elisha, <q>and put in some
            salt.</q> They did so. <verse eID="2Kgs.2.20"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.2.21" osisID="2Kgs.2.21"/> Then he went to the source of their water-supply and,
            throwing salt in, he uttered this word from the Eternal, <q>I hereby heal these waters; never again
            shall they cause death or miscarriages.</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.2.21"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.2.22" osisID="2Kgs.2.22"/> To this day the waters remain healed, exactly as Elisha said.
           <verse eID="2Kgs.2.22"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.2.23" osisID="2Kgs.2.23"/> On his way to Bethel, as he was walking up the road, some
            small boys from the town mocked him, crying, <q>Walk up, baldhead! Walk up, baldhead!</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.2.23"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.2.24" osisID="2Kgs.2.24"/> When he looked round and saw them, he cursed them in the name
            of the Eternal; two she-bears came out of the wood and mangled forty-two of the boys. <verse eID="2Kgs.2.24"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.2.25" osisID="2Kgs.2.25"/> From Bethel he went on to mount Karmel, and then made his way
            back to Samaria. <verse eID="2Kgs.2.25"/>
       </p>
     <chapter eID="2Kgs.2"/>
     <chapter osisID="2Kgs.3" sID="2Kgs.3"/>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.1" osisID="2Kgs.3.1"/> In the eighteenth year of Jehoshaphat king of Judah, Jehoram
            the son of Ahab began to reign over Israel in Samaria, and he reigned for twelve years. <verse eID="2Kgs.3.1"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/> He did what was evil in the sight of the Eternal, though not
            like his father and his mother, for he removed the obelisk of Baal which his father had made. <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.3" osisID="2Kgs.3.3"/> Still, he adhered to the sin by which Jeroboam the son of
            Nebat had led Israel into sin; he never broke away from that. <verse eID="2Kgs.3.3"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.4" osisID="2Kgs.3.4"/> Mesha king of Moab was a sheep-master; he used to pay tribute
            to the king of Israel, the fleeces of a hundred thousand sheep and a hundred thousand rams. <verse eID="2Kgs.3.4"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.5" osisID="2Kgs.3.5"/> But after Ahab died, the king of Moab rebelled against the king
            of Israel. <verse eID="2Kgs.3.5"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.6" osisID="2Kgs.3.6"/> Then king Jehoram left Samaria to muster all Israel; <verse eID="2Kgs.3.6"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.7" osisID="2Kgs.3.7"/> he also sent this message to Jehoshaphat the king of Judah:
            <q>The king of Moab has rebelled against me; will you join me in making war upon Moab?</q> <q>I
            will,</q> he answered; <q>I am one with you, my people are one with your people, my horses with your
            horses.</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.3.7"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.8" osisID="2Kgs.3.8"/> He added, <q>And how are we to march?</q> <q>By the desert of
            Edom,</q> said Jehoram. <verse eID="2Kgs.3.8"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.9" osisID="2Kgs.3.9"/> So the king of Israel started, with the king of Judah and the
            king of Edom, marching for seven days along a roundabout route, till the army and its train of beasts
            had no water. <verse eID="2Kgs.3.9"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.10" osisID="2Kgs.3.10"/> <q>Alas!</q> said the king of Israel, <q>here has the Eternal
           gathered three kings, only to put them into the hands of Moab!</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.3.10"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.11" osisID="2Kgs.3.11"/> Jehoshaphat said, <q>Is there no prophet of the Eternal here,
            by whom we may consult the Eternal?</q> An officer of the king of Israel replied, <q>Elisha the son of
            Shaphat is here, who used to be servant to Elijah.</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.3.11"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.12" osisID="2Kgs.3.12"/> Said Jehoshaphat, <q>The word of the Eternal is with him.</q>
            So the king of Israel and Jehoshaphat and the king of Edom went to him. <verse eID="2Kgs.3.12"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.13" osisID="2Kgs.3.13"/> Elisha said to the king of Israel, <q>What have you to do
            with me? Away to the prophets of your father and the prophets of your mother!</q> The king of Israel
            protested, <q>No, it is the Eternal who has gathered us three kings, only to put us into the hands of
            Moab.</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.3.13"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.14" osisID="2Kgs.3.14"/> <q>As surely as the Eternal lives, whom I serve,</q> said
            Elisha, <q>were it not that I have some respect for Jehoshaphat the king of Judah here, I would not look
            your way, I would never notice you. <verse eID="2Kgs.3.14"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.15" osisID="2Kgs.3.15"/> However, bring me a minstrel</q> (for, whenever a minstrel
            played, he would fall into a trance from the Eternal). <verse eID="2Kgs.3.15"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.16" osisID="2Kgs.3.16"/> Then he uttered this word from the Eternal: <q>I will
            <milestone type="pb" n="419"/>
            make this dry ravine pool after pool of water. <verse eID="2Kgs.3.16"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.17" osisID="2Kgs.3.17"/> For, the Eternal declares, though you see neither wind nor
            rain, this dry ravine shall be so full of water that you and your armies and your beasts shall all
            drink. <verse eID="2Kgs.3.17"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.18" osisID="2Kgs.3.18"/> So little is this to the Eternal, that he will also put the
            Moabites into your power; <verse eID="2Kgs.3.18"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.19" osisID="2Kgs.3.19"/> you shall storm every fortified town and fell every
            fruitful tree and stop every fountain and spoil every good field with stones.</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.3.19"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.20" osisID="2Kgs.3.20"/> Next morning, about the hour for the morning sacrifice,
            water did come from the direction of Edom, till the country was full of water. <verse eID="2Kgs.3.20"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.21" osisID="2Kgs.3.21"/> Now, on hearing that the kings had marched to attack them,
            all the Moabites had been mustered, all at and above the age of bearing arms; they were posted on the
            frontier. <verse eID="2Kgs.3.21"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.22" osisID="2Kgs.3.22"/> When they rose in the morning, the sun was shining on the
            water, and, seeing the water in front of them as red as blood, <verse eID="2Kgs.3.22"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.23" osisID="2Kgs.3.23"/> the Moabites said, <q>This is blood! The kings must have been
            fighting among themselves, they have killed one another! Now then, Moab to the spoil!</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.3.23"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.24" osisID="2Kgs.3.24"/> But when they reached the camp of Israel, the Israelites
            started an attack, till the Moabites fled before them; they pressed forward, cutting down the Moabites
            as they went; <verse eID="2Kgs.3.24"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.25" osisID="2Kgs.3.25"/> they demolished the towns, every man threw a stone on every
            good field till it was covered, they stopped every fountain, and they felled every fruitful tree,
            harrying Moab till no Moabites wrere left except in Kirhareseth, which the shngers surrounded and laid
            low. <verse eID="2Kgs.3.25"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.26" osisID="2Kgs.3.26"/> The king of Moab, when he saw that the battle was too hot for
            him, took seven hundred swordsmen to cut his way through to the king of Edom. This failed. <verse eID="2Kgs.3.26"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.27" osisID="2Kgs.3.27"/> So he took his eldest son, the heir to the throne, and
            sacrificed him on the wall. It brought such a storm of indignation against Israel, that the Israelites
            had to leave him alone and return home. <verse eID="2Kgs.3.27"/>
       </p>
     <chapter eID="2Kgs.3"/>
     <chapter osisID="2Kgs.4" sID="2Kgs.4"/>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.4.1" osisID="2Kgs.4.1"/> The wife of a member of the prophets' guild once made an
            appeal to Elisha. <q>Your serv­ant my husband is dead,</q> she cried, <q>and you know that your servant
           reverenced the Eternal. Now a creditor has come to seize my two children and make them his slaves.</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.4.1"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.4.2" osisID="2Kgs.4.2"/> <q>What can I do for you?</q> said Elisha. <q>Tell me what you
            have in the house.</q> She replied, <q>Your humble servant has nothing in the house at all, except a
            flask of olive-oil.</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.4.2"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.4.3" osisID="2Kgs.4.3"/> <q>Then borrow vessels here and there,</q> he said, <q>from all
            your neighbours, empty vessels, plenty of them; <verse eID="2Kgs.4.3"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.4.4" osisID="2Kgs.4.4"/> shut yourself into the house, you and your sons; pour the oil
            into all these vessels; and, whenever one is full, set it aside.</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.4.4"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.4.5" osisID="2Kgs.4.5"/> She went away and did so, shutting herself and her sons inside the
            house. They brought the vessels, while she poured out the oil. <verse eID="2Kgs.4.5"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.4.6" osisID="2Kgs.4.6"/> When the vessels had been filled, she said to her boy, <q>Bring
            another.</q> He said to her, <q>There is not one more.</q> Whereupon the oil stopped flowing. <verse eID="2Kgs.4.6"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.4.7" osisID="2Kgs.4.7"/> When she went and told the man of God, he bade her sell some of
            the oil to pay her debts, and then live, herself and her sons, off the rest. <verse eID="2Kgs.4.7"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.4.8" osisID="2Kgs.4.8"/> One day Elisha went over to Shunem, and a rich lady who lived
            there made him take some food. After this he used to turn in for a meal whenever he was passing. <verse eID="2Kgs.4.8"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.4.9" osisID="2Kgs.4.9"/> So she said to her husband,
            <milestone type="pb" n="420"/>
            <q>This is a holy man of God, I see, who is constantly passing. <verse eID="2Kgs.4.9"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.4.10" osisID="2Kgs.4.10"/> Come and let us build a small guest-chamber for him, with a
            bed and a table and a seat and a lamp, so that whenever he comes to us he can turn in.</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.4.10"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.4.11" osisID="2Kgs.4.11"/> One day he came, and he did turn in to the chamber and rested
            there. <verse eID="2Kgs.4.11"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.4.12" osisID="2Kgs.4.12"/> <q>Call this Shunammite,</q> he said to his servant Gehazi.
            And when she stood before him, at his bidding, <verse eID="2Kgs.4.12"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.4.13" osisID="2Kgs.4.13"/> he told Gehazi to ask her, <q>What is to be done for you,
            after all this thought and trouble you have taken for us? Shall we say a word for you to the king or to
            the commander-in-chief?</q> <q>No,</q> she answered, <q>I am quite safe, among my own kinsmen.</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.4.13"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.4.14" osisID="2Kgs.4.14"/> So he asked Gehazi what was to be done for her, and Gehazi
            replied, <q>She has not a son, and her husband is an old man.</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.4.14"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.4.15" osisID="2Kgs.4.15"/> <q>Call her back,</q> said Elisha. And as she stood at the
            door, in reply to his summons, <verse eID="2Kgs.4.15"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.4.16" osisID="2Kgs.4.16"/> he said, <q>This time next year you will be embracing a
            son.</q> <q>No, no, my lord,</q> she answered, <q>you are a man of God, do not deceive your humble
            servant!</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.4.16"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.4.17" osisID="2Kgs.4.17"/> But the woman did conceive, and next year, when the time came
            round, she bore a son, as Elisha had told her. <verse eID="2Kgs.4.17"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.4.18" osisID="2Kgs.4.18"/> When the boy grew up, he went out one day to his father among
            the reapers. <verse eID="2Kgs.4.18"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.4.19" osisID="2Kgs.4.19"/> He called to his father, <q>Oh, my head! my head!</q> The
            father told his servant to carry the boy to his mother, <verse eID="2Kgs.4.19"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.4.20" osisID="2Kgs.4.20"/> and when he was brought to his mother he sat on her lap till
            noon; then he died. <verse eID="2Kgs.4.20"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.4.21" osisID="2Kgs.4.21"/> She carried him up and laid him on the bed of the man of God,
            closed the door, <verse eID="2Kgs.4.21"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.4.22" osisID="2Kgs.4.22"/> and went away to her husband, saying, <q>Pray let me have one
            of the servants and one of the asses, that I may hurry to the man of God and then get back again.</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.4.22"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.4.23" osisID="2Kgs.4.23"/> <q>Why go to him today?</q> he asked; <q>it is not the
            new-moon festival or the sabbath.</q> <q>Never mind,</q> she said; <verse eID="2Kgs.4.23"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.4.24" osisID="2Kgs.4.24"/> and saddling an ass she told her servant, <q>Drive ahead,
            never check the pace for me till I tell you.</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.4.24"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.4.25" osisID="2Kgs.4.25"/> So on she went to the man of God at mount Karmel.
       </p>
       <p>
            When the man of God spied her at a distance, he said to his servant Gehazi, <q>Look, there is the
            Shunammite!
           <verse eID="2Kgs.4.25"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.4.26" osisID="2Kgs.4.26"/> Now run to meet her and ask her if she is well, if her
            husband is well, and if the child is well.</q> She answered, <q>Yes,</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.4.26"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.4.27" osisID="2Kgs.4.27"/> and went on to the man of God upon the hill, grasping his
            feet. Gehazi went up to push her away, but the man of God said, <q>Let her alone; she has a sore heart,
            and the Eternal has not told me, he has hidden it from me.</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.4.27"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.4.28" osisID="2Kgs.4.28"/> Then she cried, <q>Did I ask my lord for a son? Did I not
            say, <q>Do not deceive me</q>?</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.4.28"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.4.29" osisID="2Kgs.4.29"/> So he told Gehazi, <q>Gird up your loins, take my staff in
            your hand, and be off; if you meet anyone, do not stop to salute him, and if anyone salutes you, do not
            stop to reply; lay my staff on the face of the child.</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.4.29"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.4.30" osisID="2Kgs.4.30"/> The mother said to Elisha, <q>As surely as the Eternal lives
            and you live, I will not go home without you.</q> So he rose and went with her. <verse eID="2Kgs.4.30"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.4.31" osisID="2Kgs.4.31"/> Gehazi had gone in front of them and laid the staff on the
            face of the child; but, as there was not a sound or sign of life, he came back to tell Elisha that the
            child had not wakened. <verse eID="2Kgs.4.31"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.4.32" osisID="2Kgs.4.32"/> When Elisha entered the house, there was the child lying dead
            upon his bed! <verse eID="2Kgs.4.32"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.4.33" osisID="2Kgs.4.33"/> He went in and shut the door upon the two of
            <milestone type="pb" n="421"/>
            them, praying to the Eternal. <verse eID="2Kgs.4.33"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.4.34" osisID="2Kgs.4.34"/> Then he stretched himself over the child, putting his mouth
            on the child's mouth, his eyes on the child's eyes, and his hands on the child's hands, till, as he
            crouched over the child, its flesh grew warm. <verse eID="2Kgs.4.34"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.4.35" osisID="2Kgs.4.35"/> Rising up, he walked to and fro, and then went and stretched
            himself seven times over the child, till it opened its eyes. <verse eID="2Kgs.4.35"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.4.36" osisID="2Kgs.4.36"/> Calling Gehazi, he ordered him to summon the Shunammite. When
            she came in, at his bidding, he said, <q>Lift your son.</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.4.36"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.4.37" osisID="2Kgs.4.37"/> She fell at his feet, bowing herself to the ground; then
            lifting her son she went away. <verse eID="2Kgs.4.37"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.4.38" osisID="2Kgs.4.38"/> Elisha once came to Gilgal when there was a famine in the
            land. As the guild of prophets was sitting in front of him, he told his servant to put the large pot on
            the fire and boil some pottage for the prophets. <verse eID="2Kgs.4.38"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.4.39" osisID="2Kgs.4.39"/> One man went to gather herbs in the field, and finding a wild
            vine he gathered a lapful of wild gourds, which he cut up for the pot of pottage, not knowing what they
            were. <verse eID="2Kgs.4.39"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.4.40" osisID="2Kgs.4.40"/> The pottage was then poured out for the men. But as they were
            eating they cried out, <q>0 man of God, there is death in the pot!</q> They could not eat the pottage. <verse eID="2Kgs.4.40"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.4.41" osisID="2Kgs.4.41"/> So he said, <q>Bring some meal.</q> This he threw into the
            pot, saying, <q>Now pour out for the men to eat.</q> And now there was nothing wrong with the pot. <verse eID="2Kgs.4.41"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.4.42" osisID="2Kgs.4.42"/> A man once came from Baalshalisha, bringing the man of God
            some first-fruits as food, twenty barley loaves and fresh vegetables in a basket. Elisha said, <q>Give
            the folk something to eat.</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.4.42"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.4.43" osisID="2Kgs.4.43"/> <q>What,</q> said his servant, <q>am I to set this before a
            hundred men?</q> <q>Give the folk something to eat,</q> said Elisha, <q>for the Eternal declares that
            they shall eat and leave some over.</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.4.43"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.4.44" osisID="2Kgs.4.44"/> So he did set it before them, and, as the Eternal had
            predicted, they ate and some was left over. <verse eID="2Kgs.4.44"/>
       </p>
     <chapter eID="2Kgs.4"/>
     <chapter osisID="2Kgs.5" sID="2Kgs.5"/>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.5.1" osisID="2Kgs.5.1"/> Naaman, who commanded cf the army of the king of Aram, was
            highly regarded by his lord and famous, since the Eternal had used him to make Aram victorious; only, he was a
            leper. <verse eID="2Kgs.5.1"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.5.2" osisID="2Kgs.5.2"/> Now on one of their raids the Aramaeans had carried off a
            little girl as a prisoner from the land of Israel, who waited on Naaman's wife. <verse eID="2Kgs.5.2"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.5.3" osisID="2Kgs.5.3"/> She said to her mistress, <q>Would that my lord saw the
            prophet who lives at Samaria! He would relieve my lord of his leprosy.</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.5.3"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.5.4" osisID="2Kgs.5.4"/> Someone told his lord what the Israelite girl had said. <verse eID="2Kgs.5.4"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.5.5" osisID="2Kgs.5.5"/> Whereupon the king of Aram said, <q>Come, I will send a
            letter to the king of Israel.</q>
       </p>
       <p>
            So Naaman started off, taking over four thousand pounds in silver and over twelve thousand pounds in gold,
            with ten festal robes: <verse eID="2Kgs.5.5"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.5.6" osisID="2Kgs.5.6"/> he brought the king of Israel the letter, which ran: <q>And
           now, with this letter, I send you my servant Naaman, that you may get him relief from his leprosy.</q>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.5.6"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.5.7" osisID="2Kgs.5.7"/> When the king of Israel read the letter he tore his clothes,
           crying, <q>Am I a god, able to kill and to make men live, that this man sends to me to get a man relief
           from leprosy? Just think; see how he is trying to pick a quarrel with me!</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.5.7"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.5.8" osisID="2Kgs.5.8"/> When Elisha the man of God heard about the king of Israel
            tearing his clothes in despair, he sent this message to the king of Israel:	<q>Why tear your clothes? Let the
            man come to me now, and he shall find there
            <milestone type="pb" n="422"/>
            is a prophet in Israel.</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.5.8"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.5.9" osisID="2Kgs.5.9"/> So Naaman drove up with his horses and his chariots and stopped
            at the door of Elisha's house. <verse eID="2Kgs.5.9"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.5.10" osisID="2Kgs.5.10"/> Elisha sent out word to him, <q>Go and wash seven times in
            the Jordan, and your body shall once more be well and clean.</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.5.10"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.5.11" osisID="2Kgs.5.11"/> Naaman went off in a rage, muttering, <q>I expected he would
            come outside to me and invoke the Eternal his God, waving his hand over the place and relieving the leper.
           <verse eID="2Kgs.5.11"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.5.12" osisID="2Kgs.5.12"/> Surely Amana and Pharpar, the rivers of Damascus, are better than
            any water in Israel! Could I not wash in them and be clean?</q> So he drove away in a fit of anger. <verse eID="2Kgs.5.12"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.5.13" osisID="2Kgs.5.13"/> But his servants went up to him and said, <q>If the prophet
            had told you to do something great, would you not have done it? How much rather, then, when he tells you
            only to wash and be clean?</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.5.13"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.5.14" osisID="2Kgs.5.14"/> At this he went down and dipped seven times in the Jordan, as
            the man of God had ordered; his body became once more like a child's body, and he was clean. <verse eID="2Kgs.5.14"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.5.15" osisID="2Kgs.5.15"/> Then, returning to the man of God, he and all his retinue, he
            stood in his presence, saying, <q>Now indeed I know there is no God in all the earth except in Israel! Pray
            accept a present from your humble servant.</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.5.15"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.5.16" osisID="2Kgs.5.16"/> <q>As sure as the Eternal lives, whom I serve,</q> said Elisha,
            <q>I will not take a single thing.</q> Naaman pressed him, but he refused. <verse eID="2Kgs.5.16"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.5.17" osisID="2Kgs.5.17"/> Then said Naaman, <q>Well, let your servant at least have two
            mules' load of earth, for after this your servant will offer neither victim nor sacrifice to any god except the
            Eternal. <verse eID="2Kgs.5.17"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.5.18" osisID="2Kgs.5.18"/> But may the Eternal pardon me this: when my lord enters the
            temple of Rimmon to worship there, leaning on my arm, and I bow in the house of Rimmon when he bows in
            the house of Rimmon--may the Eternal pardon your servant then!</q>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.5.18"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.5.19" osisID="2Kgs.5.19"/>
            <q>Farewell,</q> said Elisha.
       </p>
       <p>
            He had gone only a short distance,
           <verse eID="2Kgs.5.19"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.5.20" osisID="2Kgs.5.20"/> when Gehazi said to himself, <q>Here has my master spared
            this Naaman the Aramaean, declining to accept his present! By the Eternal, I will run after him and get
            something out of him!</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.5.20"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.5.21" osisID="2Kgs.5.21"/> So Gehazi followed up Naaman. When Naaman saw him running
            behind, he alighted from the chariot to meet him, saying, <q>Is all well?</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.5.21"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.5.22" osisID="2Kgs.5.22"/> <q>All is well,</q> said Gehazi. <q>My master sends me to
           say that two young members of the prophets' guild from the uplands of Ephraim have just come to him;
           will you give them four hundred pounds in silver and two festal robes?</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.5.22"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.5.23" osisID="2Kgs.5.23"/> <q>Allow me to give you eight hundred pounds,</q> said
            Naaman. He urged this, tying up eight hundred pounds in silver inside two bags and also two festal robes;
            these he laid on Gehazi's two servants, who carried them in front of him. <verse eID="2Kgs.5.23"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.5.24" osisID="2Kgs.5.24"/> When he reached the Mound, he took them from the servants and
            put them away inside the house, letting the servants go their way. <verse eID="2Kgs.5.24"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.5.25" osisID="2Kgs.5.25"/> Then he went in to wait upon Elisha. Elisha said to him,
            <q>Where have you been, Gehazi?</q> <q>Your servant has not been anywhere,</q> he answered. <verse eID="2Kgs.5.25"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.5.26" osisID="2Kgs.5.26"/> But Elisha said to him, <q>Was I not with you in spirit when
            someone came back from his chariot to meet you? You have taken money, and you mean to get garments, oliveyards,
            vineyards, sheep, oxen, and slaves, male and female? <verse eID="2Kgs.5.26"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.5.27" osisID="2Kgs.5.27"/> Yes, and the leprosy of Naaman
            <milestone type="pb" n="423"/>
            for yourself and your descendants ever after this!</q> Then he left Elisha's presence a leper, white as
            snow. <verse eID="2Kgs.5.27"/>
       </p>
     <chapter eID="2Kgs.5"/>
     <chapter osisID="2Kgs.6" sID="2Kgs.6"/>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.6.1" osisID="2Kgs.6.1"/> The prophets' guild once said to Elisha, <q>This dwelling of
            ours, as you see for yourself, is too small for us. <verse eID="2Kgs.6.1"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.6.2" osisID="2Kgs.6.2"/> Pray let us go to the Jordan and get each of us a log, to build
            a dwelling-house for ourselves there.</q> Elisha told them to go; <verse eID="2Kgs.6.2"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.6.3" osisID="2Kgs.6.3"/> and, when one of them said, <q>Pray agree to go along with
            your servants,</q> he answered, <q>I will go,</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.6.3"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.6.4" osisID="2Kgs.6.4"/> and went. On reaching the Jordan they cut down some timber. <verse eID="2Kgs.6.4"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.6.5" osisID="2Kgs.6.5"/> But as one man was swinging his axe, the head of the axe fell
            into the water. <q>Alas, my master!</q> cried the man, <q>it was borrowed.</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.6.5"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.6.6" osisID="2Kgs.6.6"/> <q>Where did it fall?</q> said the man of God. The man showed
            him the spot. Then, cutting a stick, Elisha threw it in, and so made the iron swim. <verse eID="2Kgs.6.6"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.6.7" osisID="2Kgs.6.7"/> <q>Lift it,</q> he told the man. And the man put out his hand
            and lifted it. <verse eID="2Kgs.6.7"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.6.8" osisID="2Kgs.6.8"/> The king of Aram was fighting Israel. He planned with his
            officers to lay an ambush at a certain spot. <verse eID="2Kgs.6.8"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.6.9" osisID="2Kgs.6.9"/> But the man of God sent a warning to the king of Israel not to
            pass that spot, because the Aramaeans were lying hidden there; <verse eID="2Kgs.6.9"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.6.10" osisID="2Kgs.6.10"/> so the king of Israel, sending to the spot about which the
            man of God had warned him, saved himself. This happened more than once. <verse eID="2Kgs.6.10"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.6.11" osisID="2Kgs.6.11"/> It greatly upset the mind of the king of Aram. He summoned
            his officers and asked them, <q>Can you not show me who is betraying us to the king of Israel?</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.6.11"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.6.12" osisID="2Kgs.6.12"/> <q>None of us, my lord king!</q> said an officer. <q>It is
            Elisha the prophet in Israel; he tells the king of Israel the very words you breathe in your
            bedchamber.</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.6.12"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.6.13" osisID="2Kgs.6.13"/> So he gave orders to find out where Elisha stayed, that he
            might send and fetch him. On being told that he was at Dothan, <verse eID="2Kgs.6.13"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.6.14" osisID="2Kgs.6.14"/> the king sent cavairy, chariots, and a large force, which
            marching over-night surrounded the town. <verse eID="2Kgs.6.14"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.6.15" osisID="2Kgs.6.15"/> Early on the morning of the next day, Elisha the man of God
            rose and went outside; and there was an armed force with cavalry and chariots round the town! <q>Alas,
            my master!</q> said his servant, <q>whatever are we to do?</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.6.15"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.6.16" osisID="2Kgs.6.16"/> <q>Fear not,</q> he answered; <q>those on our side are more
            than those on their side.</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.6.16"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.6.17" osisID="2Kgs.6.17"/> Then Elisha prayed, <q>0 Eternal, open his eyes, that he may
            see.</q> The Eternal did open the young man's eyes; and what he saw was the hill covered with horses and
            chariots of fire around Elisha! <verse eID="2Kgs.6.17"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.6.18" osisID="2Kgs.6.18"/> When the enemy came down upon him, Elisha prayed to the
            Eternal, <q>Punish this host with blindness.</q> He punished them with blindness, as Elisha had asked.
           <verse eID="2Kgs.6.18"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.6.19" osisID="2Kgs.6.19"/> Whereupon Elisha said to them, <q>This is not the road, this
            is not the town; follow me and I will take you to the man you are after.</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.6.19"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.6.20" osisID="2Kgs.6.20"/> He led them to Samaria, and, once they were at Samaria,
            Elisha said, <q>0 Eternal, open the eyes of these men, that they may see.</q> When the Eternal opened
            their eyes, they looked--and there they were, inside Samaria! <verse eID="2Kgs.6.20"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.6.21" osisID="2Kgs.6.21"/> When the king of Israel saw them, he asked Elisha, <q>My
           father, shall I cut them down? Shall I cut them down?</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.6.21"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.6.22" osisID="2Kgs.6.22"/> <q>No,</q> said Elisha; <q>would you cut down prisoners you
            never captured with your own sword and bow? Set bread and water
            <milestone type="pb" n="424"/>
            before them, that they may eat and drink before returning to their master.</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.6.22"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.6.23" osisID="2Kgs.6.23"/> So he had a great feast spread for them, and after they had
            eaten and drunk he sent them away back to their master. The Aramaean raiders no longer invaded the land
            of Israel. <verse eID="2Kgs.6.23"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.6.24" osisID="2Kgs.6.24"/> It was after this that Benhadad the king of Aram mustered all his
            forces and marched to besiege Samaria. <verse eID="2Kgs.6.24"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.6.25" osisID="2Kgs.6.25"/> A severe famine raged in Samaria, as the siege went on, till
            ten pounds in silver was paid for the head of an ass and twelve shillings for a pint of doves' dung. <verse eID="2Kgs.6.25"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.6.26" osisID="2Kgs.6.26"/> As the king was passing along the wall, a woman cried out to
            him, <q>Help, my lord king!</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.6.26"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.6.27" osisID="2Kgs.6.27"/> <q>No,</q> he answered, <q>may the Eternal help you! How can
            I? Can I help you from threshing-floor or winepress?</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.6.27"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.6.28" osisID="2Kgs.6.28"/> Then the king asked, <q>What ails you?</q> She replied,
            <q>This woman here said to me, <q>Let us have your boy to eat to-day, and to-morrow we will eat my
            boy.</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.6.28"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.6.29" osisID="2Kgs.6.29"/> So we boiled my boy and ate him. Next day when I said, <q>Now
            let us have your son to eat,</q> she had hid the boy.</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.6.29"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.6.30" osisID="2Kgs.6.30"/> When the king heard what the woman said, he tore his clothes,
            as he stood on the wall. (The people noticed that he was wearing sackcloth next his skin.) <verse eID="2Kgs.6.30"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.6.31" osisID="2Kgs.6.31"/> <q>God kill me and worse,</q> he cried, <q>if the head of
            Elisha the son of Shaphat remain on his shoulders to-day!</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.6.31"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.6.32" osisID="2Kgs.6.32"/> Elisha was sitting at home with the sheikhs of Israel.
            Before ever the king's messenger arrived, he said to the sheikhs, <q>Do you see that this murderous
            creature has given orders to cut off my head? Look to it. When the messenger arrives, close the door,
            shut it in his face: is not the sound of his master’s feet behind him?</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.6.32"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.6.33" osisID="2Kgs.6.33"/> He was still talking to them when the king himself arrived,
            saying, <q>This trouble comes from the Eternal; why should I wait for the Eternal's help any longer?</q>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.6.33"/>
       </p>
     <chapter eID="2Kgs.6"/>
     <chapter osisID="2Kgs.7" sID="2Kgs.7"/>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.7.1" osisID="2Kgs.7.1"/> Elisha answered, <q>Listen to this  promise from the Eternal;
            the Eternal declares that this time to-morrow a peck of fine flour will be sold for only half-a-crown
            and two pecks of barley for only half-a-crown, at the gate of Samaria.</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.7.1"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.7.2" osisID="2Kgs.7.2"/> The adjutant, on whose arm the king leant, replied to the man
            of God, <q>Could that be, even if the Eternal were to open sluices in the sky?</q> Said Elisha,
            <q>You shall see that sight, but you shall not eat the food.</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.7.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.7.3" osisID="2Kgs.7.3"/> Now four lepers were sitting in the entry at the gates.
            <q>Why sit here till we die?</q> they said to themselves. <verse eID="2Kgs.7.3"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.7.4" osisID="2Kgs.7.4"/> <q>If we propose to enter the town, the famine is in the
            town, and we shall die there; if we remain here, we die also. Come along, let us go over to the Aramaean
            army. If they let us live, we shall live; if they kill us, we shall only die.</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.7.4"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.7.5" osisID="2Kgs.7.5"/> So in the twilight they started for the Aramaean camp. When
            they reached the fringes of the Aramaean camp, not a man was to be found! <verse eID="2Kgs.7.5"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.7.6" osisID="2Kgs.7.6"/> The Lord had made the Aramaean army hear a noise of chariots
            and a noise of cavalry, the noise of a large army, till they thought, <q>The king of Israel must have
            hired the kings of the Hittites and the kings of Muzri to attack us.</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.7.6"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.7.7" osisID="2Kgs.7.7"/> So they had fled away for their lives in the twilight, leaving
            their tents, their horses, and their asses, just as they were, in the camp. <verse eID="2Kgs.7.7"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.7.8" osisID="2Kgs.7.8"/> When the lepers reached the fringes of the camp,
            <milestone type="pb" n="425"/>
            they entered one tent, ate and drank, carried off the silver, the gold, and the clothes, and after
            hiding them came back to another tent which they also stripped, hiding its contents. <verse eID="2Kgs.7.8"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.7.9" osisID="2Kgs.7.9"/> Then they said to themselves, <q>We are not doing right. This
            is a day of good news, and we are not spreading it. If we wait till morning dawns, punishment will
            overtake us. Come along, let us go and inform the royal household.</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.7.9"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.7.10" osisID="2Kgs.7.10"/> So they went and called to the warders of the town, <q>We
            have been to the Aramaean camp, and not a man is to be found there! There is not a human sound, only
            horses tethered, asses tethered, and the tents as they were!</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.7.10"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.7.11" osisID="2Kgs.7.11"/> When the warders informed the royal household, <verse eID="2Kgs.7.11"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.7.12" osisID="2Kgs.7.12"/> the king rose in the night and said to his officers, <q>I
            will tell you what the Aramaeans have done about us. They know we are starving, and so they have left
            the camp to hide themselves in the open country, thinking that once we leave the town, they will capture
            us alive and get into the town!</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.7.12"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.7.13" osisID="2Kgs.7.13"/> One of the officers replied, <q>Pray send some men, with five
            of the horses that are left; if they live, they will fare like all the multitude of Israel who survive here,
            and if they die, they die like all the multitude of Israel that perish here. Let us send and see!</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.7.13"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.7.14" osisID="2Kgs.7.14"/> So two men on horseback were chosen, and sent by the king
            after the Aramaean army with orders to go and see. <verse eID="2Kgs.7.14"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.7.15" osisID="2Kgs.7.15"/> They followed the track as far as the Jordan, finding the
            road all littered with the garments and the weapons which the Aramaeans had thrown away in their
            hurried flight. When the messengers came back and told the king, <verse eID="2Kgs.7.15"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.7.16" osisID="2Kgs.7.16"/> the people went out and plundered the Aramaeans' camp. And a
            peck of fine flour was sold for only half-a-crown, two pecks of barley were sold for only half-a-crown,
            as the Eternal had foretold. <verse eID="2Kgs.7.16"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.7.17" osisID="2Kgs.7.17"/> The king had put the gate in charge of the adjutant on whose
            arm he was accustomed to lean; and the crowd trod on him at the gate till he died--also as the man of God had
            predicted when the king visited him. <verse eID="2Kgs.7.17"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.7.18" osisID="2Kgs.7.18"/> As the man of God had told the king that two pecks of barley
            would be sold for half-a-crown and a peck of fine flour for half-a-crown by that time next day, <verse eID="2Kgs.7.18"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.7.19" osisID="2Kgs.7.19"/> and as the man of God had said, <q>You shall see that sight,
            but you shall not eat the food,</q> to the adjutant who had said, <q>Could that be, even if the
            Eternal were to open sluices in the sky?</q>--<verse eID="2Kgs.7.19"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.7.20" osisID="2Kgs.7.20"/>so it happened to him; the crowd at the gate trod on him till
            he died. <verse eID="2Kgs.7.20"/>
       </p>
     <chapter eID="2Kgs.7"/>
     <chapter osisID="2Kgs.8" sID="2Kgs.8"/>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.8.1" osisID="2Kgs.8.1"/> Elisha said to the woman whose boy he had restored to life,
            <q>Move away, you and your household, and stay abroad wherever you can, for the Eternal has called for a
             famine.</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.8.1"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.8.2" osisID="2Kgs.8.2"/> The famine did come upon the land for seven years. But the
            woman started off, at the bidding of the man of God; she and her household went and stayed in the land
            of the Philistines for seven years. <verse eID="2Kgs.8.2"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.8.3" osisID="2Kgs.8.3"/> At the end of the seven years, when the woman came back from
            the land of the Philistines, she went to appeal to the king for her house and land. <verse eID="2Kgs.8.3"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.8.4" osisID="2Kgs.8.4"/> The king was talking to Gehazi the servant of the man of God,
            asking him to tell him about all the great deeds of Elisha; <verse eID="2Kgs.8.4"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.8.5" osisID="2Kgs.8.5"/> and just as he was telling the king how Elisha had
            <milestone type="pb" n="426"/>
            restored a boy to life, the very woman whose boy had been restored to life made her appeal to the king
            for her house and land. <q>My lord king,</q> said Gehazi, <q>this is the woman, and this is her boy whom
            Elisha restored to life!</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.8.5"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.8.6" osisID="2Kgs.8.6"/> When the king asked the woman, she told him the story. So the
            king appointed a eunuch to see that she got back all her property and all the produce that her farm had
            yielded ever since she left the country. <verse eID="2Kgs.8.6"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.8.7" osisID="2Kgs.8.7"/> Once, when Elisha came to Damascus, Benhadad king of Aram was
            ill; he was told that the man of God had arrived, <verse eID="2Kgs.8.7"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.8.8" osisID="2Kgs.8.8"/> and so the king said to Hazael, <q>Take a present with you and
            go to see the man of God; ask the Eternal through him whether I shall recover from this illness.</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.8.8"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.8.9" osisID="2Kgs.8.9"/> Hazael went to see him, taking as a present specimens of all
            the rare wares of Damascus, as much as forty camels could carry. When he reached Elisha, he stood in
            front of him and said, <q>Your son Benhadad king of Aram has sent me to ask you whether he will recover
            from this illness.</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.8.9"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.8.10" osisID="2Kgs.8.10"/> Elisha answered, <q>Go and tell him that he will certainly
            recover--though the Eternal has revealed to me that he will certainly die.</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.8.10"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.8.11" osisID="2Kgs.8.11"/> As he spoke, the man of God's face became rigid with horror,
            absolute horror. Then he burst into tears. <verse eID="2Kgs.8.11"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.8.12" osisID="2Kgs.8.12"/> <q>Why does my lord weep?</q> said Hazael. <q>Because,</q>
            he answered, <q>I know the cruelties you will practise on the Israelites, setting fortresses ablaze,
            murdering young men, dashing children to pieces, and ripping up pregnant women!</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.8.12"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.8.13" osisID="2Kgs.8.13"/> <q>Your humble servant is but a cur,</q> said Hazael; <q>how
            can he achieve all this?</q> Elisha answered, <q>The Eternal has let me see you reigning over Aram!</q>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.8.13"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.8.14" osisID="2Kgs.8.14"/> Leaving Elisha, he went back to his master, who asked,
            <q>What did Elisha say to you?</q> <verse eID="2Kgs.8.14"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.8.15" osisID="2Kgs.8.15"/> Hazael replied, <q>He told me that you would certainly
            recover.</q> Next day he took the bath-towel, soaked it and then spread it over the king's face till he was
            dead. Then Hazael reigned instead of him. <verse eID="2Kgs.8.15"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.8.16" osisID="2Kgs.8.16"/>In the fifth year of Jehoram the son of Ahab king of Israel, Jehoram
            the son of Jehoshaphat king of Judah began to reign; <verse eID="2Kgs.8.16"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.8.17" osisID="2Kgs.8.17"/> he was thirty-two years old when he began to reign, and he
            reigned in Jerusalem for eight years. <verse eID="2Kgs.8.17"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.8.18" osisID="2Kgs.8.18"/> He lived on the lines of the kings of Israel, following the
            dynasty of Ahab--for he was married to Ahab's daughter. He did what was evil in the eyes of the
            Eternal, <verse eID="2Kgs.8.18"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.8.19" osisID="2Kgs.8.19"/> but for the sake of David his servant the Eter­nal would not
            destroy Judah, since he had promised David a dynasty before the Eternal for all time. <verse eID="2Kgs.8.19"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.8.20" osisID="2Kgs.8.20"/> (It was during his reign that Edom revolted from Judah and
            set up a king for itself. <verse eID="2Kgs.8.20"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.8.21" osisID="2Kgs.8.21"/> Whereupon Jehoram went across to Zair, with all his
            chariots . . . However, Jehoram and the captains of his chariots with him rose by night and raided the
            Edomites, who hemmed them in. The rank and file scurried home. <verse eID="2Kgs.8.21"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.8.22" osisID="2Kgs.8.22"/> So Edom revolted from Judah to this day; and Libnah revolted
            at the same time.) <verse eID="2Kgs.8.22"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.8.23" osisID="2Kgs.8.23"/> The rest of the acts of Jehoram and all his deeds, are they
            not described in the book of the Annals of the Kings of Judah? <verse eID="2Kgs.8.23"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.8.24" osisID="2Kgs.8.24"/> Jehoram slept with his fathers, and was buried with his
            fathers in David's burg;
            <milestone type="pb" n="427"/>
           Ahaziah his son reigned instead of him. <verse eID="2Kgs.8.24"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.8.25" osisID="2Kgs.8.25"/> In the twelfth year of Jehoram the son of Ahab king of
            Israel, Ahaziah the son of Jehoram king of Judah began to reign; <verse eID="2Kgs.8.25"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.8.26" osisID="2Kgs.8.26"/> Ahaziah was twenty-two years old when he began to reign, and
            he reigned in Jerusalem for one year. His mother's name was Athallah, a grand­daughter of Omri king of
            Israel. <verse eID="2Kgs.8.26"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.8.27" osisID="2Kgs.8.27"/> He lived on the lines of the dynasty of Ahab, doing what was
            evil in the eyes of the Eternal as Ahab s dynasty did--for he had married a wife of that family. <verse eID="2Kgs.8.27"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.8.28" osisID="2Kgs.8.28"/> He accompanied Jehoram the son of Ahab to attack Hazael king
            of Aram at Ramoth-gilead, where the archers wounded Jehoram,
           <verse eID="2Kgs.8.28"/>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.8.29" osisID="2Kgs.8.29"/> who returned to Jezreel to recover from the wounds inflicted
            by the Aramaeans at Hamah, as he had fought against Hazael king of Aram.
       </p>
       <p>
            Ahaziah the son of Jehoram king of Judah went down to visit
            Jehoram the son of Ahab at Jezreel, where he lay ill. <verse eID="2Kgs.8.29"/>
       </p>
     <chapter eID="2Kgs.8"/>
     <chapter osisID="2Kgs.3" sID="2Kgs.3"/>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
     <chapter eID="2Kgs.3"/>
     <chapter osisID="2Kgs.3" sID="2Kgs.3"/>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
     <chapter eID="2Kgs.3"/>
     <chapter osisID="2Kgs.3" sID="2Kgs.3"/>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
     <chapter eID="2Kgs.3"/>
     <chapter osisID="2Kgs.3" sID="2Kgs.3"/>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
     <chapter eID="2Kgs.3"/>
     <chapter osisID="2Kgs.3" sID="2Kgs.3"/>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
     <chapter eID="2Kgs.3"/>
     <chapter osisID="2Kgs.3" sID="2Kgs.3"/>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
     <chapter eID="2Kgs.3"/>
     <chapter osisID="2Kgs.3" sID="2Kgs.3"/>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
     <chapter eID="2Kgs.3"/>
     <chapter osisID="2Kgs.3" sID="2Kgs.3"/>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
     <chapter eID="2Kgs.3"/>
     <chapter osisID="2Kgs.3" sID="2Kgs.3"/>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
     <chapter eID="2Kgs.3"/>
     <chapter osisID="2Kgs.3" sID="2Kgs.3"/>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
           <verse sID="2Kgs.3.2" osisID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
           <verse eID="2Kgs.3.2"/>
       </p>
     <chapter eID="2Kgs.3"/>
   </div>