   <div type="book" osisID="2Sam">
    <milestone type="pb" n="346"/>
    <chapter osisID="2Sam.1" sID="2Sam.1"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="2Sam.1.1" osisID="2Sam.1.1"/>After the death of Saul, when David had come back from slaying the
       Amalekites and had been for two days at Ziklag, <verse eID="2Sam.1.1"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.1.2" osisID="2Sam.1.2"/> on the third day a man came from Saul's camp with his clothes
       torn and earth scattered on his head. When he reached David, he fell to the ground and did obeisance. <verse eID="2Sam.1.2"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.1.3" osisID="2Sam.1.3"/> David said to him, <q>Where do you come from?</q> <q>I have
       escaped from the camp of Israel,</q> said he. <verse eID="2Sam.1.3"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.1.4" osisID="2Sam.1.4"/> Then David asked him, <q>Tell me, how did things go?</q>
       He replied, <q>The troops ran away from the fight, many of the troops have fallen, and Saul and his son
       Jonathan are also dead.</q> <verse eID="2Sam.1.4"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.1.5" osisID="2Sam.1.5"/> [[David said to the young man who told him, <q>How do you know
       that Saul and his son Jonathan are dead?</q> <verse eID="2Sam.1.5"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.1.6" osisID="2Sam.1.6"/> And the young man who told him said, <q>I happened to be on mount
       Gilboa, and there was Saul leaning on his spear! The chariots and cavalry were close upon him. <verse eID="2Sam.1.6"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.1.7" osisID="2Sam.1.7"/> When he looked behind him, he saw me and called to me. I
       answered, <q>Here I am.</q> <verse eID="2Sam.1.7"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.1.8" osisID="2Sam.1.8"/> He said to me, <q>Who are you?</q> I said to him, <q>I am an
       Amalekite.</q> <verse eID="2Sam.1.8"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.1.9" osisID="2Sam.1.9"/> Then he said to me, <q>Stand over me and des­patch me, for it is
       dizziness that has seized me--I am quite unwounded!</q> <verse eID="2Sam.1.9"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.1.10" osisID="2Sam.1.10"/> So I stood over him and killed him, for I was sure he could not
       live after he had fallen. I took the crown from his head and the armlet from his arm, and I have brought
       them here to my lord.</q>]] <verse eID="2Sam.1.10"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="2Sam.1.11" osisID="2Sam.1.11"/> Then David caught his clothes and tore them; so did all the men
       with him; <verse eID="2Sam.1.11"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.1.12" osisID="2Sam.1.12"/> they lamented and wept and fasted till evening for Saul and his
       son Jonathan and the army of Judah and the house of Israel, because they had fallen by the sword. <verse eID="2Sam.1.12"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.1.13" osisID="2Sam.1.13"/> [[David said to the young man who told him, <q>Where do you
       come from?</q> <q>I am the son of a resident alien,</q> he said, <q>an Amalekite.</q> <verse eID="2Sam.1.13"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.1.14" osisID="2Sam.1.14"/> And David said to him, <q>Why were you not afraid to lift your
       hand to de­stroy the Eternal's anointed?</q> <verse eID="2Sam.1.14"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.1.15" osisID="2Sam.1.15"/> Then David called one of the young men and said, <q>Go up to
       him and strike him down.</q> Then he felled the Amalekite, so that he died. <verse eID="2Sam.1.15"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.1.16" osisID="2Sam.1.16"/> <q>Your blood be on your own head,</q> said David; <q>your own
       lips have borne witness against you, when you said, <q>I slew the Eternal’s anointed!</q></q>]] <verse eID="2Sam.1.16"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="2Sam.1.17" osisID="2Sam.1.17"/> Then David sang this dirge over Saul and his son Jonathan <verse eID="2Sam.1.17"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.1.18" osisID="2Sam.1.18"/> (it is written in the Book of Heroes); he said:
       <lg>
        <l> O Judah, to your crying! </l>
        <l> O Israel, to your grief and woe! </l>
      <verse eID="2Sam.1.18"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.1.19" osisID="2Sam.1.19"/>
        <l> On your battle-fields the slain are lying. </l>
        <l> and heroes, alas! fallen low. </l>
      <verse eID="2Sam.1.19"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.1.20" osisID="2Sam.1.20"/>
        <l> Tell it not in Gath,</l>
        <l> proclaim it not in Ashkelon's streets,</l>
        <l> lest the daughters of the Philis­tines rejoice,</l>
        <l> lest the daughters of the uncir­cumcised exult.</l>
      <verse eID="2Sam.1.20"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.1.21" osisID="2Sam.1.21"/>
        <l> Dew never fall on you, hills of Gilboa, </l>
        <l> rain never reach you, O death's own field </l>
        <l> For there a hero dropped his shield, </l>
        <l> Saul's shield, the armour of the anointed. </l>
      <verse eID="2Sam.1.21"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.1.22" osisID="2Sam.1.22"/>
        <l> From the blood of the slain, </l>
        <l> from the flesh of the mighty, </l>
        <l> never did Jonathan’s bow turn back, </l>
        <l> nor the sword of Saul unsated. </l>
      <verse eID="2Sam.1.22"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.1.23" osisID="2Sam.1.23"/>
        <l> Saul and Jonathan, loved and lovely, </l>
       <milestone type="pb" n="347"/>
        <l> never divided in life or in death!-- </l>
        <l> swifter than eagles, stronger than lions! </l>
      <verse eID="2Sam.1.23"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.1.24" osisID="2Sam.1.24"/>
        <l> Daughters of Israel, wail for Saul, </l>
        <l> who decked you in scarlet and jewels, </l>
        <l> who adorned your robes with gold! </l>
      <verse eID="2Sam.1.24"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.1.25" osisID="2Sam.1.25"/>
        <l> Alas for heroes fallen low </l>
        <l> in the thick of the fray </l>
      <verse eID="2Sam.1.25"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.1.26" osisID="2Sam.1.26"/>
        <l> Jonathan slain in the field of battle, </l>
        <l> my heart is sore for you, </l>
        <l> O Jonathan, my brother! </l>
        <l> You were my dear delight, </l>
        <l> your love for me was a wonder, </l>
        <l> far beyond a woman’s love. </l>
      <verse eID="2Sam.1.26"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.1.27" osisID="2Sam.1.27"/>
        <l> Alas for heroes fallen low, </l>
        <l> for weapons that once felled the foe! </l>
       </lg>
      <verse eID="2Sam.1.27"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eID="2Sam.1"/>
    <chapter osisID="2Sam.2" sID="2Sam.2"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="2Sam.2.1" osisID="2Sam.2.1"/>After this David asked the Eternal, <q>Shall I go up to one of the
       towns of Judah?</q> The Eternal said to him, <q>Go up.</q> Then David said, <q>Where shall I go up?</q>
       <q>To Hebron,</q> the Eternal answered. <verse eID="2Sam.2.1"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.2.2" osisID="2Sam.2.2"/> So David went up, along with his two wives, Ahinoam the
       Jezreelitess and Abigail who had been the wife of Nabal the Karmelite. <verse eID="2Sam.2.2"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.2.3" osisID="2Sam.2.3"/> David also took the men who were with him, every man and his
       household, and they stayed in the citadel of Hebron; <verse eID="2Sam.2.3"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.2.4" osisID="2Sam.2.4"/> then the men of Judah came and anointed David there as king over
       the house of Judah. <verse eID="2Sam.2.4"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="2Sam.2.5" osisID="2Sam.2.5"/> When David was told that it was the men of Jabesh-gilead who had
       buried Saul, he sent messengers to the leading men of Jabesh-gilead, saying, <verse eID="2Sam.2.5"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.2.6" osisID="2Sam.2.6"/> <q>The Eter­nal's blessing be on you for hav­ing done this
       kindness to your lord Saul in burying him! So may the Eternal be kind and true to you! And I will be good
       to you for having done this. <verse eID="2Sam.2.6"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.2.7" osisID="2Sam.2.7"/> Courage then, be brave! Saul your lord is dead, but the house of
       Judah has anointed me to be their king.</q> <verse eID="2Sam.2.7"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="2Sam.2.8" osisID="2Sam.2.8"/> Now Abner the son of Ner, commander of Saul's army, had taken
       Saul's son Ishbaal across to Mahanaim, <verse eID="2Sam.2.8"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.2.9" osisID="2Sam.2.9"/> where he made him king over Gilead, the Asherites, Jezreel,
       Ephraim, and Ben­jamin, in fact over all Israel. <verse eID="2Sam.2.9"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.2.10" osisID="2Sam.2.10"/> Only the house of Judah adhered to David. [[Ishbaal, Saul's
       son, was forty years old when he began to reign over Israel, and he reigned two years. <verse eID="2Sam.2.10"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.2.11" osisID="2Sam.2.11"/> The time during which David reigned at Hebron over the house
       of Judah was seven years and six months.]] <verse eID="2Sam.2.11"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.2.12" osisID="2Sam.2.12"/> Then Abner the son of Ner and the adherents of Ishbaal the son
       of Saul marched from Mahanaim to Gibeon; <verse eID="2Sam.2.12"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.2.13" osisID="2Sam.2.13"/> Joab the son of Zerulah and David's adherents also marched out,
       and met them at the reser­voir of Gibeon. The two par­ties sat down, one on the one side of the reservoir
       and the other on the other side. <verse eID="2Sam.2.13"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.2.14" osisID="2Sam.2.14"/> Then Abner said to Joab, <q>Let the young men get up and have a
       fight before us.</q> <q>Very well,</q> said Joab. <verse eID="2Sam.2.14"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.2.15" osisID="2Sam.2.15"/> So the young men got up and were numbered off, twelve for
       Benjamin and Ishbaal the son of Saul, and twelve ad­herents of David. <verse eID="2Sam.2.15"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.2.16" osisID="2Sam.2.16"/> Each caught his opponent by the head and stabbed him in the
       side, so that they all dropped together. Hence the spot was called <q>The Field of Sides</q> (it is at
       Gib­eon). <verse eID="2Sam.2.16"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.2.17" osisID="2Sam.2.17"/> That day the fight that followed was most fierce, but Abner the
       son of Ner and the men of Israel were beaten by the adherents of David. <verse eID="2Sam.2.17"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="2Sam.2.18" osisID="2Sam.2.18"/> Zeruiah's three sons were there, Joab, Abishai, and Asahel.
       Asahel was swift-footed as a wild deer; <verse eID="2Sam.2.18"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.2.19" osisID="2Sam.2.19"/> so Asahel chased Abner, and as he ran he never turned
       <milestone type="pb" n="348"/>
       to right or left in his pursuit of Abner. <verse eID="2Sam.2.19"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.2.20" osisID="2Sam.2.20"/> Then Abner glanced behind him and said, <q>Is that you,
       Asahel?</q> <q>Yes,</q> he answered. <verse eID="2Sam.2.20"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.2.21" osisID="2Sam.2.21"/> So Abner said to him, <q>Turn to your right or to your left,
       catch one of the young men and take his spoil.</q> But Asahel would not turn aside from his chase. <verse eID="2Sam.2.21"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.2.22" osisID="2Sam.2.22"/> Then Abner again said to Asahel, <q>Turn aside from following
       me; why should I strike you down? How could I look your brother Joab in the face after that?</q> <verse eID="2Sam.2.22"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.2.23" osisID="2Sam.2.23"/> But he would not turn aside. So Abner gave him a backward
       stroke in the belly, the spear came out at his back, and he dropped dead on the spot. [[Everyone who came
       to the spot where Asahel had dropped dead, stopped there.l] <verse eID="2Sam.2.23"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="2Sam.2.24" osisID="2Sam.2.24"/> Joab and Abishai pursued Ab­ner, and, as the sun was setting,
       they reached the hill of Ammah, east of the road through the open country of Gibeon, <verse eID="2Sam.2.24"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.2.25" osisID="2Sam.2.25"/> where the Benjamites gathered behind Abner in a solid phalanx
       drawn up on the top of the hill of Ammah. <verse eID="2Sam.2.25"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.2.26" osisID="2Sam.2.26"/> Abner called to Joab, <q>Is the sword to devour for ever? Do
       you not know the outcome will be bitter? How long will it be before you order the troops to give up
       pursuing their fellow-countrymen?</q> <verse eID="2Sam.2.26"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.2.27" osisID="2Sam.2.27"/> <q>By God’s life!</q> said Joab, <q>unless you had said the
       word, not one of the men would have stopped pursuing his fellow till morning.</q> <verse eID="2Sam.2.27"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.2.28" osisID="2Sam.2.28"/> Then Joab sounded the trumpet, and all the troops stopped; they
       pur­sued Israel no longer, they fought no more. <verse eID="2Sam.2.28"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="2Sam.2.29" osisID="2Sam.2.29"/> All that forenoon Abner and his men made their way through the
       wady of Arabah, crossing the Jordan and pass­ing right through the ravine till they reached Mahanaim. <verse eID="2Sam.2.29"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.2.30" osisID="2Sam.2.30"/> As for Joab, he returned from his pursuit of Abner; when he had
       mustered all the troops, nineteen of David's adherents were missing, besides Asahel, <verse eID="2Sam.2.30"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.2.31" osisID="2Sam.2.31"/> whereas David's adherents had killed three hundred and sixty
       men of Benjamin and of Abner’s army. <verse eID="2Sam.2.31"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.2.32" osisID="2Sam.2.32"/> Asahel they lifted, and buried him in his father's grave at
       Bethlehem. Then Joab and his men marched all night, and the day dawned on them at Hebron. <verse eID="2Sam.2.32"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eID="2Sam.2"/>
    <chapter osisID="2Sam.3" sID="2Sam.3"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="2Sam.3.1" osisID="2Sam.3.1"/>The war between Saul's house and David's house went on; but David
       grew stronger and stronger, while the house of Saul became weaker and weaker. <verse eID="2Sam.3.1"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="2Sam.3.2" osisID="2Sam.3.2"/> Sons were born to David at Hebron: his eldest was Amnon, son of
       Ahinoam the Jezreelitess; <verse eID="2Sam.3.2"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.3.3" osisID="2Sam.3.3"/> his second was Chileab, son of Abigail who had been the wife of
       Nabal the Karmelite; his third was Absalom, son of Maakah, the daughter of Talmai the king of Geshur; <verse eID="2Sam.3.3"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.3.4" osisID="2Sam.3.4"/> his fourth was Adonijah, son of Haggith; his fifth was
       Shephatiah, son of Abital; <verse eID="2Sam.3.4"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.3.5" osisID="2Sam.3.5"/> and his sixth Ithream, son of Eglah . . . These were born to
       David at Hebron. <verse eID="2Sam.3.5"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="2Sam.3.6" osisID="2Sam.3.6"/>During the war between the house of Saul and the house of David,
       Abner strengthened his position in the house of Saul. <verse eID="2Sam.3.6"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.3.7" osisID="2Sam.3.7"/> Thus, Saul had a concubine called Rizpah, the daughter of Aiah,
       and Abner took her. Ishbaal said to Abner, <q>Why have you gone in to my father’s con­cubine?</q> <verse eID="2Sam.3.7"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.3.8" osisID="2Sam.3.8"/> But Abner was furious at what Ishbaal said. <q>Am I the mere
       head of a cur?</q> he asked, <q>I with all my good service to the house of Saul your father, to his
       kinsfolk and
       <milestone type="pb" n="349"/>
       his friends, I who have saved you from the grasp of David, that you find fault with me now about a wench?
      <verse eID="2Sam.3.8"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.3.9" osisID="2Sam.3.9"/> God kill Abner and worse, if I do not help David to what the
       Eternal swore to give him! <verse eID="2Sam.3.9"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.3.10" osisID="2Sam.3.10"/> I will transfer the kingdom from Saul's house, and set up
       David's throne over Israel and Judah, from Dan to Beersheba!</q><verse eID="2Sam.3.10"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="2Sam.3.11" osisID="2Sam.3.11"/>Ishbaal dared not say another word to Abner; he was afraid of
       him. <verse eID="2Sam.3.11"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.3.12" osisID="2Sam.3.12"/> But Abner sent messen­gers to David at Hebron, saying, <q>Make
       a pact with me, and you will get my help in bringing over all Israel to your side.</q> <verse eID="2Sam.3.12"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.3.13" osisID="2Sam.3.13"/> <q>Very well,</q> said David, <q>I will make a pact with you.
       Only, I make one demand upon you: never appear in my presence unless you bring Saul's daughter, Michal,
       when you come to see me.</q> <verse eID="2Sam.3.13"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.3.14" osisID="2Sam.3.14"/> Thereupon David sent messengers to Ishbaal, Saul's son,
       saying, <q>Hand me over my wife Michal, whom I bought for a hundred Philistine foreskins.</q> <verse eID="2Sam.3.14"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.3.15" osisID="2Sam.3.15"/> Ishbaal sent and took her away from her husband Paltiel the
       son of Laish. <verse eID="2Sam.3.15"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.3.16" osisID="2Sam.3.16"/> Her husband followed her, crying all the way, as far as
       Bahurim; then Abner said to him, <q>Back you go!</q> And back he went. <verse eID="2Sam.3.16"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="2Sam.3.17" osisID="2Sam.3.17"/> Now Abner had been in com­munication with the sheikhs of
       Israel, saying, <q>You have long wanted David as your king; <verse eID="2Sam.3.17"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.3.18" osisID="2Sam.3.18"/> now act! The Eternal has promised David, <q>By the hand of my
       servant David I will res­cue my people Israel from the power of the Philistines and from the power of all
       their enemies!</q></q> <verse eID="2Sam.3.18"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.3.19" osisID="2Sam.3.19"/> Abner also talked to the Benjamites, and then Abner went away
       to Hebron to tell David all that Israel and the whole house of Benjamin had determined to do. <verse eID="2Sam.3.19"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="2Sam.3.20" osisID="2Sam.3.20"/> When Abner came to David at Hebron, accompanied by twenty men,
       David held a feast for Ab­ner and his men. <verse eID="2Sam.3.20"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.3.21" osisID="2Sam.3.21"/> Abner said to David, <q>I will be off to rally all Israel
       round my lord the king, that they may make a compact with you, and that you may reign as far as you
       please.</q> So David dismissed Abner, who went off in peace. <verse eID="2Sam.3.21"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="2Sam.3.22" osisID="2Sam.3.22"/> Just then the followers of David came in with Joab from a
       raid, bringing rich spoil with them. Abner was not with David at Hebron, for David had dismissed him,
       and he had gone in peace. <verse eID="2Sam.3.22"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.3.23" osisID="2Sam.3.23"/> But when Joab and all his force arrived, and when Joab was
       told that Abner the son of Ner had come to the king, and that the king had dismissed him in peace, <verse eID="2Sam.3.23"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.3.24" osisID="2Sam.3.24"/> Joab went and said to the king, <q>What is this you have done?
       Here Abner came to you! Why have you dismissed him, and let him get clean away? <verse eID="2Sam.3.24"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.3.25" osisID="2Sam.3.25"/> You know quite well that Abner the son of Ner came only to
       deceive you, to note your movements, to find out all you were doing!</q> <verse eID="2Sam.3.25"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.3.26" osisID="2Sam.3.26"/> Then Joab left David, and sent mes­sengers after Abner, who
       brought him back from the well at Sirah. (David knew nothing of this.) <verse eID="2Sam.3.26"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="2Sam.3.27" osisID="2Sam.3.27"/> When Abner came back to Hebron, Joab took him apart to the
       side of the town-gate for a quiet talk, and stabbed him there in the belly. So he died for shedding the
       blood of Asahel, Joab's brother. <verse eID="2Sam.3.27"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.3.28" osisID="2Sam.3.28"/> When David afterwards heard of it, he said, <q>I and my
       kingdom are for ever innocent before the Eternal of the murder of Abner the son of Ner. <verse eID="2Sam.3.28"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.3.29" osisID="2Sam.3.29"/>
       May the doom
       <milestone type="pb" n="350"/>
       fall on Joab's head and on all his father’s clan! May Joab's house never lack some one with a running
       issue, or some leper, or some effeminate creature, or a murdered victim, or a poverty-stricken waif!</q>
      <verse eID="2Sam.3.29"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.3.30" osisID="2Sam.3.30"/> [[Joab and his brother Abishai had murdered Abner, because he
       killed their brother Asahel in the battle at Gibeon.]] <verse eID="2Sam.3.30"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.3.31" osisID="2Sam.3.31"/> Then David ordered Joab and all his troops to tear their
       clothes, put on sackcloth, and wail in front of Abner's body. King David followed the bier. <verse eID="2Sam.3.31"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.3.32" osisID="2Sam.3.32"/> So they buried Abner at Hebron; the king wept aloud at Abner's
       grave, and all the troops wept. <verse eID="2Sam.3.32"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.3.33" osisID="2Sam.3.33"/> The king also sang this dirge for Abner:
       <lg>
        <l> Was this how Abner had to die, <l>
        </l> as dies a godless wretch? </l>
      <verse eID="2Sam.3.33"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.3.34" osisID="2Sam.3.34"/>
        <l> Your hands no man did tie, </l>
        <l> none chained your feet!--and then, </l>
        <l> as falls a godless wretch, </l>
        <l> you fell to ruthless men! </l>
       </lg>
      <verse eID="2Sam.3.34"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.3.35" osisID="2Sam.3.35"/> All the troops wept over him again. And when all the troops
       went to urge David to take food before the day closed, David swore, <q>God kill me and worse if I taste
       bread or anything till sunset!</q> <verse eID="2Sam.3.35"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.3.36" osisID="2Sam.3.36"/> All the troops marked this, and it pleased them; like all that
       the king did, it pleased all the troops; <verse eID="2Sam.3.36"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.3.37" osisID="2Sam.3.37"/> all the troops and all Israel were then con­vinced that the
       king had noth­ing to do with the murder of Abner the son of Ner. <verse eID="2Sam.3.37"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.3.38" osisID="2Sam.3.38"/> The king said to his officers, <q>Do you not know that a
       prince, a great man, has fallen in Israel to-day? <verse eID="2Sam.3.38"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.3.39" osisID="2Sam.3.39"/> Yet, though he was a royal relative and officer, these sons of
       Zeruiah were too much for him. May the Eternal re­quite the wrongdoer for the wrong he did!</q> <verse eID="2Sam.3.39"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eID="2Sam.3"/>
    <chapter osisID="2Sam.4" sID="2Sam.4"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="2Sam.4.1" osisID="2Sam.4.1"/>When Saul’s son, Ishbaal, heard that Abner had died at Hebron,
       he lost heart, and all the Israelites were alarmed. <verse eID="2Sam.4.1"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.4.2" osisID="2Sam.4.2"/> He had two men who were captains of guerilla bands, one called
       Baanah and the other Recliab, sons of Rimmon the Beerothite, who belonged to the Benjamites (Beeroth is
       included in Benjamin, <verse eID="2Sam.4.2"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.4.3" osisID="2Sam.4.3"/> but the Beerothites fled to Gittaim, where they are resident
       aliens to this day). <verse eID="2Sam.4.3"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.4.4" osisID="2Sam.4.4"/> [[Jonathan, Saul's son, had a son whose feet were lame. He was
       five years old when the news came from Jezreel about Saul and Jona­than; so his nurse caught him up and
       fled. But as she hurried, he fell and became lame. His name was Mephibosheth.]] <verse eID="2Sam.4.4"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.4.5" osisID="2Sam.4.5"/> Well, the sons of Rimmon the Beerothite, Rechab and Baanah, went
       about midday to the house of Ishbaal, where he was taking his siesta at noon. <verse eID="2Sam.4.5"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.4.6-2Sam.4.7" osisID="2Sam.4.6 2Sam.4.7"/> The door-keeper of the palace, a woman who had
       been cleaning wheat, was drowsy and asleep; so Re­chab and his brother Baanah slipped into the palace,
       and stabbed Ishbaal to death as he lay in bed within his chamber; after beheading him, they took his head
       and made their way all night through the wady of Arabah. <verse eID="2Sam.4.6-2Sam.4.7"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.4.8" osisID="2Sam.4.8"/> They brought Ishbaal's head to David at Hebron, say­ing to the
       king, <q>Here is the head of Ishbaal the son of your enemy Saul, who sought your life! This day has the
       Eternal avenged my lord the king on Saul and his offspring!</q> <verse eID="2Sam.4.8"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.4.9" osisID="2Sam.4.9"/> But David said to Rechab and his brother Baanah, the sons of
       Rimmon the Beeroth­ite, <q>By the life of the Eternal, who has rescued me from every strait!--<verse eID="2Sam.4.9"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.4.10" osisID="2Sam.4.10"/> when a man told me, <q>Saul is dead!</q> supposing he had
       brought good news, I seized him and killed him at Ziklag; that was the reward I gave him for
       <milestone type="pb" n="351"/>
       his good news! <verse eID="2Sam.4.10"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.4.11" osisID="2Sam.4.11"/> And now, when scoundrels have murdered an honest man in bed
       within his own house, how much more shall I requite you murderers and wipe you off the earth?</q> <verse eID="2Sam.4.11"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.4.12" osisID="2Sam.4.12"/> Then David gave orders to his young men, who killed them, cut
       off their heads and feet, and hung them up beside the reservoir at Hebron. Ishbaal's head they took and
       buried in Abner’s grave at Hebron. <verse eID="2Sam.4.12"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eID="2Sam.4"/>
    <chapter osisID="2Sam.5" sID="2Sam.5"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="2Sam.5.1" osisID="2Sam.5.1"/>[[Then all the clans of Israel came to David at Hebron and said, <q>Here we are, your own bone and
       flesh! <verse eID="2Sam.5.1"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.5.2" osisID="2Sam.5.2"/> In bygone days, when Saul was king, it was you who led Israel out and in; the Eternal said to you,
       <q>You shall shepherd my people Israel, you shall be prince over Israel!</q></q>]] <verse eID="2Sam.5.2"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.5.3" osisID="2Sam.5.3"/> Then all the sheikhs of Israel came to the king at Hebron, and king David made a compact with them at
       Hebron in presence of the Eternal, and they anointed David king over Israel. <verse eID="2Sam.5.3"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.5.4" osisID="2Sam.5.4"/> [[David was thirty years old when he began to reign, and he reigned for forty years. <verse eID="2Sam.5.4"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.5.5" osisID="2Sam.5.5"/> He reigned over Judah at Hebron for seven years and six months; then in Jerusalem he reigned over all
       Israel and Judah for thirty-three years and six months.]] <verse eID="2Sam.5.5"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="2Sam.5.17" osisID="2Sam.5.17"/> When the Philistines heard that David had been anointed king over Israel, all the Philistines marched
       up in search of David. But David heard of it and went down to his stronghold. <verse eID="2Sam.5.17"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.5.18" osisID="2Sam.5.18"/> Meantime the Philistines had gone raiding through the valley of Ephraim. <verse eID="2Sam.5.18"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.5.19" osisID="2Sam.5.19"/> So David asked the Eternal, <q>Shall I attack the Philistines? Wilt thou put them into my hands?</q>
       The Eternal said to David, <q>Attack them, I will certainly put the Philistines into your hands.</q> <verse eID="2Sam.5.19"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.5.20" osisID="2Sam.5.20"/> Then David went to Baal-perazim and broke them there. <q>The Eternal has broken my foes down before me
       like water bursting a dam!</q> said David, and he called the spot Baal-perazim (or <q>lord of bursts</q>). <verse eID="2Sam.5.20"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.5.21" osisID="2Sam.5.21"/> The Philistines left their gods 21 behind them there, and David and his men carried them off. <verse eID="2Sam.5.21"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.5.22" osisID="2Sam.5.22"/> Back came the Philistines to the attack, raiding through the valley of Rephaim. <verse eID="2Sam.5.22"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.5.23" osisID="2Sam.5.23"/> When David consulted the Eternal, he was told, <q>You must not march against them; get round to the
       rear of them and attack them in front of the balsam-trees. <verse eID="2Sam.5.23"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.5.24" osisID="2Sam.5.24"/> Whenever you hear a sound of movement among the tops of the balsam-trees, be quick and attack, for the
       Eternal will have gone in front of you to rout the Philistine army.</q> <verse eID="2Sam.5.24"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.5.25" osisID="2Sam.5.25"/> David did as the Eternal ordered him, and routed the Philistines from Geba as far as Gezer. <verse eID="2Sam.5.25"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eID="2Sam.5"/>
   </div>