   <div type="book" osisID="2Sam">
    <milestone type="pb" n="346"/>
    <chapter osisID="2Sam.1" sID="2Sam.1"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="2Sam.1.1" osisID="2Sam.1.1"/>After the death of Saul, when David had come back from slaying the
       Amalekites and had been for two days at Ziklag, <verse eID="2Sam.1.1"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.1.2" osisID="2Sam.1.2"/> on the third day a man came from Saul's camp with his clothes
       torn and earth scattered on his head. When he reached David, he fell to the ground and did obeisance. <verse eID="2Sam.1.2"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.1.3" osisID="2Sam.1.3"/> David said to him, <q>Where do you come from?</q> <q>I have
       escaped from the camp of Israel,</q> said he. <verse eID="2Sam.1.3"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.1.4" osisID="2Sam.1.4"/> Then David asked him, <q>Tell me, how did things go?</q>
       He replied, <q>The troops ran away from the fight, many of the troops have fallen, and Saul and his son
       Jonathan are also dead.</q> <verse eID="2Sam.1.4"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.1.5" osisID="2Sam.1.5"/> [[David said to the young man who told him, <q>How do you know
       that Saul and his son Jonathan are dead?</q> <verse eID="2Sam.1.5"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.1.6" osisID="2Sam.1.6"/> And the young man who told him said, <q>I happened to be on mount
       Gilboa, and there was Saul leaning on his spear! The chariots and cavalry were close upon him. <verse eID="2Sam.1.6"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.1.7" osisID="2Sam.1.7"/> When he looked behind him, he saw me and called to me. I
       answered, <q>Here I am.</q> <verse eID="2Sam.1.7"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.1.8" osisID="2Sam.1.8"/> He said to me, <q>Who are you?</q> I said to him, <q>I am an
       Amalekite.</q> <verse eID="2Sam.1.8"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.1.9" osisID="2Sam.1.9"/> Then he said to me, <q>Stand over me and des­patch me, for it is
       dizziness that has seized me--I am quite unwounded!</q> <verse eID="2Sam.1.9"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.1.10" osisID="2Sam.1.10"/> So I stood over him and killed him, for I was sure he could not
       live after he had fallen. I took the crown from his head and the armlet from his arm, and I have brought
       them here to my lord.</q>]] <verse eID="2Sam.1.10"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="2Sam.1.11" osisID="2Sam.1.11"/> Then David caught his clothes and tore them; so did all the men
       with him; <verse eID="2Sam.1.11"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.1.12" osisID="2Sam.1.12"/> they lamented and wept and fasted till evening for Saul and his
       son Jonathan and the army of Judah and the house of Israel, because they had fallen by the sword. <verse eID="2Sam.1.12"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.1.13" osisID="2Sam.1.13"/> [[David said to the young man who told him, <q>Where do you
       come from?</q> <q>I am the son of a resident alien,</q> he said, <q>an Amalekite.</q> <verse eID="2Sam.1.13"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.1.14" osisID="2Sam.1.14"/> And David said to him, <q>Why were you not afraid to lift your
       hand to de­stroy the Eternal's anointed?</q> <verse eID="2Sam.1.14"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.1.15" osisID="2Sam.1.15"/> Then David called one of the young men and said, <q>Go up to
       him and strike him down.</q> Then he felled the Amalekite, so that he died. <verse eID="2Sam.1.15"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.1.16" osisID="2Sam.1.16"/> <q>Your blood be on your own head,</q> said David; <q>your own
       lips have borne witness against you, when you said, <q>I slew the Eternal’s anointed!</q></q>]] <verse eID="2Sam.1.16"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="2Sam.1.17" osisID="2Sam.1.17"/> Then David sang this dirge over Saul and his son Jonathan <verse eID="2Sam.1.17"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.1.18" osisID="2Sam.1.18"/> (it is written in the Book of Heroes); he said:
       <lg>
        <l> O Judah, to your crying! </l>
        <l> O Israel, to your grief and woe! </l>
      <verse eID="2Sam.1.18"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.1.19" osisID="2Sam.1.19"/>
        <l> On your battle-fields the slain are lying. </l>
        <l> and heroes, alas! fallen low. </l>
      <verse eID="2Sam.1.19"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.1.20" osisID="2Sam.1.20"/>
        <l> Tell it not in Gath,</l>
        <l> proclaim it not in Ashkelon's streets,</l>
        <l> lest the daughters of the Philis­tines rejoice,</l>
        <l> lest the daughters of the uncir­cumcised exult.</l>
      <verse eID="2Sam.1.20"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.1.21" osisID="2Sam.1.21"/>
        <l> Dew never fall on you, hills of Gilboa, </l>
        <l> rain never reach you, O death's own field </l>
        <l> For there a hero dropped his shield, </l>
        <l> Saul's shield, the armour of the anointed. </l>
      <verse eID="2Sam.1.21"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.1.22" osisID="2Sam.1.22"/>
        <l> From the blood of the slain, </l>
        <l> from the flesh of the mighty, </l>
        <l> never did Jonathan’s bow turn back, </l>
        <l> nor the sword of Saul unsated. </l>
      <verse eID="2Sam.1.22"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.1.23" osisID="2Sam.1.23"/>
        <l> Saul and Jonathan, loved and lovely, </l>
       <milestone type="pb" n="347"/>
        <l> never divided in life or in death!-- </l>
        <l> swifter than eagles, stronger than lions! </l>
      <verse eID="2Sam.1.23"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.1.24" osisID="2Sam.1.24"/>
        <l> Daughters of Israel, wail for Saul, </l>
        <l> who decked you in scarlet and jewels, </l>
        <l> who adorned your robes with gold! </l>
      <verse eID="2Sam.1.24"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.1.25" osisID="2Sam.1.25"/>
        <l> Alas for heroes fallen low </l>
        <l> in the thick of the fray </l>
      <verse eID="2Sam.1.25"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.1.26" osisID="2Sam.1.26"/>
        <l> Jonathan slain in the field of battle, </l>
        <l> my heart is sore for you, </l>
        <l> O Jonathan, my brother! </l>
        <l> You were my dear delight, </l>
        <l> your love for me was a wonder, </l>
        <l> far beyond a woman’s love. </l>
      <verse eID="2Sam.1.26"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.1.27" osisID="2Sam.1.27"/>
        <l> Alas for heroes fallen low, </l>
        <l> for weapons that once felled the foe! </l>
       </lg>
      <verse eID="2Sam.1.27"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eID="2Sam.1"/>
    <chapter osisID="2Sam.2" sID="2Sam.2"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="2Sam.2.1" osisID="2Sam.2.1"/>After this David asked the Eternal, <q>Shall I go up to one of the
       towns of Judah?</q> The Eternal said to him, <q>Go up.</q> Then David said, <q>Where shall I go up?</q>
       <q>To Hebron,</q> the Eternal answered. <verse eID="2Sam.2.1"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.2.2" osisID="2Sam.2.2"/> So David went up, along with his two wives, Ahinoam the
       Jezreelitess and Abigail who had been the wife of Nabal the Karmelite. <verse eID="2Sam.2.2"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.2.3" osisID="2Sam.2.3"/> David also took the men who were with him, every man and his
       household, and they stayed in the citadel of Hebron; <verse eID="2Sam.2.3"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.2.4" osisID="2Sam.2.4"/> then the men of Judah came and anointed David there as king over
       the house of Judah. <verse eID="2Sam.2.4"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="2Sam.2.5" osisID="2Sam.2.5"/> When David was told that it was the men of Jabesh-gilead who had
       buried Saul, he sent messengers to the leading men of Jabesh-gilead, saying, <verse eID="2Sam.2.5"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.2.6" osisID="2Sam.2.6"/> <q>The Eter­nal's blessing be on you for hav­ing done this
       kindness to your lord Saul in burying him! So may the Eternal be kind and true to you! And I will be good
       to you for having done this. <verse eID="2Sam.2.6"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.2.7" osisID="2Sam.2.7"/> Courage then, be brave! Saul your lord is dead, but the house of
       Judah has anointed me to be their king.</q> <verse eID="2Sam.2.7"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="2Sam.2.8" osisID="2Sam.2.8"/> Now Abner the son of Ner, commander of Saul's army, had taken
       Saul's son Ishbaal across to Mahanaim, <verse eID="2Sam.2.8"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.2.9" osisID="2Sam.2.9"/> where he made him king over Gilead, the Asherites, Jezreel,
       Ephraim, and Ben­jamin, in fact over all Israel. <verse eID="2Sam.2.9"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.2.10" osisID="2Sam.2.10"/> Only the house of Judah adhered to David. [[Ishbaal, Saul's
       son, was forty years old when he began to reign over Israel, and he reigned two years. <verse eID="2Sam.2.10"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.2.11" osisID="2Sam.2.11"/> The time during which David reigned at Hebron over the house
       of Judah was seven years and six months.]] <verse eID="2Sam.2.11"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.2.12" osisID="2Sam.2.12"/> Then Abner the son of Ner and the adherents of Ishbaal the son
       of Saul marched from Mahanaim to Gibeon; <verse eID="2Sam.2.12"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.2.13" osisID="2Sam.2.13"/> Joab the son of Zerulah and David's adherents also marched out,
       and met them at the reser­voir of Gibeon. The two par­ties sat down, one on the one side of the reservoir
       and the other on the other side. <verse eID="2Sam.2.13"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.2.14" osisID="2Sam.2.14"/> Then Abner said to Joab, <q>Let the young men get up and have a
       fight before us.</q> <q>Very well,</q> said Joab. <verse eID="2Sam.2.14"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.2.15" osisID="2Sam.2.15"/> So the young men got up and were numbered off, twelve for
       Benjamin and Ishbaal the son of Saul, and twelve ad­herents of David. <verse eID="2Sam.2.15"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.2.16" osisID="2Sam.2.16"/> Each caught his opponent by the head and stabbed him in the
       side, so that they all dropped together. Hence the spot was called <q>The Field of Sides</q> (it is at
       Gib­eon). <verse eID="2Sam.2.16"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.2.17" osisID="2Sam.2.17"/> That day the fight that followed was most fierce, but Abner the
       son of Ner and the men of Israel were beaten by the adherents of David. <verse eID="2Sam.2.17"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="2Sam.2.18" osisID="2Sam.2.18"/> Zeruiah's three sons were there, Joab, Abishai, and Asahel.
       Asahel was swift-footed as a wild deer; <verse eID="2Sam.2.18"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.2.19" osisID="2Sam.2.19"/> so Asahel chased Abner, and as he ran he never turned
       <milestone type="pb" n="348"/>
       to right or left in his pursuit of Abner. <verse eID="2Sam.2.19"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.2.20" osisID="2Sam.2.20"/> Then Abner glanced behind him and said, <q>Is that you,
       Asahel?</q> <q>Yes,</q> he answered. <verse eID="2Sam.2.20"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.2.21" osisID="2Sam.2.21"/> So Abner said to him, <q>Turn to your right or to your left,
       catch one of the young men and take his spoil.</q> But Asahel would not turn aside from his chase. <verse eID="2Sam.2.21"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.2.22" osisID="2Sam.2.22"/> Then Abner again said to Asahel, <q>Turn aside from following
       me; why should I strike you down? How could I look your brother Joab in the face after that?</q> <verse eID="2Sam.2.22"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.2.23" osisID="2Sam.2.23"/> But he would not turn aside. So Abner gave him a backward
       stroke in the belly, the spear came out at his back, and he dropped dead on the spot. [[Everyone who came
       to the spot where Asahel had dropped dead, stopped there.l] <verse eID="2Sam.2.23"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="2Sam.2.24" osisID="2Sam.2.24"/> Joab and Abishai pursued Ab­ner, and, as the sun was setting,
       they reached the hill of Ammah, east of the road through the open country of Gibeon, <verse eID="2Sam.2.24"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.2.25" osisID="2Sam.2.25"/> where the Benjamites gathered behind Abner in a solid phalanx
       drawn up on the top of the hill of Ammah. <verse eID="2Sam.2.25"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.2.26" osisID="2Sam.2.26"/> Abner called to Joab, <q>Is the sword to devour for ever? Do
       you not know the outcome will be bitter? How long will it be before you order the troops to give up
       pursuing their fellow-countrymen?</q> <verse eID="2Sam.2.26"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.2.27" osisID="2Sam.2.27"/> <q>By God’s life!</q> said Joab, <q>unless you had said the
       word, not one of the men would have stopped pursuing his fellow till morning.</q> <verse eID="2Sam.2.27"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.2.28" osisID="2Sam.2.28"/> Then Joab sounded the trumpet, and all the troops stopped; they
       pur­sued Israel no longer, they fought no more. <verse eID="2Sam.2.28"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="2Sam.2.29" osisID="2Sam.2.29"/> All that forenoon Abner and his men made their way through the
       wady of Arabah, crossing the Jordan and pass­ing right through the ravine till they reached Mahanaim. <verse eID="2Sam.2.29"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.2.30" osisID="2Sam.2.30"/> As for Joab, he returned from his pursuit of Abner; when he had
       mustered all the troops, nineteen of David's adherents were missing, besides Asahel, <verse eID="2Sam.2.30"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.2.31" osisID="2Sam.2.31"/> whereas David's adherents had killed three hundred and sixty
       men of Benjamin and of Abner’s army. <verse eID="2Sam.2.31"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.2.32" osisID="2Sam.2.32"/> Asahel they lifted, and buried him in his father's grave at
       Bethlehem. Then Joab and his men marched all night, and the day dawned on them at Hebron. <verse eID="2Sam.2.32"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eID="2Sam.2"/>
    <chapter osisID="2Sam.3" sID="2Sam.3"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="2Sam.3.1" osisID="2Sam.3.1"/>The war between Saul's house and David's house went on; but David
       grew stronger and stronger, while the house of Saul became weaker and weaker. <verse eID="2Sam.3.1"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="2Sam.3.2" osisID="2Sam.3.2"/> Sons were born to David at Hebron: his eldest was Amnon, son of
       Ahinoam the Jezreelitess; <verse eID="2Sam.3.2"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.3.3" osisID="2Sam.3.3"/> his second was Chileab, son of Abigail who had been the wife of
       Nabal the Karmelite; his third was Absalom, son of Maakah, the daughter of Talmai the king of Geshur; <verse eID="2Sam.3.3"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.3.4" osisID="2Sam.3.4"/> his fourth was Adonijah, son of Haggith; his fifth was
       Shephatiah, son of Abital; <verse eID="2Sam.3.4"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.3.5" osisID="2Sam.3.5"/> and his sixth Ithream, son of Eglah . . . These were born to
       David at Hebron. <verse eID="2Sam.3.5"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="2Sam.3.6" osisID="2Sam.3.6"/>During the war between the house of Saul and the house of David,
       Abner strengthened his position in the house of Saul. <verse eID="2Sam.3.6"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.3.7" osisID="2Sam.3.7"/> Thus, Saul had a concubine called Rizpah, the daughter of Aiah,
       and Abner took her. Ishbaal said to Abner, <q>Why have you gone in to my father’s con­cubine?</q> <verse eID="2Sam.3.7"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.3.8" osisID="2Sam.3.8"/> But Abner was furious at what Ishbaal said. <q>Am I the mere
       head of a cur?</q> he asked, <q>I with all my good service to the house of Saul your father, to his
       kinsfolk and
       <milestone type="pb" n="349"/>
       his friends, I who have saved you from the grasp of David, that you find fault with me now about a wench?
      <verse eID="2Sam.3.8"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.3.9" osisID="2Sam.3.9"/> God kill Abner and worse, if I do not help David to what the
       Eternal swore to give him! <verse eID="2Sam.3.9"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.3.10" osisID="2Sam.3.10"/> I will transfer the kingdom from Saul's house, and set up
       David's throne over Israel and Judah, from Dan to Beersheba!</q><verse eID="2Sam.3.10"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="2Sam.3.11" osisID="2Sam.3.11"/>Ishbaal dared not say another word to Abner; he was afraid of
       him. <verse eID="2Sam.3.11"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.3.12" osisID="2Sam.3.12"/> But Abner sent messen­gers to David at Hebron, saying, <q>Make
       a pact with me, and you will get my help in bringing over all Israel to your side.</q> <verse eID="2Sam.3.12"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.3.13" osisID="2Sam.3.13"/> <q>Very well,</q> said David, <q>I will make a pact with you.
       Only, I make one demand upon you: never appear in my presence unless you bring Saul's daughter, Michal,
       when you come to see me.</q> <verse eID="2Sam.3.13"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.3.14" osisID="2Sam.3.14"/> Thereupon David sent messengers to Ishbaal, Saul's son,
       saying, <q>Hand me over my wife Michal, whom I bought for a hundred Philistine foreskins.</q> <verse eID="2Sam.3.14"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.3.15" osisID="2Sam.3.15"/> Ishbaal sent and took her away from her husband Paltiel the
       son of Laish. <verse eID="2Sam.3.15"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.3.16" osisID="2Sam.3.16"/> Her husband followed her, crying all the way, as far as
       Bahurim; then Abner said to him, <q>Back you go!</q> And back he went. <verse eID="2Sam.3.16"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="2Sam.3.17" osisID="2Sam.3.17"/> Now Abner had been in com­munication with the sheikhs of
       Israel, saying, <q>You have long wanted David as your king; <verse eID="2Sam.3.17"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.3.18" osisID="2Sam.3.18"/> now act! The Eternal has promised David, <q>By the hand of my
       servant David I will res­cue my people Israel from the power of the Philistines and from the power of all
       their enemies!</q></q> <verse eID="2Sam.3.18"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.3.19" osisID="2Sam.3.19"/> Abner also talked to the Benjamites, and then Abner went away
       to Hebron to tell David all that Israel and the whole house of Benjamin had determined to do. <verse eID="2Sam.3.19"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="2Sam.3.20" osisID="2Sam.3.20"/> When Abner came to David at Hebron, accompanied by twenty men,
       David held a feast for Ab­ner and his men. <verse eID="2Sam.3.20"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.3.21" osisID="2Sam.3.21"/> Abner said to David, <q>I will be off to rally all Israel
       round my lord the king, that they may make a compact with you, and that you may reign as far as you
       please.</q> So David dismissed Abner, who went off in peace. <verse eID="2Sam.3.21"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="2Sam.3.22" osisID="2Sam.3.22"/> Just then the followers of David came in with Joab from a
       raid, bringing rich spoil with them. Abner was not with David at Hebron, for David had dismissed him,
       and he had gone in peace. <verse eID="2Sam.3.22"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.3.23" osisID="2Sam.3.23"/> But when Joab and all his force arrived, and when Joab was
       told that Abner the son of Ner had come to the king, and that the king had dismissed him in peace, <verse eID="2Sam.3.23"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.3.24" osisID="2Sam.3.24"/> Joab went and said to the king, <q>What is this you have done?
       Here Abner came to you! Why have you dismissed him, and let him get clean away? <verse eID="2Sam.3.24"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.3.25" osisID="2Sam.3.25"/> You know quite well that Abner the son of Ner came only to
       deceive you, to note your movements, to find out all you were doing!</q> <verse eID="2Sam.3.25"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.3.26" osisID="2Sam.3.26"/> Then Joab left David, and sent mes­sengers after Abner, who
       brought him back from the well at Sirah. (David knew nothing of this.) <verse eID="2Sam.3.26"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="2Sam.3.27" osisID="2Sam.3.27"/> When Abner came back to Hebron, Joab took him apart to the
       side of the town-gate for a quiet talk, and stabbed him there in the belly. So he died for shedding the
       blood of Asahel, Joab's brother. <verse eID="2Sam.3.27"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.3.28" osisID="2Sam.3.28"/> When David afterwards heard of it, he said, <q>I and my
       kingdom are for ever innocent before the Eternal of the murder of Abner the son of Ner. <verse eID="2Sam.3.28"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.3.29" osisID="2Sam.3.29"/>
       May the doom
       <milestone type="pb" n="350"/>
       fall on Joab's head and on all his father’s clan! May Joab's house never lack some one with a running
       issue, or some leper, or some effeminate creature, or a murdered victim, or a poverty-stricken waif!</q>
      <verse eID="2Sam.3.29"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.3.30" osisID="2Sam.3.30"/> [[Joab and his brother Abishai had murdered Abner, because he
       killed their brother Asahel in the battle at Gibeon.]] <verse eID="2Sam.3.30"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.3.31" osisID="2Sam.3.31"/> Then David ordered Joab and all his troops to tear their
       clothes, put on sackcloth, and wail in front of Abner's body. King David followed the bier. <verse eID="2Sam.3.31"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.3.32" osisID="2Sam.3.32"/> So they buried Abner at Hebron; the king wept aloud at Abner's
       grave, and all the troops wept. <verse eID="2Sam.3.32"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.3.33" osisID="2Sam.3.33"/> The king also sang this dirge for Abner:
       <lg>
        <l> Was this how Abner had to die, <l>
        </l> as dies a godless wretch? </l>
      <verse eID="2Sam.3.33"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.3.34" osisID="2Sam.3.34"/>
        <l> Your hands no man did tie, </l>
        <l> none chained your feet!--and then, </l>
        <l> as falls a godless wretch, </l>
        <l> you fell to ruthless men! </l>
       </lg>
      <verse eID="2Sam.3.34"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.3.35" osisID="2Sam.3.35"/> All the troops wept over him again. And when all the troops
       went to urge David to take food before the day closed, David swore, <q>God kill me and worse if I taste
       bread or anything till sunset!</q> <verse eID="2Sam.3.35"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.3.36" osisID="2Sam.3.36"/> All the troops marked this, and it pleased them; like all that
       the king did, it pleased all the troops; <verse eID="2Sam.3.36"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.3.37" osisID="2Sam.3.37"/> all the troops and all Israel were then con­vinced that the
       king had noth­ing to do with the murder of Abner the son of Ner. <verse eID="2Sam.3.37"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.3.38" osisID="2Sam.3.38"/> The king said to his officers, <q>Do you not know that a
       prince, a great man, has fallen in Israel to-day? <verse eID="2Sam.3.38"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.3.39" osisID="2Sam.3.39"/> Yet, though he was a royal relative and officer, these sons of
       Zeruiah were too much for him. May the Eternal re­quite the wrongdoer for the wrong he did!</q> <verse eID="2Sam.3.39"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eID="2Sam.3"/>
    <chapter osisID="2Sam.4" sID="2Sam.4"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="2Sam.4.1" osisID="2Sam.4.1"/>When Saul’s son, Ishbaal, heard that Abner had died at Hebron,
       he lost heart, and all the Israelites were alarmed. <verse eID="2Sam.4.1"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.4.2" osisID="2Sam.4.2"/> He had two men who were captains of guerilla bands, one called
       Baanah and the other Recliab, sons of Rimmon the Beerothite, who belonged to the Benjamites (Beeroth is
       included in Benjamin, <verse eID="2Sam.4.2"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.4.3" osisID="2Sam.4.3"/> but the Beerothites fled to Gittaim, where they are resident
       aliens to this day). <verse eID="2Sam.4.3"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.4.4" osisID="2Sam.4.4"/> [[Jonathan, Saul's son, had a son whose feet were lame. He was
       five years old when the news came from Jezreel about Saul and Jona­than; so his nurse caught him up and
       fled. But as she hurried, he fell and became lame. His name was Mephibosheth.]] <verse eID="2Sam.4.4"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.4.5" osisID="2Sam.4.5"/> Well, the sons of Rimmon the Beerothite, Rechab and Baanah, went
       about midday to the house of Ishbaal, where he was taking his siesta at noon. <verse eID="2Sam.4.5"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.4.6-2Sam.4.7" osisID="2Sam.4.6 2Sam.4.7"/> The door-keeper of the palace, a woman who had
       been cleaning wheat, was drowsy and asleep; so Re­chab and his brother Baanah slipped into the palace,
       and stabbed Ishbaal to death as he lay in bed within his chamber; after beheading him, they took his head
       and made their way all night through the wady of Arabah. <verse eID="2Sam.4.6-2Sam.4.7"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.4.8" osisID="2Sam.4.8"/> They brought Ishbaal's head to David at Hebron, say­ing to the
       king, <q>Here is the head of Ishbaal the son of your enemy Saul, who sought your life! This day has the
       Eternal avenged my lord the king on Saul and his offspring!</q> <verse eID="2Sam.4.8"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.4.9" osisID="2Sam.4.9"/> But David said to Rechab and his brother Baanah, the sons of
       Rimmon the Beeroth­ite, <q>By the life of the Eternal, who has rescued me from every strait!--<verse eID="2Sam.4.9"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.4.10" osisID="2Sam.4.10"/> when a man told me, <q>Saul is dead!</q> supposing he had
       brought good news, I seized him and killed him at Ziklag; that was the reward I gave him for
       <milestone type="pb" n="351"/>
       his good news! <verse eID="2Sam.4.10"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.4.11" osisID="2Sam.4.11"/> And now, when scoundrels have murdered an honest man in bed
       within his own house, how much more shall I requite you murderers and wipe you off the earth?</q> <verse eID="2Sam.4.11"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.4.12" osisID="2Sam.4.12"/> Then David gave orders to his young men, who killed them, cut
       off their heads and feet, and hung them up beside the reservoir at Hebron. Ishbaal's head they took and
       buried in Abner’s grave at Hebron. <verse eID="2Sam.4.12"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eID="2Sam.4"/>
    <chapter osisID="2Sam.5" sID="2Sam.5"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="2Sam.5.1" osisID="2Sam.5.1"/>[[Then all the clans of Israel came to David at Hebron and said, <q>Here we are, your own bone and
       flesh! <verse eID="2Sam.5.1"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.5.2" osisID="2Sam.5.2"/> In bygone days, when Saul was king, it was you who led Israel out and in; the Eternal said to you,
       <q>You shall shepherd my people Israel, you shall be prince over Israel!</q></q>]] <verse eID="2Sam.5.2"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.5.3" osisID="2Sam.5.3"/> Then all the sheikhs of Israel came to the king at Hebron, and king David made a compact with them at
       Hebron in presence of the Eternal, and they anointed David king over Israel. <verse eID="2Sam.5.3"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.5.4" osisID="2Sam.5.4"/> [[David was thirty years old when he began to reign, and he reigned for forty years. <verse eID="2Sam.5.4"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.5.5" osisID="2Sam.5.5"/> He reigned over Judah at Hebron for seven years and six months; then in Jerusalem he reigned over all
       Israel and Judah for thirty-three years and six months.]] <verse eID="2Sam.5.5"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="2Sam.5.17" osisID="2Sam.5.17"/> When the Philistines heard that David had been anointed king over Israel, all the Philistines marched
       up in search of David. But David heard of it and went down to his stronghold. <verse eID="2Sam.5.17"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.5.18" osisID="2Sam.5.18"/> Meantime the Philistines had gone raiding through the valley of Ephraim. <verse eID="2Sam.5.18"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.5.19" osisID="2Sam.5.19"/> So David asked the Eternal, <q>Shall I attack the Philistines? Wilt thou put them into my hands?</q>
       The Eternal said to David, <q>Attack them, I will certainly put the Philistines into your hands.</q> <verse eID="2Sam.5.19"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.5.20" osisID="2Sam.5.20"/> Then David went to Baal-perazim and broke them there. <q>The Eternal has broken my foes down before me
       like water bursting a dam!</q> said David, and he called the spot Baal-perazim (or <q>lord of bursts</q>). <verse eID="2Sam.5.20"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.5.21" osisID="2Sam.5.21"/> The Philistines left their gods 21 behind them there, and David and his men carried them off. <verse eID="2Sam.5.21"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.5.22" osisID="2Sam.5.22"/> Back came the Philistines to the attack, raiding through the valley of Rephaim. <verse eID="2Sam.5.22"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.5.23" osisID="2Sam.5.23"/> When David consulted the Eternal, he was told, <q>You must not march against them; get round to the
       rear of them and attack them in front of the balsam-trees. <verse eID="2Sam.5.23"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.5.24" osisID="2Sam.5.24"/> Whenever you hear a sound of movement among the tops of the balsam-trees, be quick and attack, for the
       Eternal will have gone in front of you to rout the Philistine army.</q> <verse eID="2Sam.5.24"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.5.25" osisID="2Sam.5.25"/> David did as the Eternal ordered him, and routed the Philistines from Geba as far as Gezer. <verse eID="2Sam.5.25"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eID="2Sam.5"/>
    <chapter osisID="2Sam.21" sID="2Sam.21"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="2Sam.21.15" osisID="2Sam.21.15"/>Again the Philistines were at war with Israel. When David went down with his troops to camp at Gob
       and fought the Philistines, <verse eID="2Sam.21.15"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.21.16" osisID="2Sam.21.16"/> up started ... a descendant of the giant-race; his bronze helmet weighed over twelve pounds, he
       carried a club, and he meant to kill David. <verse eID="2Sam.21.16"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.21.17" osisID="2Sam.21.17"/> However, Abishai, the son of Zerulah, came to the rescue and struck the Philistine down dead. Then
       David's men swore, <q>You must never again go into battle with us; you must not let Israel’s lamp be extinguished!</q> <verse eID="2Sam.21.17"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="2Sam.21.18" osisID="2Sam.21.18"/>After this there was another fight with the Philistines at Gob, where Sibbeehai the Hushathite
       killed Saph, a descendant of the giant-race. <verse eID="2Sam.21.18"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.21.19" osisID="2Sam.21.19"/> There was another fight with the
       <milestone type="pb" n="352"/>
       Philistines at Gob, when Elhanan the son of Jair, the Bethlehemite, killed Goliath the Gittite, whose spear had a shaft like a weaver’s beam. <verse eID="2Sam.21.19"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.21.20" osisID="2Sam.21.20"/> There was another fight at Gath, where a huge man, with six fingers on each hand and six toes on
       each foot, another descendant of the giant-race, <verse eID="2Sam.21.20"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.21.21" osisID="2Sam.21.21"/>defied Israel; but David's nephew Jonathan, the son of Shimei, killed him. <verse eID="2Sam.21.21"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.21.22" osisID="2Sam.21.22"/> These four were descendants of the giant-race in Gath, and they fell by the hand of David and his
       officers. <verse eID="2Sam.21.22"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eID="2Sam.21"/>
    <chapter osisID="2Sam.6" sID="2Sam.6"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="2Sam.6.1" osisID="2Sam.6.1"/>Then David again mustered O all the picked men of Israel, thirty thousand of them,
      <verse eID="2Sam.6.1"/>
    <chapter eID="2Sam.6"/>
    <chapter osisID="2Sam.5" sID="2Sam.5"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.5.6" osisID="2Sam.5.6"/>and the king and his men went to Jerusalem against the Jebusites, the natives of the country. They told
       David, <q>You will never get in here, blind men and cripples could drive you off!</q> (They thought David would never get in. <verse eID="2Sam.5.6"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.5.7" osisID="2Sam.5.7"/> But David did capture the stronghold of Sion--which is David’s burg). <verse eID="2Sam.5.7"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.5.8" osisID="2Sam.5.8"/> David’s orders for the day were, <q>Whoever strikes down a Jebusite is liable to death! David has no
       feud with <q>blind men and cripples</q>!</q>
       (Hence the injunction, <q>blind men and cripples shall not enter the temple.</q>) <verse eID="2Sam.5.8"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.5.9" osisID="2Sam.5.9"/> David took up his residence in the stronghold; he called it <q>David's burg,</q> and built a wall round
       the town, starting from the Millo rampart, and also round his own residence. <verse eID="2Sam.5.9"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.5.10" osisID="2Sam.5.10"/> David became greater and greater, for the Eternal, God of hosts, was on his side; <verse eID="2Sam.5.10"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.5.11" osisID="2Sam.5.11"/> and when Hiram the king of Tyre sent messengers to David with cedar logs, carpenters, and masons, who
       built a palace for him, <verse eID="2Sam.5.11"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.5.12" osisID="2Sam.5.12"/> David realized that the Eternal had set him to be king over Israel and had exalted his kingdom for the
       sake of his people Israel. <verse eID="2Sam.5.12"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="2Sam.5.13" osisID="2Sam.5.13"/> After David came from Hebron, he took more concubines and wives in Jerusalem, and more sons and
       daughters were born to David. <verse eID="2Sam.5.13"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.5.14" osisID="2Sam.5.14"/> The following are the names of those born to him in Jerusalem: Shammua, Shobab, Nathan, Solomon,
       <verse eID="2Sam.5.14"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.5.15" osisID="2Sam.5.15"/>Ibhar, Elishua, Nepheg, Japhia, <verse eID="2Sam.5.15"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.5.16" osisID="2Sam.5.16"/>Elishama, Eliada, and Eliphelet. <verse eID="2Sam.5.16"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eID="2Sam.5"/>
    <chapter osisID="2Sam.6" sID="2Sam.6"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="2Sam.6.2" osisID="2Sam.6.2"/>Then David and all the troops with him started for Baal-judah to bring up the ark of God, which belongs
       to the Lord of hosts who sits enthroned upon the kherubs. <verse eID="2Sam.6.2"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.6.3" osisID="2Sam.6.3"/> They placed the ark of God on a new cart, and brought it from the house of Abinadab on the hill, with
       Uzza and Ahio, the sons of Abinadab, leading the cart, <verse eID="2Sam.6.3"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.6.4" osisID="2Sam.6.4"/> Uzza walking beside the ark while Ahio went in front. <verse eID="2Sam.6.4"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.6.5" osisID="2Sam.6.5"/> David and all the house of Israel were dancing lustily before the Eternal and singing with lutes, with
       lyres, with drums, with rattles, and with cymbals. <verse eID="2Sam.6.5"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.6.6" osisID="2Sam.6.6"/> But when they reached the threshing-floor of Nachon, Uzza put out his hand to the ark of God and caught
       hold of it, because the oxen were slipping; <verse eID="2Sam.6.6"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.6.7" osisID="2Sam.6.7"/> then the anger of the Eternal blazed out against Uzza. God struck him down on the spot ... he died on
       the spot beside the ark of God. <verse eID="2Sam.6.7"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.6.8" osisID="2Sam.6.8"/> David was angry because the Eternal had broken out upon Uzza, and he called the spot Perez-uzza or
       <q>Breaking of Uzza</q>--as it still is called to this day. <verse eID="2Sam.6.8"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.6.9" osisID="2Sam.6.9"/> David was afraid of the Eternal that day; he said, <q>How can the Eternal’s ark ever come to me?</q>
      <verse eID="2Sam.6.9"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.6.10" osisID="2Sam.6.10"/> So David
       <milestone type="pb" n="353"/>
       was unwilling to take the Eternal's ark into David's burg; he took it aside to the house of Obed-edom the Gittite.<verse eID="2Sam.6.10"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="2Sam.6.11" osisID="2Sam.6.11"/> In the house of Obed-edom the Gittite the Eternal's ark remained for three months, and the Eternal
       blessed Obed-edom and all his household. <verse eID="2Sam.6.11"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.6.12" osisID="2Sam.6.12"/> Now when king David was told that the Eternal had blessed the household of Obed-edom and all that
       belonged to him, on account of the ark of God, David went and brought the ark of God up from Obed-edom's house to David's burg joyfully; <verse eID="2Sam.6.12"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.6.13" osisID="2Sam.6.13"/> as soon as the bearers of the Eternal's ark had gone six steps, he sacrificed an ox and a fatling;
      <verse eID="2Sam.6.13"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.6.14" osisID="2Sam.6.14"/> David whirled before the Eternal with all his might in the dance, wearing only a linen kilt round his
       middle; <verse eID="2Sam.6.14"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.6.15" osisID="2Sam.6.15"/> this was how David and all the house of Israel brought up the Eternal's ark with shouts and blasts of
       the trumpet. <verse eID="2Sam.6.15"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="2Sam.6.16" osisID="2Sam.6.16"/> As the Eternal's ark entered David's burg, Saul's daughter Michal looked out of the window; and when
       she saw king David leaping and whirling about in the dance before the Eternal, she despised him in her heart. <verse eID="2Sam.6.16"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.6.17" osisID="2Sam.6.17"/> After bringing in the ark of the Eternal, they put it in its place, inside the tent pitched for it by
       David; David sacrificed burnt-offerings and recompense-offerings before the Eternal, <verse eID="2Sam.6.17"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.6.18" osisID="2Sam.6.18"/> and, when he had finished sacrificing the burnt-offerings and recompense-offerings, he blessed the
       people in the name of the Eternal of hosts <verse eID="2Sam.6.18"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.6.19" osisID="2Sam.6.19"/> and distributed food among all the people, among the whole multitude of Israel, both men and women,
       giving each a cake of bread, a slice of meat, and a bunch of raisins. Then the people all went home. <verse eID="2Sam.6.19"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.6.20" osisID="2Sam.6.20"/> David went home to greet his family, but Saul's daughter Michal came out to meet David, saying,
       <q>Fine honour did the king of Israel gain to-day, exposing himself before women, before his own menials, as any loose fellow would expose
       himself indecently!</q> <verse eID="2Sam.6.20"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.6.21" osisID="2Sam.6.21"/> David said to Michal, <q>It was in the Eternal’s presence that I was dancing! Blessed be the Eternal,
       who chose me rather than your father or any of his family, appointing me prince over Israel the people of the Eternal! When I sport in the
       Eternal's presence, <verse eID="2Sam.6.21"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.6.22" osisID="2Sam.6.22"/> I count myself too humble for that honour!--I am not honouring myself! And I am to seek honour from
       the menials you mention--from slave-girls like these?</q> <verse eID="2Sam.6.22"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.6.23" osisID="2Sam.6.23"/> So, to the day of her death, Saul's daughter Michal had no children. <verse eID="2Sam.6.23"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eID="2Sam.6"/>
    <chapter osisID="2Sam.7" sID="2Sam.7"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="2Sam.7.1" osisID="2Sam.7.1"/>After the king had taken up residence in his palace, and the Eternal had given him rest from his enemies
       all round, <verse eID="2Sam.7.1"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.7.2" osisID="2Sam.7.2"/> the king said to the prophet Nathan, <q>Here I stay in a house of cedar, while God's ark is inside
       the curtains of a tent!</q> <verse eID="2Sam.7.2"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.7.3" osisID="2Sam.7.3"/> Nathan said to the king, <q>Go and do whatever is in your mind, for the Eternal is with you.</q> <verse eID="2Sam.7.3"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.7.4" osisID="2Sam.7.4"/> But that very night the word of the Eternal came to Nathan: <verse eID="2Sam.7.4"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.7.5" osisID="2Sam.7.5"/> <q>Go and give my servant David this message from the Eternal. <q>Are you to build me a temple to stay
       in? <verse eID="2Sam.7.5"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.7.6" osisID="2Sam.7.6"/> I have never stayed in a temple, not from the day that I brought the Israelites out of Egypt down to
       this day; I have always had my Dwelling in a tent. <verse eID="2Sam.7.6"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.7.7" osisID="2Sam.7.7"/> Wherever I moved with all the Israelites, did I ever ask a single one of Israel's leaders,
       <milestone type="pb" n="354"/>
       whom I ordered to rule my people Israel, why they had not built me a house of cedar?</q> <verse eID="2Sam.7.7"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.7.8" osisID="2Sam.7.8"/> No, give my servant David this message from the Lord of hosts: <q>I took you from the pasture-land, from
       tending sheep, that you should be prince over my people, over Israel; <verse eID="2Sam.7.8"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.7.9" osisID="2Sam.7.9"/> I have been with you wherever you went, to cut off all your enemies before you; and I will make you
       famous like the great men upon earth; <verse eID="2Sam.7.9"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.7.10" osisID="2Sam.7.10"/> I will fix a place for my people Israel and plant them firm within their place, till they are never
       unsettled again--violent men shall no longer distress them as they have done in bygone days, <verse eID="2Sam.7.10"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.7.11" osisID="2Sam.7.11"/> ever since I had to raise up champions for my people Israel: I will give them rest from all their
       enemies.</q> The Eternal also tells you that the Eternal will build up a house, a family for you. <verse eID="2Sam.7.11"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.7.12" osisID="2Sam.7.12"/> <q>When all your days are done and you sleep with your fathers, I will raise your offspring, born of
       your body, and establish their dynasty. <verse eID="2Sam.7.12"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.7.13" osisID="2Sam.7.13"/> [[Your son shall build a temple for my name, and I will establish his royal throne for all time.]] <verse eID="2Sam.7.13"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.7.14" osisID="2Sam.7.14"/>
       <lg>
        <l> To them will I be a father, </l>
        <l> to me they shall be sons; </l>
        <l> when they go astray, </l>
        <l> I will punish them as men are punished, </l>
        <l> with the stripes of the sons of Adam; </l>
      <verse eID="2Sam.7.14"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.7.15" osisID="2Sam.7.15"/>
        <l> but I will not withdraw my kindness from them, </l>
        <l> as I withdrew it from him who was before you; </l>
      <verse eID="2Sam.7.15"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.7.16" osisID="2Sam.7.16"/>
        <l> your house and your kingdom shall stand secure </l>
        <l> before me for all time, </l>
        <l> for all time shall your throne be established. </l>
       </lg></q></q>
      <verse eID="2Sam.7.16"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.7.17" osisID="2Sam.7.17"/> Thus did Nathan speak to David, in terms of all these words and of all this vision. <verse eID="2Sam.7.17"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="2Sam.7.18" osisID="2Sam.7.18"/> Then king David went in and sat down before the Eternal, saying, <q>Who am I, O Lord Eternal, and what
       is my house, that thou hast brought me thus far, Lord Eternal? <verse eID="2Sam.7.18"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.7.19" osisID="2Sam.7.19"/> And thou hast reckoned this a small favour! Thou hast gone on to speak of thy servant's house for
       ages to come, and shown me a long line of generations. <verse eID="2Sam.7.19"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.7.20" osisID="2Sam.7.20"/> What more need David say to thee? Thou knowest thy servant; <verse eID="2Sam.7.20"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.7.21" osisID="2Sam.7.21"/> thou hast promised to glorify thy servant, and from thine own heart hast thou acted in letting thy
       servant see all this great future. <verse eID="2Sam.7.21"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.7.22" osisID="2Sam.7.22"/> Great thou art, O Lord Eternal, for there is none like thee, there is no god save thee, that we have
       ever heard of. <verse eID="2Sam.7.22"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.7.23" osisID="2Sam.7.23"/> And what other nation on earth is like thy people Israel? What nation did a god go and redeem to be a
       people for himself, to win a name for himself, by doing great and terrible exploits on their behalf, by driving out a people and their gods
       before his own people? <verse eID="2Sam.7.23"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.7.24" osisID="2Sam.7.24"/> Yet thou hast established thy people Israel to be thine own people for ever; and thou, O Eternal, hast
       become their God. <verse eID="2Sam.7.24"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.7.25" osisID="2Sam.7.25"/> Now, O Lord Eternal, confirm for ever thy promise to thy servant and his house, and do as thou hast
       said, <verse eID="2Sam.7.25"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.7.26" osisID="2Sam.7.26"/> that thy renown may be great for ever, when men say, <q>The Lord of hosts is God over Israel,</q> the
       family of thy servant David being established before thee. O Lord of hosts, God of Israel, thy servant has ventured to offer this prayer to thee
      <verse eID="2Sam.7.26"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.7.27" osisID="2Sam.7.27"/> because thou hast revealed to thy servant that thou wilt build him up a family. <verse eID="2Sam.7.27"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.7.28" osisID="2Sam.7.28"/> Lord Eternal, thou art God, thy words are true, and thou hast made this kind promise to thy servant!
      <verse eID="2Sam.7.28"/>
      <milestone type="pb" n="355"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.7.29" osisID="2Sam.7.29"/>May it please thee to bless the family of thy servant, that it may continue in thy presence always! For
       thou hast said the word, O Eternal. May the family of thy servant be blessed for ever with thy blessing!</q> <verse eID="2Sam.7.29"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eID="2Sam.7"/>
    <chapter osisID="2Sam.8" sID="2Sam.8"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="2Sam.8.1" osisID="2Sam.8.1"/>After this David defeated the Philistines and subdued them; he took the supreme power from the
       Philistines. <verse eID="2Sam.8.1"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.8.2" osisID="2Sam.8.2"/> When he defeated Moab, he arranged the natives in lines, making them lie down on the ground; two lines
       of them were put to death, and one line spared alive. This made the Moabites subject to David; they brought him tribute. <verse eID="2Sam.8.2"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.8.3" osisID="2Sam.8.3"/> Then David defeated Hadadezer the son of Rehob, king of Zobah, as he went to set up his trophy of
       victory on the Euphrates; <verse eID="2Sam.8.3"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.8.4" osisID="2Sam.8.4"/> from him David captured a thousand chariots, seven thousand cavalry, and twenty thousand infantry; David
       hamstrung all the chariot horses except enough for a hundred chariots. <verse eID="2Sam.8.4"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.8.5" osisID="2Sam.8.5"/> When the Aramaeans of Damascus came to the aid of Hadadezer king of Zobah, David killed twenty-two
       thousand Aramaeans, <verse eID="2Sam.8.5"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.8.6" osisID="2Sam.8.6"/> and then posted garrisons among the Aramaeans of Damascus; this made the Aramaeans subject to David, and
       they brought him tribute. Indeed, wherever David went, the Eternal gave him victory. <verse eID="2Sam.8.6"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.8.7" osisID="2Sam.8.7"/> David took the golden shields worn by Hadadezer's officers and brought them to Jerusalem; <verse eID="2Sam.8.7"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.8.8" osisID="2Sam.8.8"/> king David also took a large quantity of bronze from Tibhath and Beerothai, towns belonging to
       Hadadezer. <verse eID="2Sam.8.8"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.8.9" osisID="2Sam.8.9"/> And when Tou the king of Hamath heard that David had defeated all the forces of Hadadezer, <verse eID="2Sam.8.9"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.8.10" osisID="2Sam.8.10"/> Tou sent his son Hadoram to salute king David and congratulate him on fighting and defeating
       Hadadezer, for Hadadezer had been at war with Tou. Hadoram brought with him silver, gold, and bronze ware, <verse eID="2Sam.8.10"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.8.11" osisID="2Sam.8.11"/> which king David dedicated to the Eternal along with the silver and gold he had dedicated as spoils
       from all the nations he had subdued, <verse eID="2Sam.8.11"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.8.12" osisID="2Sam.8.12"/> from Edom, Moab, the Ammonites, the Philistines, and Amalek, besides the spoil of Hadadezer son of
       Rehob, king of Zobah. <verse eID="2Sam.8.12"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.8.13" osisID="2Sam.8.13"/> David thus won a name for himself. On returning, he killed eighteen thousand Edomites in the wady of
       Salt, <verse eID="2Sam.8.13"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.8.14" osisID="2Sam.8.14"/> and posted garrisons all over Edom, till all the Edomites became subject to David. Wherever David
       went, the Eternal gave him victory. <verse eID="2Sam.8.14"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="2Sam.8.15" osisID="2Sam.8.15"/> David reigned over all Israel; David himself administered justice and the law to all his people, <verse eID="2Sam.8.15"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.8.16" osisID="2Sam.8.16"/> Joab the son of Zeruiah was in command of the army, Jehoshaphat the son of Ahilud was chancellor, <verse eID="2Sam.8.16"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.8.17" osisID="2Sam.8.17"/> Abiathar the son of Ahimelek (the son of Ahitub) and Zadok were his priests, Sousa was secretary, <verse eID="2Sam.8.17"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.8.18" osisID="2Sam.8.18"/> Benaiah the son of Jehoiada was in command of the foreign body-guard, and David's sons were priests. <verse eID="2Sam.8.18"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eID="2Sam.8"/>
   </div>