   <div type="book" osisID="2Sam">
    <milestone type="pb" n="346"/>
    <chapter osisID="2Sam.1" sID="2Sam.1"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="2Sam.1.1" osisID="2Sam.1.1"/>After the death of Saul, when David had come back from slaying the
       Amalekites and had been for two days at Ziklag, <verse eID="2Sam.1.1"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.1.2" osisID="2Sam.1.2"/> on the third day a man came from Saul's camp with his clothes
       torn and earth scattered on his head. When he reached David, he fell to the ground and did obeisance. <verse eID="2Sam.1.2"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.1.3" osisID="2Sam.1.3"/> David said to him, <q>Where do you come from?</q> <q>I have
       escaped from the camp of Israel,</q> said he. <verse eID="2Sam.1.3"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.1.4" osisID="2Sam.1.4"/> Then David asked him, <q>Tell me, how did things go?</q>
       He replied, <q>The troops ran away from the fight, many of the troops have fallen, and Saul and his son
       Jonathan are also dead.</q> <verse eID="2Sam.1.4"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.1.5" osisID="2Sam.1.5"/> [[David said to the young man who told him, <q>How do you know
       that Saul and his son Jonathan are dead?</q> <verse eID="2Sam.1.5"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.1.6" osisID="2Sam.1.6"/> And the young man who told him said, <q>I happened to be on mount
       Gilboa, and there was Saul leaning on his spear! The chariots and cavalry were close upon him. <verse eID="2Sam.1.6"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.1.7" osisID="2Sam.1.7"/> When he looked behind him, he saw me and called to me. I
       answered, <q>Here I am.</q> <verse eID="2Sam.1.7"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.1.8" osisID="2Sam.1.8"/> He said to me, <q>Who are you?</q> I said to him, <q>I am an
       Amalekite.</q> <verse eID="2Sam.1.8"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.1.9" osisID="2Sam.1.9"/> Then he said to me, <q>Stand over me and des­patch me, for it is
       dizziness that has seized me--I am quite unwounded!</q> <verse eID="2Sam.1.9"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.1.10" osisID="2Sam.1.10"/> So I stood over him and killed him, for I was sure he could not
       live after he had fallen. I took the crown from his head and the armlet from his arm, and I have brought
       them here to my lord.</q>]] <verse eID="2Sam.1.10"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="2Sam.1.11" osisID="2Sam.1.11"/> Then David caught his clothes and tore them; so did all the men
       with him; <verse eID="2Sam.1.11"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.1.12" osisID="2Sam.1.12"/> they lamented and wept and fasted till evening for Saul and his
       son Jonathan and the army of Judah and the house of Israel, because they had fallen by the sword. <verse eID="2Sam.1.12"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.1.13" osisID="2Sam.1.13"/> [[David said to the young man who told him, <q>Where do you
       come from?</q> <q>I am the son of a resident alien,</q> he said, <q>an Amalekite.</q> <verse eID="2Sam.1.13"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.1.14" osisID="2Sam.1.14"/> And David said to him, <q>Why were you not afraid to lift your
       hand to de­stroy the Eternal's anointed?</q> <verse eID="2Sam.1.14"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.1.15" osisID="2Sam.1.15"/> Then David called one of the young men and said, <q>Go up to
       him and strike him down.</q> Then he felled the Amalekite, so that he died. <verse eID="2Sam.1.15"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.1.16" osisID="2Sam.1.16"/> <q>Your blood be on your own head,</q> said David; <q>your own
       lips have borne witness against you, when you said, <q>I slew the Eternal’s anointed!</q></q>]] <verse eID="2Sam.1.16"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="2Sam.1.17" osisID="2Sam.1.17"/> Then David sang this dirge over Saul and his son Jonathan <verse eID="2Sam.1.17"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.1.18" osisID="2Sam.1.18"/> (it is written in the Book of Heroes); he said:
       <lg>
        <l> O Judah, to your crying! </l>
        <l> O Israel, to your grief and woe! </l>
      <verse eID="2Sam.1.18"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.1.19" osisID="2Sam.1.19"/>
        <l> On your battle-fields the slain are lying. </l>
        <l> and heroes, alas! fallen low. </l>
      <verse eID="2Sam.1.19"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.1.20" osisID="2Sam.1.20"/>
        <l> Tell it not in Gath,</l>
        <l> proclaim it not in Ashkelon’s streets,</l>
        <l> lest the daughters of the Philis­tines rejoice,</l>
        <l> lest the daughters of the uncir­cumcised exult.</l>
      <verse eID="2Sam.1.20"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.1.21" osisID="2Sam.1.21"/>
        <l> Dew never fall on you, hills of Gilboa, </l>
        <l> rain never reach you, O death's own field </l>
        <l> For there a hero dropped his shield, </l>
        <l> Saul's shield, the armour of the anointed. </l>
      <verse eID="2Sam.1.21"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.1.22" osisID="2Sam.1.22"/>
        <l> From the blood of the slain, </l>
        <l> from the flesh of the mighty, </l>
        <l> never did Jonathan’s bow turn back, </l>
        <l> nor the sword of Saul unsated. </l>
      <verse eID="2Sam.1.22"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.1.23" osisID="2Sam.1.23"/>
        <l> Saul and Jonathan, loved and lovely, </l>
       <milestone type="pb" n="347"/>
        <l> never divided in life or in death!-- </l>
        <l> swifter than eagles, stronger than lions! </l>
      <verse eID="2Sam.1.23"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.1.24" osisID="2Sam.1.24"/>
        <l> Daughters of Israel, wail for Saul, </l>
        <l> who decked you in scarlet and jewels, </l>
        <l> who adorned your robes with gold! </l>
      <verse eID="2Sam.1.24"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.1.25" osisID="2Sam.1.25"/>
        <l> Alas for heroes fallen low </l>
        <l> in the thick of the fray </l>
      <verse eID="2Sam.1.25"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.1.26" osisID="2Sam.1.26"/>
        <l> Jonathan slain in the field of battle, </l>
        <l> my heart is sore for you, </l>
        <l> O Jonathan, my brother! </l>
        <l> You were my dear delight, </l>
        <l> your love for me was a wonder, </l>
        <l> far beyond a woman’s love. </l>
      <verse eID="2Sam.1.26"/>
      <verse sID="2Sam.1.27" osisID="2Sam.1.27"/>
        <l> Alas for heroes fallen low, </l>
        <l> for weapons that once felled the foe! </l>
       </lg>
      <verse eID="2Sam.1.27"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eID="2Sam.1"/>
   </div>