   <div type="book" osisID="Deut">
    <milestone type="pb" n="197"/>
    <chapter osisId="Deut.1" sId="Deut.1"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.1" osisID="Deut.1.1"/>The following are the words which Moses spoke to all Is­rael east of the Jordan in the desert, in the wady of the Ara- bah opposite Suph, between Paran on the one side and To- phel, Laban, Hazeroth, and 3 Dizahab on the other. (It was on the first day of the eleventh month of the fortieth year that Moses spoke to the Israelites in terms of all the commands that he had received for them from 4 the Eternal.) After defeating Sihon king of the Amorites, whose capital was Heshbon, and Og king of Bashan, whose capital S was Ashtaroth, at Edrei, Moses set himself to expound this code, east of the Jordan in Moab. He said:
      <verse eID="Deut.1.1"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.3" osisID="Deut.1.3"/>
      <verse eID="Deut.1.3"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.4" osisID="Deut.1.4"/>
      <verse eID="Deut.1.4"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.5" osisID="Deut.1.5"/>
      <verse eID="Deut.1.5"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.6" osisID="Deut.1.6"/>
6 “The Eternal our God said to us at Horeb, ‘You have stayed long enough among the 7 hills here; move on, away into the highlands of the Amorites and all the surrounding country, the wady of the Arabah, the highlands, the lowlands, the southern plains and the mari­time plains where the Canaan- ites live, also the Lebanon. I hand this land over to you, as far as the great river, the river 8 Euphrates. There it lies; march in and take possession of the land that the Eternal swore he would give to your fathers, Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob, and to their descendants.5 9
      <verse eID="Deut.1.6"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.7" osisID="Deut.1.7"/>
      <verse eID="Deut.1.7"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.8" osisID="Deut.1.8"/>
      <verse eID="Deut.1.8"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.9" osisID="Deut.1.9"/>
“Then it was that I told you, ‘I cannot bear the burden of 10 you single-handed. The Eter­nal your God has multiplied you, till now your numbers are ii like the stars in the sky. (May the Eternal the God of your fathers multiply you still a thousand-fold, and prosper you as he promised you!) How can 12 I possibly bear the heavy bur­den of you and your disputes, all by myself? Choose capable 13 men, intelligent and experienced, from each of your clans, and let me put them in charge of you.5 Then you replied, ‘What you 14 propose is the right thing to do.5 So I took those capable and 15 experienced men, putting them in charge of your divisions of a thousand, of a hundred, of fifty, and of ten, as your prefects, along with officials for every clan. I also charged 16 your governors at that time, ‘Listen to your fellow-clansmen, and see justice done between a man and his fellow or any resi­dent alien; you must never 17 show partiality to any person in a case, you must listen equally to low and high, you must not be afraid of any man —for the judgment is God’s. Any case that is too hard for you must be brought to me, and I will hear it.5 I gave you 18 all your directions then.
      <verse eID="Deut.1.9"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.10" osisID="Deut.1.10"/>
      <verse eID="Deut.1.10"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.11" osisID="Deut.1.11"/>
      <verse eID="Deut.1.11"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.12" osisID="Deut.1.12"/>
      <verse eID="Deut.1.12"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.13" osisID="Deut.1.13"/>
      <verse eID="Deut.1.13"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.14" osisID="Deut.1.14"/>
      <verse eID="Deut.1.14"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.15" osisID="Deut.1.15"/>
      <verse eID="Deut.1.15"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.16" osisID="Deut.1.16"/>
      <verse eID="Deut.1.16"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.17" osisID="Deut.1.17"/>
      <verse eID="Deut.1.17"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.18" osisID="Deut.1.18"/>
      <verse eID="Deut.1.18"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.19" osisID="Deut.1.19"/>
“On setting out from Horeb 19 we passed through that wide awful desert, as you saw, on our way to the Amorite high­lands, in obedience to the Eter­nal our God. When we reached 2 Kadesh-barnea (eleven days from Horeb by the mount Seir road) I said to you, ‘Now you 20 have reached the Amorite high­lands, which the Eternal our God is to give us; here is the 21 Eternal your God handing over the land to you; march in and take possession of it, as the Eternal the God of your
      <verse eID="Deut.1.19"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.2" osisID="Deut.1.2"/>
      <verse eID="Deut.1.2"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.20" osisID="Deut.1.20"/>
      <verse eID="Deut.1.20"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.21" osisID="Deut.1.21"/>
       <milestone type="pb" n="198"/>
fathers has told you; fear not, neither he dismayed.’
      <verse eID="Deut.1.21"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.22" osisID="Deut.1.22"/>
22  Then you all came to me and proposed to send some men in front, to explore the land and bring back word about the route you should follow and the towns
23  you would reach. I thought this a good plan; so I chose twelve men, one for each clan,
24  and they made their way into the highlands as far as the wady of Eshcol, which they explored.
25  Then, carrying some fruit of the country, they brought it down to us, with this report: ‘It is a fine land that the Eternal our
26  God is to give us.’ But you would not march up; you re­belled against the orders of the
27  Eternal your God, and grumbled in your tents, ‘It is because the Eternal hates us that he has brought us out of the land of Egypt to hand us over to the Amorites, to be de-
28  stroyed! What is our fate to be? Our friends have made our courage melt by telling us that the people are stronger and taller than ourselves, and the towns large and walled up to the sky; besides, they saw giants in the land!’
      <verse eID="Deut.1.22"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.23" osisID="Deut.1.23"/>
      <verse eID="Deut.1.23"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.24" osisID="Deut.1.24"/>
      <verse eID="Deut.1.24"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.25" osisID="Deut.1.25"/>
      <verse eID="Deut.1.25"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.26" osisID="Deut.1.26"/>
      <verse eID="Deut.1.26"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.27" osisID="Deut.1.27"/>
      <verse eID="Deut.1.27"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.28" osisID="Deut.1.28"/>
      <verse eID="Deut.1.28"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.29" osisID="Deut.1.29"/>
29  Then I said to you, ‘Dread them not, have no fear of them.
30  The Eternal your God who goes in front of you, he will fight for you; he will do it all for you, as you saw him do in Egypt,
31  and also in the desert, where you saw how the Eternal your God carried you forward, as a man carries his boy, all the long road till you reached this
32  place.’ But, for all I said, you would not trust the Eternal
33  your God, who had gone in front of you upon the road, by fire during the night and by a cloud during the day, to find
out where you could pitch your camp, and to show you the road to take. When the Eternal 34 heard what you said, he was angry and swore that ‘not a 35 man of them, not a soul of this wicked generation, shall ever see the fine land that I swore to give to your fathers, none 36 except Caleb the son of Jephun- neh; he shall see it, and to him will I give the land on which he has set foot, to him and to his children, because he has been loyal to me.’ (The Eter- 37 nal was angry with me also on your account; ‘neither shall you enter,’ said he. ‘Joshua 38 the son of Nun, your attendant, shall enter; nerve him, for he is to put Israel in possession of the land.’) ‘Also the infants 39 who would be seized, you thought, and the children who know no difference yet between good and evil, they shall enter;
I   will give the land to them, and they shall hold it. But 40 as for you, move back into the desert in the direction of the Gulf of Akabah.’ You an- 41 swered me, ‘We have sinned against the Eternal, we our­selves will march up and fight, exactly as the Eternal our God has ordered us.’ Every man of you put on his armour, and made little of marching into the highlands. But the 42 Eternal said to me, ‘Tell them not to march up nor to fight, lest you are beaten by your enemies; for I am not among you.’ I told you this, but you 43 would not listen, you rebelled against the orders of the Eter­nal, and in your presumption you did march into the high­lands. Then the Amorites who 44 lived there attacked you, swarming out like bees and
      <verse eID="Deut.1.29"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.30" osisID="Deut.1.30"/>
      <verse eID="Deut.1.30"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.31" osisID="Deut.1.31"/>
      <verse eID="Deut.1.31"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.32" osisID="Deut.1.32"/>
      <verse eID="Deut.1.32"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.33" osisID="Deut.1.33"/>
      <verse eID="Deut.1.33"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.34" osisID="Deut.1.34"/>
      <verse eID="Deut.1.34"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.35" osisID="Deut.1.35"/>
      <verse eID="Deut.1.35"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.36" osisID="Deut.1.36"/>
      <verse eID="Deut.1.36"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.37" osisID="Deut.1.37"/>
      <verse eID="Deut.1.37"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.38" osisID="Deut.1.38"/>
      <verse eID="Deut.1.38"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.39" osisID="Deut.1.39"/>
      <verse eID="Deut.1.39"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.40" osisID="Deut.1.40"/>
      <verse eID="Deut.1.40"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.41" osisID="Deut.1.41"/>
      <verse eID="Deut.1.41"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.42" osisID="Deut.1.42"/>
      <verse eID="Deut.1.42"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.43" osisID="Deut.1.43"/>
      <verse eID="Deut.1.43"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.44" osisID="Deut.1.44"/>
       <milestone type="pb" n="199"/>
chasing you, from Seir to Hormah—a crushing defeat.
45  You came back and wept before the Eternal; but the Eternal would not listen to your cry, he would not hearken to you.
      <verse eID="Deut.1.44"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.45" osisID="Deut.1.45"/>
      <verse eID="Deut.1.45"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.46" osisID="Deut.1.46"/>
46  Then, after you had made that long stay of many days at
2Kadesh, we moved back into the desert in the direction of the Gulf of Akabah, as the Eter­nal had told me.
      <verse eID="Deut.1.46"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eId="Deut.1"/>
   </div>