   <div type="book" osisID="Deut">
    <milestone type="pb" n="197"/>
    <chapter osisId="Deut.1" sId="Deut.1"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.1" osisID="Deut.1.1"/>The following are the words which Moses spoke to all Is­rael east of the Jordan in the
       desert, in the wady of the Arabah opposite Suph, between Paran on the one side and Tophel, Laban, Hazeroth, and Dizahab on the
       other. <verse eID="Deut.1.1"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.3" osisID="Deut.1.3"/> (It was on the first day of the eleventh month of the fortieth year that Moses spoke to
       the Israelites in terms of all the commands that he had received for them from the Eternal.) <verse eID="Deut.1.3"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.4" osisID="Deut.1.4"/> After defeating Sihon king of the Amorites, whose capital was Heshbon, and Og king of
       Bashan, whose capital was Ashtaroth, at Edrei, <verse eID="Deut.1.4"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.5" osisID="Deut.1.5"/> Moses set himself to expound this code, east of the Jordan in Moab. He said: <verse eID="Deut.1.5"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.6" osisID="Deut.1.6"/><q>The Eternal our God said to us at Horeb, <q>You have stayed long enough among the
       hills here; <verse eID="Deut.1.6"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.7" osisID="Deut.1.7"/> move on, away into the highlands of the Amorites and all the surrounding country, the
       wady of the Arabah, the highlands, the lowlands, the southern plains and the mari­time plains where the Canaanites live, also the
       Lebanon. I hand this land over to you, as far as the great river, the river Euphrates. <verse eID="Deut.1.7"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.8" osisID="Deut.1.8"/> There it lies; march in and take possession of the land that the Eternal swore he would
       give to your fathers, Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob, and to their descendants.</q></q><verse eID="Deut.1.8"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.9" osisID="Deut.1.9"/><q>Then it was that I told you, <q>I cannot bear the burden of you single-handed. <verse eID="Deut.1.9"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.10" osisID="Deut.1.10"/> The Eter­nal your God has multiplied you, till now your numbers are like the stars in
       the sky. <verse eID="Deut.1.10"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.11" osisID="Deut.1.11"/> (May the Eternal the God of your fathers multiply you still a thousand-fold, and
       prosper you as he promised you!) <verse eID="Deut.1.11"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.12" osisID="Deut.1.12"/> How can I possibly bear the heavy bur­den of you and your disputes, all by myself? <verse eID="Deut.1.12"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.13" osisID="Deut.1.13"/> Choose capable men, intelligent and experienced, from each of your clans, and let me
       put them in charge of you.</q> <verse eID="Deut.1.13"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.14" osisID="Deut.1.14"/> Then you replied, <q>What you propose is the right thing to do.</q> <verse eID="Deut.1.14"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.15" osisID="Deut.1.15"/> So I took those capable and experienced men, putting them in charge of your divisions
       of a thousand, of a hundred, of fifty, and of ten, as your prefects, along with officials for every clan. <verse eID="Deut.1.15"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.16" osisID="Deut.1.16"/> I also charged your governors at that time, <q>Listen to your fellow-clansmen, and
       see justice done between a man and his fellow or any resi­dent alien; <verse eID="Deut.1.16"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.17" osisID="Deut.1.17"/> you must never show partiality to any person in a case, you must listen equally to
       low and high, you must not be afraid of any man--for the judgment is God’s. Any case that is too hard for you must be brought to
       me, and I will hear it.</q><verse eID="Deut.1.17"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.18" osisID="Deut.1.18"/> I gave you all your directions then.</q> <verse eID="Deut.1.18"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.19" osisID="Deut.1.19"/><q>On setting out from Horeb we passed through that wide awful desert, as you saw, on
       our way to the Amorite high­lands, in obedience to the Eter­nal our God. When we reached Kadesh-barnea <verse eID="Deut.1.19"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.2" osisID="Deut.1.2"/> (eleven days from Horeb by the mount Seir road) <verse eID="Deut.1.2"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.20" osisID="Deut.1.20"/> I said to you, <q>Now you have reached the Amorite high­lands, which the Eternal our
       God is to give us; <verse eID="Deut.1.20"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.21" osisID="Deut.1.21"/> here is the Eternal your God handing over the land to you; march in and take
       possession of it, as the Eternal the God of your
       <milestone type="pb" n="198"/>
       fathers has told you; fear not, neither he dismayed.</q></q>
      <verse eID="Deut.1.21"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.22" osisID="Deut.1.22"/>Then you all came to me and proposed to send some men in front, to explore the land
       and bring back word about the route you should follow and the towns you would reach. <verse eID="Deut.1.22"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.23" osisID="Deut.1.23"/> I thought this a good plan; so I chose twelve men, one for each clan, <verse eID="Deut.1.23"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.24" osisID="Deut.1.24"/> and they made their way into the highlands as far as the wady of Eshcol, which they
       explored. <verse eID="Deut.1.24"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.25" osisID="Deut.1.25"/>Then, carrying some fruit of the country, they brought it down to us, with this
       report: <q>It is a fine land that the Eternal our God is to give us.</q> <verse eID="Deut.1.25"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.26" osisID="Deut.1.26"/> But you would not march up; you re­belled against the orders of the Eternal your God,
      <verse eID="Deut.1.26"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.27" osisID="Deut.1.27"/> and grumbled in your tents, <q>It is because the Eternal hates us that he has brought
       us out of the land of Egypt to hand us over to the Amorites, to be destroyed! <verse eID="Deut.1.27"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.28" osisID="Deut.1.28"/> What is our fate to be? Our friends have made our courage melt by telling us that the
       people are stronger and taller than ourselves, and the towns large and walled up to the sky; besides, they saw giants in the
       land!</q> <verse eID="Deut.1.28"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.29" osisID="Deut.1.29"/>Then I said to you, <q>Dread them not, have no fear of them. <verse eID="Deut.1.29"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.30" osisID="Deut.1.30"/> The Eternal your God who goes in front of you, he will fight for you; he will do it
       all for you, as you saw him do in Egypt, <verse eID="Deut.1.30"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.31" osisID="Deut.1.31"/> and also in the desert, where you saw how the Eternal your God carried you forward,
       as a man carries his boy, all the long road till you reached this place.</q> <verse eID="Deut.1.31"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.32" osisID="Deut.1.32"/> But, for all I said, you would not trust the Eternal your God, <verse eID="Deut.1.32"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.33" osisID="Deut.1.33"/> who had gone in front of you upon the road, by fire during the night and by a cloud
       during the day, to find out where you could pitch your camp, and to show you the road to take. <verse eID="Deut.1.33"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.34" osisID="Deut.1.34"/> When the Eternal heard what you said, he was angry and swore that <verse eID="Deut.1.34"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.35" osisID="Deut.1.35"/> <q>not a man of them, not a soul of this wicked generation, shall ever see the fine
       land that I swore to give to your fathers, <verse eID="Deut.1.35"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.36" osisID="Deut.1.36"/> none except Caleb the son of Jephunneh; he shall see it, and to him will I give the
       land on which he has set foot, to him and to his children, because he has been loyal to me.</q> <verse eID="Deut.1.36"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.37" osisID="Deut.1.37"/> (The Eternal was angry with me also on your account; <q>neither shall you enter,</q>
       said he. <verse eID="Deut.1.37"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.38" osisID="Deut.1.38"/><q>Joshua the son of Nun, your attendant, shall enter; nerve him, for he is to put
       Israel in possession of the land.</q>) <verse eID="Deut.1.38"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.39" osisID="Deut.1.39"/><q>Also the infants who would be seized, you thought, and the children who know no
       difference yet between good and evil, they shall enter; I will give the land to them, and they shall hold it. <verse eID="Deut.1.39"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.40" osisID="Deut.1.40"/> But as for you, move back into the desert in the direction of the Gulf of Akabah.</q>
      <verse eID="Deut.1.40"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.41" osisID="Deut.1.41"/> You answered me, <q>We have sinned against the Eternal, we our­selves will march up
       and fight, exactly as the Eternal our God has ordered us.</q> Every man of you put on his armour, and made little of marching
       into the highlands. <verse eID="Deut.1.41"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.42" osisID="Deut.1.42"/> But the Eternal said to me, <q>Tell them not to march up nor to fight, lest you are
       beaten by your enemies; for I am not among you.</q> <verse eID="Deut.1.42"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.43" osisID="Deut.1.43"/> I told you this, but you would not listen, you rebelled against the orders of the
       Eter­nal, and in your presumption you did march into the high­lands. <verse eID="Deut.1.43"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.44" osisID="Deut.1.44"/> Then the Amorites who lived there attacked you, swarming out like bees and
       <milestone type="pb" n="199"/>
       chasing you, from Seir to Hormah--a crushing defeat. <verse eID="Deut.1.44"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.45" osisID="Deut.1.45"/> You came back and wept before the Eternal; but the Eternal would not listen to your
       cry, he would not hearken to you. <verse eID="Deut.1.45"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.46" osisID="Deut.1.46"/>Then, after you had made that long stay of many days at Kadesh, <verse eID="Deut.1.46"/>
    <chapter eId="Deut.1"/>
    <chapter osisId="Deut.2" sId="Deut.2"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.2.1" osisID="Deut.2.1"/> we moved back into the desert in the direction of the Gulf of Akabah, as the Eter­nal
       had told me. For many a day we marched round the highlands of Seir, <verse eID="Deut.2.1"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.2.2" osisID="Deut.2.2"/> till the Eternal said to me, <verse eID="Deut.2.2"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.2.3" osisID="Deut.2.3"/> <q>You have marched long enough round these highlands; turn to the north. <verse eID="Deut.2.3"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.2.4" osisID="Deut.2.4"/> Tell the people they are going to cross the territory of their kins­folk, the sons of
       Esau, who live in Seir; they will be afraid of you, <verse eID="Deut.2.4"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.2.5" osisID="Deut.2.5"/> but you must be careful never to engage in battle with them, for I have not assigned
       you any of their land, no, not a foot of it; the highlands of Seir I have assigned to Esau as his own. <verse eID="Deut.2.5"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.2.6" osisID="Deut.2.6"/> You may buy food from them, you may buy water from them <verse eID="Deut.2.6"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.2.7" osisID="Deut.2.7"/> (for the Eternal your God has always blessed your enter­prise. Think how his care
       brought you through this wide desert; the Eternal your God has been with you all these forty years, and never have you been in
       want).</q> <verse eID="Deut.2.7"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.2.8" osisID="Deut.2.8"/> So we passed through our kinsfolk the sons of Esau, who live in Seir, from Elath and
       Ezion-geber on the Arabah route; we moved round in the direction of the o plains of Moab. <verse eID="Deut.2.8"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.2.9" osisID="Deut.2.9"/> <q>Fight not with Moab,</q> said the Eternal to me, <q>do not engage them in battle,
       for I will not let you hold any of their land; Ar I have assigned to the sons of Lot as their own.</q> <verse eID="Deut.2.9"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.2.10" osisID="Deut.2.10"/> [[Long ago the Emim used to live there, a strong and numerous race, as tall as
       giants; <verse eID="Deut.2.10"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.2.11" osisID="Deut.2.11"/> like the giants, they are generally called Titans, but the Moabites call them
       <q>Emim.</q> <verse eID="Deut.2.11"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.2.12" osisID="Deut.2.12"/> Long ago also troglodytes used to live in Seir, but the sons of Esau dislodged them
       and killed them off, tak­ing possession of their country just as the Israelites did with the land which the Eternal had
       assigned as their possession.]] <verse eID="Deut.2.12"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.2.13" osisID="Deut.2.13"/> <q>Up now and cross the wady of Zered.</q> We crossed the wady of Zered; <verse eID="Deut.2.13"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.2.14" osisID="Deut.2.14"/> when we crossed that wady of Zered, thirty-eight years had passed since we left
       Kadesh-barnea, and all that generation (that is, the warriors) had died off, as the Eternal had sworn: <verse eID="Deut.2.14"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.2.15" osisID="Deut.2.15"/> the Eternal’s hand had been against them, routing them in disarray, till all had
       perished. <verse eID="Deut.2.15"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Deut.2.16" osisID="Deut.2.16"/> Now that all these warriors had perished from the people, <verse eID="Deut.2.16"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.2.17" osisID="Deut.2.17"/> the Eternal said to me, <verse eID="Deut.2.17"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.2.18" osisID="Deut.2.18"/> <q>To-day you are about to cross Ar, the territory of Moab. <verse eID="Deut.2.18"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.2.19" osisID="Deut.2.19"/> As you pass close in front of the Ammonites, do not fight with them, do not engage
       in battle with them, for I will not let you have any of the Ammonite country; I have assigned it to the sons of Lot as their
       own.</q> <verse eID="Deut.2.19"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.2.20" osisID="Deut.2.20"/> [[It also is generally called a land of the Titans; Titans used to live there long
       ago, whom the Ammonites call Zamzummin-- <verse eID="Deut.2.20"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.2.21" osisID="Deut.2.21"/> a strong and numerous race, as tall as giants, whom the Eternal killed off before
       the Ammonites, the latter dislodg­ing them and taking possession of their country, <verse eID="Deut.2.21"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.2.22" osisID="Deut.2.22"/> just as he had done for the sons of Esau who live in Seir, by killing off the
       troglodytes, whom they dis­lodged, taking possession of their country to the present day. <verse eID="Deut.2.22"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.2.23" osisID="Deut.2.23"/> So too the Avim, who lived in villages as far as Gaza,
       <milestone type="pb" n="200"/>
       were killed off by the Cretans, who came from Crete and took possession of their country.]] <verse eID="Deut.2.23"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.2.24" osisID="Deut.2.24"/> <q>Up, then, move across the wady of Arnon; I hand over to you Sihon the Amorite,
       king of Heshbon, him and his land; start to seize it and to engage him in battle, <verse eID="Deut.2.24"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.2.25" osisID="Deut.2.25"/> and I will start this very day to put the terror of you and the dread of you upon
       all races under heaven; the news of you shall make them tremble in anguish on account of you.</q> <verse eID="Deut.2.25"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.2.26" osisID="Deut.2.26"/> So I sent envoys from the desert of Kedemoth to Sihon king of Heshbon with this
       message of peace: <verse eID="Deut.2.26"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.2.27" osisID="Deut.2.27"/> <q>Let us pass through your land, we will go straight across, turning neither to
       the right nor to the left. <verse eID="Deut.2.27"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.2.28" osisID="Deut.2.28"/> You shall sell us food for money and give us drinking water for money; only allow
       us to walk through, <verse eID="Deut.2.28"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.2.29" osisID="Deut.2.29"/> as we were allowed by the sons of Esau who live in Seir and the Moabites who live
       in Ar, till we cross the Jordan into the land which the Eternal our God is giving us!</q> <verse eID="Deut.2.29"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.2.30" osisID="Deut.2.30"/> But Sihon king of Heshbon would not let us pass through his land; the Eternal your
       God had stiffened his mind and made his heart stubborn, in order to put him into your hands, as is the case to-day. <verse eID="Deut.2.30"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Deut.2.31" osisID="Deut.2.31"/> Then the Eternal said to me, <q>Here have I started to hand over to you Sihon and
       his land; start to seize it, that you may make his land your own.</q> <verse eID="Deut.2.31"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.2.32" osisID="Deut.2.32"/> And when Sihon and all his host attacked us in battle at Jahaz, <verse eID="Deut.2.32"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.2.33" osisID="Deut.2.33"/> the Eternal our God put him into our hands; we killed him and his sons and all his
       host, <verse eID="Deut.2.33"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.2.34" osisID="Deut.2.34"/> we captured all his towns, and in every town we put the citizens to death, men,
       women, and children, sparing none, <verse eID="Deut.2.34"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.2.35" osisID="Deut.2.35"/> keeping only the cattle as our prey, along with the plunder of the captured towns.
      <verse eID="Deut.2.35"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.2.36" osisID="Deut.2.36"/> From Aroer on the edge of the wady of Arnon and from the town that lies in the
       wady, right across to Gilead, no town was too much for us; the Eternal our God put them all into our hands. <verse eID="Deut.2.36"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.2.37" osisID="Deut.2.37"/> Only, as the Eternal had given strict orders, you never ventured near the land of
       the Ammonites, or near anything that lay on that side of the wady of Jabbok, or near the highland towns. <verse eID="Deut.2.37"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eId="Deut.2"/>
   </div>