   <div type="book" osisID="Deut">
    <milestone type="pb" n="197"/>
    <chapter osisId="Deut.1" sId="Deut.1"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.1" osisID="Deut.1.1"/>The following are the words which Moses spoke to all Is­rael east of the Jordan in the
       desert, in the wady of the Arabah opposite Suph, between Paran on the one side and Tophel, Laban, Hazeroth, and Dizahab on the
       other. <verse eID="Deut.1.1"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.3" osisID="Deut.1.3"/> (It was on the first day of the eleventh month of the fortieth year that Moses spoke to
       the Israelites in terms of all the commands that he had received for them from the Eternal.) <verse eID="Deut.1.3"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.4" osisID="Deut.1.4"/> After defeating Sihon king of the Amorites, whose capital was Heshbon, and Og king of
       Bashan, whose capital was Ashtaroth, at Edrei, <verse eID="Deut.1.4"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.5" osisID="Deut.1.5"/> Moses set himself to expound this code, east of the Jordan in Moab. He said: <verse eID="Deut.1.5"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.6" osisID="Deut.1.6"/><q>The Eternal our God said to us at Horeb, <q>You have stayed long enough among the
       hills here; <verse eID="Deut.1.6"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.7" osisID="Deut.1.7"/> move on, away into the highlands of the Amorites and all the surrounding country, the
       wady of the Arabah, the highlands, the lowlands, the southern plains and the mari­time plains where the Canaanites live, also the
       Lebanon. I hand this land over to you, as far as the great river, the river Euphrates. <verse eID="Deut.1.7"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.8" osisID="Deut.1.8"/> There it lies; march in and take possession of the land that the Eternal swore he would
       give to your fathers, Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob, and to their descendants.</q></q><verse eID="Deut.1.8"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.9" osisID="Deut.1.9"/><q>Then it was that I told you, <q>I cannot bear the burden of you single-handed. <verse eID="Deut.1.9"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.10" osisID="Deut.1.10"/> The Eter­nal your God has multiplied you, till now your numbers are like the stars in
       the sky. <verse eID="Deut.1.10"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.11" osisID="Deut.1.11"/> (May the Eternal the God of your fathers multiply you still a thousand-fold, and
       prosper you as he promised you!) <verse eID="Deut.1.11"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.12" osisID="Deut.1.12"/> How can I possibly bear the heavy bur­den of you and your disputes, all by myself? <verse eID="Deut.1.12"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.13" osisID="Deut.1.13"/> Choose capable men, intelligent and experienced, from each of your clans, and let me
       put them in charge of you.</q> <verse eID="Deut.1.13"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.14" osisID="Deut.1.14"/> Then you replied, <q>What you propose is the right thing to do.</q> <verse eID="Deut.1.14"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.15" osisID="Deut.1.15"/> So I took those capable and experienced men, putting them in charge of your divisions
       of a thousand, of a hundred, of fifty, and of ten, as your prefects, along with officials for every clan. <verse eID="Deut.1.15"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.16" osisID="Deut.1.16"/> I also charged your governors at that time, <q>Listen to your fellow-clansmen, and
       see justice done between a man and his fellow or any resi­dent alien; <verse eID="Deut.1.16"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.17" osisID="Deut.1.17"/> you must never show partiality to any person in a case, you must listen equally to
       low and high, you must not be afraid of any man--for the judgment is God’s. Any case that is too hard for you must be brought to
       me, and I will hear it.</q><verse eID="Deut.1.17"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.18" osisID="Deut.1.18"/> I gave you all your directions then.</q> <verse eID="Deut.1.18"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.19" osisID="Deut.1.19"/><q>On setting out from Horeb we passed through that wide awful desert, as you saw, on
       our way to the Amorite high­lands, in obedience to the Eter­nal our God. When we reached Kadesh-barnea <verse eID="Deut.1.19"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.2" osisID="Deut.1.2"/> (eleven days from Horeb by the mount Seir road) <verse eID="Deut.1.2"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.20" osisID="Deut.1.20"/> I said to you, <q>Now you have reached the Amorite high­lands, which the Eternal our
       God is to give us; <verse eID="Deut.1.20"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.21" osisID="Deut.1.21"/> here is the Eternal your God handing over the land to you; march in and take
       possession of it, as the Eternal the God of your
       <milestone type="pb" n="198"/>
       fathers has told you; fear not, neither he dismayed.</q></q>
      <verse eID="Deut.1.21"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.22" osisID="Deut.1.22"/>Then you all came to me and proposed to send some men in front, to explore the land
       and bring back word about the route you should follow and the towns you would reach. <verse eID="Deut.1.22"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.23" osisID="Deut.1.23"/> I thought this a good plan; so I chose twelve men, one for each clan, <verse eID="Deut.1.23"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.24" osisID="Deut.1.24"/> and they made their way into the highlands as far as the wady of Eshcol, which they
       explored. <verse eID="Deut.1.24"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.25" osisID="Deut.1.25"/>Then, carrying some fruit of the country, they brought it down to us, with this
       report: <q>It is a fine land that the Eternal our God is to give us.</q> <verse eID="Deut.1.25"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.26" osisID="Deut.1.26"/> But you would not march up; you re­belled against the orders of the Eternal your God,
      <verse eID="Deut.1.26"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.27" osisID="Deut.1.27"/> and grumbled in your tents, <q>It is because the Eternal hates us that he has brought
       us out of the land of Egypt to hand us over to the Amorites, to be destroyed! <verse eID="Deut.1.27"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.28" osisID="Deut.1.28"/> What is our fate to be? Our friends have made our courage melt by telling us that the
       people are stronger and taller than ourselves, and the towns large and walled up to the sky; besides, they saw giants in the
       land!</q> <verse eID="Deut.1.28"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.29" osisID="Deut.1.29"/>Then I said to you, <q>Dread them not, have no fear of them. <verse eID="Deut.1.29"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.30" osisID="Deut.1.30"/> The Eternal your God who goes in front of you, he will fight for you; he will do it
       all for you, as you saw him do in Egypt, <verse eID="Deut.1.30"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.31" osisID="Deut.1.31"/> and also in the desert, where you saw how the Eternal your God carried you forward,
       as a man carries his boy, all the long road till you reached this place.</q> <verse eID="Deut.1.31"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.32" osisID="Deut.1.32"/> But, for all I said, you would not trust the Eternal your God, <verse eID="Deut.1.32"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.33" osisID="Deut.1.33"/> who had gone in front of you upon the road, by fire during the night and by a cloud
       during the day, to find out where you could pitch your camp, and to show you the road to take. <verse eID="Deut.1.33"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.34" osisID="Deut.1.34"/> When the Eternal heard what you said, he was angry and swore that <verse eID="Deut.1.34"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.35" osisID="Deut.1.35"/> <q>not a man of them, not a soul of this wicked generation, shall ever see the fine
       land that I swore to give to your fathers, <verse eID="Deut.1.35"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.36" osisID="Deut.1.36"/> none except Caleb the son of Jephunneh; he shall see it, and to him will I give the
       land on which he has set foot, to him and to his children, because he has been loyal to me.</q> <verse eID="Deut.1.36"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.37" osisID="Deut.1.37"/> (The Eternal was angry with me also on your account; <q>neither shall you enter,</q>
       said he. <verse eID="Deut.1.37"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.38" osisID="Deut.1.38"/><q>Joshua the son of Nun, your attendant, shall enter; nerve him, for he is to put
       Israel in possession of the land.</q>) <verse eID="Deut.1.38"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.39" osisID="Deut.1.39"/><q>Also the infants who would be seized, you thought, and the children who know no
       difference yet between good and evil, they shall enter; I will give the land to them, and they shall hold it. <verse eID="Deut.1.39"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.40" osisID="Deut.1.40"/> But as for you, move back into the desert in the direction of the Gulf of Akabah.</q>
      <verse eID="Deut.1.40"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.41" osisID="Deut.1.41"/> You answered me, <q>We have sinned against the Eternal, we our­selves will march up
       and fight, exactly as the Eternal our God has ordered us.</q> Every man of you put on his armour, and made little of marching
       into the highlands. <verse eID="Deut.1.41"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.42" osisID="Deut.1.42"/> But the Eternal said to me, <q>Tell them not to march up nor to fight, lest you are
       beaten by your enemies; for I am not among you.</q> <verse eID="Deut.1.42"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.43" osisID="Deut.1.43"/> I told you this, but you would not listen, you rebelled against the orders of the
       Eter­nal, and in your presumption you did march into the high­lands. <verse eID="Deut.1.43"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.44" osisID="Deut.1.44"/> Then the Amorites who lived there attacked you, swarming out like bees and
       <milestone type="pb" n="199"/>
       chasing you, from Seir to Hormah--a crushing defeat. <verse eID="Deut.1.44"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.45" osisID="Deut.1.45"/> You came back and wept before the Eternal; but the Eternal would not listen to your
       cry, he would not hearken to you. <verse eID="Deut.1.45"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.46" osisID="Deut.1.46"/>Then, after you had made that long stay of many days at Kadesh, <verse eID="Deut.1.46"/>
    <chapter eId="Deut.1"/>
    <chapter osisId="Deut.2" sId="Deut.2"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.2.1" osisID="Deut.2.1"/> we moved back into the desert in the direction of the Gulf of Akabah, as the Eter­nal
       had told me. For many a day we marched round the highlands of Seir, <verse eID="Deut.2.1"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.2.2" osisID="Deut.2.2"/> till the Eternal said to me, <verse eID="Deut.2.2"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.2.3" osisID="Deut.2.3"/> <q>You have marched long enough round these highlands; turn to the north. <verse eID="Deut.2.3"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.2.4" osisID="Deut.2.4"/> Tell the people they are going to cross the territory of their kins­folk, the sons of
       Esau, who live in Seir; they will be afraid of you, <verse eID="Deut.2.4"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.2.5" osisID="Deut.2.5"/> but you must be careful never to engage in battle with them, for I have not assigned
       you any of their land, no, not a foot of it; the highlands of Seir I have assigned to Esau as his own. <verse eID="Deut.2.5"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.2.6" osisID="Deut.2.6"/> You may buy food from them, you may buy water from them <verse eID="Deut.2.6"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.2.7" osisID="Deut.2.7"/> (for the Eternal your God has always blessed your enter­prise. Think how his care
       brought you through this wide desert; the Eternal your God has been with you all these forty years, and never have you been in
       want).</q> <verse eID="Deut.2.7"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.2.8" osisID="Deut.2.8"/> So we passed through our kinsfolk the sons of Esau, who live in Seir, from Elath and
       Ezion-geber on the Arabah route; we moved round in the direction of the o plains of Moab. <verse eID="Deut.2.8"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.2.9" osisID="Deut.2.9"/> <q>Fight not with Moab,</q> said the Eternal to me, <q>do not engage them in battle,
       for I will not let you hold any of their land; Ar I have assigned to the sons of Lot as their own.</q> <verse eID="Deut.2.9"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.2.10" osisID="Deut.2.10"/> [[Long ago the Emim used to live there, a strong and numerous race, as tall as
       giants; <verse eID="Deut.2.10"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.2.11" osisID="Deut.2.11"/> like the giants, they are generally called Titans, but the Moabites call them
       <q>Emim.</q> <verse eID="Deut.2.11"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.2.12" osisID="Deut.2.12"/> Long ago also troglodytes used to live in Seir, but the sons of Esau dislodged them
       and killed them off, tak­ing possession of their country just as the Israelites did with the land which the Eternal had
       assigned as their possession.]] <verse eID="Deut.2.12"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.2.13" osisID="Deut.2.13"/> <q>Up now and cross the wady of Zered.</q> We crossed the wady of Zered; <verse eID="Deut.2.13"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.2.14" osisID="Deut.2.14"/> when we crossed that wady of Zered, thirty-eight years had passed since we left
       Kadesh-barnea, and all that generation (that is, the warriors) had died off, as the Eternal had sworn: <verse eID="Deut.2.14"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.2.15" osisID="Deut.2.15"/> the Eternal’s hand had been against them, routing them in disarray, till all had
       perished. <verse eID="Deut.2.15"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Deut.2.16" osisID="Deut.2.16"/> Now that all these warriors had perished from the people, <verse eID="Deut.2.16"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.2.17" osisID="Deut.2.17"/> the Eternal said to me, <verse eID="Deut.2.17"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.2.18" osisID="Deut.2.18"/> <q>To-day you are about to cross Ar, the territory of Moab. <verse eID="Deut.2.18"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.2.19" osisID="Deut.2.19"/> As you pass close in front of the Ammonites, do not fight with them, do not engage
       in battle with them, for I will not let you have any of the Ammonite country; I have assigned it to the sons of Lot as their
       own.</q> <verse eID="Deut.2.19"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.2.20" osisID="Deut.2.20"/> [[It also is generally called a land of the Titans; Titans used to live there long
       ago, whom the Ammonites call Zamzummin-- <verse eID="Deut.2.20"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.2.21" osisID="Deut.2.21"/> a strong and numerous race, as tall as giants, whom the Eternal killed off before
       the Ammonites, the latter dislodg­ing them and taking possession of their country, <verse eID="Deut.2.21"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.2.22" osisID="Deut.2.22"/> just as he had done for the sons of Esau who live in Seir, by killing off the
       troglodytes, whom they dis­lodged, taking possession of their country to the present day. <verse eID="Deut.2.22"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.2.23" osisID="Deut.2.23"/> So too the Avim, who lived in villages as far as Gaza,
       <milestone type="pb" n="200"/>
       were killed off by the Cretans, who came from Crete and took possession of their country.]] <verse eID="Deut.2.23"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.2.24" osisID="Deut.2.24"/> <q>Up, then, move across the wady of Arnon; I hand over to you Sihon the Amorite,
       king of Heshbon, him and his land; start to seize it and to engage him in battle, <verse eID="Deut.2.24"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.2.25" osisID="Deut.2.25"/> and I will start this very day to put the terror of you and the dread of you upon
       all races under heaven; the news of you shall make them tremble in anguish on account of you.</q> <verse eID="Deut.2.25"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.2.26" osisID="Deut.2.26"/> So I sent envoys from the desert of Kedemoth to Sihon king of Heshbon with this
       message of peace: <verse eID="Deut.2.26"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.2.27" osisID="Deut.2.27"/> <q>Let us pass through your land, we will go straight across, turning neither to
       the right nor to the left. <verse eID="Deut.2.27"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.2.28" osisID="Deut.2.28"/> You shall sell us food for money and give us drinking water for money; only allow
       us to walk through, <verse eID="Deut.2.28"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.2.29" osisID="Deut.2.29"/> as we were allowed by the sons of Esau who live in Seir and the Moabites who live
       in Ar, till we cross the Jordan into the land which the Eternal our God is giving us!</q> <verse eID="Deut.2.29"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.2.30" osisID="Deut.2.30"/> But Sihon king of Heshbon would not let us pass through his land; the Eternal your
       God had stiffened his mind and made his heart stubborn, in order to put him into your hands, as is the case to-day. <verse eID="Deut.2.30"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Deut.2.31" osisID="Deut.2.31"/> Then the Eternal said to me, <q>Here have I started to hand over to you Sihon and
       his land; start to seize it, that you may make his land your own.</q> <verse eID="Deut.2.31"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.2.32" osisID="Deut.2.32"/> And when Sihon and all his host attacked us in battle at Jahaz, <verse eID="Deut.2.32"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.2.33" osisID="Deut.2.33"/> the Eternal our God put him into our hands; we killed him and his sons and all his
       host, <verse eID="Deut.2.33"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.2.34" osisID="Deut.2.34"/> we captured all his towns, and in every town we put the citizens to death, men,
       women, and children, sparing none, <verse eID="Deut.2.34"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.2.35" osisID="Deut.2.35"/> keeping only the cattle as our prey, along with the plunder of the captured towns.
      <verse eID="Deut.2.35"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.2.36" osisID="Deut.2.36"/> From Aroer on the edge of the wady of Arnon and from the town that lies in the
       wady, right across to Gilead, no town was too much for us; the Eternal our God put them all into our hands. <verse eID="Deut.2.36"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.2.37" osisID="Deut.2.37"/> Only, as the Eternal had given strict orders, you never ventured near the land of
       the Ammonites, or near anything that lay on that side of the wady of Jabbok, or near the highland towns. <verse eID="Deut.2.37"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eId="Deut.2"/>
    <chapter osisId="Deut.3" sId="Deut.3"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Deut.3.1" osisID="Deut.3.1"/> We then moved up in the direction of Bashan, and Og king of Bashan with all his host
       attacked us in battle at Edrei. <verse eID="Deut.3.1"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.3.2" osisID="Deut.3.2"/> But the Eternal said to me, <q>Do not fear him, for I hand him over to you, with all
       his host and his land; you shall do to him what you did to Sihon king of the Amorites who lived at Heshbon.</q> <verse eID="Deut.3.2"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.3.3" osisID="Deut.3.3"/> So the Eternal our God put Og king of Bashan also into our hands, together with all
       his host; we defeated him, till not a survivor was left, <verse eID="Deut.3.3"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.3.4" osisID="Deut.3.4"/> and we captured all his towns--there was not a town that we did not take—sixty towns
       in all, in the region of Argob, Og’s realm in Bashan. <verse eID="Deut.3.4"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.3.5" osisID="Deut.3.5"/> All these towns, fortified with high walls, gates, and bars, besides many an open
       hamlet, <verse eID="Deut.3.5"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.3.6" osisID="Deut.3.6"/> we exterminated, as we did in the case of Sihon king of Heshbon, putting the citizens
       to death, men, women, and children, <verse eID="Deut.3.6"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.3.7" osisID="Deut.3.7"/> but keeping all the cattle and the plunder of the towns as our prey. <verse eID="Deut.3.7"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Deut.3.8" osisID="Deut.3.8"/> Thus did we seize the land of the two Amorite kings east of the Jordan, from the wady
       of Arnon to mount Hermon
      <verse eID="Deut.3.8"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.3.9" osisID="Deut.3.9"/>
       (called Sirion by the Phoenicians, and
       <milestone type="pb" n="201"/>
       Senir by the Amorites), <verse eID="Deut.3.9"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.3.10" osisID="Deut.3.10"/> all the towns of the tableland, all Gilead and all Baslian as far as Salchah and
       Edrei, towns belonging to Og’s realm in Bashan. <verse eID="Deut.3.10"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.3.11" osisID="Deut.3.11"/> [[Og king of Bashan was the only survivor left of the Titans; his sarcophagus of
       ba­salt, is it not lying still at Kabbah-Ammon, fourteen feet long and six feet broad?]] <verse eID="Deut.3.11"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Deut.3.12" osisID="Deut.3.12"/> Of this country which we cap­tured at that time, I gave the Reubenites and the
       Gadites the land north of Aroer on the wady of Arnon and half of the highlands of Gilead, towns and all; <verse eID="Deut.3.12"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.3.13" osisID="Deut.3.13"/> the rest of Gilead and the whole of Bashan, Og’s realm, the whole of the Argob
       region, I gave to the half-clan of Manasseh. [[This Bashan is all called a land of the Titans; <verse eID="Deut.3.13"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.3.14" osisID="Deut.3.14"/> it was Jair a Manassite who captured the whole of the Argob region to the frontiers
       of the Geshurites and the Maacathites, call­ing this part of Bashan <q>Havvoth-jair</q> after himself--a name that lasts to
       this day. <verse eID="Deut.3.14"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.3.15" osisID="Deut.3.15"/> To Machir I gave Gilead. <verse eID="Deut.3.15"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.3.16" osisID="Deut.3.16"/> To the Reubenites and the Gadites I gave the country from Gilead to the Arnon wady,
       with the middle of the wady as a bound­ary, as far north as the Jabbok wady, which bounds the Amorites, <verse eID="Deut.3.16"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.3.17" osisID="Deut.3.17"/> along with the Arabah, bounded by the Jordan, from the lake of Kinnereth to the sea
       of the Arabah, the Salt Sea, lying under the slopes of Pisgah to the east.]] <verse eID="Deut.3.17"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Deut.3.18" osisID="Deut.3.18"/> I gave you these orders then: <q>The Eternal your God has given you this land for
       your own; all your warriors shall march on under arms, in front of your fellow-Israelites. <verse eID="Deut.3.18"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.3.19" osisID="Deut.3.19"/> But your wives and children and cattle (and I know you have many cattle) shall
       remain here in the towns I have assigned you, <verse eID="Deut.3.19"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.3.20" osisID="Deut.3.20"/> till such time as the Eternal has settled not only yourselves but your fellows,
       till such time as they get possession of the land which the Eternal your God assigns them west of the Jordan. Then you can
       each go home to the land I have assigned you as your own.</q> <verse eID="Deut.3.20"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.3.21" osisID="Deut.3.21"/> I also gave these orders to Joshua then: <q>Your eyes have seen all that the
       Eter­nal your God has done to these two kings; so shall the Eternal do to all the realms you are crossing to invade. <verse eID="Deut.3.21"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.3.22" osisID="Deut.3.22"/> Fear them not; it is the Eternal your God who fights for you.</q> <verse eID="Deut.3.22"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Deut.3.23" osisID="Deut.3.23"/> I also entreated the Eternal then, saying: <verse eID="Deut.3.23"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.3.24" osisID="Deut.3.24"/> <q>O Eternal, my Lord, thou hast only begun to let thy servant see how great and
       strong thou art; what god in heaven or earth could do deeds like to thine, and mighty acts like thine? <verse eID="Deut.3.24"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.3.25" osisID="Deut.3.25"/> Ah, let me cross and see the fine land over the Jordan, the fair hill-country, and
       Lebanon.</q> <verse eID="Deut.3.25"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.3.26" osisID="Deut.3.26"/> But the Eternal was wroth with me on your account and would not listen to me.
       <q>Enough of this,</q> said the Eternal, <q>say not another word about it. <verse eID="Deut.3.26"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.3.27" osisID="Deut.3.27"/> Climb to the top of Pisgah and look round you, west, north, south, and east: look,
       for you shall never cross this Jordan. <verse eID="Deut.3.27"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.3.28" osisID="Deut.3.28"/> But counsel Joshua, nerve him, strengthen him, for he shall lead the people across
       and he shall put them in possession of the land on which you look.</q> <verse eID="Deut.3.28"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.3.29" osisID="Deut.3.29"/> (We were in the valley opposite Beth-peor.) <verse eID="Deut.3.29"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eId="Deut.3"/>
    <chapter osisId="Deut.4" sId="Deut.4"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Deut.4.1" osisID="Deut.4.1"/>And now, O Israel, listen to the rules and regulations that I teach you, and obey
       them, so that you may live and enter on possession of the land which the Eternal the God of your
       <milestone type="pb" n="202"/>
       fathers is assigning you. <verse eID="Deut.4.1"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.4.2" osisID="Deut.4.2"/> You shall not add one word to my commands, nor take one word from them; you shall
       obey the commands of the Eternal your God which I enjoin upon you. <verse eID="Deut.4.2"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.4.3" osisID="Deut.4.3"/> You have seen for yourselves what the Eternal did at Baal-peor; the Eternal your God
       has killed every man of you who followed the Baal of Peor, <verse eID="Deut.4.3"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.4.4" osisID="Deut.4.4"/> but those of you who held to the Eternal your God are all alive to-day. <verse eID="Deut.4.4"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Deut.4.5" osisID="Deut.4.5"/> Here am I teaching you, as the Eternal my God ordered me, the rules and regulations
       for what you are to do in the land you are entering to possess; <verse eID="Deut.4.5"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.4.6" osisID="Deut.4.6"/> keep them, obey them, for that will prove your wisdom and intelligence to the
       nations; when they hear all these rules they will say, <q>This great nation is indeed a wise, intelligent race!</q> <verse eID="Deut.4.6"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.4.7" osisID="Deut.4.7"/> For what great nation has a god so near to it as the Eternal our God is, whenever we
       invoke him? <verse eID="Deut.4.7"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.4.8" osisID="Deut.4.8"/> What great nation has rules and regulations as just as all this code that I am
       putting before you now? <verse eID="Deut.4.8"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.4.9" osisID="Deut.4.9"/> Only be careful to watch yourselves well, all through your life, lest you for­get what
       you have seen for yourselves, and let it pass from your mind; impart it to your children and your children’s children, <verse eID="Deut.4.9"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.4.10" osisID="Deut.4.10"/> the story of the day when you stood before the Eternal your God at Horeb and the
       Eternal said to me, <q>Gather the people round me, and I will let them hear my words, that they may learn to reverence me all
       the days of their life on earth, and that they may instruct their children in reverence</q>-- <verse eID="Deut.4.10"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.4.11" osisID="Deut.4.11"/> the story of how you approached and stood below the mountain that flamed up to the
       very heart of heaven, shrouded in darkness, cloud, and gloom, <verse eID="Deut.4.11"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.4.12" osisID="Deut.4.12"/> and how the Eternal spoke to you out of the flames. You heard the sound of words,
       but you saw no shape; it was only a voice. <verse eID="Deut.4.12"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.4.13" osisID="Deut.4.13"/> He made known to you his compact, the ten sayings which he ordered you to obey,
       writing them on two stone tablets. <verse eID="Deut.4.13"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.4.14" osisID="Deut.4.14"/> The Eternal then ordered me to teach you rules and regulations to be fol­lowed in
       the land which you are entering to possess. <verse eID="Deut.4.14"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.4.15" osisID="Deut.4.15"/> Now, be careful. You saw no shape on the day when the Eternal spoke to you out of
       the flames at Horeb; <verse eID="Deut.4.15"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.4.16" osisID="Deut.4.16"/> beware, then, of depraving yourselves by carving an idol in the shape of any statue,
       either male or female, <verse eID="Deut.4.16"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.4.17" osisID="Deut.4.17"/> or like any beast on earth, any bird that flies, <verse eID="Deut.4.17"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.4.18" osisID="Deut.4.18"/> any insect crawling on the ground, or any fish in the sea; <verse eID="Deut.4.18"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.4.19" osisID="Deut.4.19"/> beware of looking up to the sky and then, as you see the whole host of heaven, the
       sun and moon and stars, letting yourselves be allured to bend in worship of them. The Eter­nal your God has allotted them for
       worship to all nations under the broad sky, <verse eID="Deut.4.19"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.4.20" osisID="Deut.4.20"/> but the Eternal took you and lifted you from the iron furnace of Egypt, to be a
       people of his own, as it is to-day. <verse eID="Deut.4.20"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.4.21" osisID="Deut.4.21"/> Besides, while the Eternal was angry with me on your account and swore that I was
       not to cross the Jordan, nor to enter the fine country which the Eternal assigns to you as your possession, <verse eID="Deut.4.21"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.4.22" osisID="Deut.4.22"/> but that I must die here, instead of crossing the Jordan, you are to cross it and
       take possession of that fine country. <verse eID="Deut.4.22"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.4.23" osisID="Deut.4.23"/> So be careful never to forget the com­pact that the Eternal your God has made with
       you, never to carve an idol in the shape of
       <milestone type="pb" n="203"/>
       anything forbidden by the Eternal your God. <verse eID="Deut.4.23"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.4.24" osisID="Deut.4.24"/> For the Eternal your God is a consuming fire, a jeal­ous God. <verse eID="Deut.4.24"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Deut.4.25" osisID="Deut.4.25"/>When you produce children and children’s children, if you lose your freshness in the
       land and deprave yourselves by carv­ing an idol in the sight of the Eternal your God, and so vexing him, <verse eID="Deut.4.25"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.4.26" osisID="Deut.4.26"/> then here and now I call heaven and earth to witness against you, that you will
       soon be wiped out of the land which you are crossing Jordan to pos­sess; you shall not live long there, you shall be wiped out.
      <verse eID="Deut.4.26"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.4.27" osisID="Deut.4.27"/> The Eternal will scatter you among the nations; few of you will be left among the
       nations where the Eternal exiles you, <verse eID="Deut.4.27"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.4.28" osisID="Deut.4.28"/> and there you will have to wor­ship hand-made gods, gods of wood and stone that
       neither see nor hear nor eat nor smell. <verse eID="Deut.4.28"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.4.29" osisID="Deut.4.29"/> Yet if there you seek the Eternal your God, you shall find him, provided that you
       seek for him with all your mind and all your soul. <verse eID="Deut.4.29"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.4.30" osisID="Deut.4.30"/> When you are in anguish, with all these woes upon you, in the end you shall come
       back to the Eternal your God and listen to his voice; <verse eID="Deut.4.30"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.4.31" osisID="Deut.4.31"/> for the Eter­nal your God is a merciful God, he will not let you go, he will not
       destroy you, he will not forget the compact he swore to your fathers. <verse eID="Deut.4.31"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Deut.4.32" osisID="Deut.4.32"/><q>Ask the days of old, ere ever you were born, ask if anything as great has ever
       happened or been heard of, from one end of the world to another, ever since the day that God made man upon earth: <verse eID="Deut.4.32"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.4.33" osisID="Deut.4.33"/> did any nation ever hear the voice of a god speaking from fire, as you have heard,
       and remain alive? <verse eID="Deut.4.33"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.4.34" osisID="Deut.4.34"/> Has any god ever ventured to go and take a nation for himself out of another nation
       by a series of tests, by signal acts, by war, by sheer strength and main force, with awful terrors, as you saw the Eternal
       your God do for you in Egypt? <verse eID="Deut.4.34"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.4.35" osisID="Deut.4.35"/> You had all this shown to you, to teach you that the Eternal is God and God alone.
      <verse eID="Deut.4.35"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.4.36" osisID="Deut.4.36"/> He let you hear his voice out of heaven, for discipline, and on earth he let you
       see his mighty fire--you heard his voice out of the flames. <verse eID="Deut.4.36"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.4.37" osisID="Deut.4.37"/> And because he loved your fathers and chose their descend­ants after them, because
       he brought you out of Egypt with his own presence and his mighty power, <verse eID="Deut.4.37"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.4.38" osisID="Deut.4.38"/> dispossessing nations greater and stronger than your­selves that he might bring you
       in to let you have their land for your own, as it is to-day, <verse eID="Deut.4.38"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.4.39" osisID="Deut.4.39"/> therefore be sure of this, remind your­selves, that it is the Eternal who is God in
       heaven above and on the earth beneath, the only God. <verse eID="Deut.4.39"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.4.40" osisID="Deut.4.40"/> You must obey his rules and orders which I command you this day, that all may go
       well with you and with your children after you, and that you may live long on the land which the Eternal your God assigns you.
       </q> <verse eID="Deut.4.40"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Deut.4.41" osisID="Deut.4.41"/> Then Moses set apart three towns across the Jordan towards the east, <verse eID="Deut.4.41"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.4.42" osisID="Deut.4.42"/> as a refuge for the homicide who had killed some neighbour unintentionally, not on
       account of any previous feud; he might save his life by running to one of those towns, <verse eID="Deut.4.42"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.4.43" osisID="Deut.4.43"/> to Bezer on the table-land (which was meant for the Reubenites), to Ramoth in
       Gilead (which was meant for the Gadites), or to Golan in Bashan (which was meant for the Manassites). <verse eID="Deut.4.43"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Deut.4.44" osisID="Deut.4.44"/> Here is the code which Moses put before the Israelites: <verse eID="Deut.4.44"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.4.45" osisID="Deut.4.45"/> here
       <milestone type="pb" n="204"/>
       are the decrees, the rules, and the regulations which Moses issued to the Israelites when they left Egypt, <verse eID="Deut.4.45"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.4.46" osisID="Deut.4.46"/> when they were east of the Jordan, in the valley opposite Beth-peor, in the land of
       Sihon king of the Amorites whose capital was Heshbon, and whom Moses and the Israelites defeated after they left Egypt, <verse eID="Deut.4.46"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.4.47" osisID="Deut.4.47"/> taking possession of his land and also the land of Og king of Bashan, the two
       Amorite kings who lived to the east of the Jordan <verse eID="Deut.4.47"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.4.48" osisID="Deut.4.48"/> from Aroer on the edge of the Arnon wady as far as to mount Sion (that is, Hermon),
      <verse eID="Deut.4.48"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.4.49" osisID="Deut.4.49"/> with all the Arabah east of the Jordan down to the sea of the Arabah which lies
       under the slopes of Pisgah. <verse eID="Deut.4.49"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eId="Deut.4"/>
    <chapter osisId="Deut.5" sId="Deut.5"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Deut.5.1" osisID="Deut.5.1"/>Moses summoned all Israel and said to them: <q>O Israel, listen to the rules and
       regula­tions which I announce in your hearing this day, that you may learn them and be careful to obey them. <verse eID="Deut.5.1"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.5.2" osisID="Deut.5.2"/> The Eternal our God has made a compact with us at Horeb; <verse eID="Deut.5.2"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.5.3" osisID="Deut.5.3"/> the Eternal made this compact, not with our fore­fathers but with ourselves, with us
       who are all here and now alive. <verse eID="Deut.5.3"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.5.4" osisID="Deut.5.4"/> The Eternal spoke to you face to face, out of the fire at the hill, <verse eID="Deut.5.4"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.5.5" osisID="Deut.5.5"/> while I stood between the Eternal and you, in order to report what the Eternal
       said--for you were ter­rified at the fire and would not ascend the hill. He said: <verse eID="Deut.5.5"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.5.6" osisID="Deut.5.6"/> <q>I am the Eternal your God, who brought you from the land of Egypt, that
       slave-pen.</q></q> <verse eID="Deut.5.6"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Deut.5.7" osisID="Deut.5.7"/><q><q>You shall have no gods but me.</q></q><verse eID="Deut.5.7"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Deut.5.8" osisID="Deut.5.8"/><q><q>You shall not carve for your­selves any idol, the shape of anything in heaven
       above or on the earth below or in the sea: <verse eID="Deut.5.8"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.5.9" osisID="Deut.5.9"/> you shall not bow down to them nor worship them, for I the Eternal your God am a
       jealous God, punishing children for the sins of their fathers, punishing those who hate me, to the third and the fourth
       gen­eration, <verse eID="Deut.5.9"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.5.10" osisID="Deut.5.10"/> but showing kindness to thousands of those who love me and obey my orders.</q></q><verse eID="Deut.5.10"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Deut.5.11" osisID="Deut.5.11"/><q><q> You shall not use the name of the Eternal, your God, pro­fanely; for the
       Eternal will never acquit anyone who uses his name profanely.</q></q> <verse eID="Deut.5.11"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Deut.5.12" osisID="Deut.5.12"/><q><q> Keep the sabbath sacred, as the Eternal your God has ordered you. <verse eID="Deut.5.12"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.5.13" osisID="Deut.5.13"/> Six days you may labour and do all your business, <verse eID="Deut.5.13"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.5.14" osisID="Deut.5.14"/> but the seventh day is the sabbath in honour of the Eternal, your God, and on it
       you must not do any business, neither you nor your son nor your daughter nor your slaves, male or female, nor your ox nor your
       ass nor any of your cattle, nor the alien who is among you. Your slaves, male and female, are to rest as well as yourselves. <verse eID="Deut.5.14"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.5.15" osisID="Deut.5.15"/> Remember that you were once slaves in the land of Egypt, and that the Eternal your
       God brought you out by sheer strength and main force. Hence the Eternal your God has or­dered you to keep the sabbath.</q></q>
      <verse eID="Deut.5.15"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Deut.5.16" osisID="Deut.5.16"/><q><q> Honour your father and your mother, as the Eternal your God has ordered you,
       that you may have a long life and that all may go well with you in the land which the Eternal your God is giving you.</q></q>
      <verse eID="Deut.5.16"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Deut.5.17" osisID="Deut.5.17"/><q><q>You shall not murder, <verse eID="Deut.5.17"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.5.18" osisID="Deut.5.18"/> nor commit adultery, <verse eID="Deut.5.18"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.5.19" osisID="Deut.5.19"/> nor steal, <verse eID="Deut.5.19"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.5.20" osisID="Deut.5.20"/> nor give false evidence against a fellow-countryman, <verse eID="Deut.5.20"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.5.21" osisID="Deut.5.21"/> nor lust after his wife, nor covet his household, his property, his slaves, male or
       female, his ox,
       <milestone type="pb" n="205"/>
       his ass, or anything that be­longs to a fellow-countryman.</q></q> <verse eID="Deut.5.21"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Deut.5.22" osisID="Deut.5.22"/><q>These sayings the Eternal spoke to all your gathering at the mountain, speaking
       with a loud voice out of the flames, the cloud, and the black darkness. He then ceased, and wrote them on two stone tablets
       which he handed to me. <verse eID="Deut.5.22"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.5.23" osisID="Deut.5.23"/> And when you heard the voice out of the dark­ness, as the mountain was aflame with
       fire, you ap­proached me, that is, all the chiefs of your clans and your sheikhs, <verse eID="Deut.5.23"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.5.24" osisID="Deut.5.24"/> saying, <q>Here has the Eternal our God shown us his glory and greatness; we have
       heard his voice out of the flames, we have seen to-day how a man can live after God has spoken to him. <verse eID="Deut.5.24"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.5.25" osisID="Deut.5.25"/> But why are we to die? This great fire will burn us up; if we hear the voice of the
       Eternal our God any longer, we shall die. <verse eID="Deut.5.25"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.5.26" osisID="Deut.5.26"/> For what mortal ever lived after hearing the voice of a living God out of the
       flames, as we have heard it? <verse eID="Deut.5.26"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.5.27" osisID="Deut.5.27"/> Do you ap­proach the Eternal our God, and hear all he has to say; then tell us
       whatever the Eternal our God tells you, and we will listen and obey.</q> <verse eID="Deut.5.27"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.5.28" osisID="Deut.5.28"/> The Eter­nal heard what you said to me, and the Eternal said to me, <q>I have heard
       what this people says to you; they are right. <verse eID="Deut.5.28"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.5.29" osisID="Deut.5.29"/> If only they had always a mind like this, to reverence me and obey all my orders,
       so that things might always go well with them and with their children! <verse eID="Deut.5.29"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.5.30" osisID="Deut.5.30"/> Tell them to go home to their tents, <verse eID="Deut.5.30"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.5.31" osisID="Deut.5.31"/> but do you stand beside me here, and I will tell you all the code, the rules and
       regulations, which you are to teach them to obey within the land which I am giving them for their own. <verse eID="Deut.5.31"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.5.32" osisID="Deut.5.32"/> Be mindful then, to do as the Eternal your God has ordered you; you must not
       swerve to the right or to the left, <verse eID="Deut.5.32"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.5.33" osisID="Deut.5.33"/> but always follow the straight road of life which the Eternal your God has laid
       down for you, that you may live, that things may go well with you, and that you may have a long life in the land that is to
       be your own.</q></q> <verse eID="Deut.5.33"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eId="Deut.5"/>
    <chapter osisId="Deut.6" sId="Deut.6"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Deut.6.1" osisID="Deut.6.1"/>Now here is the code, the rules and regulations, which O the Eternal your God has
       di­rected that you are to be taught to follow in the land which you are crossing to make your own, a land abounding with milk
       and honey, <verse eID="Deut.6.1"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.6.2" osisID="Deut.6.2"/> that you may reverence the Eternal your God by obey­ing all his rules and orders all
       your life, as I enjoin them upon you and your sons and your grandsons, that you may have a long life. <verse eID="Deut.6.2"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.6.3" osisID="Deut.6.3"/> Listen then, Israel, and be mindful to obey, that things may go well with you, and
       that you may multiply greatly, as the Eternal the God of your fathers has promised you. <verse eID="Deut.6.3"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Deut.6.4" osisID="Deut.6.4"/> Listen, Israel: <q>the Eternal, the Eternal alone, is our God. <verse eID="Deut.6.4"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.6.5" osisID="Deut.6.5"/> And you must love the Eternal your God with all your mind and all your soul and all
       your strength.</q> <verse eID="Deut.6.5"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.6.6" osisID="Deut.6.6"/> These words you must learn by heart, this charge of mine; <verse eID="Deut.6.6"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.6.7" osisID="Deut.6.7"/> you must impress them on your children, you must talk about them when you are
       sit­ting at home and when you are on the road, when you lie down and when you rise up. <verse eID="Deut.6.7"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.6.8" osisID="Deut.6.8"/> You must tie them on your hands as a memento, and wear them on your forehead as a
       badge; <verse eID="Deut.6.8"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.6.9" osisID="Deut.6.9"/> you must inscribe them on the door-posts of your houses and on your gates. <verse eID="Deut.6.9"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.6.10" osisID="Deut.6.10"/> And when the Eternal your God brings you
       <milestone type="pb" n="206"/>
       into the land which he swore to your fathers, Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob, that he would give you, with its great, splendid
       towns, which you never built, <verse eID="Deut.6.10"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.6.11" osisID="Deut.6.11"/> with houses full of all stores, which you never gathered, with reservoirs that you
       never dug, and with vines and olives that you never planted, when you eat and are satisfied, <verse eID="Deut.6.11"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.6.12" osisID="Deut.6.12"/> then be­ware of forgetting the Eternal, who brought you out of the land of Egypt,
       that slave-pen. <verse eID="Deut.6.12"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.6.13" osisID="Deut.6.13"/> You must reverence the Eternal your God, you must worship him, and by his name you
       must swear. <verse eID="Deut.6.13"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.6.14" osisID="Deut.6.14"/> You must never follow any other gods, belonging to the nations round you <verse eID="Deut.6.14"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.6.15" osisID="Deut.6.15"/> (for the Eternal your God, who is among you, is a jealous God), lest the anger of
       the Eternal your God blaze out against you and wipe you off the face of the earth. <verse eID="Deut.6.15"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.6.16" osisID="Deut.6.16"/> You must not put the Eternal your God to the proof, as you did at Massah. <verse eID="Deut.6.16"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.6.17" osisID="Deut.6.17"/> You must be careful to obey the orders of the Eternal your God, the decrees and
       rules which he has enjoined upon you; <verse eID="Deut.6.17"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.6.18" osisID="Deut.6.18"/> you must do whatever the Eternal holds to be right and good, that things may go
       well with you, and that you may enter into possession of the fine country which the Eternal swore to your fathers <verse eID="Deut.6.18"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.6.19" osisID="Deut.6.19"/> that he would clear of all enemies for you, as he promised. <verse eID="Deut.6.19"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Deut.6.20" osisID="Deut.6.20"/> When your son asks you, in time to come, about the mean­ing of the decrees and
       rules and regulations which the Eternal our God has enjoined upon you, <verse eID="Deut.6.20"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.6.21" osisID="Deut.6.21"/> then you must tell your son, <q>We were once the Pharaoh’s slaves in Egypt, but
       the Eternal brought us out of Egypt by sheer strength. <verse eID="Deut.6.21"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.6.22" osisID="Deut.6.22"/> The Eternal displayed signal acts, awful and heavy, against the Pharaoh and all
       his household before our very eyes, <verse eID="Deut.6.22"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.6.23" osisID="Deut.6.23"/> but he brought us out, to bring us into the land which he had sworn to our fathers
       that he would give us. <verse eID="Deut.6.23"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.6.24" osisID="Deut.6.24"/> And the Eternal ordered us to keep all these rules, and to reverence the Eternal
       our God, for our own lasting good, that he might keep us alive, as alive we are to-day. <verse eID="Deut.6.24"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.6.25" osisID="Deut.6.25"/> It will be the saving of us if we are mindful before the Eternal our God to do all
       these orders of his.</q> <verse eID="Deut.6.25"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eId="Deut.6"/>
    <chapter osisId="Deut.7" sId="Deut.7"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Deut.7.1" osisID="Deut.7.1"/>When the Eternal your God brings you into the land of which you are going to take
       possession, and clears it of many a nation for you, of the Hittites, the Girgashites, the Amorites, the Canaanites, the
       Perizzites, the Hivites, and the Jebusites, seven nations greater and stronger than yourselves, <verse eID="Deut.7.1"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.7.2" osisID="Deut.7.2"/> when the Eternal your God puts them into your hands and you rout them, then you must
       exterminate them, making no compact with them and show­ing them no mercy; <verse eID="Deut.7.2"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.7.3" osisID="Deut.7.3"/> you must not intermarry with them, you must never let your daughters marry their
       sons nor your sons their daughters, <verse eID="Deut.7.3"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.7.4" osisID="Deut.7.4"/> for they will seduce your sons from following me to worshipping other gods, and the
       anger of the Eternal will blaze out against you, till he destroys you rapidly.
      <verse eID="Deut.7.4"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.7.5" osisID="Deut.7.5"/> This is how you are to treat them: demolish their altars, break their obelisks, cut
       down their sacred poles, and burn up their carved idols. <verse eID="Deut.7.5"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.7.6" osisID="Deut.7.6"/> For you are a people sacred to the Eternal your God; the Eternal your God has chosen
       you to be his prized possession, out of all nations on the face of the earth.
      <verse eID="Deut.7.6"/>
      <milestone type="pb" n="207"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.7.7" osisID="Deut.7.7"/> It was not because you were larger than any other nation, that the Eternal set his
       heart upon you and chose you; no, you were the smallest of the nations. <verse eID="Deut.7.7"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.7.8" osisID="Deut.7.8"/> It was because the Eternal loves you, because he meant to keep his oath to your
       fathers, that the Eternal has brought you out by sheer strength, rescuing you from that slave-pen, from the power of the
       Pharaoh, king of Egypt. <verse eID="Deut.7.8"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.7.9" osisID="Deut.7.9"/> Understand, then, that the Eternal your God is God indeed, a faithful God who
       carries out his compact of kindness to those who love him and carry out his orders, for a thousand generations, <verse eID="Deut.7.9"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.7.10" osisID="Deut.7.10"/> a God who repays those that hate him by destroy­ing them personally--he never
       delays to deal with anyone who hates him, he repays him personally. <verse eID="Deut.7.10"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.7.11" osisID="Deut.7.11"/> So keep the orders, the rules and regulations, which I enjoin upon you to-day, and
       carry them out. <verse eID="Deut.7.11"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Deut.7.12" osisID="Deut.7.12"/> And as you listen to these regulations, as you keep them and carry them out, the
       Eternal your God will carry out for you the compact of kindness which he swore to your fathers; <verse eID="Deut.7.12"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.7.13" osisID="Deut.7.13"/> he will love you, prosper you, and multiply you, he will prosper the fruit of your
       womb and the fruit of your ground, your corn and wine and oil, the young of your cattle and the lambs of your flock, in the
       land which he swore to your fathers that he would give to you. <verse eID="Deut.7.13"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.7.14" osisID="Deut.7.14"/> You shall have more prosperity than any nation; not a male or female shall be
       barren among you or among your cattle. <verse eID="Deut.7.14"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.7.15" osisID="Deut.7.15"/>The Eternal will also free you from all sickness; he will not inflict upon you any
       of the evil diseases of Egypt which you know so well, but will inflict them upon all who hate you. <verse eID="Deut.7.15"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Deut.7.16" osisID="Deut.7.16"/> And you must annihilate all the nations whom the Eternal your God puts into your
       hands, without pity; you must never worship their gods, for that will endanger you. <verse eID="Deut.7.16"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.7.17" osisID="Deut.7.17"/> If you say to yourselves, <q>But these nations are stronger than I am; how can I
       disposses them?</q> <verse eID="Deut.7.17"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.7.18" osisID="Deut.7.18"/> never fear them; be sure to remember what the Eternal your God did to the Pharaoh
       and to all Egypt, <verse eID="Deut.7.18"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.7.19" osisID="Deut.7.19"/> the terrible tests you saw with your own eyes, the signal acts, the sheer
       strength and main force, by means of which the Eternal your God brought you out. So shall the Eternal your God do to all the
       nations of whom you are afraid. <verse eID="Deut.7.19"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.7.20" osisID="Deut.7.20"/> Yes, the Eternal your God will send hornets among them, till their survivors hide
       and die off before you. <verse eID="Deut.7.20"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.7.21" osisID="Deut.7.21"/> You must not dread them, for the Eternal your God is among you, a great and awful
       God. <verse eID="Deut.7.21"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Deut.7.22" osisID="Deut.7.22"/> The Eternal your God will only clear out these nations gradually; you are not to
       annihi­late them all at once, lest wild beasts grow too numerous for you. <verse eID="Deut.7.22"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.7.23" osisID="Deut.7.23"/> But the Eternal your God will put them into your hands and rout them in a crush­ing
       defeat, till they are de­stroyed; <verse eID="Deut.7.23"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.7.24" osisID="Deut.7.24"/> he will hand over their kings to you, till you wipe out the very name of them
       under heaven; not a man shall be able to hold his own against you, till you destroy them. <verse eID="Deut.7.24"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.7.25" osisID="Deut.7.25"/> Burn up the carved images of their gods; you must not covet the silver or the gold
       upon them, you must not keep it for yourselves, or you will be en­dangered; it is an abomination to the Eternal your God, <verse eID="Deut.7.25"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.7.26" osisID="Deut.7.26"/> and you must not let any
       <milestone type="pb" n="208"/>
       abomination into your houses and so share its doom; you must loathe it and detest it, as a doomed thing. <verse eID="Deut.7.26"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eId="Deut.7"/>
    <chapter osisId="Deut.8" sId="Deut.8"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Deut.8.1" osisID="Deut.8.1"/>All that I order you to-day, you must be mindful to do, that you may live and
       multiply and enter on possession of the land which the Eternal swore to your fathers; <verse eID="Deut.8.1"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.8.2" osisID="Deut.8.2"/> and you must remember all about how the Eternal your God led you through the desert
       during these forty years, to teach you your need of him, to prove you, to find out if it was your purpose to obey his orders
       or not. <verse eID="Deut.8.2"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.8.3" osisID="Deut.8.3"/> So he made you feel your need of him, he let you hunger and then fed you with manna,
       which neither you nor your fathers had ever known, that he might make you know that man lives not only by food but by every
       word that comes out of the lips of the Eternal. <verse eID="Deut.8.3"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.8.4" osisID="Deut.8.4"/> Your clothes never wore out, and your feet never blistered, during these forty
       years. <verse eID="Deut.8.4"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.8.5" osisID="Deut.8.5"/> You must keep this in mind, that the Eternal your God disciplines you as a man
       disciplines his son. <verse eID="Deut.8.5"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.8.6" osisID="Deut.8.6"/> You must obey the orders of the Eternal your God by living his life and reverencing
       him, <verse eID="Deut.8.6"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.8.7" osisID="Deut.8.7"/> for the Eternal your God is bring­ing you into a fine country, a country with
       streams of water, with springs and pools, welling up in valleys and on the hills, <verse eID="Deut.8.7"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.8.8" osisID="Deut.8.8"/> a country of wheat and barley, of vines and fig-trees and pome­granates, of olive
       oil and honey, <verse eID="Deut.8.8"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.8.9" osisID="Deut.8.9"/> a country where you can eat and never famish, where you shall lack for nothing, a
       country whose ore is iron and from whose hills you can dig copper. <verse eID="Deut.8.9"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.8.10" osisID="Deut.8.10"/> You shall eat and be satisfied, and you shall bless the Eternal your God for the
       fine country he has given you. <verse eID="Deut.8.10"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Deut.8.11" osisID="Deut.8.11"/> Beware of forgetting the Eternal your God by failing to obey his orders and
       regulations and rules, which I enjoin upon you this day; <verse eID="Deut.8.11"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.8.12" osisID="Deut.8.12"/> lest, when you have eaten and satisfied your­selves, when you have built grand
       houses to live in, <verse eID="Deut.8.12"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.8.13" osisID="Deut.8.13"/> when your herds and flocks multiply and your silver and gold in­crease, and all
       you possess grows larger, <verse eID="Deut.8.13"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.8.14" osisID="Deut.8.14"/> then you turn proud and forget the Eternal your God, who brought you out of the
       land of Egypt, from that slave-pen, <verse eID="Deut.8.14"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.8.15" osisID="Deut.8.15"/> who led you through the wide, awful desert, with its stinging serpents and
       scor­pions and its thirsty, waterless ground, who brought you water out of the flinty rock, <verse eID="Deut.8.15"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.8.16" osisID="Deut.8.16"/> who fed you in the desert with manna, which your fathers had never known, that he
       might teach you your need of him and prove you, in order to make you prosper in the end. <verse eID="Deut.8.16"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Deut.8.17" osisID="Deut.8.17"/> Beware of saying to yourselves, <q>My own power and the strength of my own hand
       have won me all this wealth.</q> <verse eID="Deut.8.17"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.8.18" osisID="Deut.8.18"/> You must remember the Eternal your God, for it is he who gives you the power of
       gain­ing wealth, that he may ratify the compact which he swore to your fathers, as it is to­day. <verse eID="Deut.8.18"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.8.19" osisID="Deut.8.19"/> If ever you forget the Eternal your God and follow other gods, worshipping them
       and doing homage to them, then I testify against you this day that you shall be wiped out, wiped out <verse eID="Deut.8.19"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.8.20" osisID="Deut.8.20"/> like the nations which the Eternal is to wipe out before you, since you would not
       listen to the voice of the Eternal your God. <verse eID="Deut.8.20"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eId="Deut.8"/>
    <milestone type="pb" n="209"/>
    <chapter osisId="Deut.9" sId="Deut.9"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Deut.9.1" osisID="Deut.9.1"/>Listen, Israel: to-day you are to cross the Jordan, to invade and dispossess nations
       stronger and more powerful than your­selves, to take possession of towns large and walled up to the sky, <verse eID="Deut.9.1"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.9.2" osisID="Deut.9.2"/> a tall, doughty race, the giants you know so well, and of whom you have heard it
       said, <q>Who can stand up to the giants?</q> <verse eID="Deut.9.2"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.9.3" osisID="Deut.9.3"/> Be sure, then, this day, that it is the Eternal your God who goes in front of you
       as a consuming fire, to destroy them, to subdue them before you; so shall you drive them out and kill them off quickly, as
       the Eter­nal has promised you. <verse eID="Deut.9.3"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Deut.9.4" osisID="Deut.9.4"/>After the Eternal your God has cleared them out before you, never say to yourselves,
       <q>It is for my goodness that the Eternal has brought me in to possess this country.</q> <verse eID="Deut.9.4"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.9.5" osisID="Deut.9.5"/> For no goodness of yours, for no integrity of mind, are you entering upon
       pos­session of their country; it is on account of the vice of these na­tions that the Eternal your God is dispossessing them
       before you, and in order to fulfil the oath which the Eternal swore to your fathers Abraham and Isaac and Jacob. <verse eID="Deut.9.5"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Deut.9.6" osisID="Deut.9.6"/>Be sure of this, it is not for your goodness that the Eternal your God is giving you
       this fine country; for you are an obstinate race. <verse eID="Deut.9.6"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.9.7" osisID="Deut.9.7"/> Remember, never forget, how you provoked the Eternal your God to anger in the
       desert; from the day you left the land of Egypt to the day you arrived here, you Have been rebels against the Eternal. <verse eID="Deut.9.7"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Deut.9.8" osisID="Deut.9.8"/>Even at Horeb you provoked the Eternal to anger; indeed, the Eternal was so angry
       with you that he meant to kill you. <verse eID="Deut.9.8"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.9.9" osisID="Deut.9.9"/> I had gone up the hill to receive the stone tablets, the tablets of the compact
       which the Eternal made with you: I remained forty days and forty nights upon the hill, neither eating nor drinking <verse eID="Deut.9.9"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.9.10" osisID="Deut.9.10"/> [[and the Eternal handed me the two stone tablets, on which the divine fingers
       had inscribed all the words spoken to you at the hill by the Eternal out of the fire, on the day of your gathering]]; <verse eID="Deut.9.10"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.9.11" osisID="Deut.9.11"/> then, after the forty days and forty nights, the Eter­nal gave me the two stone
       tab­lets, the tablets of the compact, <verse eID="Deut.9.11"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.9.12" osisID="Deut.9.12"/> and the Eternal said to me, <q>Make haste, get away down, for your people whom
       you have brought out of Egypt have de­praved themselves, they have been quick to swerve from the line of my orders, they have
       made themselves a metal idol! <verse eID="Deut.9.12"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.9.13" osisID="Deut.9.13"/> I have watched this nation,</q> <verse eID="Deut.9.13"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.9.14" osisID="Deut.9.14"/> the Eternal added, <q> Not a word! Let me destroy them and blot out their name
       from under heaven; I will make you into a nation mightier and larger than they are.</q> <verse eID="Deut.9.14"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Deut.9.15" osisID="Deut.9.15"/> So I turned down the hill, which was blazing with fire, the two stone tablets in
       my hands; <verse eID="Deut.9.15"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.9.16" osisID="Deut.9.16"/> and when I looked, there you had sinned against the Eternal your God, you had
       made a molten calf, you had swerved quickly from the line of the Eternal’s orders! <verse eID="Deut.9.16"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.9.17" osisID="Deut.9.17"/> Seizing the two tablets, I flung them from my hands and broke them be­fore your
       eyes. <verse eID="Deut.9.17"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.9.18" osisID="Deut.9.18"/> And I lay down before the Eternal for forty days and forty nights as be­fore,
       neither eating nor drink­ing--for all the sin you had committed in doing what was evil in the sight of the Eternal,
       vexing him and provoking him to anger. <verse eID="Deut.9.18"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.9.19" osisID="Deut.9.19"/> (For I dreaded the anger and fierce wrath of the
       <milestone type="pb" n="210"/> Eternal against you, to your destruction. But again the Eternal listened to me;
      <verse eID="Deut.9.19"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.9.20" osisID="Deut.9.20"/> he was also angry with Aaron and would have destroyed him, but I prayed for Aaron
       also at the same time. <verse eID="Deut.9.20"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.9.21" osisID="Deut.9.21"/> Then, taking the sinful calf you had made, I burned it up, breaking it to pieces
       and grinding it down till it was crushed into a fine powder, and I threw the dust of it into the stream that flowed from the
       hill. <verse eID="Deut.9.21"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.9.22" osisID="Deut.9.22"/> At Taberah, at Massah, and at Kibroth-hattaavah also, you provoked the Eternal to
       anger. <verse eID="Deut.9.22"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.9.23" osisID="Deut.9.23"/> And when the Eternal sent you forward from Kadesh-barnea, telling you to march up
       and take ossession of the country which he had given to you, then you rebelled against the orders of the Eternal your God;
       you would not trust him nor listen to what he said. <verse eID="Deut.9.23"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.9.24" osisID="Deut.9.24"/> You have been rebels against the Eternal ever since he chose you.) <verse eID="Deut.9.24"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Deut.9.25" osisID="Deut.9.25"/> Well, I lay down before the Eternal for these forty days and forty nights,
       because the Eternal had threatened to destroy you; <verse eID="Deut.9.25"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.9.26" osisID="Deut.9.26"/> I prayed to the Eternal, <q>O Lord the Eternal, destroy not thy people, thine own
       people, whom thou hast rescued by thy might, whom thou hast brought out of Egypt by sheer strength. <verse eID="Deut.9.26"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.9.27" osisID="Deut.9.27"/> Remember thy servants Abra­ham and Isaac and Jacob. Heed not the obstinacy of this
       nation, nor their wickedness, nor their sin, <verse eID="Deut.9.27"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.9.28" osisID="Deut.9.28"/> lest the land from which thou didst bring us out may say, <q>The Eternal could not
       bring them to the land he promised them! The Eternal hated them; that is why he took them into the desert, to slay them!</q>
      <verse eID="Deut.9.28"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.9.29" osisID="Deut.9.29"/> And yet they are thy people, thy very own, whom thou didst bring out by sheer
       strength and main force.</q> <verse eID="Deut.9.29"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eId="Deut.9"/>
    <chapter osisId="Deut.10" sId="Deut.10"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Deut.10.1" osisID="Deut.10.1"/>The Eternal then said to me, <q>Cut two tablets of stone like the former ones, and
       come up the hill to me; make an ark of wood, <verse eID="Deut.10.1"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.10.2" osisID="Deut.10.2"/> and, when I have written on the tablets what was written on the former tablets
       which you broke, then put them inside the ark.</q> <verse eID="Deut.10.2"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.10.3" osisID="Deut.10.3"/> So I made an ark of acacia wood, cut two stone tablets like the former ones, and
       went up the hill, with the two tablets in my hand. <verse eID="Deut.10.3"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.10.4" osisID="Deut.10.4"/> The Eternal wrote on the tablets as before, the ten sayings which the Eternal had
       spoken out of the fire to you at the hill on the day of your gathering. He handed them to me, <verse eID="Deut.10.4"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.10.5" osisID="Deut.10.5"/> and going down the hill I did as the Eternal had ordered, I put the tablets
       inside the ark I had made, and there they lie. <verse eID="Deut.10.5"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.10.6" osisID="Deut.10.6"/> [[The Israelites marched from the wells of Bene-jaakan to Moserah, where Aaron
       died and was buried, Eleazar his son succeeding him in the office of priest. <verse eID="Deut.10.6"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.10.7" osisID="Deut.10.7"/> Thence they marched to Gudgodah, and from Gudgodah to Jotbathah, a district with
       streams of water. <verse eID="Deut.10.7"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.10.8" osisID="Deut.10.8"/> Then the Eternal set apart the clan of Levi to carry the ark of the Eternal’s
       compact, to serve the Eternal as his ministers, and to bless the others in his name, as they do to this day. <verse eID="Deut.10.8"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.10.9" osisID="Deut.10.9"/> Levi therefore enjoys no property or possession like his brothers; his possession
       is the Eternal, as the Eternal your God has prom­ised.]] <verse eID="Deut.10.9"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.10.10" osisID="Deut.10.10"/> As before, I remained on the hill for forty days and forty nights, and the
       Eter­nal again listened to me; the Eternal would not destroy you. <verse eID="Deut.10.10"/>
     </p>
     <milestone type="pb" n="211"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Deut.10.11" osisID="Deut.10.11"/>
       The Eternal said to me, <q>Go on your way at the head of the people, till they enter on pos­session of the country which I
       swore to their fathers that I would give to them.</q> <verse eID="Deut.10.11"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.10.12" osisID="Deut.10.12"/> And now, Israel, what is the Eternal your God asking from you but to reverence
       the Eter­nal your God, always to live his life, to love him, to worship the Eternal your God with all your mind and all your
       heart, <verse eID="Deut.10.12"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.10.13" osisID="Deut.10.13"/> and to obey the orders and rules of the Eternal which I am en­joining upon you
       for your own good this day? <verse eID="Deut.10.13"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.10.14" osisID="Deut.10.14"/> Why, al­though heaven, the highest heaven, belongs to the Eternal your God, and
       the earth with all it holds, <verse eID="Deut.10.14"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.10.15" osisID="Deut.10.15"/> yet the Eternal set his heart in love upon your fathers, and chose their
       descendants after them, chose you out of all nations, as it is to-day. <verse eID="Deut.10.15"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.10.16" osisID="Deut.10.16"/> Devote your heart to him then, and cease to be obstinate. <verse eID="Deut.10.16"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.10.17" osisID="Deut.10.17"/> For the Eternal your God is the supreme God, the supreme Lord, the great God,
       mighty and awful, never partial, never to be bribed; <verse eID="Deut.10.17"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.10.18" osisID="Deut.10.18"/> he secures justice for the orphan and the widow, and he loves an alien, giving
       him food and clothing. <verse eID="Deut.10.18"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.10.19" osisID="Deut.10.19"/> Love the alien, then: for once you were aliens yourselves in the land of Egypt.
      <verse eID="Deut.10.19"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Deut.10.20" osisID="Deut.10.20"/> You must reverence the Eter­nal your God; you must wor­ship him, you must be loyal
       to him, and by his name you shall swear. <verse eID="Deut.10.20"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.10.21" osisID="Deut.10.21"/> He it is whom you must praise; he is your God, who has done for you the great
       and awful deeds which you saw with your own eyes. <verse eID="Deut.10.21"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.10.22" osisID="Deut.10.22"/> Your fathers went down to Egypt, seventy in number; and now the Eternal your
       God has made you as numerous as the stars in the sky. <verse eID="Deut.10.22"/>
    <chapter eId="Deut.10"/>
    <chapter osisId="Deut.11" sId="Deut.11"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.11.1" osisID="Deut.11.1"/>So you must love the Eternal your God and always do your duty to him, obeying his
       injunctions, his rules, his regulations, and his orders. <verse eID="Deut.11.1"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Deut.11.2" osisID="Deut.11.2"/> And mark this day his discipline. For you are not like your children, who have
       neither known nor seen the discipline of the Eternal your God, his might, his sheer strength and main force, <verse eID="Deut.11.2"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.11.3" osisID="Deut.11.3"/> and the proofs of power he gave by what he did in Egypt to the Pharaoh king of
       Egypt and to all his land, <verse eID="Deut.11.3"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.11.4" osisID="Deut.11.4"/> or what he did to the horses and chariots of the Egyptian army, how he made the
       water of the Reed Sea overflow them as they chased you, and how the Eter­nal destroyed them finally, <verse eID="Deut.11.4"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.11.5" osisID="Deut.11.5"/> and how he treated you in the desert till you reached this place, <verse eID="Deut.11.5"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.11.6" osisID="Deut.11.6"/> and what he did to Dathan and Abiram, the sons of Eliab, Reuben’s son--how the
       earth yawned and swallowed them up with their households, their tents, and every animal in their train, before the eyes of
       all Israel. <verse eID="Deut.11.6"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.11.7" osisID="Deut.11.7"/> No, it is your eyes that have seen all the great ac­tions of the Eternal. <verse eID="Deut.11.7"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.11.8" osisID="Deut.11.8"/> Therefore you must obey all the orders I enjoin upon you this day, that you may
       be strong to enter upon possession of the country which you are crossing to make your own, <verse eID="Deut.11.8"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.11.9" osisID="Deut.11.9"/> and that your life may be long upon the land which the Eternal swore he would
       give to your fathers and their descend­ants, a land abounding in milk and honey. <verse eID="Deut.11.9"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Deut.11.10" osisID="Deut.11.10"/> For the land which you are entering to make your own is not like the land of
       Egypt from which you have come, a land where you sowed your seed and then watered it by working with
       <milestone type="pb" n="212"/>
       your foot, as in a vegetable garden; <verse eID="Deut.11.10"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.11.11" osisID="Deut.11.11"/> no, it is a land of hills and valleys, which drinks water as the rain falls,
      <verse eID="Deut.11.11"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.11.12" osisID="Deut.11.12"/> a land for which the Eternal your God cares--the eyes of the Eternal your God
       are always on it, from the begin­ning of the year to the end of the year; <verse eID="Deut.11.12"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.11.13" osisID="Deut.11.13"/> [[and if you listen care­fully to the orders which I en­join upon you to-day, to
       love the Eternal your God and worship him with all your mind and all your heart,]] <verse eID="Deut.11.13"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.11.14" osisID="Deut.11.14"/> he will give rain to your land at the right season, the spring rains and the
       autumn rains, that you may gather in your corn and wine and oil, <verse eID="Deut.11.14"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.11.15" osisID="Deut.11.15"/> and he will put grass in your fields for your cattle, and you shall eat and be
       satisfied. <verse eID="Deut.11.15"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.11.16" osisID="Deut.11.16"/> Beware of letting yourselves be fooled into swerving aside to the worship and
       homage of other gods, <verse eID="Deut.11.16"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.11.17" osisID="Deut.11.17"/> till the Eternal’s anger blazes out against you, and he shuts up the skies so
       that no rain falls and your land yields no produce, and you quickly die off the fine country which the Eternal gives you.
      <verse eID="Deut.11.17"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Deut.11.18" osisID="Deut.11.18"/> [[So you must lay to heart these words of mine, you must tie them on your hands
       as a memento and wear them as a badge on your forehead; <verse eID="Deut.11.18"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.11.19" osisID="Deut.11.19"/> you must teach them to your chil­dren, talking of them when you are sitting at
       home and when you are on the road, when you lie down and when you rise up: <verse eID="Deut.11.19"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.11.20" osisID="Deut.11.20"/> you must inscribe them on the door-posts of your houses and on your gates--
      <verse eID="Deut.11.20"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.11.21" osisID="Deut.11.21"/> that your life and the life of your children may be prolonged in the land which
       the Eternal swore he would give to your fathers as long as the sky hangs over the earth.]] <verse eID="Deut.11.21"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Deut.11.22" osisID="Deut.11.22"/> If you are mindful to obey all that I am ordering you to do, loving the Eternal
       your God, al­ways living his life, and loyal to him, <verse eID="Deut.11.22"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.11.23" osisID="Deut.11.23"/> then the Eternal will dis­possess all these nations before you, and you shall
       take posses­sion of nations stronger and more powerful than yourselves, <verse eID="Deut.11.23"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.11.24" osisID="Deut.11.24"/> every foot of ground you tread shall be your own, and your frontier shall
       stretch from the desert to Lebanon, from the River, the river Euphrates, to the Mediterranean Sea; <verse eID="Deut.11.24"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.11.25" osisID="Deut.11.25"/> not a man shall be able to hold his own against you, for the Eternal will lay
       the terror of you and the dread of you upon all the land you tread--as he assured you. <verse eID="Deut.11.25"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.11.26" osisID="Deut.11.26"/> Here I put before you this day a blessing and a curse: <verse eID="Deut.11.26"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.11.27" osisID="Deut.11.27"/> a blessing, if you listen to the orders of the Eternal your God which I enjoin
       upon you this day, <verse eID="Deut.11.27"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.11.28" osisID="Deut.11.28"/> and a curse, if you will not listen to the orders of the Eternal your God, but
       swerve from the line I lay down for you this day, following other gods who are strange to you. <verse eID="Deut.11.28"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.11.29" osisID="Deut.11.29"/> [[And it shall be that when the Eternal your God brings you into the land of
       which you are going to take possession, you must lay the blessing on mount Gerizim and the curse on mount Ebal. <verse eID="Deut.11.29"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.11.30" osisID="Deut.11.30"/> Are they not across the Jordan, west of it, lying on the western route through
       the land of the Canaanites, opposite the Gilgal, which is beside the oracular oak?]] <verse eID="Deut.11.30"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.11.31" osisID="Deut.11.31"/> For you are crossing the Jordan to enter up­on possession of the land which the
       Eternal your God assigns to you; you shall take pos­session of it and live in it, <verse eID="Deut.11.31"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.11.32" osisID="Deut.11.32"/> being mindful to keep all the rules and regulations which I am
       <milestone type="pb" n="213"/>
       putting before you this day. <verse eID="Deut.11.32"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eId="Deut.11"/>
    <chapter osisId="Deut.12" sId="Deut.12"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Deut.12.1" osisID="Deut.12.1"/>Here are the rules and regulations which you must be mindful to keep in the land
       which the Eternal your fathers’ God has allowed you to possess, all the days of your life on earth. <verse eID="Deut.12.1"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Deut.12.2" osisID="Deut.12.2"/> You shall destroy all the spots at which the nations whom you dispossess
       worshipped their gods, on high mountains, on hills, and under any leafy tree; <verse eID="Deut.12.2"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.12.3" osisID="Deut.12.3"/> you must demolish their altars, break their obelisks, burn up their sacred poles,
       and cut down the carved images of their gods, wiping their very name from the spot. <verse eID="Deut.12.3"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.12.4" osisID="Deut.12.4"/> Not thus shall you worship the Eternal your God; <verse eID="Deut.12.4"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.12.5" osisID="Deut.12.5"/> no, you shall resort to the sacred spot which the Eternal your God shall choose
       amid all your clans as the seat of his presence; <verse eID="Deut.12.5"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.12.6" osisID="Deut.12.6"/> thither shall you go, thither shall you bring your offerings and sacrifices, your
       tithes and contributions, what you have vowed and what you offer vol­untarily, the firstlings of your herd and flock; <verse eID="Deut.12.6"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.12.7" osisID="Deut.12.7"/> there shall you eat your sacrificial meal before the Eternal your God, you and
       your households, rejoicing over all the fruit of your labour with which the Eternal your God has blessed you. <verse eID="Deut.12.7"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Deut.12.8" osisID="Deut.12.8"/> You shall not do as we are do­ing here to-day, every man pleasing himself--
      <verse eID="Deut.12.8"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.12.9" osisID="Deut.12.9"/> for you have not yet reached the resting-place and possession which the Eternal
       your God is to give you. <verse eID="Deut.12.9"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.12.10" osisID="Deut.12.10"/> No, when you cross the Jordan and live in the land of which the Eternal puts
       you in possession, when he gives you rest from all your foes around, so that you can live in security, <verse eID="Deut.12.10"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.12.11" osisID="Deut.12.11"/> then to the sacred spot which the Eternal your God chooses as the seat of his
       presence, shall you bring all that I bid you, your offerings and sacrifices, your tithes and contributions, and whatever you
       choose to vow to the Eter­nal; <verse eID="Deut.12.11"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.12.12" osisID="Deut.12.12"/> and you shall rejoice before the Eternal your God, you and your sons and your
       daugh­ters, your male slaves and your female slaves, as well as the Levite belonging to your house­hold (since he owns no
       prop­erty or possession in your land). <verse eID="Deut.12.12"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Deut.12.13" osisID="Deut.12.13"/> Beware of sacrificing your burnt-offerings at any sacred spot you see; <verse eID="Deut.12.13"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.12.14" osisID="Deut.12.14"/> at the sacred spot which the Eternal chooses in one of your clans, there you
       shall sacrifice your burnt-offer­ings, there you shall do all that I bid you. <verse eID="Deut.12.14"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.12.15" osisID="Deut.12.15"/> [[Still, you may slaughter animals and eat their flesh to your heart’s desire,
       wherever you reside, as the Eternal your God has blessed you with his gifts; consecrated and unconsecrated alike may eat it,
       as they would a gazelle or a hart. <verse eID="Deut.12.15"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.12.16" osisID="Deut.12.16"/> Only, you must not eat it with the blood; pour out the blood like water on the
       ground.]] <verse eID="Deut.12.16"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Deut.12.17" osisID="Deut.12.17"/> You must not eat at home your tithe of corn or wine or oil or the firstlings
       of your herd and flock, nor anything you have vowed, nor anything you offer voluntarily, nor your contribu­tions; <verse eID="Deut.12.17"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.12.18" osisID="Deut.12.18"/> you must eat them before the Eternal your God at the sacred spot which the
       Eternal your God chooses, both you and your son and your daughter, your male slave and your fe­male slave, and the Levite who
       belongs to your household, re­joicing before the Eternal your God over all the fruit of your labour. <verse eID="Deut.12.18"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.12.19" osisID="Deut.12.19"/> (Beware of neglecting the Levite, all the days of your life upon this land.)
      <verse eID="Deut.12.19"/>
     </p>
     <milestone type="pb" n="214"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Deut.12.20" osisID="Deut.12.20"/>When the Eternal your God enlarges your territory, as he promised you, and you
       say to yourself, <q>I will eat flesh</q> (since your heart longs to eat flesh), then you may eat flesh to your heart’s
       desire. <verse eID="Deut.12.20"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.12.21" osisID="Deut.12.21"/> Should the sacred spot which the Eternal your God has chosen as the seat of his
       presence be too far away, then you may slaughter any ox or sheep which the Eternal has given you, and eat at home to your
       heart’s desire, as I have ordered you. <verse eID="Deut.12.21"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.12.22" osisID="Deut.12.22"/> You may eat it as you would eat a gazelle or a hart, consecrated and
       unconsecrated alike. <verse eID="Deut.12.22"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.12.23" osisID="Deut.12.23"/> Only, be sure never to eat it with the blood, for the blood is its soul, and
       you must not eat the soul along with the flesh; <verse eID="Deut.12.23"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.12.24" osisID="Deut.12.24"/> you must not eat it, you must pour it out like water on the ground. <verse eID="Deut.12.24"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.12.25" osisID="Deut.12.25"/> You must not eat it, that things may go well with you and with your children
       after you, as you do what is right in the eyes of the Eternal. <verse eID="Deut.12.25"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.12.26" osisID="Deut.12.26"/> But your sacred dues and vo­tive offerings you must take to the sacred spot
       which the Eternal chooses, <verse eID="Deut.12.26"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.12.27" osisID="Deut.12.27"/> sacrificing your burnt-offerings, flesh and blood, on the altar of the Eternal
       your God, pouring out the blood of your sacrifices on the altar of the Eternal your God and eating the flesh yourselves. <verse eID="Deut.12.27"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.12.28" osisID="Deut.12.28"/> Listen carefully to all these orders of mine, that things may go well with you
       and with your chil­dren after you for all time, as you do what is good and right in the eyes of the Eternal your God. <verse eID="Deut.12.28"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Deut.12.29" osisID="Deut.12.29"/> When the Eternal your God puts an end to the nations before you, as you
       advance to dispos­sess them, and when you live in their land after dispossessing them, <verse eID="Deut.12.29"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.12.30" osisID="Deut.12.30"/> beware of letting yourselves be beguiled into copying them, after they have
       been de­stroyed before you; beware of resorting to their gods, asking yourselves, <q>How did these na­tions worship their
        gods?--that I may do the same.</q> <verse eID="Deut.12.30"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.12.31" osisID="Deut.12.31"/> You must not worship the Eternal your God thus; for they offered their gods all
       that is abominable and hate­ful to the Eternal, burning even their sons and daughters to their gods. <verse eID="Deut.12.31"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eId="Deut.12"/>
    <chapter osisId="Deut.16" sId="Deut.16"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Deut.16.21" osisID="Deut.16.21"/>You must never plant a sacred pole or any timber post beside the altar of the
       Eternal your God which you are erecting; <verse eID="Deut.16.21"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.16.22" osisID="Deut.16.22"/> nor must you set up an obelisk, which the Eternal your God hates. <verse eID="Deut.16.22"/>
    <chapter eId="Deut.17"/>
    <chapter osisId="Deut.17" sId="Deut.17"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.17.1" osisID="Deut.17.1"/> You must not sacrifice to the Eternal your God any ani­mal, large or small,
       which has a blemish or anything amiss with it: that is abominable to the Eternal your God. <verse eID="Deut.17.1"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Deut.17.2" osisID="Deut.17.2"/>If there happens to be any man or woman among you, in any of the townships granted
       you by the Eternal your God, who does evil in the sight of the Eternal your God by break­ing his compact, <verse eID="Deut.17.2"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.17.3" osisID="Deut.17.3"/> by going and worshipping other gods, bowing down to them or to the sun, the moon,
       or any of the stars above--which I forbade; <verse eID="Deut.17.3"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.17.4" osisID="Deut.17.4"/> if you are told of it, if you hear of it, then you must look into it thoroughly,
       and if the thing be true, if it is certain that such an abominable crime has been committed in Israel, <verse eID="Deut.17.4"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.17.5" osisID="Deut.17.5"/> you must take the evildoer, man or woman, outside the town and stone him to
       death. <verse eID="Deut.17.5"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.17.6" osisID="Deut.17.6"/> On the evidence of two witnesses or of three shall the doomed man be put to
       death; he shall not be put to death on the evidence of a single witness. <verse eID="Deut.17.6"/>
      <milestone type="pb" n="215"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.17.7" osisID="Deut.17.7"/> The witnesses shall he the first to take a hand in killing him; then all the
       people shall follow. So shall you eradicate the evil from your midst. <verse eID="Deut.17.7"/>
     </p>
    <chapter osisId="Deut.12" sId="Deut.12"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Deut.12.32" osisID="Deut.12.32"/> Whatever I command you, that you must he mindful to obey, adding nothing to it,
       taking nothing from it. <verse eID="Deut.12.32"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eId="Deut.12"/>
    <chapter osisId="Deut.13" sId="Deut.13"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Deut.13.1" osisID="Deut.13.1"/>If a prophet or dreamer arises among you, offering you some proof or portent,
      <verse eID="Deut.13.1"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.13.2" osisID="Deut.13.2"/> and say­ing, <q>Let us follow other gods (gods that are strange to you) and let
       us worship them,</q> even if the proof or portent comes true which he promised you, <verse eID="Deut.13.2"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.13.3" osisID="Deut.13.3"/> you must not listen to what that prophet or dreamer says; it is the Eternal
       your God testing you, to see whether you really love the Eternal your God with all your mind and all your heart. <verse eID="Deut.13.3"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.13.4" osisID="Deut.13.4"/> The Eternal your God you shall follow, him you shall revere, his commands you
       shall keep, his voice you shall obey, him shall you worship, and to him shall you be loyal. <verse eID="Deut.13.4"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.13.5" osisID="Deut.13.5"/> As for that prophet or dreamer, he shall be put to death for his talk of
       apos­tasy from the Eternal your God who brought you out of the land of Egypt and rescued you from that slave-pen, for
       attempting to allure you from the path that the Eternal your God has or­dered you to follow. So shall you eradicate the evil
       from your­selves. <verse eID="Deut.13.5"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Deut.13.6" osisID="Deut.13.6"/>If your half-brother or your full brother, your son or your daughter, the wife of
       your bosom or the friend who is your other self, whispers to you the enticing word, <q>Let us go and worship other gods</q>
      <verse eID="Deut.13.6"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.13.7" osisID="Deut.13.7"/> (gods who are strange to you or to your fathers, gods of the nations near or
       far away, from one end of the earth to another), <verse eID="Deut.13.7"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.13.8" osisID="Deut.13.8"/> then you must refuse him, you must never listen to him, you must have no pity on
       him, you must not spare him, you must not conceal his guilt, you must denounce him; <verse eID="Deut.13.8"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.13.9" osisID="Deut.13.9"/> you shall be the first to take a hand in killing him, and then all the people
       shall follow, <verse eID="Deut.13.9"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.13.10" osisID="Deut.13.10"/> stoning him to death for having tried to allure you from the Eternal your God,
       who brought you out of the land of Egypt, that slave-pen. <verse eID="Deut.13.10"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.13.11" osisID="Deut.13.11"/> So shall all Israel n hear and fear and never again be guilty of a crime like
       this. <verse eID="Deut.13.11"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Deut.13.12" osisID="Deut.13.12"/> If you hear that in any of the towns which the Eternal your God has given you
       to stay in, <verse eID="Deut.13.12"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.13.13" osisID="Deut.13.13"/> some low creatures have broken loose and allured their fellow-citizens with the
       cry, <q>Let us go and worship other gods!</q> (gods who are strange to you), <verse eID="Deut.13.13"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.13.14" osisID="Deut.13.14"/> then you must examine and investi­gate the matter, making a thor­ough inquiry;
       and if the thing be true, if it is certain that such an abominable crime has been committed in your midst, <verse eID="Deut.13.14"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.13.15" osisID="Deut.13.15"/> you must slay the inhabitants of that town without quarter, exterminating the
       town and all in it, cattle and human beings alike; <verse eID="Deut.13.15"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.13.16" osisID="Deut.13.16"/> you must gather all its spoil into the market-place, and then burn up the town
       and all its spoil as a holocaust to the Eternal your God; the town shall lie in ruins for all time, never to be rebuilt.
      <verse eID="Deut.13.16"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.13.17" osisID="Deut.13.17"/> Not one whit of what is doomed must be retained by you, that instead of
       breaking out in fierce anger the Eternal may be kind and com­passionate to you and multiply you, as he swore to your
       fathers, <verse eID="Deut.13.17"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.13.18" osisID="Deut.13.18"/>provided that you listen to the voice of the Eternal your God, to obey his
       commands which I en­join upon you this day, to do
       <milestone type="pb" n="216"/>
       what is right in the eyes of the Eternal your God. <verse eID="Deut.13.18"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eId="Deut.13"/>
    <chapter osisId="Deut.14" sId="Deut.14"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Deut.14.1" osisID="Deut.14.1"/>You are sons to the Eternal your God: you must not gash yourselves nor shave your
       foreheads for the dead; <verse eID="Deut.14.1"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.14.2" osisID="Deut.14.2"/> for you are a people sacred to the Eter­nal your God, and the Eternal has chosen
       you to he his prized possession, out of all nations on the face of the earth. <verse eID="Deut.14.2"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Deut.14.3" osisID="Deut.14.3"/> You must not eat any detestable food. <verse eID="Deut.14.3"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.14.4" osisID="Deut.14.4"/> Here are the animals you may eat: the ox, the sheep, the goat, <verse eID="Deut.14.4"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.14.5" osisID="Deut.14.5"/> the hart, the gazelle, the roebuck, the ibex, the antelope, and the
       mountain-sheep. <verse eID="Deut.14.5"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.14.6" osisID="Deut.14.6"/> Also, you may eat any animal with a parted hoof, that has each hoof divided
       through, and that chews the cud. <verse eID="Deut.14.6"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.14.7" osisID="Deut.14.7"/> But of those that either chew the cud or have the hoof divided through, you must
       not eat the following: the camel, the hare, and the hyrax, which are unclean for you, since they chew the cud but have no
       divided hoof; <verse eID="Deut.14.7"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.14.8" osisID="Deut.14.8"/> also the pig, which is unclean for you because he has a divided hoof but does
       not chew the cud; of their meat you must not eat, their carcases you must not touch. <verse eID="Deut.14.8"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Deut.14.9" osisID="Deut.14.9"/> As for fish, you may eat any­thing in the waters that has fins and scales, <verse eID="Deut.14.9"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.14.10" osisID="Deut.14.10"/> but you must not eat anything that has not fins and scales; that is unclean
       for you. <verse eID="Deut.14.10"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Deut.14.11" osisID="Deut.14.11"/> You may eat any clean bird, <verse eID="Deut.14.11"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.14.12" osisID="Deut.14.12"/> but the following you must not eat: the griffon, the vulture, the eagle,
      <verse eID="Deut.14.12"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.14.13" osisID="Deut.14.13"/> the glede, the buzzard, the kite of any species, <verse eID="Deut.14.13"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.14.14" osisID="Deut.14.14"/> the raven of any species, <verse eID="Deut.14.14"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.14.15" osisID="Deut.14.15"/> the ostrich, the nightjar, the sea-mew, the hawk of any species, <verse eID="Deut.14.15"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.14.16" osisID="Deut.14.16"/> the barn-owl and the eagle-owl, the water-hen, <verse eID="Deut.14.16"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.14.17" osisID="Deut.14.17"/> the pelican, the carrion-vulture, the cormorant, <verse eID="Deut.14.17"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.14.18" osisID="Deut.14.18"/> the stork, the heron of any species, the bittern, and the bat. <verse eID="Deut.14.18"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Deut.14.19" osisID="Deut.14.19"/> Also all winged insects are unclean for you; they must not be eaten. <verse eID="Deut.14.19"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.14.20" osisID="Deut.14.20"/> Any winged thing that is clean, you may eat. <verse eID="Deut.14.20"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Deut.14.21" osisID="Deut.14.21"/> You must not eat any creature that has died a natural death, for you are a
       people sacred to the Eternal your God; you may give it as food to any alien in your settlement, or sell it to a for­eigner.
       You must not boil a kid in its mother’s milk. <verse eID="Deut.14.21"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Deut.14.22" osisID="Deut.14.22"/> Every year you must take a tenth of all the produce from your property, <verse eID="Deut.14.22"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.14.23" osisID="Deut.14.23"/> and, in presence of the Eternal your God, at the sacred spot which he chooses
       for his presence, you must eat the tithe of your corn, your wine, your oil, and the firstlings of your herd and flock, that
       you may learn always to revere the Eternal your God. <verse eID="Deut.14.23"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.14.24" osisID="Deut.14.24"/> If the road is too long, so that you cannot carry your tithe, if the sacred
       spot which the Eternal your God chooses for his presence is too far away, then, when the Eternal your God has prospered
       you, <verse eID="Deut.14.24"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.14.25" osisID="Deut.14.25"/> you must turn your tithe into money and carry it in your hand to the sacred
       spot chosen by the Eter­nal your God, <verse eID="Deut.14.25"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.14.26" osisID="Deut.14.26"/> where you may spend your money on whatever your heart desires, oxen, sheep,
       wine, or liquor--anything you have a craving for; there you must eat before the Eternal your God, you and your household,
       rejoicing; <verse eID="Deut.14.26"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.14.27" osisID="Deut.14.27"/> nor must you neglect the Levite belonging to your household, for he owns no
       prop­erty or possession in your land. <verse eID="Deut.14.27"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.14.28" osisID="Deut.14.28"/> At the end of every three years you must take the full tithe of your produce
       for that year and deposit it at home; <verse eID="Deut.14.28"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.14.29" osisID="Deut.14.29"/> then the Levite (since he owns no property
       <milestone type="pb" n="217"/>
       or possession in your land), the alien, the fatherless, and the widow in your community, shall come and eat till they are
       satisfied--that the Eternal your God may bless you in all the work to which you set your hand. <verse eID="Deut.14.29"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eId="Deut.14"/>
   </div>