   <div type="book" osisID="Deut">
    <milestone type="pb" n="197"/>
    <chapter osisId="Deut.1" sId="Deut.1"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.1" osisID="Deut.1.1"/>The following are the words which Moses spoke to all Is­rael east of the Jordan in the
       desert, in the wady of the Arabah opposite Suph, between Paran on the one side and Tophel, Laban, Hazeroth, and Dizahab on the
       other. <verse eID="Deut.1.1"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.3" osisID="Deut.1.3"/> (It was on the first day of the eleventh month of the fortieth year that Moses spoke to
       the Israelites in terms of all the commands that he had received for them from the Eternal.) <verse eID="Deut.1.3"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.4" osisID="Deut.1.4"/> After defeating Sihon king of the Amorites, whose capital was Heshbon, and Og king of
       Bashan, whose capital was Ashtaroth, at Edrei, <verse eID="Deut.1.4"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.5" osisID="Deut.1.5"/> Moses set himself to expound this code, east of the Jordan in Moab. He said: <verse eID="Deut.1.5"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.6" osisID="Deut.1.6"/><q>The Eternal our God said to us at Horeb, <q>You have stayed long enough among the
       hills here; <verse eID="Deut.1.6"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.7" osisID="Deut.1.7"/> move on, away into the highlands of the Amorites and all the surrounding country, the
       wady of the Arabah, the highlands, the lowlands, the southern plains and the mari­time plains where the Canaanites live, also the
       Lebanon. I hand this land over to you, as far as the great river, the river Euphrates. <verse eID="Deut.1.7"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.8" osisID="Deut.1.8"/> There it lies; march in and take possession of the land that the Eternal swore he would
       give to your fathers, Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob, and to their descendants.</q></q><verse eID="Deut.1.8"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.9" osisID="Deut.1.9"/><q>Then it was that I told you, <q>I cannot bear the burden of you single-handed. <verse eID="Deut.1.9"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.10" osisID="Deut.1.10"/> The Eter­nal your God has multiplied you, till now your numbers are like the stars in
       the sky. <verse eID="Deut.1.10"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.11" osisID="Deut.1.11"/> (May the Eternal the God of your fathers multiply you still a thousand-fold, and
       prosper you as he promised you!) <verse eID="Deut.1.11"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.12" osisID="Deut.1.12"/> How can I possibly bear the heavy bur­den of you and your disputes, all by myself? <verse eID="Deut.1.12"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.13" osisID="Deut.1.13"/> Choose capable men, intelligent and experienced, from each of your clans, and let me
       put them in charge of you.</q> <verse eID="Deut.1.13"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.14" osisID="Deut.1.14"/> Then you replied, <q>What you propose is the right thing to do.</q> <verse eID="Deut.1.14"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.15" osisID="Deut.1.15"/> So I took those capable and experienced men, putting them in charge of your divisions
       of a thousand, of a hundred, of fifty, and of ten, as your prefects, along with officials for every clan. <verse eID="Deut.1.15"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.16" osisID="Deut.1.16"/> I also charged your governors at that time, <q>Listen to your fellow-clansmen, and
       see justice done between a man and his fellow or any resi­dent alien; <verse eID="Deut.1.16"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.17" osisID="Deut.1.17"/> you must never show partiality to any person in a case, you must listen equally to
       low and high, you must not be afraid of any man--for the judgment is God’s. Any case that is too hard for you must be brought to
       me, and I will hear it.</q><verse eID="Deut.1.17"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.18" osisID="Deut.1.18"/> I gave you all your directions then.</q> <verse eID="Deut.1.18"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.19" osisID="Deut.1.19"/><q>On setting out from Horeb we passed through that wide awful desert, as you saw, on
       our way to the Amorite high­lands, in obedience to the Eter­nal our God. When we reached Kadesh-barnea <verse eID="Deut.1.19"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.2" osisID="Deut.1.2"/> (eleven days from Horeb by the mount Seir road) <verse eID="Deut.1.2"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.20" osisID="Deut.1.20"/> I said to you, <q>Now you have reached the Amorite high­lands, which the Eternal our
       God is to give us; <verse eID="Deut.1.20"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.21" osisID="Deut.1.21"/> here is the Eternal your God handing over the land to you; march in and take
       possession of it, as the Eternal the God of your
       <milestone type="pb" n="198"/>
       fathers has told you; fear not, neither he dismayed.</q></q>
      <verse eID="Deut.1.21"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.22" osisID="Deut.1.22"/>Then you all came to me and proposed to send some men in front, to explore the land
       and bring back word about the route you should follow and the towns you would reach. <verse eID="Deut.1.22"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.23" osisID="Deut.1.23"/> I thought this a good plan; so I chose twelve men, one for each clan, <verse eID="Deut.1.23"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.24" osisID="Deut.1.24"/> and they made their way into the highlands as far as the wady of Eshcol, which they
       explored. <verse eID="Deut.1.24"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.25" osisID="Deut.1.25"/>Then, carrying some fruit of the country, they brought it down to us, with this
       report: <q>It is a fine land that the Eternal our God is to give us.</q> <verse eID="Deut.1.25"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.26" osisID="Deut.1.26"/> But you would not march up; you re­belled against the orders of the Eternal your God,
      <verse eID="Deut.1.26"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.27" osisID="Deut.1.27"/> and grumbled in your tents, <q>It is because the Eternal hates us that he has brought
       us out of the land of Egypt to hand us over to the Amorites, to be destroyed! <verse eID="Deut.1.27"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.28" osisID="Deut.1.28"/> What is our fate to be? Our friends have made our courage melt by telling us that the
       people are stronger and taller than ourselves, and the towns large and walled up to the sky; besides, they saw giants in the
       land!</q> <verse eID="Deut.1.28"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.29" osisID="Deut.1.29"/>Then I said to you, <q>Dread them not, have no fear of them. <verse eID="Deut.1.29"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.30" osisID="Deut.1.30"/> The Eternal your God who goes in front of you, he will fight for you; he will do it
       all for you, as you saw him do in Egypt, <verse eID="Deut.1.30"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.31" osisID="Deut.1.31"/> and also in the desert, where you saw how the Eternal your God carried you forward,
       as a man carries his boy, all the long road till you reached this place.</q> <verse eID="Deut.1.31"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.32" osisID="Deut.1.32"/> But, for all I said, you would not trust the Eternal your God, <verse eID="Deut.1.32"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.33" osisID="Deut.1.33"/> who had gone in front of you upon the road, by fire during the night and by a cloud
       during the day, to find out where you could pitch your camp, and to show you the road to take. <verse eID="Deut.1.33"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.34" osisID="Deut.1.34"/> When the Eternal heard what you said, he was angry and swore that <verse eID="Deut.1.34"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.35" osisID="Deut.1.35"/> <q>not a man of them, not a soul of this wicked generation, shall ever see the fine
       land that I swore to give to your fathers, <verse eID="Deut.1.35"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.36" osisID="Deut.1.36"/> none except Caleb the son of Jephunneh; he shall see it, and to him will I give the
       land on which he has set foot, to him and to his children, because he has been loyal to me.</q> <verse eID="Deut.1.36"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.37" osisID="Deut.1.37"/> (The Eternal was angry with me also on your account; <q>neither shall you enter,</q>
       said he. <verse eID="Deut.1.37"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.38" osisID="Deut.1.38"/><q>Joshua the son of Nun, your attendant, shall enter; nerve him, for he is to put
       Israel in possession of the land.</q>) <verse eID="Deut.1.38"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.39" osisID="Deut.1.39"/><q>Also the infants who would be seized, you thought, and the children who know no
       difference yet between good and evil, they shall enter; I will give the land to them, and they shall hold it. <verse eID="Deut.1.39"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.40" osisID="Deut.1.40"/> But as for you, move back into the desert in the direction of the Gulf of Akabah.</q>
      <verse eID="Deut.1.40"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.41" osisID="Deut.1.41"/> You answered me, <q>We have sinned against the Eternal, we our­selves will march up
       and fight, exactly as the Eternal our God has ordered us.</q> Every man of you put on his armour, and made little of marching
       into the highlands. <verse eID="Deut.1.41"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.42" osisID="Deut.1.42"/> But the Eternal said to me, <q>Tell them not to march up nor to fight, lest you are
       beaten by your enemies; for I am not among you.</q> <verse eID="Deut.1.42"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.43" osisID="Deut.1.43"/> I told you this, but you would not listen, you rebelled against the orders of the
       Eter­nal, and in your presumption you did march into the high­lands. <verse eID="Deut.1.43"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.44" osisID="Deut.1.44"/> Then the Amorites who lived there attacked you, swarming out like bees and
       <milestone type="pb" n="199"/>
       chasing you, from Seir to Hormah--a crushing defeat. <verse eID="Deut.1.44"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.45" osisID="Deut.1.45"/> You came back and wept before the Eternal; but the Eternal would not listen to your
       cry, he would not hearken to you. <verse eID="Deut.1.45"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Deut.1.46" osisID="Deut.1.46"/>Then, after you had made that long stay of many days at Kadesh, <verse eID="Deut.1.46"/>
    <chapter eId="Deut.1"/>
    <chapter osisId="Deut.2" sId="Deut.2"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.2.1" osisID="Deut.2.1"/> we moved back into the desert in the direction of the Gulf of Akabah, as the Eter­nal
       had told me. For many a day we marched round the highlands of Seir, <verse eID="Deut.2.1"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.2.2" osisID="Deut.2.2"/> till the Eternal said to me, <verse eID="Deut.2.2"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.2.3" osisID="Deut.2.3"/> <q>You have marched long enough round these highlands; turn to the north. <verse eID="Deut.2.3"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.2.4" osisID="Deut.2.4"/> Tell the people they are going to cross the territory of their kins­folk, the sons of
       Esau, who live in Seir; they will be afraid of you, <verse eID="Deut.2.4"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.2.5" osisID="Deut.2.5"/> but you must be careful never to engage in battle with them, for I have not assigned
       you any of their land, no, not a foot of it; the highlands of Seir I have assigned to Esau as his own. <verse eID="Deut.2.5"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.2.6" osisID="Deut.2.6"/> You may buy food from them, you may buy water from them <verse eID="Deut.2.6"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.2.7" osisID="Deut.2.7"/> (for the Eternal your God has always blessed your enter­prise. Think how his care
       brought you through this wide desert; the Eternal your God has been with you all these forty years, and never have you been in
       want).</q> <verse eID="Deut.2.7"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.2.8" osisID="Deut.2.8"/> So we passed through our kinsfolk the sons of Esau, who live in Seir, from Elath and
       Ezion-geber on the Arabah route; we moved round in the direction of the o plains of Moab. <verse eID="Deut.2.8"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.2.9" osisID="Deut.2.9"/> <q>Fight not with Moab,</q> said the Eternal to me, <q>do not engage them in battle,
       for I will not let you hold any of their land; Ar I have assigned to the sons of Lot as their own.</q> <verse eID="Deut.2.9"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.2.10" osisID="Deut.2.10"/> [[Long ago the Emim used to live there, a strong and numerous race, as tall as
       giants; <verse eID="Deut.2.10"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.2.11" osisID="Deut.2.11"/> like the giants, they are generally called Titans, but the Moabites call them
       <q>Emim.</q> <verse eID="Deut.2.11"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.2.12" osisID="Deut.2.12"/> Long ago also troglodytes used to live in Seir, but the sons of Esau dislodged them
       and killed them off, tak­ing possession of their country just as the Israelites did with the land which the Eternal had
       assigned as their possession.]] <verse eID="Deut.2.12"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.2.13" osisID="Deut.2.13"/> <q>Up now and cross the wady of Zered.</q> We crossed the wady of Zered; <verse eID="Deut.2.13"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.2.14" osisID="Deut.2.14"/> when we crossed that wady of Zered, thirty-eight years had passed since we left
       Kadesh-barnea, and all that generation (that is, the warriors) had died off, as the Eternal had sworn: <verse eID="Deut.2.14"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.2.15" osisID="Deut.2.15"/> the Eternal’s hand had been against them, routing them in disarray, till all had
       perished. <verse eID="Deut.2.15"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Deut.2.16" osisID="Deut.2.16"/> Now that all these warriors had perished from the people, <verse eID="Deut.2.16"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.2.17" osisID="Deut.2.17"/> the Eternal said to me, <verse eID="Deut.2.17"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.2.18" osisID="Deut.2.18"/> <q>To-day you are about to cross Ar, the territory of Moab. <verse eID="Deut.2.18"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.2.19" osisID="Deut.2.19"/> As you pass close in front of the Ammonites, do not fight with them, do not engage
       in battle with them, for I will not let you have any of the Ammonite country; I have assigned it to the sons of Lot as their
       own.</q> <verse eID="Deut.2.19"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.2.20" osisID="Deut.2.20"/> [[It also is generally called a land of the Titans; Titans used to live there long
       ago, whom the Ammonites call Zamzummin-- <verse eID="Deut.2.20"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.2.21" osisID="Deut.2.21"/> a strong and numerous race, as tall as giants, whom the Eternal killed off before
       the Ammonites, the latter dislodg­ing them and taking possession of their country, <verse eID="Deut.2.21"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.2.22" osisID="Deut.2.22"/> just as he had done for the sons of Esau who live in Seir, by killing off the
       troglodytes, whom they dis­lodged, taking possession of their country to the present day. <verse eID="Deut.2.22"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.2.23" osisID="Deut.2.23"/> So too the Avim, who lived in villages as far as Gaza,
       <milestone type="pb" n="200"/>
       were killed off by the Cretans, who came from Crete and took possession of their country.]] <verse eID="Deut.2.23"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.2.24" osisID="Deut.2.24"/> <q>Up, then, move across the wady of Arnon; I hand over to you Sihon the Amorite,
       king of Heshbon, him and his land; start to seize it and to engage him in battle, <verse eID="Deut.2.24"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.2.25" osisID="Deut.2.25"/> and I will start this very day to put the terror of you and the dread of you upon
       all races under heaven; the news of you shall make them tremble in anguish on account of you.</q> <verse eID="Deut.2.25"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.2.26" osisID="Deut.2.26"/> So I sent envoys from the desert of Kedemoth to Sihon king of Heshbon with this
       message of peace: <verse eID="Deut.2.26"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.2.27" osisID="Deut.2.27"/> <q>Let us pass through your land, we will go straight across, turning neither to
       the right nor to the left. <verse eID="Deut.2.27"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.2.28" osisID="Deut.2.28"/> You shall sell us food for money and give us drinking water for money; only allow
       us to walk through, <verse eID="Deut.2.28"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.2.29" osisID="Deut.2.29"/> as we were allowed by the sons of Esau who live in Seir and the Moabites who live
       in Ar, till we cross the Jordan into the land which the Eternal our God is giving us!</q> <verse eID="Deut.2.29"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.2.30" osisID="Deut.2.30"/> But Sihon king of Heshbon would not let us pass through his land; the Eternal your
       God had stiffened his mind and made his heart stubborn, in order to put him into your hands, as is the case to-day. <verse eID="Deut.2.30"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Deut.2.31" osisID="Deut.2.31"/> Then the Eternal said to me, <q>Here have I started to hand over to you Sihon and
       his land; start to seize it, that you may make his land your own.</q> <verse eID="Deut.2.31"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.2.32" osisID="Deut.2.32"/> And when Sihon and all his host attacked us in battle at Jahaz, <verse eID="Deut.2.32"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.2.33" osisID="Deut.2.33"/> the Eternal our God put him into our hands; we killed him and his sons and all his
       host, <verse eID="Deut.2.33"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.2.34" osisID="Deut.2.34"/> we captured all his towns, and in every town we put the citizens to death, men,
       women, and children, sparing none, <verse eID="Deut.2.34"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.2.35" osisID="Deut.2.35"/> keeping only the cattle as our prey, along with the plunder of the captured towns.
      <verse eID="Deut.2.35"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.2.36" osisID="Deut.2.36"/> From Aroer on the edge of the wady of Arnon and from the town that lies in the
       wady, right across to Gilead, no town was too much for us; the Eternal our God put them all into our hands. <verse eID="Deut.2.36"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.2.37" osisID="Deut.2.37"/> Only, as the Eternal had given strict orders, you never ventured near the land of
       the Ammonites, or near anything that lay on that side of the wady of Jabbok, or near the highland towns. <verse eID="Deut.2.37"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eId="Deut.2"/>
    <chapter osisId="Deut.3" sId="Deut.3"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Deut.3.1" osisID="Deut.3.1"/> We then moved up in the direction of Bashan, and Og king of Bashan with all his host
       attacked us in battle at Edrei. <verse eID="Deut.3.1"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.3.2" osisID="Deut.3.2"/> But the Eternal said to me, <q>Do not fear him, for I hand him over to you, with all
       his host and his land; you shall do to him what you did to Sihon king of the Amorites who lived at Heshbon.</q> <verse eID="Deut.3.2"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.3.3" osisID="Deut.3.3"/> So the Eternal our God put Og king of Bashan also into our hands, together with all
       his host; we defeated him, till not a survivor was left, <verse eID="Deut.3.3"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.3.4" osisID="Deut.3.4"/> and we captured all his towns--there was not a town that we did not take—sixty towns
       in all, in the region of Argob, Og’s realm in Bashan. <verse eID="Deut.3.4"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.3.5" osisID="Deut.3.5"/> All these towns, fortified with high walls, gates, and bars, besides many an open
       hamlet, <verse eID="Deut.3.5"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.3.6" osisID="Deut.3.6"/> we exterminated, as we did in the case of Sihon king of Heshbon, putting the citizens
       to death, men, women, and children, <verse eID="Deut.3.6"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.3.7" osisID="Deut.3.7"/> but keeping all the cattle and the plunder of the towns as our prey. <verse eID="Deut.3.7"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Deut.3.8" osisID="Deut.3.8"/> Thus did we seize the land of the two Amorite kings east of the Jordan, from the wady
       of Arnon to mount Hermon
      <verse eID="Deut.3.8"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.3.9" osisID="Deut.3.9"/>
       (called Sirion by the Phoenicians, and
       <milestone type="pb" n="201"/>
       Senir by the Amorites), <verse eID="Deut.3.9"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.3.10" osisID="Deut.3.10"/> all the towns of the tableland, all Gilead and all Baslian as far as Salchah and
       Edrei, towns belonging to Og’s realm in Bashan. <verse eID="Deut.3.10"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.3.11" osisID="Deut.3.11"/> [[Og king of Bashan was the only survivor left of the Titans; his sarcophagus of
       ba­salt, is it not lying still at Kabbah-Ammon, fourteen feet long and six feet broad?]] <verse eID="Deut.3.11"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Deut.3.12" osisID="Deut.3.12"/> Of this country which we cap­tured at that time, I gave the Reubenites and the
       Gadites the land north of Aroer on the wady of Arnon and half of the highlands of Gilead, towns and all; <verse eID="Deut.3.12"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.3.13" osisID="Deut.3.13"/> the rest of Gilead and the whole of Bashan, Og’s realm, the whole of the Argob
       region, I gave to the half-clan of Manasseh. [[This Bashan is all called a land of the Titans; <verse eID="Deut.3.13"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.3.14" osisID="Deut.3.14"/> it was Jair a Manassite who captured the whole of the Argob region to the frontiers
       of the Geshurites and the Maacathites, call­ing this part of Bashan <q>Havvoth-jair</q> after himself--a name that lasts to
       this day. <verse eID="Deut.3.14"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.3.15" osisID="Deut.3.15"/> To Machir I gave Gilead. <verse eID="Deut.3.15"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.3.16" osisID="Deut.3.16"/> To the Reubenites and the Gadites I gave the country from Gilead to the Arnon wady,
       with the middle of the wady as a bound­ary, as far north as the Jabbok wady, which bounds the Amorites, <verse eID="Deut.3.16"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.3.17" osisID="Deut.3.17"/> along with the Arabah, bounded by the Jordan, from the lake of Kinnereth to the sea
       of the Arabah, the Salt Sea, lying under the slopes of Pisgah to the east.]] <verse eID="Deut.3.17"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Deut.3.18" osisID="Deut.3.18"/> I gave you these orders then: <q>The Eternal your God has given you this land for
       your own; all your warriors shall march on under arms, in front of your fellow-Israelites. <verse eID="Deut.3.18"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.3.19" osisID="Deut.3.19"/> But your wives and children and cattle (and I know you have many cattle) shall
       remain here in the towns I have assigned you, <verse eID="Deut.3.19"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.3.20" osisID="Deut.3.20"/> till such time as the Eternal has settled not only yourselves but your fellows,
       till such time as they get possession of the land which the Eternal your God assigns them west of the Jordan. Then you can
       each go home to the land I have assigned you as your own.</q> <verse eID="Deut.3.20"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.3.21" osisID="Deut.3.21"/> I also gave these orders to Joshua then: <q>Your eyes have seen all that the
       Eter­nal your God has done to these two kings; so shall the Eternal do to all the realms you are crossing to invade. <verse eID="Deut.3.21"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.3.22" osisID="Deut.3.22"/> Fear them not; it is the Eternal your God who fights for you.</q> <verse eID="Deut.3.22"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Deut.3.23" osisID="Deut.3.23"/> I also entreated the Eternal then, saying: <verse eID="Deut.3.23"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.3.24" osisID="Deut.3.24"/> <q>O Eternal, my Lord, thou hast only begun to let thy servant see how great and
       strong thou art; what god in heaven or earth could do deeds like to thine, and mighty acts like thine? <verse eID="Deut.3.24"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.3.25" osisID="Deut.3.25"/> Ah, let me cross and see the fine land over the Jordan, the fair hill-country, and
       Lebanon.</q> <verse eID="Deut.3.25"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.3.26" osisID="Deut.3.26"/> But the Eternal was wroth with me on your account and would not listen to me.
       <q>Enough of this,</q> said the Eternal, <q>say not another word about it. <verse eID="Deut.3.26"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.3.27" osisID="Deut.3.27"/> Climb to the top of Pisgah and look round you, west, north, south, and east: look,
       for you shall never cross this Jordan. <verse eID="Deut.3.27"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.3.28" osisID="Deut.3.28"/> But counsel Joshua, nerve him, strengthen him, for he shall lead the people across
       and he shall put them in possession of the land on which you look.</q> <verse eID="Deut.3.28"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.3.29" osisID="Deut.3.29"/> (We were in the valley opposite Beth-peor.) <verse eID="Deut.3.29"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eId="Deut.3"/>
    <chapter osisId="Deut.4" sId="Deut.4"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Deut.4.1" osisID="Deut.4.1"/>And now, O Israel, listen to the rules and regulations that I teach you, and obey
       them, so that you may live and enter on possession of the land which the Eternal the God of your
       <milestone type="pb" n="202"/>
       fathers is assigning you. <verse eID="Deut.4.1"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.4.2" osisID="Deut.4.2"/> You shall not add one word to my commands, nor take one word from them; you shall
       obey the commands of the Eternal your God which I enjoin upon you. <verse eID="Deut.4.2"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.4.3" osisID="Deut.4.3"/> You have seen for yourselves what the Eternal did at Baal-peor; the Eternal your God
       has killed every man of you who followed the Baal of Peor, <verse eID="Deut.4.3"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.4.4" osisID="Deut.4.4"/> but those of you who held to the Eternal your God are all alive to-day. <verse eID="Deut.4.4"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Deut.4.5" osisID="Deut.4.5"/> Here am I teaching you, as the Eternal my God ordered me, the rules and regulations
       for what you are to do in the land you are entering to possess; <verse eID="Deut.4.5"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.4.6" osisID="Deut.4.6"/> keep them, obey them, for that will prove your wisdom and intelligence to the
       nations; when they hear all these rules they will say, <q>This great nation is indeed a wise, intelligent race!</q> <verse eID="Deut.4.6"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.4.7" osisID="Deut.4.7"/> For what great nation has a god so near to it as the Eternal our God is, whenever we
       invoke him? <verse eID="Deut.4.7"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.4.8" osisID="Deut.4.8"/> What great nation has rules and regulations as just as all this code that I am
       putting before you now? <verse eID="Deut.4.8"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.4.9" osisID="Deut.4.9"/> Only be careful to watch yourselves well, all through your life, lest you for­get what
       you have seen for yourselves, and let it pass from your mind; impart it to your children and your children’s children, <verse eID="Deut.4.9"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.4.10" osisID="Deut.4.10"/> the story of the day when you stood before the Eternal your God at Horeb and the
       Eternal said to me, <q>Gather the people round me, and I will let them hear my words, that they may learn to reverence me all
       the days of their life on earth, and that they may instruct their children in reverence</q>-- <verse eID="Deut.4.10"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.4.11" osisID="Deut.4.11"/> the story of how you approached and stood below the mountain that flamed up to the
       very heart of heaven, shrouded in darkness, cloud, and gloom, <verse eID="Deut.4.11"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.4.12" osisID="Deut.4.12"/> and how the Eternal spoke to you out of the flames. You heard the sound of words,
       but you saw no shape; it was only a voice. <verse eID="Deut.4.12"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.4.13" osisID="Deut.4.13"/> He made known to you his compact, the ten sayings which he ordered you to obey,
       writing them on two stone tablets. <verse eID="Deut.4.13"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.4.14" osisID="Deut.4.14"/> The Eternal then ordered me to teach you rules and regulations to be fol­lowed in
       the land which you are entering to possess. <verse eID="Deut.4.14"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.4.15" osisID="Deut.4.15"/> Now, be careful. You saw no shape on the day when the Eternal spoke to you out of
       the flames at Horeb; <verse eID="Deut.4.15"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.4.16" osisID="Deut.4.16"/> beware, then, of depraving yourselves by carving an idol in the shape of any statue,
       either male or female, <verse eID="Deut.4.16"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.4.17" osisID="Deut.4.17"/> or like any beast on earth, any bird that flies, <verse eID="Deut.4.17"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.4.18" osisID="Deut.4.18"/> any insect crawling on the ground, or any fish in the sea; <verse eID="Deut.4.18"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.4.19" osisID="Deut.4.19"/> beware of looking up to the sky and then, as you see the whole host of heaven, the
       sun and moon and stars, letting yourselves be allured to bend in worship of them. The Eter­nal your God has allotted them for
       worship to all nations under the broad sky, <verse eID="Deut.4.19"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.4.20" osisID="Deut.4.20"/> but the Eternal took you and lifted you from the iron furnace of Egypt, to be a
       people of his own, as it is to-day. <verse eID="Deut.4.20"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.4.21" osisID="Deut.4.21"/> Besides, while the Eternal was angry with me on your account and swore that I was
       not to cross the Jordan, nor to enter the fine country which the Eternal assigns to you as your possession, <verse eID="Deut.4.21"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.4.22" osisID="Deut.4.22"/> but that I must die here, instead of crossing the Jordan, you are to cross it and
       take possession of that fine country. <verse eID="Deut.4.22"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.4.23" osisID="Deut.4.23"/> So be careful never to forget the com­pact that the Eternal your God has made with
       you, never to carve an idol in the shape of
       <milestone type="pb" n="203"/>
       anything forbidden by the Eternal your God. <verse eID="Deut.4.23"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.4.24" osisID="Deut.4.24"/> For the Eternal your God is a consuming fire, a jeal­ous God. <verse eID="Deut.4.24"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Deut.4.25" osisID="Deut.4.25"/>When you produce children and children’s children, if you lose your freshness in the
       land and deprave yourselves by carv­ing an idol in the sight of the Eternal your God, and so vexing him, <verse eID="Deut.4.25"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.4.26" osisID="Deut.4.26"/> then here and now I call heaven and earth to witness against you, that you will
       soon be wiped out of the land which you are crossing Jordan to pos­sess; you shall not live long there, you shall be wiped out.
      <verse eID="Deut.4.26"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.4.27" osisID="Deut.4.27"/> The Eternal will scatter you among the nations; few of you will be left among the
       nations where the Eternal exiles you, <verse eID="Deut.4.27"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.4.28" osisID="Deut.4.28"/> and there you will have to wor­ship hand-made gods, gods of wood and stone that
       neither see nor hear nor eat nor smell. <verse eID="Deut.4.28"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.4.29" osisID="Deut.4.29"/> Yet if there you seek the Eternal your God, you shall find him, provided that you
       seek for him with all your mind and all your soul. <verse eID="Deut.4.29"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.4.30" osisID="Deut.4.30"/> When you are in anguish, with all these woes upon you, in the end you shall come
       back to the Eternal your God and listen to his voice; <verse eID="Deut.4.30"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.4.31" osisID="Deut.4.31"/> for the Eter­nal your God is a merciful God, he will not let you go, he will not
       destroy you, he will not forget the compact he swore to your fathers. <verse eID="Deut.4.31"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Deut.4.32" osisID="Deut.4.32"/><q>Ask the days of old, ere ever you were born, ask if anything as great has ever
       happened or been heard of, from one end of the world to another, ever since the day that God made man upon earth: <verse eID="Deut.4.32"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.4.33" osisID="Deut.4.33"/> did any nation ever hear the voice of a god speaking from fire, as you have heard,
       and remain alive? <verse eID="Deut.4.33"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.4.34" osisID="Deut.4.34"/> Has any god ever ventured to go and take a nation for himself out of another nation
       by a series of tests, by signal acts, by war, by sheer strength and main force, with awful terrors, as you saw the Eternal
       your God do for you in Egypt? <verse eID="Deut.4.34"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.4.35" osisID="Deut.4.35"/> You had all this shown to you, to teach you that the Eternal is God and God alone.
      <verse eID="Deut.4.35"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.4.36" osisID="Deut.4.36"/> He let you hear his voice out of heaven, for discipline, and on earth he let you
       see his mighty fire--you heard his voice out of the flames. <verse eID="Deut.4.36"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.4.37" osisID="Deut.4.37"/> And because he loved your fathers and chose their descend­ants after them, because
       he brought you out of Egypt with his own presence and his mighty power, <verse eID="Deut.4.37"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.4.38" osisID="Deut.4.38"/> dispossessing nations greater and stronger than your­selves that he might bring you
       in to let you have their land for your own, as it is to-day, <verse eID="Deut.4.38"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.4.39" osisID="Deut.4.39"/> therefore be sure of this, remind your­selves, that it is the Eternal who is God in
       heaven above and on the earth beneath, the only God. <verse eID="Deut.4.39"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.4.40" osisID="Deut.4.40"/> You must obey his rules and orders which I command you this day, that all may go
       well with you and with your children after you, and that you may live long on the land which the Eternal your God assigns you.
       </q> <verse eID="Deut.4.40"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Deut.4.41" osisID="Deut.4.41"/> Then Moses set apart three towns across the Jordan towards the east, <verse eID="Deut.4.41"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.4.42" osisID="Deut.4.42"/> as a refuge for the homicide who had killed some neighbour unintentionally, not on
       account of any previous feud; he might save his life by running to one of those towns, <verse eID="Deut.4.42"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.4.43" osisID="Deut.4.43"/> to Bezer on the table-land (which was meant for the Reubenites), to Ramoth in
       Gilead (which was meant for the Gadites), or to Golan in Bashan (which was meant for the Manassites). <verse eID="Deut.4.43"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Deut.4.44" osisID="Deut.4.44"/> Here is the code which Moses put before the Israelites: <verse eID="Deut.4.44"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.4.45" osisID="Deut.4.45"/> here
       <milestone type="pb" n="204"/>
       are the decrees, the rules, and the regulations which Moses issued to the Israelites when they left Egypt, <verse eID="Deut.4.45"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.4.46" osisID="Deut.4.46"/> when they were east of the Jordan, in the valley opposite Beth-peor, in the land of
       Sihon king of the Amorites whose capital was Heshbon, and whom Moses and the Israelites defeated after they left Egypt, <verse eID="Deut.4.46"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.4.47" osisID="Deut.4.47"/> taking possession of his land and also the land of Og king of Bashan, the two
       Amorite kings who lived to the east of the Jordan <verse eID="Deut.4.47"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.4.48" osisID="Deut.4.48"/> from Aroer on the edge of the Arnon wady as far as to mount Sion (that is, Hermon),
      <verse eID="Deut.4.48"/>
      <verse sID="Deut.4.49" osisID="Deut.4.49"/> with all the Arabah east of the Jordan down to the sea of the Arabah which lies
       under the slopes of Pisgah. <verse eID="Deut.4.49"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eId="Deut.4"/>
   </div>