   <div type="book" osisID="Exod">
    <milestone type="pb" n="61"/>
    <chapter osisId="Exod.1" sId="Exod.1"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Exod.1.1" osisID="Exod.1.1"/>Here are the names of the sons of Israel who went to Egypt with Jacob, each
       man along with his household: <verse eID="Exod.1.1"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.1.2" osisID="Exod.1.2"/> Reu­ben, Simeon, Levi, and Judah,<verse eID="Exod.1.2"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.1.3" osisID="Exod.1.3"/> Issachar, Zebulun, and Benjamin, <verse eID="Exod.1.3"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.1.4" osisID="Exod.1.4"/> Dan and Naphtali, Gad and Asher; <verse eID="Exod.1.4"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.1.5" osisID="Exod.1.5"/> and the direct descend­ants of Jacob numbered seventy in all.
       (Joseph was in Egypt already.) <verse eID="Exod.1.5"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.1.7" osisID="Exod.1.7"/> The sons of Israel were fruitful and swarmed, they multiplied and teemed
       till the land was full of them. <verse eID="Exod.1.7"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.1.13" osisID="Exod.1.13"/> The Egyptians made slaves of the Israelites harshly; <verse eID="Exod.1.13"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.1.14" osisID="Exod.1.14"/> they made life bitter for them with hard service, forcing them to build
       with mortar and bricks and to do all manner of field-work--lot of slaves harshly treated. <verse eID="Exod.1.14"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <hi type="italic">
       <verse sID="Exod.1.6" osisID="Exod.1.6"/>Joseph died, so did all his brothers and all that generation. <verse eID="Exod.1.6"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.1.8" osisID="Exod.1.8"/> A new king rose over Egypt, who had not knowledge of Joseph; <verse eID="Exod.1.8"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.1.9" osisID="Exod.1.9"/> he said to his people, <q>Look, the Israelites are too many and too mighty
        for us! <verse eID="Exod.1.9"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.1.10" osisID="Exod.1.10"/> We must handle them carefully, lest they multi­ply and then, if we happen
        to be at war, join our enemies and fight against us, so as to escape from the country.</q><verse eID="Exod.1.10"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.1.11" osisID="Exod.1.11"/> So they put them under captains of the la­bour gangs, to crush them with
        heavy loads; and they built for the Pharaoh the store-towns of Pithom and Ramses. <verse eID="Exod.1.11"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.1.12" osisID="Exod.1.12"/> But the more they were crushed, the more they multiplied and ex­panded,
        till the Egyptians dreaded the Israelites. <verse eID="Exod.1.12"/>
      </hi>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Exod.1.15" osisID="Exod.1.15"/>[Then the king of Egypt told the Hebrew midwives, one of whom was called
       Shiphrah and the other Puah, <verse eID="Exod.1.15"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.1.16" osisID="Exod.1.16"/> that when they attended the Hebrew women and saw them on the birth-stool
       they were to kill the child, if it was a male, and to let it live, if it was a girl. <verse eID="Exod.1.16"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.1.17" osisID="Exod.1.17"/> But the midwives reverenced God; they did not do as the king of Egypt
       ordered them, but saved the male chil­dren alive. <verse eID="Exod.1.17"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.1.18" osisID="Exod.1.18"/> Then the king of Egypt summoned the midwives. <q>Why have you done
       this,</q> he asked, <q>saving the male children alive?</q> <verse eID="Exod.1.18"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.1.19" osisID="Exod.1.19"/> The midwives said to the Pharaoh, <q>Because the He­brew women are not
       like the Egyptian women; they are brisk creatures, delivered before ever a midwife reaches them!</q> <verse eID="Exod.1.19"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.1.20" osisID="Exod.1.20"/> So the people continued to multiply and teem. God prospered the midwives; <verse eID="Exod.1.20"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.1.21" osisID="Exod.1.21"/> since the midwives had reverenced God, he made them mothers of families. <verse eID="Exod.1.21"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Exod.1.22" osisID="Exod.1.22"/>The Pharaoh then ordered all his people to throw every son born to the
       Hebrews into the Nile, but to save every girl alive. <verse eID="Exod.1.22"/>
    <chapter eId="Exod.1"/>
    <chapter osisId="Exod.2" sId="Exod.2"/>
    <chapter eId="Exod.2"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.2.1" osisID="Exod.2.1"/> Now a man belonging to the house of Levi went and married a daughter of
       Levi; <verse eID="Exod.2.1"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.2.2" osisID="Exod.2.2"/> the woman conceived and bore a son, and as she saw he was a handsome boy,
       she hid him for three months. <verse eID="Exod.2.2"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.2.3" osisID="Exod.2.3"/> When she could hide him no longer, she took a creel made of papyrus reeds,
       daubed it over with bitumen and pitch, and put the child in it, laying it among the reeds at the side of the Nile. <verse eID="Exod.2.3"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.2.4" osisID="Exod.2.4"/> His sister placed herself at a distance, to see what would happen to him. <verse eID="Exod.2.4"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Exod.2.5" osisID="Exod.2.5"/>The daughter of the Pharaoh came down to bathe at the river; her maidens
       were walking along the bank, and as she saw the creel among the reeds she sent her slave-girl to fetch it. <verse eID="Exod.2.5"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.2.6" osisID="Exod.2.6"/> On opening it she saw the child--it was a boy crying! She
       <milestone type="pb" n="62"/>
       pitied him, and said, <q>This is one of the Hebrews’ children.</q> <verse eID="Exod.2.6"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.2.7" osisID="Exod.2.7"/> His sister said to the Pharaoh’s daughter, <q>Shall I go and get you a
       Hebrew nurse, to suckle the child for you?</q> <verse eID="Exod.2.7"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.2.8" osisID="Exod.2.8"/> <q>Yes,</q> said the Pharaoh’s daughter. So the girl went for the child’s
       mother, <verse eID="Exod.2.8"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.2.9" osisID="Exod.2.9"/> and the Pharaoh’s daughter said to her, <q>Take this child away and suckle
       it for me, and I will pay you your wages.</q> The woman took and suckled the child, <verse eID="Exod.2.9"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.2.10" osisID="Exod.2.10"/> and when the child grew up she brought him to the Pha­raoh’s daughter,
       who adopted him as her son; she called his name Moses (Removed), <q>for,</q> she said, <q>I removed him from the
       water.</q>] <verse eID="Exod.2.10"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <hi type="italic">
       <verse sID="Exod.2.11" osisID="Exod.2.11"/>It was during those days that Moses, now a man, once went out to his
        fellow-countrymen. He noted the loads they had to bear. And he saw an Egyptian striking a Hebrew, one of his own
        country men. <verse eID="Exod.2.11"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.2.12" osisID="Exod.2.12"/> Moses looked round, there was no one to be seen; so he knocked the
        Egyptian down and hid his body in the sand. <verse eID="Exod.2.12"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.2.13" osisID="Exod.2.13"/> Next day, when he went out, there were two Hebrews quarrel­ling! Moses
        said to the man in the wrong, <q>Why are you striking a fellow-countryman?</q> <verse eID="Exod.2.13"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.2.14" osisID="Exod.2.14"/> He replied, <q>Who made you an au­thority and umpire over us? Do you mean
        to murder me as you murdered the Egyptian?</q> This made Moses afraid; he reflected that what he had done must be
        known. <verse eID="Exod.2.14"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.2.15" osisID="Exod.2.15"/> When the Pharaoh heard of it, he tried to kill Moses, but Moses escaped
        from the Pharaoh to the land of Midian.
      </hi>
     </p>
     <p>
      <hi type="italic">
        He was sitting beside a well,
       <verse eID="Exod.2.15"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.2.16" osisID="Exod.2.16"/> when the seven daughters of the priest of Midian came to draw water,
        to fill the troughs for their father’s flock. <verse eID="Exod.2.16"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.2.17" osisID="Exod.2.17"/> The shepherds drove them off, but Moses came forward and helped them to
        water their flock. <verse eID="Exod.2.17"/>
      </hi>
     </p>
     <p>
      <hi type="italic">
       <verse sID="Exod.2.18" osisID="Exod.2.18"/> When they got home to their father [[Reuel]], he asked them how they
        had returned so soon that day. <verse eID="Exod.2.18"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.2.19" osisID="Exod.2.19"/> They said, <q>An Egyptian protected us from the shep­herds. He even drew
        water for us, to water the flock!</q> <verse eID="Exod.2.19"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.2.20" osisID="Exod.2.20"/><q>And where is he?</q> the man asked his daughters. <q>Why have you
        left him behind? Ask him to take food with us.</q> <verse eID="Exod.2.20"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.2.21" osisID="Exod.2.21"/> Moses agreed to live with the man, and he gave Moses his daughter
        Zipporah in marriage; <verse eID="Exod.2.21"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.2.22" osisID="Exod.2.22"/> she bore him a son, whom he called Oershom or Stranger, <q>for I have
        been a stranger,</q> he said, <q>in a foreign land.</q> <verse eID="Exod.2.22"/>
      </hi>
     </p>
     <p>
      <hi type="italic">
       <verse sID="Exod.2.23" osisID="Exod.2.23"/>During this long time the king of Egypt died. <verse eID="Exod.2.23"/>
    <chapter eId="Exod.2"/>
    <chapter osisId="Exod.4" sId="Exod.4"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.4.19" osisID="Exod.4.19"/> Then the Eternal said to Moses in Midian, <q>Go back to Egypt, for all
        the men who tried to kill you are dead.</q> <verse eID="Exod.4.19"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.4.20" osisID="Exod.4.20"/> So Moses put his wife and his son on an ass, and went back to the land
        of Egypt. <verse eID="Exod.4.20"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.4.24" osisID="Exod.4.24"/> On the way back, the Eternal met him at a khan and tried to kill him. <verse eID="Exod.4.24"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.4.25" osisID="Exod.4.25"/> So Zipporah taking a flint-knife cut off her boy's foreskin and touched
        his feet with it, cry­ing, <q>There, you are my bride­groom in blood!</q> <verse eID="Exod.4.25"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.4.26" osisID="Exod.4.26"/> Then the Eternal let him alone, when Zip­porah cried, <q>You are my
        bride­groom in blood, by this circum­cision.</q>
       <verse eID="Exod.4.26"/>
      </hi>
    <chapter eId="Exod.4"/>
    <chapter osisId="Exod.2" sId="Exod.2"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Exod.2.23" osisID="Exod.2.23"/>The Israelites were groaning under their bondage, and the wail of their
       cries for help came up to God. <verse eID="Exod.2.23"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.2.24" osisID="Exod.2.24"/> God heard their moaning, and God remem­bered his compact with Abra­ham,
       Isaac, and Jacob; <verse eID="Exod.2.24"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.2.25" osisID="Exod.2.25"/> God noted the plight of the Israelites and God made himself known to
       them. <verse eID="Exod.2.25"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eId="Exod.2"/>
     </p>
    <chapter osisId="Exod.3" sId="Exod.3"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Exod.3.1" osisID="Exod.3.1"/>[One day, as Moses was tending the flock of his
       <milestone type="pb" n="63"/>
       father-in-law Jethro, the priest of Midian, he led the flock to the western side of the prairie, and reached the
       sacred hill of Horeb.] <verse eID="Exod.3.1"/>
      <hi type="italic">
       <verse sID="Exod.3.2" osisID="Exod.3.2"/> The angel of the Eter­nal appeared, to him in a flame of fire rising out of
        a thorn-bush. When he looked, there was the thorn-bush ablaze with fire, yet not consumed! <verse eID="Exod.3.2"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.3.3" osisID="Exod.3.3"/><q>I will step aside,</q> said Moses, <q>and see this marvel, why the
        thorn-bush is not yet burnt up.</q> <verse eID="Exod.3.3"/>
      </hi>
      <verse sID="Exod.3.4" osisID="Exod.3.4"/> When the Eternal saw that he stepped aside to look at it, [God called to
       him out of the thorn-bush, say­ing, <q>Moses, Moses!</q> He answered, <q>Here I am!</q>] <verse eID="Exod.3.4"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.3.5" osisID="Exod.3.5"/> and he said, <q>Do not come close; remove your sandals from your feet, for
       the place where you are standing is sacred ground.</q> <verse eID="Exod.3.5"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.3.6" osisID="Exod.3.6"/> [He said, <q>I am the God of your father, the God of Abraham, the God of
       Isaac, and the God of Jacob.</q>
     </p>
     <p>
       Moses covered his face; he was afraid to look at God.]
      <verse eID="Exod.3.6"/>
      <hi type="italic">
       <verse sID="Exod.3.7" osisID="Exod.3.7"/> The Eternal said, <q>I have indeed seen the distress of my people in
        Egypt, I have heard them wail­ing under their slave-drivers; for I know their sorrows
       <verse eID="Exod.3.7"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.3.8" osisID="Exod.3.8"/> and I have come down to rescue them from the Egyptians and to bring them
        out of that land to a fine, large land, abounding in milk and honey, the country of the Canaanites, the Hittites,
        the Amorites, the Perizzites, the Hivites, and the JebUsites.</q><verse eID="Exod.3.8"/>
      </hi>
      <verse sID="Exod.3.9" osisID="Exod.3.9"/> <q>[And now the wail of the Israelites has reached me; I have also seen how
       the Egyptians are oppressing them. <verse eID="Exod.3.9"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.3.10" osisID="Exod.3.10"/> So come, I will send you to the Pharaoh that you may bring my people the
       Israelites out of Egypt.</q> <verse eID="Exod.3.10"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Exod.3.11" osisID="Exod.3.11"/>Moses said to God, <q>But who am I, to go to the Pharaoh and to bring the
       Israelites out of Egypt?</q> <verse eID="Exod.3.11"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.3.12" osisID="Exod.3.12"/> He answered, <q>I will be with you. And here is your proof that I myself
       have sent you: when you have brought the people out of Egypt, they shall worship God on this very hill.</q> <verse eID="Exod.3.12"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.3.13" osisID="Exod.3.13"/> <q>But,</q> said Moses to God, <q>when I go to the Israelites and tell
       them that the God of their fathers has sent me to them, and when they ask me, <q>What is his name?</q> what am I to
       say to them?</q> <verse eID="Exod.3.13"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.3.14" osisID="Exod.3.14"/> God said to Moses, <q>I-will-be-what-I-will-be: tell the Israelites that
       I-will-be has sent you to them.</q> <verse eID="Exod.3.14"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.3.15" osisID="Exod.3.15"/>God also said to Moses, <q>You must tell the Israelites that the Eter­nal,
       the God of their fathers, the God of Abraham, the God of Isaac, and the God of Jacob, has sent you to them; tell
       them
       <lg>
        <l> This is my name for all time, </l>
        <l> this is my title for all ages.] </l>
       </lg>
      <verse eID="Exod.3.15"/>
      <hi type="italic">
       <verse sID="Exod.3.16" osisID="Exod.3.16"/> Go and gather the sheikhs of Israel, and tell them that the Eter­nal, the
        God of their fathers, the God of Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob, has appeared to you, say­ing, <q>I have remembered you and
        all that is being done to you in Egypt; <verse eID="Exod.3.16"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.3.17" osisID="Exod.3.17"/> I have resolved to bring you out of your distress in Egypt to the
        country of the Canaanites, the Hittites, the Amorites, the Perizzites, the Hivites, and the Jebvsites, to a land
        abounding in milk and honey.</q> <verse eID="Exod.3.17"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.3.18" osisID="Exod.3.18"/> They will listen to what you say. Then you and the sheikhs of Israel
        must go to the king of Egypt and tell him that <q>the Eternal, the God of the Hebrews, has met us. Pray let us
        travel for three days into the desert, then, that we may sacrifice to the Eternal our God.</q> <verse eID="Exod.3.18"/>
      </hi>
      <verse sID="Exod.3.19" osisID="Exod.3.19"/> [Well do I know that the king of Egypt will not let you go, except by
       force. <verse eID="Exod.3.19"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.3.20" osisID="Exod.3.20"/> So I will exert my force and strike Egypt with all the marvels I in­tend
       to work there; after that
       <milestone type="pb" n="64"/> he will let you go. <verse eID="Exod.3.20"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.3.21" osisID="Exod.3.21"/> And I will make this people so much in favour with the Egyptians that
       you shall not leave the country empty-handed; <verse eID="Exod.3.21"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.3.22" osisID="Exod.3.22"/> no, every woman shall ask her neighbour and her slave for jewels of
       silver and of gold as well as for raiment, to bedeck your sons and daughters. You shall take toll of the
       Egyp­tians.]</q> <verse eID="Exod.3.22"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eId="Exod.3"/>
    <chapter osisId="Exod.4" sId="Exod.4"/>
     <p>
      <hi type="italic">
       <verse sID="Exod.4.1" osisID="Exod.4.1"/>Moses answered, <q>But sup­pose they will not believe me, or listen to what
        I say; sup­pose they say,<q>The Eternal never appeared to you.</q></q> <verse eID="Exod.4.1"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.4.2" osisID="Exod.4.2"/> The Eternal said to him, <q>What is that in your hand?</q> <q>A stick</q>
       he said. <verse eID="Exod.4.2"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.4.3" osisID="Exod.4.3"/> <q>Throw it on the ground,</q> said the Eternal. He threw it on the
        ground, and it turned into a snake. Moses ran away from it, <verse eID="Exod.4.3"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.4.4" osisID="Exod.4.4"/> but the Eternal said to Moses, <q>Put your hand out and catch it by the
        tail</q>--he did put his hand out and caught it by the tail, when it became a stick in his hand-- <verse eID="Exod.4.4"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.4.5" osisID="Exod.4.5"/> <q>that they may believe the Eternal, the God of their fathers, the God
        of Abraham, the God of Isaac, and the God of Jacob, has appeared to you.</q> <verse eID="Exod.4.5"/>
      </hi>
     </p>
     <p>
      <hi type="italic">
       <verse sID="Exod.4.6" osisID="Exod.4.6"/> The Eternal also said to him, <q>Put your hand into your bos­om.</q>
        He did so, and when he took it out, there was his hand all leprous, white as snow! <verse eID="Exod.4.6"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.4.7" osisID="Exod.4.7"/><q>Put your hand back into your bosom,</q> said the Eternal; he did so,
        and when he took it out, there it was, like his other flesh again! <verse eID="Exod.4.7"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.4.8" osisID="Exod.4.8"/> <q>If they will not believe you, if they will not credit the first
        portent, then they will believe the second. <verse eID="Exod.4.8"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.4.9" osisID="Exod.4.9"/> If they will not believe even these two por­tents, if they will not listen
        to what you say, then you must take some water from the Nile and pour it on the dry ground, and the water you take
        from the Nile shall turn into blood on the dry ground.</q> <verse eID="Exod.4.9"/>
      </hi>
     </p>
     <p>
      <hi type="italic">
       <verse sID="Exod.4.10" osisID="Exod.4.10"/>Moses said to the Eternal, <q>But, Lord, I am no speaker, I never have
        been and I am not now, not even since thou hast spoken to thy servant; I am slow of speech, I have no com­mand of
        words.</q> <verse eID="Exod.4.10"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.4.11" osisID="Exod.4.11"/> The Eternal said to him, <q>Who gives man his mouth? Who makes one man
        dumb or deaf, who gives him sight or makes him blind? Is it not I, the Eternal? <verse eID="Exod.4.11"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.4.12" osisID="Exod.4.12"/> Go, then, I be with your mouth and teach you what to say.</q> <verse eID="Exod.4.12"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.4.13" osisID="Exod.4.13"/> [<q>Send 13 whom thou wilt, Lord!</q> he re­plied. <verse eID="Exod.4.13"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.4.14" osisID="Exod.4.14"/> The Eternal’s anger blazed against Moses; he said, <q>What of your
        brother Aaron the Levite? He, I know, can speak well. Why, there he is, coming to meet you; when he sees you, he
        will be glad at heart!> <verse eID="Exod.4.14"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.4.15" osisID="Exod.4.15"/> You must speak to him and tell him what to say; I will be with your
        mouth and with his mouth to instruct you. <verse eID="Exod.4.15"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.4.16" osisID="Exod.4.16"/> He shall be your spokesman to the people; he shall serve as a
        mouthpiece for you, and you shall inspire him.]</q><verse eID="Exod.4.16"/>
      </hi>
      <verse sID="Exod.4.17" osisID="Exod.4.17"/><q>[Take this stick in your hand, to work portents. <verse eID="Exod.4.17"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.4.21" osisID="Exod.4.21"/> And when you return to Egypt, see that you perform before the Pharaoh
       all the portents I have given you power to perform--though I will make him obdu­rate, and he will not let the peo­ple
       go.</q> <verse eID="Exod.4.21"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Exod.4.20" osisID="Exod.4.20"/>So Moses took the stick of God in his hand. <verse eID="Exod.4.20"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.4.18" osisID="Exod.4.18"/> He went back to his father-in-law Jethro, and said to him, <q>Pray let
       me re­turn to my relatives in Egypt, to see if they are still alive!</q> <q>Go with my blessing,</q> said Jethro.
      <verse eID="Exod.4.18"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.4.27" osisID="Exod.4.27"/> Then the Eternal said to Aaron, <q>Go into the desert to meet Moses.</q>
       He went, and he met him at the sacred hill;
       <milestone type="pb" n="65"/>
       he kissed him, <verse eID="Exod.4.27"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.4.28" osisID="Exod.4.28"/> and then Moses told Aaron all the commission of the Eternal and all the
       por­tents he had been charged to perform.] <verse eID="Exod.4.28"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <hi type="italic">
       <verse sID="Exod.4.29" osisID="Exod.4.29"/>Moses and Aaron then gath­ered all the sheikhs of Israel, <verse eID="Exod.4.29"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.4.30" osisID="Exod.4.30"/> and Aaron told them all that the Eternal had said to Moses, while Moses
        performed the por­tents in the sight of the people. <verse eID="Exod.4.30"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.4.31" osisID="Exod.4.31"/> The people believed; when they heard that the Eternal had re­membered
        the Israelites and marked their distress, they bowed their heads and wor­shipped. <verse eID="Exod.4.31"/>
      </hi>
     </p>
    <chapter eId="Exod.4"/>
    <chapter osisId="Exod.5" sId="Exod.5"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Exod.5.1" osisID="Exod.5.1"/>[After that, Moses and Aaron went and told the Pharaoh that the Eternal,
       the God of Israel, bade him let the Eternal’s people go and hold a festival in his honour in the desert. <verse eID="Exod.5.1"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.5.2" osisID="Exod.5.2"/> <q>Who is the Eternal,</q> said the Pha­raoh, <q>that I should listen to
       his order to let Israel go? I know nothing about the Eter­nal; besides, I will not let 3 Israel go.</q>] <verse eID="Exod.5.2"/>
      <hi type="italic">
       <verse sID="Exod.5.3" osisID="Exod.5.3"/> They said, <q>The God of the Hebrews has met us; pray, then, let us travel
        for three days into the desert that we may sacrifice to the Eternal our God, lest he fall upon us with pesti­lence
        or with the sword.</q> <verse eID="Exod.5.3"/>
      </hi>
      <verse sID="Exod.5.4" osisID="Exod.5.4"/> [<q>Moses and Aaron,</q> said the king of Egypt, <q>why would you
       unsettle the people from their labours? Get to your tasks.</q>] <verse eID="Exod.5.4"/>
      <hi type="italic">
       <verse sID="Exod.5.5" osisID="Exod.5.5"/> <q>The work-people are now nu­merous,</q> said the Pharaoh, <q>and you are
        putting them off their tasks!</q> <verse eID="Exod.5.5"/>
      </hi>
     </p>
     <p>
      <hi type="italic">
       <verse sID="Exod.5.6" osisID="Exod.5.6"/>That very day the Pharaoh ordered the slave-drivers and the foremen, <verse eID="Exod.5.6"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.5.7" osisID="Exod.5.7"/> <q>You must no longer give the people straw for making bricks; after
        this, let them go and gather the straw for themselves. <verse eID="Exod.5.7"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.5.8" osisID="Exod.5.8"/> But you must exact from them the same number of bricks as they have had
        to make up till now; you must not reduce the quantity. For they are lazy; that is why they are crying, <q>Let us
        go and sacrifice to our God.</q> <verse eID="Exod.5.8"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.5.9" osisID="Exod.5.9"/> Make the men do heavier work, that they may attend to that instead of
        attending to lying words.</q> <verse eID="Exod.5.9"/>
      </hi>
     </p>
     <p>
      <hi type="italic">
       <verse sID="Exod.5.10" osisID="Exod.5.10"/>So the slave-drivers and the foremen went and told the peo­ple, <q>The
        Pharaoh declares that he will not give you any more straw. <verse eID="Exod.5.10"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.5.11" osisID="Exod.5.11"/> Go and gather straw for yourselves wherever you can find it; but your
        output of work is not to be reduced.</q> <verse eID="Exod.5.11"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.5.12" osisID="Exod.5.12"/> The people scattered all over Egypt in search of stubble for straw, <verse eID="Exod.5.12"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.5.13" osisID="Exod.5.13"/> while the slave-drivers urged them on to complete their daily amount of
        bricks, as when straw had been provided. <verse eID="Exod.5.13"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.5.14" osisID="Exod.5.14"/> The foremen of the Israelites, whom the Pha­raoh’s slave-drivers had put
        over them, were thrashed, and asked why they had not completed their amount of bricks as usual. <verse eID="Exod.5.14"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.5.15" osisID="Exod.5.15"/> Then the foremen of the Israelites went and appealed to the Pharaoh,
        <q>Why do you treat your servants so?<verse eID="Exod.5.15"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.5.16" osisID="Exod.5.16"/> Your servants have no straw supplied to them and yet we are told to
        make bricks; and your servants get thrashed, whereas it is you who are wronging your people.</q> <verse eID="Exod.5.16"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.5.17" osisID="Exod.5.17"/> He answered, <q>You are lazy, lazy, that is why you cry, <q>Let us go
        and sacrifice to the Eternal.</q> <verse eID="Exod.5.17"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.5.18" osisID="Exod.5.18"/> Begone to your work; you shall get no straw, but you must de­liver your
        quantity of bricks.</q> <verse eID="Exod.5.18"/>
      </hi>
      <hi type="italic">
       <verse sID="Exod.5.19" osisID="Exod.5.19"/>The foremen of the Israelites saw the plight they were in, when they
        were told not to reduce their daily number of bricks. <verse eID="Exod.5.19"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.5.20" osisID="Exod.5.20"/>As they left the Pharaoh, they met Moses and Aaron, who were waiting for
        them, <verse eID="Exod.5.20"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.5.21" osisID="Exod.5.21"/> and cried out, <q>May the Eternal look on what
        <milestone type="pb" n="65"/>
        you have done and punish you! You have brought us into bad odour with the Pharaoh and his officers, putting a
        weapon in their hands to kill us!</q> <verse eID="Exod.5.21"/>
      </hi>
     </p>
    <chapter eId="Exod.5"/>
   </div>
