   <div type="book" osisID="Exod">
    <milestone type="pb" n="61"/>
    <chapter osisId="Exod.1" sId="Exod.1"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Exod.1.1" osisID="Exod.1.1"/>Here are the names of the sons of Israel who went to Egypt with Jacob, each
       man along with his household: <verse eID="Exod.1.1"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.1.2" osisID="Exod.1.2"/> Reu­ben, Simeon, Levi, and Judah,<verse eID="Exod.1.2"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.1.3" osisID="Exod.1.3"/> Issachar, Zebulun, and Benjamin, <verse eID="Exod.1.3"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.1.4" osisID="Exod.1.4"/> Dan and Naphtali, Gad and Asher; <verse eID="Exod.1.4"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.1.5" osisID="Exod.1.5"/> and the direct descend­ants of Jacob numbered seventy in all.
       (Joseph was in Egypt already.) <verse eID="Exod.1.5"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.1.7" osisID="Exod.1.7"/> The sons of Israel were fruitful and swarmed, they multiplied and teemed
       till the land was full of them. <verse eID="Exod.1.7"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.1.13" osisID="Exod.1.13"/> The Egyptians made slaves of the Israelites harshly; <verse eID="Exod.1.13"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.1.14" osisID="Exod.1.14"/> they made life bitter for them with hard service, forcing them to build
       with mortar and bricks and to do all manner of field-work--lot of slaves harshly treated. <verse eID="Exod.1.14"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <hi type="italic">
       <verse sID="Exod.1.6" osisID="Exod.1.6"/>Joseph died, so did all his brothers and all that generation. <verse eID="Exod.1.6"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.1.8" osisID="Exod.1.8"/> A new king rose over Egypt, who had not knowledge of Joseph; <verse eID="Exod.1.8"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.1.9" osisID="Exod.1.9"/> he said to his people, <q>Look, the Israelites are too many and too mighty
        for us! <verse eID="Exod.1.9"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.1.10" osisID="Exod.1.10"/> We must handle them carefully, lest they multi­ply and then, if we happen
        to be at war, join our enemies and fight against us, so as to escape from the country.</q><verse eID="Exod.1.10"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.1.11" osisID="Exod.1.11"/> So they put them under captains of the la­bour gangs, to crush them with
        heavy loads; and they built for the Pharaoh the store-towns of Pithom and Ramses. <verse eID="Exod.1.11"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.1.12" osisID="Exod.1.12"/> But the more they were crushed, the more they multiplied and ex­panded,
        till the Egyptians dreaded the Israelites. <verse eID="Exod.1.12"/>
      </hi>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Exod.1.15" osisID="Exod.1.15"/>[Then the king of Egypt told the Hebrew midwives, one of whom was called
       Shiphrah and the other Puah, <verse eID="Exod.1.15"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.1.16" osisID="Exod.1.16"/> that when they attended the Hebrew women and saw them on the birth-stool
       they were to kill the child, if it was a male, and to let it live, if it was a girl. <verse eID="Exod.1.16"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.1.17" osisID="Exod.1.17"/> But the midwives reverenced God; they did not do as the king of Egypt
       ordered them, but saved the male chil­dren alive. <verse eID="Exod.1.17"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.1.18" osisID="Exod.1.18"/> Then the king of Egypt summoned the midwives. <q>Why have you done
       this,</q> he asked, <q>saving the male children alive?</q> <verse eID="Exod.1.18"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.1.19" osisID="Exod.1.19"/> The midwives said to the Pharaoh, <q>Because the He­brew women are not
       like the Egyptian women; they are brisk creatures, delivered before ever a midwife reaches them!</q> <verse eID="Exod.1.19"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.1.20" osisID="Exod.1.20"/> So the people continued to multiply and teem. God prospered the midwives; <verse eID="Exod.1.20"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.1.21" osisID="Exod.1.21"/> since the midwives had reverenced God, he made them mothers of families. <verse eID="Exod.1.21"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Exod.1.22" osisID="Exod.1.22"/>The Pharaoh then ordered all his people to throw every son born to the
       Hebrews into the Nile, but to save every girl alive. <verse eID="Exod.1.22"/>
    <chapter eId="Exod.1"/>
    <chapter osisId="Exod.2" sId="Exod.2"/>
    <chapter eId="Exod.2"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.2.1" osisID="Exod.2.1"/> Now a man belonging to the house of Levi went and married a daughter of
       Levi; <verse eID="Exod.2.1"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.2.2" osisID="Exod.2.2"/> the woman conceived and bore a son, and as she saw he was a handsome boy,
       she hid him for three months. <verse eID="Exod.2.2"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.2.3" osisID="Exod.2.3"/> When she could hide him no longer, she took a creel made of papyrus reeds,
       daubed it over with bitumen and pitch, and put the child in it, laying it among the reeds at the side of the Nile. <verse eID="Exod.2.3"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.2.4" osisID="Exod.2.4"/> His sister placed herself at a distance, to see what would happen to him. <verse eID="Exod.2.4"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Exod.2.5" osisID="Exod.2.5"/>The daughter of the Pharaoh came down to bathe at the river; her maidens
       were walking along the bank, and as she saw the creel among the reeds she sent her slave-girl to fetch it. <verse eID="Exod.2.5"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.2.6" osisID="Exod.2.6"/> On opening it she saw the child--it was a boy crying! She
       <milestone type="pb" n="62"/>
       pitied him, and said, <q>This is one of the Hebrews’ children.</q> <verse eID="Exod.2.6"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.2.7" osisID="Exod.2.7"/> His sister said to the Pharaoh’s daughter, <q>Shall I go and get you a
       Hebrew nurse, to suckle the child for you?</q> <verse eID="Exod.2.7"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.2.8" osisID="Exod.2.8"/> <q>Yes,</q> said the Pharaoh’s daughter. So the girl went for the child’s
       mother, <verse eID="Exod.2.8"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.2.9" osisID="Exod.2.9"/> and the Pharaoh’s daughter said to her, <q>Take this child away and suckle
       it for me, and I will pay you your wages.</q> The woman took and suckled the child, <verse eID="Exod.2.9"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.2.10" osisID="Exod.2.10"/> and when the child grew up she brought him to the Pha­raoh’s daughter,
       who adopted him as her son; she called his name Moses (Removed), <q>for,</q> she said, <q>I removed him from the
       water.</q>] <verse eID="Exod.2.10"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <hi type="italic">
       <verse sID="Exod.2.11" osisID="Exod.2.11"/>It was during those days that Moses, now a man, once went out to his
        fellow-countrymen. He noted the loads they had to bear. And he saw an Egyptian striking a Hebrew, one of his own
        country men. <verse eID="Exod.2.11"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.2.12" osisID="Exod.2.12"/> Moses looked round, there was no one to be seen; so he knocked the
        Egyptian down and hid his body in the sand. <verse eID="Exod.2.12"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.2.13" osisID="Exod.2.13"/> Next day, when he went out, there were two Hebrews quarrel­ling! Moses
        said to the man in the wrong, <q>Why are you striking a fellow-countryman?</q> <verse eID="Exod.2.13"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.2.14" osisID="Exod.2.14"/> He replied, <q>Who made you an au­thority and umpire over us? Do you mean
        to murder me as you murdered the Egyptian?</q> This made Moses afraid; he reflected that what he had done must be
        known. <verse eID="Exod.2.14"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.2.15" osisID="Exod.2.15"/> When the Pharaoh heard of it, he tried to kill Moses, but Moses escaped
        from the Pharaoh to the land of Midian.
      </hi>
     </p>
     <p>
      <hi type="italic">
        He was sitting beside a well,
       <verse eID="Exod.2.15"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.2.16" osisID="Exod.2.16"/> when the seven daughters of the priest of Midian came to draw water,
        to fill the troughs for their father’s flock. <verse eID="Exod.2.16"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.2.17" osisID="Exod.2.17"/> The shepherds drove them off, but Moses came forward and helped them to
        water their flock. <verse eID="Exod.2.17"/>
      </hi>
     </p>
     <p>
      <hi type="italic">
       <verse sID="Exod.2.18" osisID="Exod.2.18"/> When they got home to their father [[Reuel]], he asked them how they
        had returned so soon that day. <verse eID="Exod.2.18"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.2.19" osisID="Exod.2.19"/> They said, <q>An Egyptian protected us from the shep­herds. He even drew
        water for us, to water the flock!</q> <verse eID="Exod.2.19"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.2.20" osisID="Exod.2.20"/><q>And where is he?</q> the man asked his daughters. <q>Why have you
        left him behind? Ask him to take food with us.</q> <verse eID="Exod.2.20"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.2.21" osisID="Exod.2.21"/> Moses agreed to live with the man, and he gave Moses his daughter
        Zipporah in marriage; <verse eID="Exod.2.21"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.2.22" osisID="Exod.2.22"/> she bore him a son, whom he called Oershom or Stranger, <q>for I have
        been a stranger,</q> he said, <q>in a foreign land.</q> <verse eID="Exod.2.22"/>
      </hi>
     </p>
     <p>
      <hi type="italic">
       <verse sID="Exod.2.23" osisID="Exod.2.23"/>During this long time the king of Egypt died. <verse eID="Exod.2.23"/>
    <chapter eId="Exod.2"/>
    <chapter osisId="Exod.4" sId="Exod.4"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.4.19" osisID="Exod.4.19"/> Then the Eternal said to Moses in Midian, <q>Go back to Egypt, for all
        the men who tried to kill you are dead.</q> <verse eID="Exod.4.19"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.4.20" osisID="Exod.4.20"/> So Moses put his wife and his son on an ass, and went back to the land
        of Egypt. <verse eID="Exod.4.20"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.4.24" osisID="Exod.4.24"/> On the way back, the Eternal met him at a khan and tried to kill him. <verse eID="Exod.4.24"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.4.25" osisID="Exod.4.25"/> So Zipporah taking a flint-knife cut off her boy's foreskin and touched
        his feet with it, cry­ing, <q>There, you are my bride­groom in blood!</q> <verse eID="Exod.4.25"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.4.26" osisID="Exod.4.26"/> Then the Eternal let him alone, when Zip­porah cried, <q>You are my
        bride­groom in blood, by this circum­cision.</q>
       <verse eID="Exod.4.26"/>
      </hi>
    <chapter eId="Exod.4"/>
    <chapter osisId="Exod.2" sId="Exod.2"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Exod.2.23" osisID="Exod.2.23"/>The Israelites were groaning under their bondage, and the wail of their
       cries for help came up to God. <verse eID="Exod.2.23"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.2.24" osisID="Exod.2.24"/> God heard their moaning, and God remem­bered his compact with Abra­ham,
       Isaac, and Jacob; <verse eID="Exod.2.24"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.2.25" osisID="Exod.2.25"/> God noted the plight of the Israelites and God made himself known to
       them. <verse eID="Exod.2.25"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eId="Exod.2"/>
     </p>
    <chapter osisId="Exod.3" sId="Exod.3"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Exod.3.1" osisID="Exod.3.1"/>[One day, as Moses was tending the flock of his
       <milestone type="pb" n="63"/>
       father-in-law Jethro, the priest of Midian, he led the flock to the western side of the prairie, and reached the
       sacred hill of Horeb.] <verse eID="Exod.3.1"/>
      <hi type="italic">
       <verse sID="Exod.3.2" osisID="Exod.3.2"/> The angel of the Eter­nal appeared, to him in a flame of fire rising out of
        a thorn-bush. When he looked, there was the thorn-bush ablaze with fire, yet not consumed! <verse eID="Exod.3.2"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.3.3" osisID="Exod.3.3"/><q>I will step aside,</q> said Moses, <q>and see this marvel, why the
        thorn-bush is not yet burnt up.</q> <verse eID="Exod.3.3"/>
      </hi>
      <verse sID="Exod.3.4" osisID="Exod.3.4"/> When the Eternal saw that he stepped aside to look at it, [God called to
       him out of the thorn-bush, say­ing, <q>Moses, Moses!</q> He answered, <q>Here I am!</q>] <verse eID="Exod.3.4"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.3.5" osisID="Exod.3.5"/> and he said, <q>Do not come close; remove your sandals from your feet, for
       the place where you are standing is sacred ground.</q> <verse eID="Exod.3.5"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.3.6" osisID="Exod.3.6"/> [He said, <q>I am the God of your father, the God of Abraham, the God of
       Isaac, and the God of Jacob.</q>
     </p>
     <p>
       Moses covered his face; he was afraid to look at God.]
      <verse eID="Exod.3.6"/>
      <hi type="italic">
       <verse sID="Exod.3.7" osisID="Exod.3.7"/> The Eternal said, <q>I have indeed seen the distress of my people in
        Egypt, I have heard them wail­ing under their slave-drivers; for I know their sorrows
       <verse eID="Exod.3.7"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.3.8" osisID="Exod.3.8"/> and I have come down to rescue them from the Egyptians and to bring them
        out of that land to a fine, large land, abounding in milk and honey, the country of the Canaanites, the Hittites,
        the Amorites, the Perizzites, the Hivites, and the JebUsites.</q><verse eID="Exod.3.8"/>
      </hi>
      <verse sID="Exod.3.9" osisID="Exod.3.9"/> <q>[And now the wail of the Israelites has reached me; I have also seen how
       the Egyptians are oppressing them. <verse eID="Exod.3.9"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.3.10" osisID="Exod.3.10"/> So come, I will send you to the Pharaoh that you may bring my people the
       Israelites out of Egypt.</q> <verse eID="Exod.3.10"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Exod.3.11" osisID="Exod.3.11"/>Moses said to God, <q>But who am I, to go to the Pharaoh and to bring the
       Israelites out of Egypt?</q> <verse eID="Exod.3.11"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.3.12" osisID="Exod.3.12"/> He answered, <q>I will be with you. And here is your proof that I myself
       have sent you: when you have brought the people out of Egypt, they shall worship God on this very hill.</q> <verse eID="Exod.3.12"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.3.13" osisID="Exod.3.13"/> <q>But,</q> said Moses to God, <q>when I go to the Israelites and tell
       them that the God of their fathers has sent me to them, and when they ask me, <q>What is his name?</q> what am I to
       say to them?</q> <verse eID="Exod.3.13"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.3.14" osisID="Exod.3.14"/> God said to Moses, <q>I-will-be-what-I-will-be: tell the Israelites that
       I-will-be has sent you to them.</q> <verse eID="Exod.3.14"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.3.15" osisID="Exod.3.15"/>God also said to Moses, <q>You must tell the Israelites that the Eter­nal,
       the God of their fathers, the God of Abraham, the God of Isaac, and the God of Jacob, has sent you to them; tell
       them
       <lg>
        <l> This is my name for all time, </l>
        <l> this is my title for all ages.] </l>
       </lg>
      <verse eID="Exod.3.15"/>
      <hi type="italic">
       <verse sID="Exod.3.16" osisID="Exod.3.16"/> Go and gather the sheikhs of Israel, and tell them that the Eter­nal, the
        God of their fathers, the God of Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob, has appeared to you, say­ing, <q>I have remembered you and
        all that is being done to you in Egypt; <verse eID="Exod.3.16"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.3.17" osisID="Exod.3.17"/> I have resolved to bring you out of your distress in Egypt to the
        country of the Canaanites, the Hittites, the Amorites, the Perizzites, the Hivites, and the Jebvsites, to a land
        abounding in milk and honey.</q> <verse eID="Exod.3.17"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.3.18" osisID="Exod.3.18"/> They will listen to what you say. Then you and the sheikhs of Israel
        must go to the king of Egypt and tell him that <q>the Eternal, the God of the Hebrews, has met us. Pray let us
        travel for three days into the desert, then, that we may sacrifice to the Eternal our God.</q> <verse eID="Exod.3.18"/>
      </hi>
      <verse sID="Exod.3.19" osisID="Exod.3.19"/> [Well do I know that the king of Egypt will not let you go, except by
       force. <verse eID="Exod.3.19"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.3.20" osisID="Exod.3.20"/> So I will exert my force and strike Egypt with all the marvels I in­tend
       to work there; after that
       <milestone type="pb" n="64"/> he will let you go. <verse eID="Exod.3.20"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.3.21" osisID="Exod.3.21"/> And I will make this people so much in favour with the Egyptians that
       you shall not leave the country empty-handed; <verse eID="Exod.3.21"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.3.22" osisID="Exod.3.22"/> no, every woman shall ask her neighbour and her slave for jewels of
       silver and of gold as well as for raiment, to bedeck your sons and daughters. You shall take toll of the
       Egyp­tians.]</q> <verse eID="Exod.3.22"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eId="Exod.3"/>
    <chapter osisId="Exod.4" sId="Exod.4"/>
     <p>
      <hi type="italic">
       <verse sID="Exod.4.1" osisID="Exod.4.1"/>Moses answered, <q>But sup­pose they will not believe me, or listen to what
        I say; sup­pose they say,<q>The Eternal never appeared to you.</q></q> <verse eID="Exod.4.1"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.4.2" osisID="Exod.4.2"/> The Eternal said to him, <q>What is that in your hand?</q> <q>A stick</q>
       he said. <verse eID="Exod.4.2"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.4.3" osisID="Exod.4.3"/> <q>Throw it on the ground,</q> said the Eternal. He threw it on the
        ground, and it turned into a snake. Moses ran away from it, <verse eID="Exod.4.3"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.4.4" osisID="Exod.4.4"/> but the Eternal said to Moses, <q>Put your hand out and catch it by the
        tail</q>--he did put his hand out and caught it by the tail, when it became a stick in his hand-- <verse eID="Exod.4.4"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.4.5" osisID="Exod.4.5"/> <q>that they may believe the Eternal, the God of their fathers, the God
        of Abraham, the God of Isaac, and the God of Jacob, has appeared to you.</q> <verse eID="Exod.4.5"/>
      </hi>
     </p>
     <p>
      <hi type="italic">
       <verse sID="Exod.4.6" osisID="Exod.4.6"/> The Eternal also said to him, <q>Put your hand into your bos­om.</q>
        He did so, and when he took it out, there was his hand all leprous, white as snow! <verse eID="Exod.4.6"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.4.7" osisID="Exod.4.7"/><q>Put your hand back into your bosom,</q> said the Eternal; he did so,
        and when he took it out, there it was, like his other flesh again! <verse eID="Exod.4.7"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.4.8" osisID="Exod.4.8"/> <q>If they will not believe you, if they will not credit the first
        portent, then they will believe the second. <verse eID="Exod.4.8"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.4.9" osisID="Exod.4.9"/> If they will not believe even these two por­tents, if they will not listen
        to what you say, then you must take some water from the Nile and pour it on the dry ground, and the water you take
        from the Nile shall turn into blood on the dry ground.</q> <verse eID="Exod.4.9"/>
      </hi>
     </p>
     <p>
      <hi type="italic">
       <verse sID="Exod.4.10" osisID="Exod.4.10"/>Moses said to the Eternal, <q>But, Lord, I am no speaker, I never have
        been and I am not now, not even since thou hast spoken to thy servant; I am slow of speech, I have no com­mand of
        words.</q> <verse eID="Exod.4.10"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.4.11" osisID="Exod.4.11"/> The Eternal said to him, <q>Who gives man his mouth? Who makes one man
        dumb or deaf, who gives him sight or makes him blind? Is it not I, the Eternal? <verse eID="Exod.4.11"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.4.12" osisID="Exod.4.12"/> Go, then, I be with your mouth and teach you what to say.</q> <verse eID="Exod.4.12"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.4.13" osisID="Exod.4.13"/> [<q>Send 13 whom thou wilt, Lord!</q> he re­plied. <verse eID="Exod.4.13"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.4.14" osisID="Exod.4.14"/> The Eternal’s anger blazed against Moses; he said, <q>What of your
        brother Aaron the Levite? He, I know, can speak well. Why, there he is, coming to meet you; when he sees you, he
        will be glad at heart!> <verse eID="Exod.4.14"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.4.15" osisID="Exod.4.15"/> You must speak to him and tell him what to say; I will be with your
        mouth and with his mouth to instruct you. <verse eID="Exod.4.15"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.4.16" osisID="Exod.4.16"/> He shall be your spokesman to the people; he shall serve as a
        mouthpiece for you, and you shall inspire him.]</q><verse eID="Exod.4.16"/>
      </hi>
      <verse sID="Exod.4.17" osisID="Exod.4.17"/><q>[Take this stick in your hand, to work portents. <verse eID="Exod.4.17"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.4.21" osisID="Exod.4.21"/> And when you return to Egypt, see that you perform before the Pharaoh
       all the portents I have given you power to perform--though I will make him obdu­rate, and he will not let the peo­ple
       go.</q> <verse eID="Exod.4.21"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Exod.4.20" osisID="Exod.4.20"/>So Moses took the stick of God in his hand. <verse eID="Exod.4.20"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.4.18" osisID="Exod.4.18"/> He went back to his father-in-law Jethro, and said to him, <q>Pray let
       me re­turn to my relatives in Egypt, to see if they are still alive!</q> <q>Go with my blessing,</q> said Jethro.
      <verse eID="Exod.4.18"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.4.27" osisID="Exod.4.27"/> Then the Eternal said to Aaron, <q>Go into the desert to meet Moses.</q>
       He went, and he met him at the sacred hill;
       <milestone type="pb" n="65"/>
       he kissed him, <verse eID="Exod.4.27"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.4.28" osisID="Exod.4.28"/> and then Moses told Aaron all the commission of the Eternal and all the
       por­tents he had been charged to perform.] <verse eID="Exod.4.28"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <hi type="italic">
       <verse sID="Exod.4.29" osisID="Exod.4.29"/>Moses and Aaron then gath­ered all the sheikhs of Israel, <verse eID="Exod.4.29"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.4.30" osisID="Exod.4.30"/> and Aaron told them all that the Eternal had said to Moses, while Moses
        performed the por­tents in the sight of the people. <verse eID="Exod.4.30"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.4.31" osisID="Exod.4.31"/> The people believed; when they heard that the Eternal had re­membered
        the Israelites and marked their distress, they bowed their heads and wor­shipped. <verse eID="Exod.4.31"/>
      </hi>
     </p>
    <chapter eId="Exod.4"/>
    <chapter osisId="Exod.5" sId="Exod.5"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Exod.5.1" osisID="Exod.5.1"/>[After that, Moses and Aaron went and told the Pharaoh that the Eternal,
       the God of Israel, bade him let the Eternal’s people go and hold a festival in his honour in the desert. <verse eID="Exod.5.1"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.5.2" osisID="Exod.5.2"/> <q>Who is the Eternal,</q> said the Pha­raoh, <q>that I should listen to
       his order to let Israel go? I know nothing about the Eter­nal; besides, I will not let 3 Israel go.</q>] <verse eID="Exod.5.2"/>
      <hi type="italic">
       <verse sID="Exod.5.3" osisID="Exod.5.3"/> They said, <q>The God of the Hebrews has met us; pray, then, let us travel
        for three days into the desert that we may sacrifice to the Eternal our God, lest he fall upon us with pesti­lence
        or with the sword.</q> <verse eID="Exod.5.3"/>
      </hi>
      <verse sID="Exod.5.4" osisID="Exod.5.4"/> [<q>Moses and Aaron,</q> said the king of Egypt, <q>why would you
       unsettle the people from their labours? Get to your tasks.</q>] <verse eID="Exod.5.4"/>
      <hi type="italic">
       <verse sID="Exod.5.5" osisID="Exod.5.5"/> <q>The work-people are now nu­merous,</q> said the Pharaoh, <q>and you are
        putting them off their tasks!</q> <verse eID="Exod.5.5"/>
      </hi>
     </p>
     <p>
      <hi type="italic">
       <verse sID="Exod.5.6" osisID="Exod.5.6"/>That very day the Pharaoh ordered the slave-drivers and the foremen, <verse eID="Exod.5.6"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.5.7" osisID="Exod.5.7"/> <q>You must no longer give the people straw for making bricks; after
        this, let them go and gather the straw for themselves. <verse eID="Exod.5.7"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.5.8" osisID="Exod.5.8"/> But you must exact from them the same number of bricks as they have had
        to make up till now; you must not reduce the quantity. For they are lazy; that is why they are crying, <q>Let us
        go and sacrifice to our God.</q> <verse eID="Exod.5.8"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.5.9" osisID="Exod.5.9"/> Make the men do heavier work, that they may attend to that instead of
        attending to lying words.</q> <verse eID="Exod.5.9"/>
      </hi>
     </p>
     <p>
      <hi type="italic">
       <verse sID="Exod.5.10" osisID="Exod.5.10"/>So the slave-drivers and the foremen went and told the peo­ple, <q>The
        Pharaoh declares that he will not give you any more straw. <verse eID="Exod.5.10"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.5.11" osisID="Exod.5.11"/> Go and gather straw for yourselves wherever you can find it; but your
        output of work is not to be reduced.</q> <verse eID="Exod.5.11"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.5.12" osisID="Exod.5.12"/> The people scattered all over Egypt in search of stubble for straw, <verse eID="Exod.5.12"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.5.13" osisID="Exod.5.13"/> while the slave-drivers urged them on to complete their daily amount of
        bricks, as when straw had been provided. <verse eID="Exod.5.13"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.5.14" osisID="Exod.5.14"/> The foremen of the Israelites, whom the Pha­raoh’s slave-drivers had put
        over them, were thrashed, and asked why they had not completed their amount of bricks as usual. <verse eID="Exod.5.14"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.5.15" osisID="Exod.5.15"/> Then the foremen of the Israelites went and appealed to the Pharaoh,
        <q>Why do you treat your servants so?<verse eID="Exod.5.15"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.5.16" osisID="Exod.5.16"/> Your servants have no straw supplied to them and yet we are told to
        make bricks; and your servants get thrashed, whereas it is you who are wronging your people.</q> <verse eID="Exod.5.16"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.5.17" osisID="Exod.5.17"/> He answered, <q>You are lazy, lazy, that is why you cry, <q>Let us go
        and sacrifice to the Eternal.</q> <verse eID="Exod.5.17"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.5.18" osisID="Exod.5.18"/> Begone to your work; you shall get no straw, but you must de­liver your
        quantity of bricks.</q> <verse eID="Exod.5.18"/>
      </hi>
     </p>
     <p>
      <hi type="italic">
       <verse sID="Exod.5.19" osisID="Exod.5.19"/>The foremen of the Israelites saw the plight they were in, when they
        were told not to reduce their daily number of bricks. <verse eID="Exod.5.19"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.5.20" osisID="Exod.5.20"/>As they left the Pharaoh, they met Moses and Aaron, who were waiting for
        them, <verse eID="Exod.5.20"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.5.21" osisID="Exod.5.21"/> and cried out, <q>May the Eternal look on what
        <milestone type="pb" n="66"/>
        you have done and punish you! You have brought us into bad odour with the Pharaoh and his officers, putting a
        weapon in their hands to kill us!</q> <verse eID="Exod.5.21"/>
      </hi>
     </p>
     <p>
      <hi type="italic">
       <verse sID="Exod.5.22" osisID="Exod.5.22"/>Then Moses turned to the Eternal and said, <q>O Eternal, why hast thou
        ill-treated this people? Why didst thou ever send me here? <verse eID="Exod.5.22"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.5.23" osisID="Exod.5.239"/> Ever since I came to speak in thy name to the Pharaoh, he has
        ill-treated this people, and thou hast done nothing to rescue thy people.</q> <verse eID="Exod.5.23"/>
    <chapter eId="Exod.5"/>
    <chapter osisId="Exod.6" sId="Exod.6"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.6.1" osisID="Exod.6.1"/> The Eternal said to Moses, <q>Now you shall see what I will do to the
        Pharaoh; he will be forced to let them go, he will be forced to put them out of his country.</q> <verse eID="Exod.6.1"/>
      </hi>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Exod.6.2" osisID="Exod.6.2"/>Now God said this to Moses, <q>I am the Eternal; <verse eID="Exod.6.2"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.6.3" osisID="Exod.6.3"/> I appeared to Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob as God Almighty, but I never made
       myself known to them as <q>the Eternal.</q> <verse eID="Exod.6.3"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.6.4" osisID="Exod.6.4"/> I made my com­pact with them, to give them the land of Canaan where they
       were residing for a while. <verse eID="Exod.6.4"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.6.5" osisID="Exod.6.5"/> Also I have heard the moaning of the Israelites, whom the Egyptians
       enslave, and I have remembered my compact. <verse eID="Exod.6.5"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.6.6" osisID="Exod.6.6"/> So tell the Is­raelites that I am the Eternal, I will free them from the
       load of the Egyptians and rid them of their bondage. I will deliver them by main force and mighty victories, <verse eID="Exod.6.6"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.6.7" osisID="Exod.6.7"/> I will take them to be a people for me and I will be a God to them; so
       shall they find that I am the Eternal, their God, who frees them from the load of the Egyptians.
      <verse eID="Exod.6.7"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.6.8" osisID="Exod.6.8"/> I will bring them into the land that I solemnly swore to give to Abraham,
       Isaac, and Jacob, giv­ing it to them as a possession. I am the Eternal.</q> <verse eID="Exod.6.8"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Exod.6.9" osisID="Exod.6.9"/>Moses told this to the Israel­ites, but they would not listen to Moses,
       they were so impatient and hard pressed. <verse eID="Exod.6.9"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.6.10" osisID="Exod.6.10"/> Then the Eternal told Moses <verse eID="Exod.6.10"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.6.11" osisID="Exod.6.11"/> to go and bid the Pharaoh king of Egypt let the Israelites go from his
       coun­try. <verse eID="Exod.6.11"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.6.12" osisID="Exod.6.12"/> Moses protested, <q>The Israelites have not listened to me, and how will
       the Pharaoh listen to me, clumsy speaker that I am?</q> <verse eID="Exod.6.12"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.6.13" osisID="Exod.6.13"/> [[The Eternal spoke to Moses and Aaron and gave them a commission for
       the Is­raelites and also for the Pha­raoh king of Egypt, to bring the Israelites out of the land of Egypt. <verse eID="Exod.6.13"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Exod.6.14" osisID="Exod.6.14"/>These are the heads of their clans. The sons of Reuben the first-born of
       Israel were Hanok, Pallu, Hezron, and Karmi; these are the families of Reuben. <verse eID="Exod.6.14"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.6.15" osisID="Exod.6.15"/> The sons of Simeon were Jemuel, Jamin, Ohad, Jachin, Zohar, and Saul
       (whose mother was a Canaanite); these are the families of Simeon. <verse eID="Exod.6.15"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.6.16" osisID="Exod.6.16"/> The sons of Levi, according to their ages, were Gershon, Kohath, and
       Merari: Levi lived for a hundred and thirty-seven years. <verse eID="Exod.6.16"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.6.17" osisID="Exod.6.17"/> Gershon’s sons were Libni and Shimei, by their families; <verse eID="Exod.6.17"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.6.18" osisID="Exod.6.18"/> Kohath’s sons were Amram, Izhar, Hebron, and Uzziel—Kohath lived for a
       hundred and thirty-three years; <verse eID="Exod.6.18"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.6.19" osisID="Exod.6.19"/> Merari’s sons were Mahli and Mushi; these are the families of the
       Levites in order of age. <verse eID="Exod.6.19"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.6.20" osisID="Exod.6.20"/> Amram married Jochebed his aunt, who bore him Aaron and Moses; Amram
       lived for a hun­dred and thirty-seven years. <verse eID="Exod.6.20"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.6.21" osisID="Exod.6.21"/> Izhar’s sons were Korah, Nepheg, and Zichri; <verse eID="Exod.6.21"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.6.22" osisID="Exod.6.22"/> Uzziel’s sons were Mishael, Elzaphan. and Sithri. <verse eID="Exod.6.22"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.6.23" osisID="Exod.6.23"/> Aaron married Elisheba the daughter of Amminadab, the sister of Nahshon,
       who bore him Nadab, Abihu, Eleazar, and Ithamar. <verse eID="Exod.6.23"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.6.24" osisID="Exod.6.24"/> Korah’s sons were Assir, Elkanah, and
       <milestone type="pb" n="67"/>
       Abiasaph; these are the families of the Korahites. <verse eID="Exod.6.24"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.6.25" osisID="Exod.6.25"/> Aaron’s son Eleazar married a daughter of Putiel, who bore him Phinehas.
       These are the heads of the Levite clans, by their families. <verse eID="Exod.6.25"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Exod.6.26" osisID="Exod.6.26"/>Such were the Moses and Aaron whom the Eternal or­dered to bring the
       Israelites out of the land of Egypt in all their array. <verse eID="Exod.6.26"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.6.27" osisID="Exod.6.27"/> They it was who spoke to the Pharaoh king of Egypt, about bringing the
       Is­raelites out of Egypt; it was this Moses and Aaron. <verse eID="Exod.6.27"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Exod.6.28" osisID="Exod.6.28"/>Now on the day when the Eternal spoke to Moses in the land of Egypt, <verse eID="Exod.6.28"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.6.29" osisID="Exod.6.29"/> the Eternal said to Moses, <q>I am the Eternal; tell the Pharaoh king of
       Egypt all that I tell you.</q> <verse eID="Exod.6.29"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.6.30" osisID="Exod.6.30"/> Moses protested, <q>But I am a clumsy speaker; how will the Pharaoh ever
       listen to me?</q>]] <verse eID="Exod.6.30"/>
    <chapter eId="Exod.6"/>
    <chapter osisId="Exod.7" sId="Exod.7"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.7.1" osisID="Exod.7.1"/> The Eternal answered Moses, <q>I make you a god for the Pharaoh, and your
       brother Aaron shall be a prophet for you. <verse eID="Exod.7.1"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.7.2" osisID="Exod.7.2"/> You must utter all that I command you, and your brother Aaron will tell
       the Pharaoh to let the Israelites go from his land. <verse eID="Exod.7.2"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.7.3" osisID="Exod.7.3"/> But I will make the Pharaoh stub­born; I will do many a signal act in the
       land of Egypt, <verse eID="Exod.7.3"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.7.4" osisID="Exod.7.4"/> but the Pharaoh will not listen to you; so I will let my hand fall on
       Egypt and bring out my people in their hosts, the Is­raelites, by mighty victories, <verse eID="Exod.7.4"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.7.5" osisID="Exod.7.5"/> that the Egyptians may learn I am the Eternal as I stretch out my hand to
       crush Egypt and bring away the Israelites.</q> <verse eID="Exod.7.5"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.7.6" osisID="Exod.7.6"/> Moses and Aaron did so; they did exactly as the Eternal ordered them. <verse eID="Exod.7.6"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.7.7" osisID="Exod.7.7"/> When they spoke to the Pharaoh, Moses was eighty years old, and Aaron
       eighty-three. <verse eID="Exod.7.7"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Exod.7.8" osisID="Exod.7.8"/>The Eternal told Moses and Aaron, <verse eID="Exod.7.8"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.7.9" osisID="Exod.7.9"/> <q>If the Pharaoh bids you work some miracle for your credit, then tell
       Aaron to throw his rod down in front of the Pharaoh, that it may turn into a reptile.</q> <verse eID="Exod.7.9"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.7.10" osisID="Exod.7.10"/> Moses and Aaron entered the presence of the Pharaoh and did as the
       Eternal ordered them; Aaron threw his rod down in front of the Pha­raoh and his officers, and it turned into a
       reptile. <verse eID="Exod.7.10"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.7.11" osisID="Exod.7.11"/> Whereupon the Pharaoh summoned sages and sorcerers, the ma­gicians of
       Egypt, and they by their clever tricks did the same; <verse eID="Exod.7.11"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.7.12" osisID="Exod.7.12"/> every man of them threw his rod down, and it turned into a reptile.
       Only, Aaron’s rod swallowed up their rods. <verse eID="Exod.7.12"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.7.13" osisID="Exod.7.13"/> But the Pharaoh was obdurate and would not listen to them, just as the
       Eternal had predicted. <verse eID="Exod.7.13"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <hi type="italic">
       <verse sID="Exod.7.14" osisID="Exod.7.14"/>The Eternal said to Moses, <q>The Pharaoh is stubborn, he refuses to let
        the people leave. <verse eID="Exod.7.14"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.7.15" osisID="Exod.7.15"/> [In the morning go to him, as he goes out to the waters; stand be­side
        the bank of the Nile to meet him, holding in your hand your stick which was turned into a snake.] <verse eID="Exod.7.15"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.7.16" osisID="Exod.7.16"/> Tell him that the Eternal, the God of the Hebrews, has sent you to him
        with orders to let my people go and worship me in the desert. <verse eID="Exod.7.16"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.7.17" osisID="Exod.7.17"/> Tell him this: <q>As yet you have not obeyed me. Therefore the Eternal
        declares, you shall find out that he is the Eternal by this, by me striking the stick in my hand upon the waters
        of the Nile, till they turn into blood, <verse eID="Exod.7.17"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.7.18" osisID="Exod.7.18"/> till the fish in the Nile die, and the Nile stinks, and the Egyptians
        have a weary search for water.</q></q> <verse eID="Exod.7.18"/>
      </hi>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Exod.7.19" osisID="Exod.7.19"/>The Eternal said to Moses, <q>Tell Aaron to stretch out his rod over the
       waters of Egypt, over their rivers, canals, reser­voirs, and ponds, till they all
       <milestone type="pb" n="68"/>
       turn into blood, till blood is everywhere in Egypt, even in bowls of wood and stone jars.</q> <verse eID="Exod.7.19"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.7.20" osisID="Exod.7.20"/> Moses and Aaron did as the Eternal ordered them; <verse eID="Exod.7.20"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.7.21" osisID="Exod.7.21"/> blood was everywhere in Egypt. <verse eID="Exod.7.21"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.7.22" osisID="Exod.7.22"/> But the magicians of Egypt did the same, by their clever tricks; and, as
       the Eternal had pre­dicted, the Pharaoh was ob­durate and would not listen to Moses and Aaron. <verse eID="Exod.7.22"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <hi type="italic">
       <verse sID="Exod.7.20" osisID="Exod.7.20"/>[Moses raised, the stick and struck the waters of the Nile in presence
        of the Pharaoh and his officers, and all the water in the river turned into blood.] <verse eID="Exod.7.20"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.7.21" osisID="Exod.7.21"/> The fish in the river died, the Nile itself stank, till the Egyptians
        could not drink its water. <verse eID="Exod.7.21"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.7.23" osisID="Exod.7.23"/> [The Pharaoh turned and went home; he did not heed even this.] <verse eID="Exod.7.23"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.7.24" osisID="Exod.7.24"/> The Egyptians had all to dig round the Nile for water to drink, as they
        could not drink the water of the river.
      </hi>
     </p>
     <p>
      <hi type="italic">
       Seven days passed after the Eternal had struck the Nile;
       <verse eID="Exod.7.24"/>
    <chapter eId="Exod.7"/>
    <chapter osisId="Exod.8" sId="Exod.8"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.8.1" osisID="Exod.8.1"/> then the Eternal told Moses to go to the Pharaoh with this message from
        the Eternal: <q>Let my people go and worship me. <verse eID="Exod.8.1"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.8.2" osisID="Exod.8.2"/> If you refuse to let them go, I will plague all your country with
        frogs; <verse eID="Exod.8.2"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.8.3" osisID="Exod.8.3"/> the Nile shall swarm with frogs, crawling up into your pal­ace, into
        your bedroom, into your bed, into the houses of your officers and your people, into ovens and kneading-bowls, <verse eID="Exod.8.3"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.8.4" osisID="Exod.8.4"/> all over you and your people and your officers.</q> <verse eID="Exod.8.4"/>
      </hi>
     </p>
     <p>
      <hi type="italic">
       <verse sID="Exod.8.8" osisID="Exod.8.8"/>Then the Pharaoh called Moses and Aaron, saying, <q>Be­seech the Eternal
        to take the frogs away from me and my people, and then I will let the people go, to sacrifice to the Eternal.</q> <verse eID="Exod.8.8"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.8.9" osisID="Exod.8.9"/> Moses said to the Pharaoh, <q>You may have the honour of saying when I
        am to beseech the Eternal for you and your officers and your people, that the frogs may be destroyed from you
        and your houses and confined to the Nile!</q> <verse eID="Exod.8.9"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.8.10" osisID="Exod.8.10"/> He said, <q>Ask it for to-morrow.</q> <q>As you please,</q> said
        Moses; <q>it will teach you that there is no one like the Eternal, our God. <verse eID="Exod.8.10"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.8.11" osisID="Exod.8.11"/> The frogs shall leave you and your houses, your officers and your
        people; they shall be confined to the Nile.</q> <verse eID="Exod.8.11"/>
      </hi>
     </p>
     <p>
      <hi type="italic">
       <verse sID="Exod.8.12" osisID="Exod.8.12"/>So Moses and Aaron left the Pharaoh. Moses implored the Eternal to
        remove the frogs as he had promised the Pharaoh, <verse eID="Exod.8.12"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.8.13" osisID="Exod.8.13"/> and the Eternal did as Moses asked; the frogs did die out of the
        houses, the courtyards, and the fields. <verse eID="Exod.8.13"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.8.14" osisID="Exod.8.14"/> They were piled up in heaps, till the land stank with them. <verse eID="Exod.8.14"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.8.15" osisID="Exod.8.15"/> But when the Pharaoh saw that relief had come, he stiffened himself. <verse eID="Exod.8.15"/>
      </hi>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Exod.8.5" osisID="Exod.8.5"/>The Eternal said to Moses, <q>Tell Aaron to stretch his rod out over the
       river, the canals, and the reservoirs, and make frogs swarm over the land of Egypt.</q> <verse eID="Exod.8.5"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.8.6" osisID="Exod.8.6"/> Aaron stretched his hand out over the waters of Egypt, till frogs
       crawled up and covered the land of Egypt. <verse eID="Exod.8.6"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.8.7" osisID="Exod.8.7"/> The magicians did the same, by their clever tricks, bringing frogs up
       over the land of Egypt. <verse eID="Exod.8.7"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.8.15" osisID="Exod.8.15"/> And the Pharaoh would not listen to Moses and Aaron, just as the
       Eternal had predicted. <verse eID="Exod.8.15"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Exod.8.16" osisID="Exod.8.16"/>The Eternal then said to Moses, <q>Tell Aaron to stretch his rod out
       and strike the dust on the ground, till it turns into mosquitoes all over the land of Egypt.</q> <verse eID="Exod.8.16"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.8.17" osisID="Exod.8.17"/> This was done; Aaron stretched his rod out and struck the dust on the
       ground, till it became mosquitoes, infesting men and beasts; all the dust on the ground throughout all the
       <milestone type="pb" n="69"/>
       land of Egypt became mosquitoes. <verse eID="Exod.8.17"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.8.18" osisID="Exod.8.18"/> The magicians also tried with their clever tricks to pro­duce
       mosquitoes, but they could not. The mosquitoes infested men and beasts, <verse eID="Exod.8.18"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.8.19" osisID="Exod.8.19"/> and the ma­gicians said to the Pharaoh, <q>This is the finger of God!</q>
       But, as the Eternal had predicted, the Pharaoh was obdurate and would not listen to Moses and Aaron.
      <verse eID="Exod.8.19"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <hi type="italic">
       <verse sID="Exod.8.20" osisID="Exod.8.20"/>The Eternal said to Moses, <q>Appear before the Pharaoh early in the
        morning, as he goes out to the waters, and tell him this from the Eternal: <q>Let my people go, to worship me. <verse eID="Exod.8.20"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.8.21" osisID="Exod.8.21"/> Otherwise, if you will not let my people go, I will send swarms of
        gnats on you and your officers and your people, inside your houses, till the houses of the Egyptians and the
        ground they tread on are covered with swarms of gnats.
       <verse eID="Exod.8.21"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.8.22" osisID="Exod.8.22"/> But I will then set apart the land of Goshen where my people are
        living, so that no swarms of gnats light there, in order to teach you that I am the Eternal on earth; <verse eID="Exod.8.22"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.8.23" osisID="Exod.8.23"/> I will make a difference between my people and your people. This
        portent shall occur to-morrow.</q></q> <verse eID="Exod.8.23"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.8.24" osisID="Exod.8.24"/> The Eternal did so. Sore swarms of gnats came into the palace of the
        Pharaoh and the houses of his officers and all the land of Egypt, till the whole land was ruined with gnats. <verse eID="Exod.8.24"/>
      </hi>
     </p>
     <p>
      <hi type="italic">
       <verse sID="Exod.8.25" osisID="Exod.8.25"/>The Pharaoh called Moses and Aaron, saying, <q>Go and sacrifice to
        your God within Egypt.</q> <verse eID="Exod.8.25"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.8.26" osisID="Exod.8.26"/> <q>No, indeed,</q> said Moses, <q>that would be wrong; we would have
        to sacrifice to the Eternal, our God, victims which are abominable to the Egyptians. Are we to sacrifice what
        the Egyptians abominate, under their very eyes, and be stoned for it? <verse eID="Exod.8.26"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.8.27" osisID="Exod.8.27"/> We will travel three days into the desert and sacrifice to the Eternal,
        our God, as he may command us.</q> <verse eID="Exod.8.27"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.8.28" osisID="Exod.8.28"/> The Pharaoh answered, <q>I will let you go, to sacrifice to the
        Eternal, your God, in the desert; only, you must not go very far. And beseech him for me.</q> <verse eID="Exod.8.28"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.8.29" osisID="Exod.8.29"/> Moses said, <q>I withdraw from your presence, and I will beseech the
        Eternal that the swarms of gnats may leave the Pharaoh and his officers and his people, to-morrow. Only, the
        Pharaoh must no longer play false by refusing to let the people go and sacrifice to the Eternal.</q>
       <verse eID="Exod.8.29"/>
      </hi>
     </p>
     <p>
      <hi type="italic">
       <verse sID="Exod.8.30" osisID="Exod.8.30"/>Then Moses withdrew from the Pharaoh and besought the Eternal. <verse eID="Exod.8.30"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.8.31" osisID="Exod.8.31"/> The Eternal did as Moses asked; he removed the swarms of gnats from
        the Pharaoh and his officers and his people, till not one remained. <verse eID="Exod.8.31"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.8.32" osisID="Exod.8.32"/> And once more the Pharaoh 32 stiffened himself and would not let the
        people go. <verse eID="Exod.8.32"/>
      </hi>
     </p>
    <chapter eId="Exod.8"/>
    <chapter osisId="Exod.9" sId="Exod.9"/>
     <p>
      <hi type="italic">
       <verse sID="Exod.9.1" osisID="Exod.9.1"/>The Eternal told Moses to go to the Pharaoh with this message from the
        Eternal, the God of theHebrews: <q>Let my people go, to worship me. <verse eID="Exod.9.1"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.9.2" osisID="Exod.9.2"/> If you refuse to let them go, if you detain them still, <verse eID="Exod.9.2"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.9.3" osisID="Exod.9.3"/> then the hand of the Eternal will fall on your live-stock in the fields,
        on horses, asses, camels, herds, and flocks, with a deadly pest. <verse eID="Exod.9.3"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.9.4" osisID="Exod.9.4"/> The Eternal will make a difference between the live-stock of Israel and
        the live­stock of Egypt; no beast belonging to the Israelites shall die.</q> <verse eID="Exod.9.4"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.9.5" osisID="Exod.9.5"/> The Eternal fixed the time for this; <q>To-morrow,</q> he said, <q>the
        Eternal will do this in the land.</q> <verse eID="Exod.9.5"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.9.6" osisID="Exod.9.6"/> Next day the Eternal did it; the live-stock of Egypt all died, but none
        of the live-stock of the Israelites died. <verse eID="Exod.9.6"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.9.7" osisID="Exod.9.7"/> The Pharaoh sent, only to find that not a single
        <milestone type="pb" n="70"/>
        animal belonging to the Israelites was dead. But the Pharaoh stiffened himself and would not let the people go.
       <verse eID="Exod.9.7"/>
      </hi>
     </p>
     <p>
       <verse sID="Exod.9.8" osisID="Exod.9.8"/>The Eternal then said to Moses and Aaron, <q>Take two handfuls of soot
        from a kiln, and let Moses toss it high in front of the Pharaoh. <verse eID="Exod.9.8"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.9.9" osisID="Exod.9.9"/> It shall turn into fine dust over all the land of Egypt, producing
        boils that break into blisters on man and beast throughout all Egypt.</q> <verse eID="Exod.9.9"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.9.10" osisID="Exod.9.10"/> They took some soot from a kiln and stood in front of the Pharaoh;
        then Moses tossed it high, and it turned into boils breaking into blisters on man and beast. <verse eID="Exod.9.10"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.9.11" osisID="Exod.9.11"/> The magicians could not hold their ground before Moses on account of
        the boils, for the boils attacked the magicians as well as all the Egyptians. <verse eID="Exod.9.11"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.9.12" osisID="Exod.9.12"/> But the Eternal made the Pharaoh stubborn, and he would not listen to
        Moses and Aaron, just as the Eternal had predicted to Moses. <verse eID="Exod.9.12"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <hi type="italic">
       <verse sID="Exod.9.13" osisID="Exod.9.13"/>The Eternal said to Moses, <q>Appear before the Pharaoh early in the
        morning and tell him this from the Eternal, the God of the Hebrews: <q>Let my people go, to worship me. <verse eID="Exod.9.13"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.9.14" osisID="Exod.9.14"/> For this time I will rain all these my strokes on you and your
        officers and your people, to teach you that there is no one like me in all the world. <verse eID="Exod.9.14"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.9.15" osisID="Exod.9.15"/> Otherwise, I would have exerted my force and struck you and your
        people with pestilence, till you were swept off the earth; <verse eID="Exod.9.15"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.9.16" osisID="Exod.9.16"/> but this is why I have kept you alive, to let you see my power and
        to publish my fame all over the world. <verse eID="Exod.9.16"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.9.17" osisID="Exod.9.17"/> You still thwart my people, refusing to let them go? <verse eID="Exod.9.17"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.9.18" osisID="Exod.9.18"/> About this time to-morrow I will rain down terrible hail, such as
        never has been seen since Egypt arose. <verse eID="Exod.9.18"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.9.19" osisID="Exod.9.19"/> 19  Send out and hurry in your live­stock and all you have in your
        fields, for the hail shall fall on every man and beast to be found out in the fields, left outside, and it will
        kill them.</q></q> <verse eID="Exod.9.19"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.9.20" osisID="Exod.9.20"/> Anyone of the Pharaoh’s officers who stood in awe of the Eternal’s
        word made his servants and live-stock hurry indoors; <verse eID="Exod.9.20"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.9.21" osisID="Exod.9.21"/> anyone who disregarded the word of the Eternal left his servants and
        live-stock in the fields. <verse eID="Exod.9.21"/>
      </hi>
      <verse sID="Exod.9.22" osisID="Exod.9.22"/> [The Eternal said to Moses, <q>Stretch your hand up to the sky, that
       hail may fall over all the land of Egypt, on man and beast and all things growing in the fields throughout all
       Egypt.</q> <verse eID="Exod.9.22"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.9.23" osisID="Exod.9.23"/> Moses stretched his stick to the sky, and the Eternal sent a
       thunderstorm, hail and lightning shooting down to the earth.] <verse eID="Exod.9.23"/>
      <hi type="italic">
       <verse sID="Exod.9.24" osisID="Exod.9.24"/> The Eternal rained hail on the land of Egypt[; there was hail, with 
        lightning flashing through it], most fearful hail, such as never had been in all Egypt ever since it was a
        nation[. <verse eID="Exod.9.24"/>
      </hi>
      <verse sID="Exod.9.25" osisID="Exod.9.25"/> The hail struck down everything in the fields throughout all the land
       of Egypt, both man and beast];
      <hi type="italic">
        the hail struck down all that grew in the fields and broke all the trees. <verse eID="Exod.9.25"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.9.26" osisID="Exod.9.26"/> Only in the land of Goshen, where the Israelites lived, there was no
        hail. <verse eID="Exod.9.26"/>
      </hi>
     </p>
     <p>
      <hi type="italic">
       <verse sID="Exod.9.27" osisID="Exod.9.27"/> Then the Pharaoh sent for Moses and Aaron. <q>I have sinned this
        time,</q> he said; <q>the Eternal is in the right, I and my people are in the wrong. <verse eID="Exod.9.27"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.9.28" osisID="Exod.9.28"/> Beseech the Eternal for me; we have had enough of all God’s thunder
        and hail; I will let you go, and you shall stay here no longer.</q> <verse eID="Exod.9.28"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.9.29" osisID="Exod.9.29"/> Moses said to him, <q>As soon as I leave the city, I will stretch my
        hands out in prayer to the Eternal; the thundering shall cease, and there shall be no more hail--to teach you
        that the earth belongs to the
        <milestone type="pb" n="71"/>
        Eternal. <verse eID="Exod.9.29"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.9.30" osisID="Exod.9.30"/> Though, as for you and your officers, I know you are not yet afraid
        of the Eternal.</q> <verse eID="Exod.9.30"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.9.31" osisID="Exod.9.31"/> (The flax and barley were ruined, for the barley was in ear and the
        flax was in bud; <verse eID="Exod.9.31"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.9.32" osisID="Exod.9.32"/> but the wheat and spelt were not ruined, for they grow later.) <verse eID="Exod.9.32"/>
      </hi>
     </p>
     <p>
      <hi type="italic">
       <verse sID="Exod.9.33" osisID="Exod.9.33"/>So Moses left the Pharaoh in the city and stretched his hands out in
        prayer to the Eternal; the thundering and the hail ceased, and the rain no longer poured on earth. <verse eID="Exod.9.33"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.9.34" osisID="Exod.9.34"/> When the Pharaoh saw that the rain and hail and thundering had ceased,
        he sinned again; he and his officers stiffened themselves. <verse eID="Exod.9.34"/>
      </hi>
      <verse sID="Exod.9.35" osisID="Exod.9.35"/> [The Pharaoh was obdurate; he would not let the Israelites go, as the
       Eternal had predicted through Moses.] <verse eID="Exod.9.35"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eId="Exod.9"/>
    <chapter osisId="Exod.10" sId="Exod.10"/>
     <p>
      <hi type="italic">
       <verse sID="Exod.10.1" osisID="Exod.10.1"/>The Eternal said to Moses, <q>Go to the Pharaoh; for I have made him and his
        officers stubborn, that I may work these portents among them, <verse eID="Exod.10.1"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.10.2" osisID="Exod.10.2"/> and that you may tell your sons and grandsons how I made fools of the Egyptians
        and worked my portents among them, to teach you that I am the Eternal.</q> <verse eID="Exod.10.2"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.10.3" osisID="Exod.10.3"/> So Moses and Aaron went in to the Pharaoh with this message from the Eternal,
        the God of the He­brews. <q>How long will you re­fuse to submit to me? Let my people go and worship me. <verse eID="Exod.10.3"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.10.4" osisID="Exod.10.4"/> Otherwise, if you refuse to let my people go, then to-morrow I will let locusts
        loose upon your land, <verse eID="Exod.10.4"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.10.5" osisID="Exod.10.5"/> covering the face of the country till the country cannot be seen for them; they
        shall eat up all that is left to you after the hail, devouring any tree you have in the field, <verse eID="Exod.10.5"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.10.6" osisID="Exod.10.6"/> filling your houses and the houses of all your officers and the houses of all
        the Egyptians, as neither your fathers nor your grandfathers have ever seen, since the day they were born.</q> Then he 
        turned and left the Pharaoh. <verse eID="Exod.10.6"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.10.7" osisID="Exod.10.7"/> The Pharaoh’s officers said to him, <q>How long is this fellow to endanger us?
        Let the men go and worship the Eternal. Do you not know by this time that Egypt is ruined?</q>
       <verse eID="Exod.10.7"/>
      </hi>
     </p>
     <p>
      <hi type="italic">
       <verse sID="Exod.10.8" osisID="Exod.10.8"/> So Moses and Aaron were brought back to the Pharaoh; he said to them, <q>Go and
        worship the Eternal, your God. But who are to go?</q> <verse eID="Exod.10.8"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.10.9" osisID="Exod.10.9"/> Moses answered, <q>We will take our young people and our old people, our sons
        and our daugh­ters; we will go with our flocks and herds, for we must celebrate the Eternal’s festival.</q> <verse eID="Exod.10.9"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.10.10" osisID="Exod.10.10"/> <q>Well,</q> said the Pharaoh, <q>may the Eternal be with you, if ever I let
        you and your little ones go! Let you go? Plainly you are out for some mischief. <verse eID="Exod.10.10"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.10.11" osisID="Exod.10.11"/> No, no! But your males may go and worship the Eternal, since that is what you
        want!</q> And with that they were driven out of the Pharaoh’s presence. <verse eID="Exod.10.11"/>
      </hi>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Exod.10.12" osisID="Exod.10.12"/>[The Eternal said to Moses, <q>Stretch your hand out over the land of Egypt, to
       bring the lo­custs over the land of Egypt eating up all the growth of the fields that the hail has left.</q> <verse eID="Exod.10.12"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.10.13" osisID="Exod.10.13"/> So Moses stretched his stick out over the land of Egypt,]
      <hi type="italic">
        and the Eternal swept an east wind over the land all that day and night; when morning came, the east wind brought the
        locusts,
       <verse eID="Exod.10.13"/>
      </hi>
      <verse sID="Exod.10.14" osisID="Exod.10.14"/>[and 14 the locusts swarmed all over Egypt,]
       <hi type="italic">
         dropping on all the country of Egypt, a terrible plague of locusts such as never had been before, such as never will be
         again;
        <verse eID="Exod.10.14"/>
        <verse sID="Exod.10.15" osisID="Exod.10.15"/> they covered the face of the whole land, till the country was black with them
       </hi>
       [; they ate up all the green growth of the fields and all the fruit left by the hail on the trees],
       <milestone type="pb" n="72"/>
       <hi type="italic">
        till not a green blade or leaf re­mained anywhere in the land of Egypt.
       </hi>
       <verse eID="Exod.10.15"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <hi type="italic">
       <verse sID="Exod.10.16" osisID="Exod.10.16"/>Then the Pharaoh called for Moses and Aaron in haste; <q>I have sinned against
        the Eternal your God and against you,</q> he said; <verse eID="Exod.10.16"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.10.17" osisID="Exod.10.17"/> <q>pray, pardon my sin only this once, and beseech the Eter­nal your God to
        remove for once this deadly pest</q> <verse eID="Exod.10.17"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.10.18" osisID="Exod.10.18"/> Moses left the Pharaoh and besought the Eternal; <verse eID="Exod.10.18"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.10.19" osisID="Exod.10.19"/> and the Eternal now made a furious west wind, which caught up the locusts and
        whirled them into the Reed Sea, till not a locust was left in the land of Egypt. <verse eID="Exod.10.19"/>
      </hi>
      <verse sID="Exod.10.20" osisID="Exod.10.20"/> [But the Eter­nal made the Pharaoh stubborn, and he would not let the Israel­ites
       go. <verse eID="Exod.10.20"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Exod.10.21" osisID="Exod.10.21"/>The Eternal then said to Moses, <q>Stretch your hand up to the sky, that
       darkness may fall on the land of Egypt, a darkness that may be felt.</q> <verse eID="Exod.10.21"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.10.22" osisID="Exod.10.22"/> So Moses stretched his hand up to the sky, and darkness was over all the land
       of Egypt for three days; <verse eID="Exod.10.22"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.10.23" osisID="Exod.10.23"/>
       no one could see another, and no one could move about for three days, although the Israelites
       enjoyed light in their dwellings; <verse eID="Exod.10.23"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.10.27" osisID="Exod.10.27"/> but the Eternal made the Pharaoh stubborn, and he would not let them go. <verse eID="Exod.10.27"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eId="Exod.10"/>
    <chapter osisId="Exod.4" sId="Exod.4"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Exod.4.22" osisID="Exod.4.22"/>Then the Eternal said to Moses, <q>Tell the Pharaoh this from the Eternal:
       <q>Israel is my son, my first-born son; <verse eID="Exod.4.22"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.4.23" osisID="Exod.4.23"/> I told you to let my son go, that he might worship me, and you have re­fused to
       let him go. So now I will slay your son, your first­born son.</q></q>]
      <verse eID="Exod.4.23"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eId="Exod.4"/>
    <chapter osisId="Exod.10" sId="Exod.10"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Exod.10.24" osisID="Exod.10.24"/>The Pharaoh then called for Moses and said, <q>Go and worship the Eternal; you
       may take your little ones, but let your flocks and herds stay, behind.</q> <verse eID="Exod.10.24"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.10.25" osisID="Exod.10.25"/> Moses answered, <q>You must let us have animals too for sacrifice and
       burnt-offerings, that we may sacrifice to the Eternal our God. <verse eID="Exod.10.25"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.10.26" osisID="Exod.10.26"/> And our live-stock must go with us; not a hoof is to be left behind, for we need
       them in order to worship the Eternal, our God. Till we reach the spot, we do not know with what animals we must worship the
       Eternal.</q> <verse eID="Exod.10.26"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.10.28" osisID="Exod.10.28"/> <q>Begone,</q> said the Pharaoh, <q>leave my presence and never enter it again;
       see to that. For the day you enter my presence, you die.</q> <verse eID="Exod.10.28"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.10.29" osisID="Exod.10.29"/> <q>A true word,</q> Moses answered; <q>never again will I enter your pres­ence.</q> <verse eID="Exod.10.29"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eId="Exod.10"/>
    <chapter osisId="Exod.11" sId="Exod.11"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Exod.11.1" osisID="Exod.11.1"/>[The Eternal then said to Moses, <q>One shock more will I let fall upon the
       Pharaoh and upon Egypt, and then he will let you leave; indeed, when he lets you go without any re­serve, he will push you
       out of the country. <verse eID="Exod.11.1"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.11.2" osisID="Exod.11.2"/> So make it known to the people that every man is to ask his neighbour, and every
       woman to ask her neighbour, for jewels of silver and jewels of gold.</q> <verse eID="Exod.11.2"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.11.3" osisID="Exod.11.3"/> The Eternal made the people in favour with the Egyptians; besides, Moses was a
       terrible person in the land of Egypt, in the opinion of the Pharaoh’s officers and of the people.] <verse eID="Exod.11.3"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <hi type="italic">
       <verse sID="Exod.11.4" osisID="Exod.11.4"/>Moses said, <q>The Eternal declares that he will pass through Egypt about
        midnight, <verse eID="Exod.11.4"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.11.5" osisID="Exod.11.5"/> when all the first-born in Egypt shall die, from the eldest son of the Pha­raoh
        on the throne to the eldest son of the slave-girl at the mill, with the first-born of all cattle; <verse eID="Exod.11.5"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.11.6" osisID="Exod.11.6"/> then shall a loud wail ring through all the land of Egypt, such as never has
        been heard, such as never will be heard again. <verse eID="Exod.11.6"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.11.7" osisID="Exod.11.7"/> But not even a dog shall bark against any of the
        <milestone type="pb" n="73"/>
        Israelites, against man or beast oj them—to teach you that the Eternal does make a difference between the Egyptians and
        Israel. <verse eID="Exod.11.7"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.11.8" osisID="Exod.11.8"/> And,</q> Moses added, <q>all these officers of yours shall come down to me and
        bow down to me, beg­ging me and all my followers to leave; then and then only will I leave the country.</q> And away he went
        from the Pharaoh’s presence in hot anger. <verse eID="Exod.11.8"/>
      </hi>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Exod.11.9" osisID="Exod.11.9"/>The Eternal said to Moses, <q>The Pharaoh will not listen to you--that my
       marvellous deeds may he multiplied in the land of Egypt.</q> <verse eID="Exod.11.9"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.11.10" osisID="Exod.11.10"/> So Moses and Aaron performed all these mar­vels in front of the Pharaoh; but
       the Eternal made the Pharaoh stubborn, and he would not let the Israelites go from his land. <verse eID="Exod.11.10"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eId="Exod.11"/>
    <chapter osisId="Exod.12" sId="Exod.12"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Exod.12.1" osisID="Exod.12.1"/>Then the Eternal said to Moses and Aaron in the land of Egypt, <verse eID="Exod.12.1"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.12.2" osisID="Exod.12.2"/> <q>This month shall be for you the first month in the year, the month
       when the year begins. <verse eID="Exod.12.2"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.12.3" osisID="Exod.12.3"/> Tell all the community of Israel that on the tenth day of this month
       they are each to take a lamb or kid, one lamb for every household; <verse eID="Exod.12.3"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.12.4" osisID="Exod.12.4"/> if any household is too small for a lamb, then the man and his next
       neighbour must take one between them, reckoning the lamb in proportion to what each member of the family can eat. <verse eID="Exod.12.4"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.12.5" osisID="Exod.12.5"/> The lamb must be a male year­ling, unblemished; it may be a lamb or a
       kid, <verse eID="Exod.12.5"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.12.6" osisID="Exod.12.6"/> but you must keep it till the fourteenth day of the month, when every
       member of the community of Israel shall kill it between sunset and dark. <verse eID="Exod.12.6"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.12.7" osisID="Exod.12.7"/> Then they must take some of the blood and smear it on the two
       door-posts and on the lintel of the house where it is eaten. <verse eID="Exod.12.7"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.12.8" osisID="Exod.12.8"/> That evening they must roast the flesh and eat it with unleavened
       cakes, also with some bitter herbs; <verse eID="Exod.12.8"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.12.9" osisID="Exod.12.9"/> it is not to be eaten raw or boiled in water, but roasted in the fire,
       head and legs and all. <verse eID="Exod.12.9"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.12.10" osisID="Exod.12.10"/> You must not leave any over till the morning; any part of it left
       over must be burned. <verse eID="Exod.12.10"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.12.11" osisID="Exod.12.11"/> And you must eat it with belt tight round your waist, sandals on
       your feet, and staff in hand; eat it in a hurry. For it is the Eternal’s passover;
      <verse eID="Exod.12.11"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.12.12" osisID="Exod.12.12"/> I will pass through the land of Egypt that night, striking down all
       the first-born in Egypt, man and beast alike, and dooming all the gods of Egypt; I am the Eternal. <verse eID="Exod.12.12"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.12.13" osisID="Exod.12.13"/> The blood shall mark the houses where you live, and when I see the
       blood I will pass over you, sparing you a deadly stroke, as I strike down the land of Egypt.</q> <verse eID="Exod.12.13"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.12.28" osisID="Exod.12.28"/> The Israelites went and did exactly as the Eternal had ordered Moses
       and Aaron. <verse eID="Exod.12.28"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <hi type="italic">
       <verse sID="Exod.12.21" osisID="Exod.12.21"/>Then Moses summoned all the sheikhs of Israel and said to them,
        <q>Select lambs or kids from the folds, family by family, and kill the passover victim. <verse eID="Exod.12.21"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.12.22" osisID="Exod.12.22"/> You must also take a bunch of mar­joram, dip it in the blood within
        the basin, and put some of the blood on the lintel and the two door-posts; then none of you must go out of the
        door of his house till next morning. <verse eID="Exod.12.22"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.12.23" osisID="Exod.12.23"/> For the Eternal will be passing through the land to strike down the
        Egyptians, and whenever he sees the blood on the lintel and on the two door-posts, the Eternal will pass over
        that door and not allow the destroying angel to enter your houses to strike you down. <verse eID="Exod.12.23"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.12.24" osisID="Exod.12.24"/> This rite you must keep as a standing order for yourselves and your
        descendants. <verse eID="Exod.12.24"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.12.25" osisID="Exod.12.25"/> And when you come to the land that the Eternal will give you, as he
        has promised, you must
        <milestone type="pb" n="74"/>
        keep up this worship; <verse eID="Exod.12.25"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.12.26" osisID="Exod.12.26"/> when your children ask you what this service of worship means, <verse eID="Exod.12.26"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.12.27" osisID="Exod.12.27"/> you must answer that it is the sacrifice of the Eternal’s passover,
        for he passed over the houses of the Israelites in Egypt when he was striking down the Egyptians; he kept our
        houses safe.</q> The people bowed their heads and worshipped. <verse eID="Exod.12.27"/>
      </hi>
     </p>
     <p>
      <hi type="italic">
       <verse sID="Exod.12.29" osisID="Exod.12.29"/>And at midnight the Eternal struck down all the first-born in the
        land of Egypt, from the eldest son of the Pharaoh on the throne to the eldest son of the prisoner in the dungeon,
        as well as the first-born of all the cattle. <verse eID="Exod.12.29"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.12.30" osisID="Exod.12.30"/> The Pharaoh started up in the night, he and all his officers and
        all the Egyptians; there was a loud wail in Egypt, for there was not a house where some one was not dead. <verse eID="Exod.12.30"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.12.31" osisID="Exod.12.31"/> He sent for Moses and Aaron during the night, and said, <q>Away
        with you from among my people, both you and the Israelites; go and worship the Eternal, as you have asked. <verse eID="Exod.12.31"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.12.32" osisID="Exod.12.32"/> Take both your flocks and your herds, as you demand, and, begone;
        and ask a blessing for me also.</q> <verse eID="Exod.12.32"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.12.33" osisID="Exod.12.33"/> The Egyptians pressed the people to hurry out of the land, crying,
        <q>We are all dead men!</q> <verse eID="Exod.12.33"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.12.34" osisID="Exod.12.34"/> So the people snatched up their dough, unleavened as it was, and
        wrapped their kneading-bowls inside their mantles, carrying them on their shoulders. <verse eID="Exod.12.34"/>
      </hi>
      <verse sID="Exod.12.35" osisID="Exod.12.35"/> [The Israelites had also done as Moses told them; they had asked the
       Egyptians for jewels of silver and jewels of gold and raiment, <verse eID="Exod.12.35"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.12.36" osisID="Exod.12.36"/> and the Eternal had given them such favour with the Egyptians that
       they let the people have what­ever they asked. They had thus taken toll of the Egyptians.] <verse eID="Exod.12.36"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <hi type="italic">
       <verse sID="Exod.12.37" osisID="Exod.12.37"/>From Ramses the Israelites moved to Sukkoth, about six hundred
        thousand of them on foot, besides women and children; <verse eID="Exod.12.37"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.12.38" osisID="Exod.12.38"/> a motley mob accompanied them, and large numbers of live­stock both
        flocks and herds. <verse eID="Exod.12.38"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.12.39" osisID="Exod.12.39"/> They baked unleavened pancakes of the dough they had brought from
        Egypt, for the dough was unleavened; they had been pushed out of Egypt and could not wait,
      </hi>
       nor had they pre­pared any food for the journey. 
      <verse eID="Exod.12.39"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.12.40" osisID="Exod.12.40"/> (The time spent by the Israelites in Egypt was four hundred and
       thirty years; <verse eID="Exod.12.40"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.12.41" osisID="Exod.12.41"/> and at the end of the four hundred and thirty years it was on that
       very day that all the array of the Eternal left Egypt. <verse eID="Exod.12.41"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.12.42" osisID="Exod.12.42"/> It was a night when the Eternal was on the watch to bring them out
       of Egypt, a night when all Israelites must keep watch for the Eternal, age after age.) <verse eID="Exod.12.42"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Exod.12.43" osisID="Exod.12.43"/>The Eternal said to Moses and Aaron, <q>This is the order for the
       passover; no foreigner is to partake of it, <verse eID="Exod.12.43"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.12.44" osisID="Exod.12.44"/> but any slave, bought for money, may partake of it, if he has been
       circumcised; <verse eID="Exod.12.44"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.12.45" osisID="Exod.12.45"/> no alien or hired servant is to partake of it. <verse eID="Exod.12.45"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.12.46" osisID="Exod.12.46"/> It must be eaten in one house; you must not carry any of the flesh
       outside the house. Nor must you break any bone of the victim. <verse eID="Exod.12.46"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.12.47" osisID="Exod.12.47"/> And all the community of Israel must keep this feast. <verse eID="Exod.12.47"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.12.48" osisID="Exod.12.48"/> When a resident alien who is with you desires to keep the Eternal’s
       passover, all the male members of his household must be first circumcised; then he may draw near to keep the
       passover, he shall count as a native; but no uncircumcised person shall partake of it. <verse eID="Exod.12.48"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.12.49" osisID="Exod.12.49"/> There shall be one and the same law for the native and for the
       resident alien. <verse eID="Exod.12.49"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.12.14" osisID="Exod.12.14"/> And this day shall he a memorial day for you, to be kept as a
       festival for
       <milestone type="pb" n="75"/>
       the Eternal; age after age you must keep this as a standing festival. <verse eID="Exod.12.14"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.12.15" osisID="Exod.12.15"/> For seven days you must eat un­leavened cakes; on the first day you
       must be sure to clean all dough out of your houses, for anyone who eats a leavened cake between the first day and
       the seventh day shall be outlawed from Israel. <verse eID="Exod.12.15"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.12.16" osisID="Exod.12.16"/> On the first day you must hold a sacred gathering, and on the
       seventh day a sacred gathering; you shall do no business on these days, no work except in preparing the food that
       everyone needs. <verse eID="Exod.12.16"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.12.17" osisID="Exod.12.17"/> You must keep this custom of unleavened cakes, for on that very day
       I brought all your array out of the land of Egypt; that is why you must keep this day, age after age, as a
       standing order. <verse eID="Exod.12.17"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.12.18" osisID="Exod.12.18"/> On the evening of the fourteenth day of the first month you shall eat
       unleavened cakes, and so on till the evening of the twenty-first day; <verse eID="Exod.12.18"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.12.19" osisID="Exod.12.19"/> for these seven days no dough must be found inside your houses, for
       anyone eating anything leavened shall be outlawed from the community of Israel, whether he is a resident alien or
       a native. <verse eID="Exod.12.19"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.12.20" osisID="Exod.12.20"/> You must not eat anything leavened; eat unleavened cakes in every
       household.</q> <verse eID="Exod.12.20"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Exod.12.50" osisID="Exod.12.50"/>The Israelites all did so; they did exactly as the Eternal had
       ordered Moses and Aaron. <verse eID="Exod.12.50"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.12.51" osisID="Exod.12.51"/> And on that very day the Eternal brought the Israelites in their
       array out of the land of Egypt. <verse eID="Exod.12.51"/>
    <chapter eId="Exod.12"/>
    <chapter osisId="Exod.13" sId="Exod.13"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.13.1" osisID="Exod.13.1"/> Then said the Eternal to Moses, <verse eID="Exod.13.1"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.13.2" osisID="Exod.13.2"/> <q>Consecrate all the first-born to me, whatever is the first to open
       the womb in Israel, human or animal, for it belongs to me.</q> <verse eID="Exod.13.2"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <hi type="italic">
       <verse sID="Exod.13.3" osisID="Exod.13.3"/>Moses said to the people, <q>Re­member this day, when you left Egypt, that
        slave-pen; for by sheer strength the Eternal brought you out of this place; no leavened cakes are to be eaten <verse eID="Exod.13.3"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.13.4" osisID="Exod.13.4"/> on this day of the month Abib, <verse eID="Exod.13.4"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.13.5" osisID="Exod.13.5"/> when you leave. And when the Eternal brings you to the land of the Canaanites,
        the Hittites, the Amorites, the Hivites, and the Jebusites, which he swore to your fathers he would give you, a land
        abounding in milk and honey, then you must hold this service in this month: <verse eID="Exod.13.5"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.13.6" osisID="Exod.13.6"/> for seven days you must eat unleavened cakes, and hold a festi­val for the
        Eternal on the sev­enth day; <verse eID="Exod.13.6"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.13.7" osisID="Exod.13.7"/> during all the seven days unleavened cakes must be eaten, no leavened cakes
        must be seen among you, and no dough at all, throughout your country. <verse eID="Exod.13.7"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.13.8" osisID="Exod.13.8"/> And you must each tell your son on that day that this is on account of what
        the Eternal did for you when you left Egypt. <verse eID="Exod.13.8"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.13.9" osisID="Exod.13.9"/> It shall serve you as a mark on the hand or a badge between your eyes, that
        the law of the Eternal may be ever on your lips; for by sheer strength the Eternal has brought you out of Egypt. <verse eID="Exod.13.9"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.13.10" osisID="Exod.13.10"/> So keep this customary rite in its due season, year by year. <verse eID="Exod.13.10"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.13.11" osisID="Exod.13.11"/> And when the Eternal brings you into the Canaanite land, and gives it to
        you, as he swore to you and to your fathers, <verse eID="Exod.13.11"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.13.12" osisID="Exod.13.12"/> you shall make over to the Eternal whatever is the first to open the womb,
        and every firstling animal; these males shall belong to the Eter­nal. <verse eID="Exod.13.12"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.13.13" osisID="Exod.13.13"/> You may buy back a firstling ass with a lamb or a kid, but if you do not
        choose to buy it back, you must break its neck. Any first-born boy you must buy back. <verse eID="Exod.13.13"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.13.14" osisID="Exod.13.14"/> And when your son asks any of you in after days what this means, you must
        tell him: <q>By sheer strength the Eternal
        <milestone type="pb" n="76"/>
        brought us out of Egypt, that slave-pen, <verse eID="Exod.13.14"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.13.15" osisID="Exod.13.15"/> and when the Pharaoh made difficulties about letting us go, the Eternal
        killed all the first­born in the land of Egypt, both of man and of beast; that is why I sacrifice to the Eternal any male
        animal that opens the womb, though I buy back a firstborn son.</q>
       <verse eID="Exod.13.15"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.13.16" osisID="Exod.13.16"/> This shall serve you as a mark on the hand or a me­mento bound between the
        eyes, for by sheer strength the Eternal has brought us out of Egypt.</q> <verse eID="Exod.13.16"/>
      </hi>
      <verse sID="Exod.13.17" osisID="Exod.13.17"/>[Now when the Pharaoh let the people go, God did not lead them along the road
       to the land of the Philistines, although that lay close at hand, for God thought that perhaps the people might have
       regrets and return to Egypt, if they had to fight their way; <verse eID="Exod.13.17"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.13.18" osisID="Exod.13.18"/> so God led the people by a roundabout road in the direc­tion of the desert,
       towards the Reed Sea. <verse eID="Exod.13.18"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Exod.13.17" osisID="Exod.13.17"/>[Now when the Pharaoh let the people go, God did not lead them along the road
       to the land of the Philistines, although that lay close at hand, for God thought that perhaps the people might have
       regrets and return to Egypt, if they had to fight their way; <verse eID="Exod.13.17"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.13.18" osisID="Exod.13.18"/> so God led the people by a roundabout road in the direc­tion of the desert,
       towards the Reed Sea. <verse eID="Exod.13.18"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Exod.13.19" osisID="Exod.13.19"/>The Israelites left Egypt in orderly array. And Moses took the bones of
       Joseph; for Joseph had made the Israelites swear they would do this, saying, <q>God will be sure to remember you,
       and you must carry my bones away with you.</q>] <verse eID="Exod.13.19"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Exod.13.20" osisID="Exod.13.20"/> Moving from Sukkoth, they camped at Etham on the edge of the desert. The <verse eID="Exod.13.20"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.13.21" osisID="Exod.13.21"/> Eternal went in front of them, in a column of cloud, to lead them by day,
       and in a column of fire, to light them through the night, so that they might travel both by day and by night; <verse eID="Exod.13.21"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.13.22" osisID="Exod.13.22"/> the column of cloud by day and the column of fire by night never ceased to
       go in front of the people. <verse eID="Exod.13.22"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eId="Exod.13"/>
    <chapter osisId="Exod.14" sId="Exod.14"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Exod.14.1" osisID="Exod.14.1"/>Then the Eternal told Moses <verse eID="Exod.14.1"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.14.2" osisID="Exod.14.2"/> to order the Israel­ites to wheel round and camp in front of Pihahiroth
       between Migdol and the sea, in front of Baal-zephon, opposite which they were to camp beside the sea. <verse eID="Exod.14.2"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.14.3" osisID="Exod.14.3"/> For <q>the Pharaoh,</q> he said, <q>will think that the Israelites are
       bewildered, caught by the desert; <verse eID="Exod.14.3"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.14.4" osisID="Exod.14.4"/> I will make the Pharaoh stubborn, till he pursues them, and I will gain honour
       out of the Pharaoh and all his army, to teach the Egyptians that I am the Eternal.</q> They did so.
      <verse eID="Exod.14.4"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.14.8" osisID="Exod.14.8"/> And the Eternal made the Pharaoh stubborn, so that he chased the Israelites,
       who were marching away quite confi­dently; <verse eID="Exod.14.8"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.14.9" osisID="Exod.14.9"/> the Egyptians chased them and came up on them as they lay camped on the
       sea-coast beside Pihahiroth, in front of Baal-zephon. <verse eID="Exod.14.9"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <hi type="italic">
       <verse sID="Exod.14.5" osisID="Exod.14.5"/>When the king of Egypt was told that the people had fled, the Pharaoh and his
        officers changed their minds about the people. <q>Whatever have we done,</q> they said, <q>in letting the Israelites
        leave our service?</q> <verse eID="Exod.14.5"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.14.6" osisID="Exod.14.6"/> So the Pharaoh got his chariots ready and took his men with him, <verse eID="Exod.14.6"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.14.7" osisID="Exod.14.7"/> six hundred picked chariots and all the rest of the chariots of Egypt, manned
        by their captains. <verse eID="Exod.14.7"/>
      </hi>
     </p>
     <p>
      <hi type="italic">
       <verse sID="Exod.14.10" osisID="Exod.14.10"/>When the Pharaoh approached, the Israelites looked up, and there were the
        Egyptians after them! They were terribly afraid. They cried to the Eter­nal. <verse eID="Exod.14.10"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.14.11" osisID="Exod.14.11"/> And they said to Moses, <q>Was it because there were no graves in Egypt
        that you have brought us to die in the desert? Why have you misguided us by bringing us out of Egypt? <verse eID="Exod.14.11"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.14.12" osisID="Exod.14.12"/> Did we not tell you in Egypt to let us alone and let us serve the
        Egyp­tians? Better serve the Egyp­tians than die in the desert!</q> <verse eID="Exod.14.12"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.14.13" osisID="Exod.14.13"/> Moses said to the people, <q>Have no fear, stand firm and watch how the
        Eternal will deliver you to-day; for as surely as you see
        <milestone type="pb" n="77"/>
        the Egyptians to-day, you shall never see them again. <verse eID="Exod.14.13"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.14.14" osisID="Exod.14.14"/> The Eter­nal will fight for you, and you have only to keep still.</q> <verse eID="Exod.14.14"/>
      </hi>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Exod.14.15" osisID="Exod.14.15"/>The Eternal said to Moses, <q>Why cry to me? Tell the Israelites to march
       forward. <verse eID="Exod.14.15"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.14.16" osisID="Exod.14.16"/> And as for you, [raise your stick and] stretch your hand over the sea; part
       it in two, that the Israelites may march on dry ground through the sea. <verse eID="Exod.14.16"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.14.17" osisID="Exod.14.17"/> I am going to make the Egyptians so stubborn that they will pass in after
       them, and I will gain hon­our out of the Pharaoh and all his army, his chariots and cavalry-- <verse eID="Exod.14.17"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.14.18" osisID="Exod.14.18"/> to teach the Egyptians that I am the Eternal, when I gain honour out of the
       Pharaoh and his chariots and his cavalry.</q> <verse eID="Exod.14.18"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Exod.14.19" osisID="Exod.14.19"/>[Then the angel of God in front of the army of Israel moved to their rear
       <hi type="italic">
        (the column of cloud moved from before them to behind them), <verse eID="Exod.14.19"/>
       </hi>
      <verse sID="Exod.14.20" osisID="Exod.14.20"/> and went be­tween the army of Egypt and the army of Israel. When it was dark,
       the cloud lit up the night, so that the one army did not come near the other all night.] <verse eID="Exod.14.20"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Exod.14.21" osisID="Exod.14.21"/>Moses stretched his hand out over the sea; the waters parted, <verse eID="Exod.14.21"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.14.22" osisID="Exod.14.22"/> and the Israelites marched through the sea on dry ground, the waters forming
       a wall to right and left. <verse eID="Exod.14.22"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.14.23" osisID="Exod.14.23"/> The Egyptians in pursuit of them went into the sea, all the Pharaoh’s horses
       and chariots and cavalry. <verse eID="Exod.14.23"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.14.26" osisID="Exod.14.26"/> Then said the Eternal to Moses, <q>Stretch your hand out over the sea, to
       make the waters flow back upon the chariots and cavalry of the Egyptians.</q> <verse eID="Exod.14.26"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.14.27" osisID="Exod.14.27"/> Moses stretched his hand out over the sea; the waters did flow back over the
       chariots and cavalry, over the whole army of the Pha­raoh which had followed them into the sea, <verse eID="Exod.14.27"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.14.28" osisID="Exod.14.28"/> till not a single one of them was left. <verse eID="Exod.14.28"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.14.29" osisID="Exod.14.29"/> But the Israelites walked through the sea on dry ground, the waters forming
       a wall to right and left. <verse eID="Exod.14.29"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <hi type="italic">
       <verse sID="Exod.14.21" osisID="Exod.14.21"/>[Then the Eternal swept the sea along by a strong east wind, all night, till
        the bed of the sea was dry. <verse eID="Exod.14.21"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.14.24" osisID="Exod.14.24"/> And in the watch before the dawn the Eternal looked out from the column of
        fire and cloud on the Egyptian army and threw them into a panic; <verse eID="Exod.14.24"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.14.25" osisID="Exod.14.25"/> he clogged their chariot-wheels till they drove heavily. The Egyp­tians
        cried, <q>Let us flee from the Israelites! The Eternal is fight­ing for them against the Egyp­tians!</q> <verse eID="Exod.14.25"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.14.27" osisID="Exod.14.27"/> Then, as morning broke, the sea returned to its wonted flow, and while the
        Egyptians were fleeing against it, the Eter­nal overwhelmed the Egyptians in the middle of the sea.] <verse eID="Exod.14.27"/>
      </hi>
     </p>
     <p>
      <hi type="italic">
       <verse sID="Exod.14.30" osisID="Exod.14.30"/>Thus did the Eternal save Israel that day from the Egyp­tians, till Israel
        saw the Egyp­tians lying dead on the sea-shore; <verse eID="Exod.14.30"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.14.31" osisID="Exod.14.31"/> Israel saw the mighty action of the Eternal against the Egyp­tians, and the
        people stood in awe of the Eternal, believing in the Eternal and in his servant Moses. <verse eID="Exod.14.31"/>
      </hi>
     </p>
    <chapter eId="Exod.14"/>
    <chapter osisId="Exod.15" sId="Exod.15"/>
     <p>
      <hi type="italic">
       <verse sID="Exod.15.1" osisID="Exod.15.1"/>Then Moses and the Israelites sang this song to the Eternal:
        <lg>
         <l> I will sing to the Eternal, for he rose up in his might, </l>
         <l> hurling horse and chariot into the sea. </l>
        </lg>
       <verse eID="Exod.15.1"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.15.2" osisID="Exod.15.2"/>
        <lg>
         <l> My song is of the Eternal; he is my strength, </l>
         <l> and he has brought me victory; </l>
         <l> this is my God, I will thank him, </l>
         <l> my father’s God, I will exalt him. </l>
        </lg>
       <verse eID="Exod.15.2"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.15.3" osisID="Exod.15.3"/>
        <lg>
         <l> The Eternal knows well how to fight--</l>
         <l> the Eternal is his name--</l>
        </lg>
       <verse eID="Exod.15.3"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.15.4" osisID="Exod.15.4"/>
        <lg>
         <l> flinging the Pharaoh’s chariots </l>
         <l> and his army into the sea,</l>
         <milestone type="pb" n="78"/>
         <l> swamping his picked captains in the Reed Sea; </l>
        </lg>
       <verse eID="Exod.15.4"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.15.5" osisID="Exod.15.5"/>
        <lg>
         <l> the depths did cover them, </l>
         <l> they sank down like a stone. </l>
        </lg>
       <verse eID="Exod.15.5"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.15.6" osisID="Exod.15.6"/>
        <lg>
         <l> 'Twas thy right hand, O Eternal, glorious in power,</l>
         <l> ’twas thy right hand that shattered the foe;</l>
        </lg>
       <verse eID="Exod.15.6"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.15.7" osisID="Exod.15.7"/>
        <lg>
         <l> in thy great majesty thou didst crush the rebels, </l>
         <l> thou didst speed thy fury to burn them up like straw. </l>
        </lg>
       <verse eID="Exod.15.7"/>
      </hi>
     </p>
     <p>
      <hi type="italic">
       <verse sID="Exod.15.8" osisID="Exod.15.8"/>
        <lg>
         <l> At thy blast the waters piled up,</l>
         <l>the tides were dammed, </l>
         <l> the depths turned hard in the heart of the sea. </l>
        </lg>
       <verse eID="Exod.15.8"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.15.9" osisID="Exod.15.9"/>
        <lg><q>
         <l>I will chase them, said the foe, </l>
         <l>I will catch them and divide their spoil,</l>
         <l> I will take my will of them, </l>
         <l> I will unsheath my sword and destroy them! </l>
        </q> </lg>
       <verse eID="Exod.15.9"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.15.10" osisID="Exod.15.10"/>
        <lg>
         <l> Thou didst blow thy blast, and the sea covered them, </l>
         <l> like lead they sank into the mighty deep! </l>
        </lg>
       <verse eID="Exod.15.10"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.15.11" osisID="Exod.15.11"/>
        <lg>
         <l> O Eternal, what god is there like thee, </l>
         <l> who is like thee, so gloriously supreme, </l>
         <l> so awful, whom we praise for signal deeds? </l>
        </lg>
       <verse eID="Exod.15.11"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.15.12" osisID="Exod.15.12"/>
        <lg>
         <l> Thou didst stretch thy right hand out, </l>
         <l> and they were swallowed up; </l>
        </lg>
       <verse eID="Exod.15.12"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.15.13" osisID="Exod.15.13"/>
        <lg>
         <l> thou in love didst lead thy ransomed people, </l>
         <l> guiding them by thy power to thine own sacred abode. </l>
        </lg>
       <verse eID="Exod.15.13"/>
      </hi>
     </p>
     <p>
      <hi type="italic">
       <verse sID="Exod.15.14" osisID="Exod.15.14"/>
        <lg>
         <l> Nations heard of it and trembled, </l>
         <l> pangs seized on Philistia’s folk, </l>
        </lg>
       <verse eID="Exod.15.14"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.15.15" osisID="Exod.15.15"/>
        <lg>
         <l> the chiefs of Edom were in agony, </l>
         <l> a shudder seized the lords of Moab, </l>
         <l> the folk of Canaan fainted all for fear-- </l>
        </lg>
       <verse eID="Exod.15.15"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.15.16" osisID="Exod.15.16"/>
        <lg>
         <l> terror and dread fell on them, </l>
         <l> they stood motionless under the sweep of thine arm, </l>
         <l> till thy folk went through, O Eternal, </l>
         <l> till the folk thou hadst won passed through them. </l>
        </lg>
       <verse eID="Exod.15.16"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.15.17" osisID="Exod.15.17"/>
        <lg>
         <l> Thou didst bring thy folk in, </l>
         <l> settling them on thine own hills, </l>
         <l> at the shrine thou hast made for thyself, O Eternal, </l>
         <l> the sanctuary thou hast formed, O Eternal. </l>
        </lg>
       <verse eID="Exod.15.17"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.15.18" osisID="Exod.15.18"/> The Eternal reigns for evermore! <verse eID="Exod.15.18"/>
      </hi>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Exod.15.19" osisID="Exod.15.19"/>[[For the horses of the Pharaoh with his chariots and his cavalry
       entered the sea, and the Eternal made the sea flow back on them, while the Israelites went through the sea on
       dry land.]] <verse eID="Exod.15.19"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Exod.15.20" osisID="Exod.15.20"/> [Then the prophetess Miriam, Aaron’s sister, tambourine in hand,
       went outside the camp, followed by all the women dancing to their tambourines, <verse eID="Exod.15.20"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.15.21" osisID="Exod.15.21"/> while Miriam led them in the song:
       <lg>
        <l> Sing to the Eternal, for he rose up in his might, </l>
        <l> hurling horse and chariot into the sea. </l>
       </lg>
      <verse eID="Exod.15.21"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Exod.15.22" osisID="Exod.15.22"/> From the Reed Sea Moses led Israel forward into the desert of Shur,
       and after marching for three days into the desert they found no water. <verse eID="Exod.15.22"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.15.23" osisID="Exod.15.23"/> When they reached Marah, they could not drink the water there, it
       was so marred and bitter (hence its name was <q>Marah</q>). <verse eID="Exod.15.23"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.15.24" osisID="Exod.15.24"/> The people grumbled against Moses, crying, <q>What are we to drink?</q> <verse eID="Exod.15.24"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.15.25" osisID="Exod.15.25"/> He appealed to the Eternal, who showed him a tree, which he threw
       into the water, and then the water became fresh. He made a certain rule and rite for them there; he put them to
       the test there, <verse eID="Exod.15.25"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.15.26" osisID="Exod.15.26"/> saying, <q>If you will listen carefully to the voice of the Eternal,
       your God, and do what is right in his eyes and pay heed to his commands and fol­low all his rules, then the
       Eternal promises never to inflict upon you any of the diseases he inflicted on the Egyptians; for he is the
       Eternal who heals you.</q> <verse eID="Exod.15.26"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Exod.15.27" osisID="Exod.15.27"/>They came to Elim, where there were twelve springs of
       <milestone type="pb" n="79"/>
       water and seventy palm trees; there they camped beside the springs.] <verse eID="Exod.15.27"/>
    <chapter eId="Exod.15"/>
    <chapter osisId="Exod.16" sId="Exod.16"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.16.1" osisID="Exod.16.1"/> Marching from Elim, the community of the Israelites all came to the desert
       of Sin between Elim and Sinai, on the fifteenth day of the second month after they left Egypt. <verse eID="Exod.16.1"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.16.2" osisID="Exod.16.2"/> The community of the Israelites all grumbled against Moses and Aaron in the
       desert, <verse eID="Exod.16.2"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.16.3" osisID="Exod.16.3"/> crying, <q>Would that we had died by the hand of the Eternal in the land of
       Egypt, where we could sit beside pots of flesh, where we had plenty to eat! Here you have brought us into the desert,
       to starve the whole people to death!</q> <verse eID="Exod.16.3"/>
      <hi type="italic">
       <verse sID="Exod.16.4" osisID="Exod.16.4"/> Then said the Eternal to Moses, <q>I will shower food out of the sky for
        you, and the people must go out and gather their daily rations every day; this is to test them, to see if they will
        follow my directions or not. <verse eID="Exod.16.4"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.16.5" osisID="Exod.16.5"/> Every sixth day they shall find that when they cook what they bring in, it
        is twice as much as usual.</q> <verse eID="Exod.16.5"/>
      </hi>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Exod.16.9" osisID="Exod.16.9"/>Moses told Aaron to order all the community of Israel to ap­proach the
       presence of the Eter­nal, since the Eternal had heard them grumbling. <verse eID="Exod.16.9"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.16.10" osisID="Exod.16.10"/> When Aaron said this to all the community of Israel, they looked in the
       direc­tion of the sanctuary, and there was the Eternal manifest in radiance within the cloud! <verse eID="Exod.16.10"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.16.11" osisID="Exod.16.11"/> The Eternal said to Moses, <verse eID="Exod.16.11"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.16.12" osisID="Exod.16.12"/> <q>I have heard the Israelites grumbling; tell them that between sunset
       and dusk they shall have flesh and also plenty of food in the morning—to teach them that I am the Eternal their God.</q>
      <verse eID="Exod.16.12"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.16.6" osisID="Exod.16.6"/> So Moses and Aaron told all the Israelites, <q>In the evening you shall find
       that it was the Eternal who brought you out of the land of Egypt, <verse eID="Exod.16.6"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.16.7" osisID="Exod.16.7"/> and in the morning you shall see the Eternal mani­fested in might, since he
       has heard you grumbling against himself (for we do not count— why grumble against us?) <verse eID="Exod.16.7"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.16.8" osisID="Exod.16.8"/> [[When the Eternal gives you flesh in the evening and plenty to eat in the
       morning, then you will know that he has heard you grumbling against himself; for we do not count, it is against the
       Eternal, not against us, that you are grumbling!]]</q>
      <verse eID="Exod.16.8"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Exod.16.13" osisID="Exod.16.13"/>In the evening quails flew up and dropped all over the camp, and in the
       morning there was a fall of dew round the camp; <verse eID="Exod.16.13"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.16.14" osisID="Exod.16.14"/> when the dew evaporated, there, on the surface of the ground, lay thin
       flakes, as tiny as hoar-frost! <verse eID="Exod.16.14"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.16.15" osisID="Exod.16.15"/> When the Israelites saw it, they said to one another, <q>What is it?</q>
       --for they did not know what it was. <q>That,</q> said Moses, <q>is the food the Eternal gives to you. <verse eID="Exod.16.15"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.16.16" osisID="Exod.16.16"/> That is what the Eternal orders each of you to gather, as much as you can
       eat, about seven pints a head, for every person in your house­holds.</q> <verse eID="Exod.16.16"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.16.17" osisID="Exod.16.17"/> The Israelites did so; 17 they gathered it, some more, some less. <verse eID="Exod.16.17"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.16.18" osisID="Exod.16.18"/> When they measured it in a pint-measure, they found that he who had
       gathered much had not too much, and he who had gathered little had not too little; each man had gathered the exact
       quantity he required. <verse eID="Exod.16.18"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.16.19" osisID="Exod.16.19"/> Moses told them that no one was to leave any of it over till next morning.<verse eID="Exod.16.19"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.16.20" osisID="Exod.16.20"/> In spite of this, they would not listen to Moses; some did leave a little
       of it over till next morning, but it bred worms and stank. Which made Moses angry with them. <verse eID="Exod.16.20"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.16.21" osisID="Exod.16.21"/> Morning by morning they gathered the food, and whenever the sun grew hot
       it melted. <verse eID="Exod.16.21"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.16.22" osisID="Exod.16.22"/> On the sixth day they gathered twice as
       <milestone type="pb" n="80"/>
       much as usual, fourteen pints a head; and when all the authorities reported this to Moses, <verse eID="Exod.16.22"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.16.23" osisID="Exod.16.23"/> he said to them, <q>This is what the Eternal means; to-morrow is to be a
       day of complete rest, a sab­bath sacred to the Eternal; so bake or boil to-day as you please, and keep what is left over
       till to-morrow morning.</q> <verse eID="Exod.16.23"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.16.24" osisID="Exod.16.24"/>They kept it over, as Moses told them, till next morning, and it did not
       stink, it bred no worms. <verse eID="Exod.16.24"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.16.25" osisID="Exod.16.25"/> Then said Moses, <q>Eat this to-day, for to-day is a sab­bath for the
       Eternal; you will not find any of the food in the fields to-day. <verse eID="Exod.16.25"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.16.26" osisID="Exod.16.26"/> Gather it for six days, but on the seventh day, on the sabbath, there
       shall be none.</q> <verse eID="Exod.16.26"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.16.27" osisID="Exod.16.27"/> And on the seventh day, when some of the people did go out to gather it,
       they found none. <verse eID="Exod.16.27"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.16.28" osisID="Exod.16.28"/> The Eternal then said to Moses, <q>How long will you people refuse to obey
       my orders and rules? <verse eID="Exod.16.28"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.16.29" osisID="Exod.16.29"/> Mark this: since the Eternal gives you the sabbath, he also gives you on
       the sixth day food enough for two days; stay where you are, every man of you, and never make a movement on the seventh
       day.</q> <verse eID="Exod.16.29"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.16.30" osisID="Exod.16.30"/>So the people desisted from work on the seventh day. <verse eID="Exod.16.30"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Exod.16.31" osisID="Exod.16.31"/> The house of Israel called this food Manna (what-is); it was as white as
       coriander seed and tasted like wafers made with honey. <verse eID="Exod.16.31"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.16.32" osisID="Exod.16.32"/> Moses said, <q>This is what the Eternal has ordered you to keep seven pints
       of, age after age, that your descendants may see the food with which he fed you in the desert when he brought you out of
       the land of Egypt.</q> <verse eID="Exod.16.32"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.16.33" osisID="Exod.16.33"/> Then said Moses to Aaron, <q>Put seven pints of it in a jar and place it
       before the Eternal, to keep it for age after age.</q> <verse eID="Exod.16.33"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.16.34" osisID="Exod.16.34"/> As the Eternal ordered Moses, so Aaron placed it in front of the ark of the
       Presence, to be kept there. <verse eID="Exod.16.34"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.16.35" osisID="Exod.16.35"/> For forty years the Israelites ate manna, till they reached a cultivated
       land; they ate manna till they reached the frontier of the land of Canaan. <verse eID="Exod.16.35"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.16.36" osisID="Exod.16.36"/> (Seven pints or an <q>omer</q> is the tenth of an ephah.) <verse eID="Exod.16.36"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eId="Exod.16"/>
    <chapter osisId="Exod.17" sId="Exod.17"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Exod.17.1" osisID="Exod.17.1"/>From the desert of Sin the whole community of the Israelites travelled by
       stages, as the Eternal bade them, and camped at Rephidim. [As there was no water to drink, <verse eID="Exod.17.1"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.17.2" osisID="Exod.17.2"/> the people complained to Moses; <q>Give us water to drink,</q> they cried.
       <q>Why complain to me?</q> said Moses.] <verse eID="Exod.17.2"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.17.3" osisID="Exod.17.3"/> The people thirsted for water there, and grumbled against Moses, crying,
       <q>Why did you bring us out of Egypt, only to kill us and our children and our cattle with thirst?</q> <q>Why put the
       Eternal to the proof?</q> said Moses. <verse eID="Exod.17.3"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.17.4" osisID="Exod.17.4"/> [So Moses appealed 4 to the Eternal, <q>What am I to do with this people?
       They are almost ready to stone me!</q> <verse eID="Exod.17.4"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.17.5" osisID="Exod.17.5"/> <q>Move ahead of the people,</q> said the Eternal, <q>along with some of the
       sheikhs of Israel; take the stick with which you struck the Nile, and advance. <verse eID="Exod.17.5"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.17.6" osisID="Exod.17.6"/> I will stand before you yonder on the rocks of Horeb; when you strike the
       rocks, water shall gush out, to let the people drink.</q> Moses did so, in the sight of the sheikhs of Israel.] <verse eID="Exod.17.6"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.17.7" osisID="Exod.17.7"/> He called the spot Massah (Proof), because they put the Eternal to the proof
       by wondering whether he was among them or not[, also Meribah (Complaint), because the Israelites had complained]. <verse eID="Exod.17.7"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Exod.17.8" osisID="Exod.17.8"/>[It was at Rephidim that Amalek came and fought against Israel. <verse eID="Exod.17.8"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.17.9" osisID="Exod.17.9"/> So Moses said to Joshua, <q>Pick out some men to go and
       <milestone type="pb" n="81"/>
       fight against Amalek; to-mor­row I will take my stand on the top of the hill, holding the divine stick in my hand.</q> <verse eID="Exod.17.9"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.17.10" osisID="Exod.17.10"/> Joshua did as Moses told him; he fought against Amalek, while Moses, Aaron,
       and Hur went up to the top of the hill. <verse eID="Exod.17.10"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.17.11" osisID="Exod.17.11"/> Whenever Moses raised his hand, then Is­rael won; whenever he lowered his
       hand, then Amalek won. <verse eID="Exod.17.11"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Exod.17.12" osisID="Exod.17.12"/>As the hands of Moses grew tired, they put a stone below him, on which he
       sat; Aaron and Hur held his hands up, one on one side and the other on the other side, so that his hands remained
       steady till sunset, <verse eID="Exod.17.12"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.17.13" osisID="Exod.17.13"/> while Joshua laid Amalek low, giving no quarter. <verse eID="Exod.17.13"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.17.14" osisID="Exod.17.14"/> <q>Write this down in a book,</q> said the Eternal to Moses, <q>in
       commemoration of the day, and read it aloud to Joshua; for I mean to blot Amalek from the very memory of men.</q> <verse eID="Exod.17.14"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.17.15" osisID="Exod.17.15"/> Moses built an altar, which he called <q>Under-the-Eternal’s-Banner,</q> <verse eID="Exod.17.15"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.17.16" osisID="Exod.17.16"/> declaring, <q>We pledge loyalty to the Eter­nal’s banner in his feud
       against Amalek from age to age!</q> <verse eID="Exod.17.16"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eId="Exod.17"/>
    <chapter osisId="Exod.18" sId="Exod.18"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Exod.18.1" osisID="Exod.18.1"/>Now Jethro, the priest of Midian, the father-in-law of Moses, heard of all
       that God had done for Moses and for his people Israel (for the Eternal had brought Israel out of Egypt). <verse eID="Exod.18.1"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.18.2" osisID="Exod.18.2"/> Jethro, the father-in-law of Moses, had taken back Zipporah the wife of
       Moses, after Moses had dismissed her, <verse eID="Exod.18.2"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.18.3" osisID="Exod.18.3"/> and her two sons one called Gershom or Stranger (for, said he, I have been
       a stranger in a foreign land) <verse eID="Exod.18.3"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.18.4" osisID="Exod.18.4"/> and the other called Eliezer or Godhelp (for, said he, my father’s God has
       been a help to me, rescuing me from the Pharaoh’s sword). <verse eID="Exod.18.4"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.18.5" osisID="Exod.18.5"/> Jethro, the father-in-law of Moses, came into the desert then, with the
       sons and the wife of Moses, to where Moses was camped, at the hill of God. <verse eID="Exod.18.5"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.18.6" osisID="Exod.18.6"/> Moses was told, <q>Here is your father-in-law Jethro coming to you, along
       with your wife and her two boys!</q> <verse eID="Exod.18.6"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <hi type="italic">
       <verse sID="Exod.18.7" osisID="Exod.18.7"/>So Moses went out to meet his father-in-law; he bowed low before him and
        kissed him; then they asked for one another’s health and went inside the tent, <verse eID="Exod.18.7"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.18.8" osisID="Exod.18.8"/> where Moses told his father-in-law all that the Eternal had done to the
        Pharaoh and the Egyp­tians for Israel’s sake, all the dis­tress they had suffered in their journey, and how the Eternal
        had preserved them. <verse eID="Exod.18.8"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.18.9" osisID="Exod.18.9"/> Jethro rejoiced over all the goodness of the Eternal to Israel, in
        rescuing them from the Egyptians. <verse eID="Exod.18.9"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.18.10" osisID="Exod.18.10"/><q>Blessed be the Eternal,</q> said he, <q>who has rescued you from, the
        Egyptians and from the Pha­raoh, who has rescued the peo­ple from the grip of the Egyp­tians! <verse eID="Exod.18.10"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.18.11" osisID="Exod.18.11"/> I see now that the Eternal is stronger than all other gods, for he has
        routed the haughty foes of his folk.</q> <verse eID="Exod.18.11"/>
      </hi>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Exod.18.12" osisID="Exod.18.12"/>So Jethro, the father-in-law of Moses, brought a burnt-offer­ing and some
       sacrifices for God, and Aaron and all the sheikhs of Israel came to join the sacri­ficial meal made by the
       father-in-law of Moses before God. <verse eID="Exod.18.12"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.18.13" osisID="Exod.18.13"/> Next day, as Moses was holding a popular court, with the people
       surrounding him from morning to night, <verse eID="Exod.18.13"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.18.14" osisID="Exod.18.14"/> the father-in-law of Moses noticed all his labour for the people, and
       said to him, <q>What is this you are doing? Why sit alone as a judge, with the people all round you from morning to
       night?</q> <verse eID="Exod.18.14"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.18.15" osisID="Exod.18.15"/> Moses said to his father-in-law, <q>Because the people come to me to get
       God’s own decision in
       <milestone type="pb" n="82"/> 
       their cases; <verse eID="Exod.18.15"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.18.16" osisID="Exod.18.16"/> whenever they have any disputes, they come to me, I decide between one
       man and another, and let them hear the rules and directions of God.</q> <verse eID="Exod.18.16"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.18.17" osisID="Exod.18.17"/> The father-in-law of Moses said to him, <q>You are not doing right. <verse eID="Exod.18.17"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.18.18" osisID="Exod.18.18"/> You will wear yourself out, you and your people; this work is too heavy
       for you, and you cannot manage it alone. <verse eID="Exod.18.18"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.18.19" osisID="Exod.18.19"/>Now listen to me, let me advise you, that God may be with you; do you
       represent God to the peo­ple, laying their cases before God, <verse eID="Exod.18.19"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.18.20" osisID="Exod.18.20"/> and instructing them in his rules and directions, letting them see how
       they are to live and what they are to do; <verse eID="Exod.18.20"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.18.21" osisID="Exod.18.21"/> but look out some capable men among the people, religious men, honest men,
       who scorn unjust profits, and appoint them to supervise groups of thousands, of hundreds, of fifties, and of tens; <verse eID="Exod.18.21"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.18.22" osisID="Exod.18.22"/> let them act as judges in ordinary cases; they can refer any special case
       to you, and judge lesser matters by them­selves. That will make things easier for you, as they share the work with you. <verse eID="Exod.18.22"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.18.23" osisID="Exod.18.23"/> If you do this, supposing that God so orders you, then you can stand the
       strain, and all the people will go home satisfied.</q> <verse eID="Exod.18.23"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Exod.18.24" osisID="Exod.18.24"/>Moses listened to what his father-in-law said, and did exactly as he
       told him; <verse eID="Exod.18.24"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.18.25" osisID="Exod.18.25"/> he chose capable men out of all Israel, and put them at the head of the
       people, over groups of thousands, of hundreds, of fifties, and of tens; <verse eID="Exod.18.25"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.18.26" osisID="Exod.18.26"/> they acted as judges in ordinary cases, deciding lesser matters by
       themselves, and re­ferring difficult cases to Moses. <verse eID="Exod.18.26"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.18.27" osisID="Exod.18.27"/> Then Moses let his father-in-law go; he betook himself to his own
       country.] <verse eID="Exod.18.27"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eId="Exod.18"/>
    <chapter osisId="Exod.19" sId="Exod.19"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Exod.19.2" osisID="Exod.19.2"/>Leaving Rephidim, the Israelites reached the desert of Sinai, where they
       pitched camp in the desert; <verse eID="Exod.19.2"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.19.1" osisID="Exod.19.1"/> it was in the third month after leaving the land of Egypt ... on this
       day they entered the desert of Sinai.
       [There Israel pitched camp in front of the mountain, <verse eID="Exod.19.1"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.19.3" osisID="Exod.19.3"/>
       and Moses went up to God.]
      <hi type="italic">
        The Eternal called to him from the mountain, saying, <q>Tell this to the house of Jacob,
        tell the Is­raelites: <verse eID="Exod.19.3"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.19.4" osisID="Exod.19.4"/>
        <q>You have seen for yourselves what I did to the Egyp­tians and how I bore you safe on eagle’s wings and brought
        you hither to myself. <verse eID="Exod.19.4"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.19.5" osisID="Exod.19.5"/> Now then, if you will listen to what I say and keep my compact, you
        shall be my own prized possession among all nations (for all the world is mine), <verse eID="Exod.19.5"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.19.6" osisID="Exod.19.6"/> and you shall be a dynasty of priests for me, a sacred nation.</q>
        This is what you must tell the Israelites.</q> <verse eID="Exod.19.6"/>
      </hi>
     </p>
     <p>
      <hi type="italic">
       <verse sID="Exod.19.9" osisID="Exod.19.9"/>The Eternal added, to Moses, <q>I am coming to you in a thick cloud, so
        that the people may hear me speaking to you and al­ways believe you also[.</q> <verse eID="Exod.19.9"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.19.10" osisID="Exod.19.10"/> The Eternal added, to Moses, <q>Go to the people and consecrate them
        to-day and to-morrow; let them wash their clothes <verse eID="Exod.19.10"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.19.11" osisID="Exod.19.11"/> and be ready for the third day], for on the third day the Eternal will
        de­scend upon the mountain of Sinai in sight of all the people. <verse eID="Exod.19.11"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.19.12" osisID="Exod.19.12"/>
        You must mark off the mountain all round and tell the peo­ple to be careful never to ascend it nor even to touch the
        edge of it; anyone who touches the mountain shall be put to death, <verse eID="Exod.19.12"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.19.13" osisID="Exod.19.13"/> not touched by any hand but either stoned or shot through; man or
        beast, no intruder shall live. Once the ram’s horn is sounded, then they may come up the mountain.</q>
       <verse eID="Exod.19.13"/>
      </hi>
     </p>
     <milestone type="pb" n="83"/> 
     <p>
      <verse sID="Exod.19.14" osisID="Exod.19.14"/>[So Moses went down the mountain to the people and con­secrated them;
       they washed their clothes, <verse eID="Exod.19.14"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.19.15" osisID="Exod.19.15"/> and he told them to be ready for the third day and to touch no woman. <verse eID="Exod.19.15"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.19.16" osisID="Exod.19.16"/> On the third day, in the morning, there was thunder and lightning, a
       dense cloud on the mountain, and a loud trumpet blast, till all the people in the camp trembled. <verse eID="Exod.19.16"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.19.17" osisID="Exod.19.17"/> Then Moses brought the people out of the camp to meet God; they took
       their stand at the foot of the mountain. <verse eID="Exod.19.17"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.19.19" osisID="Exod.19.19"/> As the trumpet blast grew louder and louder, Moses spoke and God
       answered him.] <verse eID="Exod.19.19"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <hi type="italic">
       <verse sID="Exod.19.20" osisID="Exod.19.20"/>Then the Eternal descended on the mountain of Sinai, to the top of the
        mountain; <verse eID="Exod.19.20"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.19.18" osisID="Exod.19.18"/> and the mountain of Sinai was all wrapped in smoke, as the Eter­nal
        descended in fire upon it; the smoke rose like steam from a kiln, till the people all trembled terribly. <verse eID="Exod.19.18"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.19.20" osisID="Exod.19.20"/> The Eternal called Moses to the top of the moun­tain; and when Moses
        went up, <verse eID="Exod.19.20"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.19.21" osisID="Exod.19.21"/> the Eternal told him to go down and warn the people against in­truding
        to gaze at the Eternal, lest a number of them should be struck down; <verse eID="Exod.19.21"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.19.22" osisID="Exod.19.22"/> even the priests were to consecrate themselves, the priests who were
        to approach the Eternal, lest he broke out upon them. <verse eID="Exod.19.22"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.19.23" osisID="Exod.19.23"/> Moses said to the Eternal, <q>But the people cannot come up the
        mountain of Sinai, for thou thyself didst charge us to mark off the mountain and render it sacred.</q> <verse eID="Exod.19.23"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.19.24" osisID="Exod.19.24"/> The Eternal said to him, <q>Go down yourself; then come up, along with
        Aaron, but let neither the people nor the priests intrude and come up to the Eternal, lest he break out upon them.</q>
       <verse eID="Exod.19.24"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.19.25" osisID="Exod.19.25"/> So Moses went down and said to them . . . <verse eID="Exod.19.25"/>
      </hi>
     </p>
    <chapter eId="Exod.19"/>
    <chapter osisId="Exod.20" sId="Exod.20"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Exod.20.1" osisID="Exod.20.1"/>[God spoke all these words. <verse eID="Exod.20.1"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.20.2" osisID="Exod.20.2"/> <q>I am the Eternal, your God, who brought you from the land of Egypt,
       that slave-pen.</q><verse eID="Exod.20.2"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Exod.20.3" osisID="Exod.20.3"/><q>You shall have no gods but me.</q><verse eID="Exod.20.3"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Exod.20.4" osisID="Exod.20.4"/><q>You shall not carve any idols for yourselves, the shape of any­thing in
       heaven above or on the earth below or in the sea; <verse eID="Exod.20.4"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.20.5" osisID="Exod.20.5"/> you shall not bow down to them nor worship them, for I the Eternal, your
       God, am a jealous God, punishing children for the sins of their fathers, punishing those who hate me, down to the
       third and the fourth generation <verse eID="Exod.20.5"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.20.6" osisID="Exod.20.6"/> but showing kindness to thousands of those who love me and obey my
       orders.</q><verse eID="Exod.20.6"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Exod.20.7" osisID="Exod.20.7"/><q>You shall not use the name of the Eternal, your God, pro­fanely; for
       the Eternal will never acquit anyone who uses his name profanely.</q> <verse eID="Exod.20.7"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Exod.20.8" osisID="Exod.20.8"/><q> Remember to hold the sabbath sacred. <verse eID="Exod.20.8"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.20.9" osisID="Exod.20.9"/> Six days you may labour and do all your business, <verse eID="Exod.20.9"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.20.10" osisID="Exod.20.10"/> but the seventh day is the sabbath in honour of the Eternal, your God,
       and on it you must do no business, neither you nor your son nor your daughter nor your slaves, male or female, nor
       your cattle, nor the alien who is among you; <verse eID="Exod.20.10"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.20.11" osisID="Exod.20.11"/> for in six days the Eternal made sky and earth and sea and all that
       they contain, and then he rested on the sev­enth day; therefore the Eternal blessed the sabbath, making it a sacred
       day. </q> <verse eID="Exod.20.11"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Exod.20.12" osisID="Exod.20.12"/><q>Honour your father and your mother, that you may have a long life in
       the land which the Eternal, your God, is giving you. </q> <verse eID="Exod.20.12"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Exod.20.13" osisID="Exod.20.13"/><q> You shall not murder. </q> <verse eID="Exod.20.13"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Exod.20.14" osisID="Exod.20.14"/><q> You shall not commit adultery. </q> <verse eID="Exod.20.14"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Exod.20.15" osisID="Exod.20.15"/><q> You shall not steal. </q> <verse eID="Exod.20.15"/>
     </p>
     <milestone type="pb" n="84"/> 
     <p>
      <verse sID="Exod.20.16" osisID="Exod.20.16"/><q>You shall not give false evi­dence against a fellow-country­man. </q> <verse eID="Exod.20.16"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Exod.20.17" osisID="Exod.20.17"/><q> You shall not covet a fellow- countryman’s household; you shall not
       covet a fellow-country­man’s wife, nor his slaves, male or female, nor his ox, nor his ass, nor anything that
       belongs to a fellow-countryman. </q> <verse eID="Exod.20.17"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eId="Exod.20"/>
    <chapter osisId="Exod.19" sId="Exod.19"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Exod.19.7" osisID="Exod.19.7"/>Then Moses went and summoned the sheikhs of the people, putting before
       them all these orders given him by the Eternal; <verse eID="Exod.19.7"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.19.8" osisID="Exod.19.8"/> and the people all an­swered together, <q>Whatever the Eternal has
       ordered, we will do.</q> <verse eID="Exod.19.8"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eId="Exod.19"/>
    <chapter osisId="Exod.20" sId="Exod.20"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Exod.20.18" osisID="Exod.20.18"/>But when the people saw all the thunder and light­ning and the trumpet
       blast and the mountain in smoke, the peo­ple were all afraid and trembled; they stood far back <verse eID="Exod.20.18"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.20.19" osisID="Exod.20.19"/> and said to Moses, <q>Speak you to us, and we will listen; but let not
       God speak to us, lest we die.</q> <verse eID="Exod.20.19"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.20.20" osisID="Exod.20.20"/><q>Fear not,</q> said Moses to the people, <q>God is only testing you;
       it is to keep you from sinning by a steady awe of him.</q> <verse eID="Exod.20.20"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.20.21" osisID="Exod.20.21"/> Still the people stood far back, while Moses approached the dense
       darkness where God was. <verse eID="Exod.20.21"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Exod.20.22" osisID="Exod.20.22"/>Then the Eternal bade Moses give the Israelites this message:
       <q>You have seen for yourselves that I have been talking to you out of heaven; <verse eID="Exod.20.22"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.20.23" osisID="Exod.20.23"/> you must not carve yourselves any gods of silver or of gold, to rank
       with me <verse eID="Exod.20.23"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.20.24" osisID="Exod.20.24"/> You must erect an altar of earth to me and sacrifice on it your
       burnt-offerings and your recompense-offerings, your sheep and your oxen; wherever I choose to be remembered,
       there I will come to you and bless you. <verse eID="Exod.20.24"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.20.25" osisID="Exod.20.25"/> If you build a stone altar, it must not be of dressed stones; for you
       will pollute the altar by taking a tool to it. <verse eID="Exod.20.25"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.20.26" osisID="Exod.20.26"/> And you must never mount on steps to my altar, lest you ex­pose your
       limbs.</q><verse eID="Exod.20.26"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eId="Exod.20"/>
    <chapter osisId="Exod.21" sId="Exod.21"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Exod.21.1" osisID="Exod.21.1"/>Here are the regulations you must lay before them. <verse eID="Exod.21.1"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.21.2" osisID="Exod.21.2"/> When you buy a Hebrew slave, he shall serve for six years and go free
       in the seventh year with­out paying any ransom. <verse eID="Exod.21.2"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.21.3" osisID="Exod.21.3"/> If he was single when he entered his master’s house, he shall go free
       alone; if he was married, his wife shall go free with him. <verse eID="Exod.21.3"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.21.4" osisID="Exod.21.4"/> If his master has given him a wife, and if she has borne him sons or
       daughters, the wife with her chil­dren belong to her master, and the man shall go free alone. <verse eID="Exod.21.4"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.21.5" osisID="Exod.21.5"/> But if the slave declares, <q>I am fond of my master, my wife and my
       children; I will not go free,</q> <verse eID="Exod.21.5"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.21.6" osisID="Exod.21.6"/> then his master shall take him to the local sanctuary, to the door or
       to the door-post, where his master shall pierce his ear with an awl; after which the slave shall serve him for all
       time. <verse eID="Exod.21.6"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Exod.21.7" osisID="Exod.21.7"/>When a man’s daughter is sold to be a slave, she shall not go free like
       the male slaves. <verse eID="Exod.21.7"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.21.8" osisID="Exod.21.8"/> If her master, who meant her for him­self, is not satisfied with her, he
       must allow her to be bought back; he has no power to sell her to foreigners, since he has not treated her fairly. <verse eID="Exod.21.8"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.21.9" osisID="Exod.21.9"/> If he meant her for his son, he must treat her as a daughter. <verse eID="Exod.21.9"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.21.10" osisID="Exod.21.10"/> If he takes another concubine, he must not di­minish the first woman’s
       rations of flesh, or of clothes, nor her conjugal rights; <verse eID="Exod.21.10"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.21.11" osisID="Exod.21.11"/> if he fails in any of these three duties, then she shall go free,
       without paying any ransom in money. <verse eID="Exod.21.11"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Exod.21.12" osisID="Exod.21.12"/> He who strikes a man, so that he dies, must be put to death. <verse eID="Exod.21.12"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.21.13" osisID="Exod.21.13"/> But if he did not intend it maliciously, if it was accidental, I will
       appoint a place of asylum for such among you.
      <verse eID="Exod.21.13"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.21.14" osisID="Exod.21.14"/> Only, if
       <milestone type="pb" n="85"/>
       one man wilfully attacks an­other, to murder him craftily, you must take that man from my very altar and put him to
       death. <verse eID="Exod.21.14"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.21.15" osisID="Exod.21.15"/> He who strikes his father or his mother must be put to death; <verse eID="Exod.21.15"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.21.17" osisID="Exod.21.17"/> and he who curses his father or his mother must be put to death. <verse eID="Exod.21.17"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.21.16" osisID="Exod.21.16"/> (He who kidnaps a man and either sells him or is found in possession
       of him must be put to death.) <verse eID="Exod.21.16"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.21.18" osisID="Exod.21.18"/> If two men quarrel, and one strikes the other with a stone or with
       his fist, so that the man is laid up in bed, though he does not die, <verse eID="Exod.21.18"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.21.19" osisID="Exod.21.19"/> then, if the man rises and limps about on his stick, the striker shall
       go unpunished, except that he must pay for the man’s loss of time and also see that he is thoroughly restored to
       health. <verse eID="Exod.21.19"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.21.20" osisID="Exod.21.20"/> If a man strikes one of his slaves, male or female, with a rod, so
       that the slave dies under the blow, he shall be punished; <verse eID="Exod.21.20"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.21.21" osisID="Exod.21.21"/> but if the slave survives a day or two, he shall not be punished, for
       the slave is his own property. <verse eID="Exod.21.21"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.21.22" osisID="Exod.21.22"/> If, as men are quarrelling, a pregnant woman is struck, so that she
       miscarries, without any further mischief to herself, the striker must pay such fine as the woman’s husband imposes
       upon him, as a payment for the untimely birth; <verse eID="Exod.21.22"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.21.23" osisID="Exod.21.23"/> but, if any further mischief follows, then it must be life for life, <verse eID="Exod.21.23"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.21.24" osisID="Exod.21.24"/> an eye for an eye, a tooth for a tooth, a hand for a hand, a foot for
       a foot, <verse eID="Exod.21.24"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.21.25" osisID="Exod.21.25"/> a burn for a burn, a wound for a wound, a lash for a lash. <verse eID="Exod.21.25"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.21.26" osisID="Exod.21.26"/> If a man strikes and destroys the eye of a slave of his, male or
       female, he must let the slave go free, for the sake of that eye; <verse eID="Exod.21.26"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.21.27" osisID="Exod.21.27"/> and if he knocks out the tooth of a slave of his, male or female, he
       must let the slave go free, for the sake of that tooth. <verse eID="Exod.21.27"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.21.28" osisID="Exod.21.28"/> If an ox gores a man or a woman to death, the ox must be stoned to
       death, and its flesh must not be eaten, though the owner of the ox shall go unpunished. <verse eID="Exod.21.28"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.21.29" osisID="Exod.21.29"/> But if the ox was in the habit of goring people, if the owner was
       warned of this and yet did not shut him up but left him to kill a man or a wom­an, then the ox shall be stoned to
       death and the owner shall also be put to death. <verse eID="Exod.21.29"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.21.30" osisID="Exod.21.30"/> However, if a fine only is imposed upon him, he must buy his life
       back for the sum imposed, as a forfeit. <verse eID="Exod.21.30"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.21.31" osisID="Exod.21.31"/> The same law holds for him, if his ox has gored a boy or a girl to
       death; <verse eID="Exod.21.31"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.21.32" osisID="Exod.21.32"/> but if the ox has gored a slave, male or female, he must pay the
       slave’s master four guineas, and the ox must be stoned to death. <verse eID="Exod.21.32"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Exod.21.33" osisID="Exod.21.33"/>If a man re-opens a pit or digs a pit and fails to cover it over, so
       that an ox or an ass falls into it, <verse eID="Exod.21.33"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.21.34" osisID="Exod.21.34"/> the owner of the pit shall make good the loss; he must pay the price
       of it to the owner, keeping the dead beast for him­self. <verse eID="Exod.21.34"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Exod.21.35" osisID="Exod.21.35"/>If one man’s ox hurt another’s ox, so that it dies, then the live ox
       must be sold and the money divided between the two men, as well as the dead animal. <verse eID="Exod.21.35"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.21.36" osisID="Exod.21.36"/> If the ox is known to have been in the habit of goring, and yet the
       owner has not shut him up, he must pay ox for ox, keeping the dead beast for himself. <verse eID="Exod.21.36"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eId="Exod.21"/>
    <chapter osisId="Exod.22" sId="Exod.22"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Exod.22.1" osisID="Exod.22.1"/>If a man steal an ox or a sheep and either slays it or sells it, he must
       pay five oxen for the ox and four sheep for the sheep. <verse eID="Exod.22.1"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.22.3" osisID="Exod.22.3"/> Pay he must; if he has nothing, he must be sold, to pay for what he has
       stolen. <verse eID="Exod.22.3"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.22.4" osisID="Exod.22.4"/> If the stolen creature is found alive in his possession, either ox or
       ass or sheep, he must pay back two
       <milestone type="pb" n="86"/>
       animals. <verse eID="Exod.22.4"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.22.2" osisID="Exod.22.2"/> If a thief is caught breaking into a house and struck so that he dies,
       the householder is not guilty; <verse eID="Exod.22.2"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.22.3" osisID="Exod.22.3"/> but if it was after dawn, the householder is guilty. <verse eID="Exod.22.3"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.22.5" osisID="Exod.22.5"/>If a man is burning some field or vineyard and lets the fire spread till
       another man’s field catches fire, he must pay for it with the very best produce of his own field and vineyard. <verse eID="Exod.22.5"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.22.6" osisID="Exod.22.6"/> If the bon­fire breaks out and kindles a thorn-hedge, so that the shocks
       of corn or the standing corn or the field itself is burned up, then the man who lit the bonfire must pay for the
       damage. <verse eID="Exod.22.6"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.22.7" osisID="Exod.22.7"/> If a man puts money or any article into the keeping of a
       fellow-countryman, and it is stolen out of the man’s house, the thief must pay double if he is caught. <verse eID="Exod.22.7"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.22.8" osisID="Exod.22.8"/>If the thief is not caught, the owner of the house must appear at the
       local sanctuary, till it be ascertained whether he has not laid hands on the other man’s property. <verse eID="Exod.22.8"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.22.9" osisID="Exod.22.9"/> Whatever be the of­fence, whether an ox or an ass or a sheep or clothes
       or any lost property is claimed, the case must go to the local sanctuary, and the convicted party must pay twice
       the amount to his fellow-countryman. <verse eID="Exod.22.9"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.22.10" osisID="Exod.22.10"/> If a man puts an ass or an ox or a sheep or any animal into the
       keeping of a fellow-countryman, and it dies or is injured or is raided, without anyone seeing it, <verse eID="Exod.22.10"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.22.11" osisID="Exod.22.11"/> then the man must swear before the Eternal that he has not laid hands
       on the other man’s prop­erty; the owner must accept this oath, and no restitution shall be made. <verse eID="Exod.22.11"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.22.12" osisID="Exod.22.12"/> But if the ani­mal has been stolen, the man must make restitution to
       the owner. <verse eID="Exod.22.12"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.22.13" osisID="Exod.22.13"/> If the animal has been torn to pieces, let him bring the torn flesh
       as evidence; he need not make good what has been torn to pieces. <verse eID="Exod.22.13"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.22.14" osisID="Exod.22.14"/> If a man borrows an animal from a fellow-countryman and it is injured
       or dies, in the owner’s absence, the man must make restitution; <verse eID="Exod.22.14"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.22.15" osisID="Exod.22.15"/> if the owner is beside it, the man need not make good the loss; be­ing
       hired, it came as a hired thing. <verse eID="Exod.22.15"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Exod.22.16" osisID="Exod.22.16"/>If a man seduces a maiden who is not betrothed and lies with her, he
       must pay for her and marry her; <verse eID="Exod.22.16"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.22.17" osisID="Exod.22.17"/> if her father absolutely refuses to let him have her, he must still
       pay the usual marriage-fee for a daughter. <verse eID="Exod.22.17"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Exod.22.18" osisID="Exod.22.18"/>You shall not allow any sorceress to live. <verse eID="Exod.22.18"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Exod.22.19" osisID="Exod.22.19"/> Whoever lies with a beast shall be put to death. <verse eID="Exod.22.19"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Exod.22.20" osisID="Exod.22.20"/> Whoever sacrifices to any god except the Eternal alone shall be
       solemnly destroyed. <verse eID="Exod.22.20"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Exod.22.21" osisID="Exod.22.21"/>You must not injure or maltreat an alien among you, for you were
       aliens yourselves in the land of Egypt. <verse eID="Exod.22.21"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.22.22" osisID="Exod.22.22"/> You must not oppress a widow or an orphan; <verse eID="Exod.22.22"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.22.23" osisID="Exod.22.23"/> if ever you oppress them and if ever they cry to me, I will listen to
       their cry, <verse eID="Exod.22.23"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.22.24" osisID="Exod.22.24"/> and my wrath shall blaze till I kill you in war, leav­ing your own
       wives widows and your own children orphans. <verse eID="Exod.22.24"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Exod.22.25" osisID="Exod.22.25"/>If you lend money to any poor man of my people, you must not treat him
       as his creditor, nor must you exact interest from him. <verse eID="Exod.22.25"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.22.26" osisID="Exod.22.26"/> If you ever take a fellow-countryman’s garment in pledge, you must
       give it back to him by sun-down; <verse eID="Exod.22.26"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.22.27" osisID="Exod.22.27"/> for that is the only rug he has, the mantle for his body. What else
       can he sleep in? If he cries to me, I will listen to his cry, for I am pitiful.
      <verse eID="Exod.22.27"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Exod.22.28" osisID="Exod.22.28"/>You shall not revile God, nor shall you curse any of the au­thorities
       of your people. <verse eID="Exod.22.28"/>
     </p>
     <milestone type="pb" n="87"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Exod.22.29" osisID="Exod.22.29"/>You must be prompt to make the offering from your harvested grain and
       wines. You must give me your eldest sons. <verse eID="Exod.22.29"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.22.30" osisID="Exod.22.30"/> And so with your oxen and your sheep; for seven days the firstling
       may remain with its dam, but on the eighth day you must give it to me. <verse eID="Exod.22.30"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Exod.22.31" osisID="Exod.22.31"/>Also, as you are to be sacred men to me, you must never eat the flesh
       of an animal torn to pieces in the field; fling that to the dogs. <verse eID="Exod.22.31"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eId="Exod.22"/> 
    <chapter osisId="Exod.23" sId="Exod.23"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Exod.23.1" osisID="Exod.23.1"/>You must never repeat a baseless rumour; never side with a bad man, to
       give malicious evidence. <verse eID="Exod.23.1"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.23.2" osisID="Exod.23.2"/> You must not follow a majority to do wrong, nor must you bear witness
       in court so as to side with an unjust majority; <verse eID="Exod.23.2"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.23.3" osisID="Exod.23.3"/> neither must you be partial to a poor man’s plea. <verse eID="Exod.23.3"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.23.4" osisID="Exod.23.4"/>If you come across your ene­my’s ox or ass wandering, you must be sure to
       take it back to him; <verse eID="Exod.23.4"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.23.5" osisID="Exod.23.5"/> if you see the ass of a man who hates you lying helpless un­der its load,
       you must not leave it all to him, you must help him to release the animal. <verse eID="Exod.23.5"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Exod.23.6" osisID="Exod.23.6"/>You must never tamper with a poor man’s rights in court. <verse eID="Exod.23.6"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.23.7" osisID="Exod.23.7"/>Avoid false charges, never have innocent and guiltless people put to
       death, nor acquit bad men. <verse eID="Exod.23.7"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.23.8" osisID="Exod.23.8"/> You must never accept a bribe, for a bribe blinds even men whose eyes
       are open, and it destroys the case of a good man. <verse eID="Exod.23.8"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.23.9" osisID="Exod.23.9"/>(You must not maltreat an alien; for you were aliens your­selves in the
       land of Egypt, you know how a foreigner feels.) <verse eID="Exod.23.9"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Exod.23.10" osisID="Exod.23.10"/>For six years you may sow your land and gather in your crops, <verse eID="Exod.23.10"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.23.11" osisID="Exod.23.11"/> but every seventh year you must let the land alone, to lie fallow, so
       that poor people may pick up something; any­thing they leave, the wild ani­mals can eat. So with your vineyards and
       your olive-yards. <verse eID="Exod.23.11"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.23.12" osisID="Exod.23.12"/> For six days you shall labour, but on the seventh day you shall
       desist from work, that your ox and your ass may rest, and that the sons born to your female slaves and also the
       aliens in your employment may get refreshed. <verse eID="Exod.23.12"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Exod.23.14" osisID="Exod.23.14"/>Three times a year you must hold a festival for me. <verse eID="Exod.23.14"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.23.15" osisID="Exod.23.15"/> Hold the festival of unleavened cakes-- for seven days you must eat
       un­leavened cakes--as I com­manded you, at the time fixed in the month of Abib (since then it was that you left
       Egypt); none of you must appear before me empty-handed. <verse eID="Exod.23.15"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.23.16" osisID="Exod.23.16"/> Then the harvest festival, when you offer the first fruits of your
       labour, of what you sowed in your fields. Then the festival of ingathering, at the end of the year, when you
       gather in your crops. <verse eID="Exod.23.16"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.23.17" osisID="Exod.23.17"/> Three times a year shall all your male members appear before the Lord.<verse eID="Exod.23.17"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.23.18" osisID="Exod.23.18"/> You must not offer the blood of my sacrifices with leavened cakes, nor
       must the fat slices of my victims be left all night till the morning. <verse eID="Exod.23.18"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.23.19" osisID="Exod.23.19"/> You must bring the very first and finest of what the land bears, into
       the house of the Eternal your God.--You must not boil a kid in its mother’s milk.-- <verse eID="Exod.23.19"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.23.13" osisID="Exod.23.13"/> Pay careful heed to all that I have ordered you; and never mention
       the name of any other god, never let it pass your lips. <verse eID="Exod.23.13"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Exod.23.20" osisID="Exod.23.20"/>Now I am sending an angel in front of you, to guard you as you go and
       to guide you to the place I have prepared. <verse eID="Exod.23.20"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.23.21" osisID="Exod.23.21"/> Attend to him, listen to what he says; never defy him, for he will not
       pardon your offence, since I am manifest in him. <verse eID="Exod.23.21"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.23.22" osisID="Exod.23.22"/> But if you listen to what he says and do all that I tell you, then I
       will be an
       <milestone type="pb" n="88"/>
       enemy to your enemies and to your foes a foe. <verse eID="Exod.23.22"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.23.23" osisID="Exod.23.23"/> For my angel shall go in front of you and guide you home, to where
       the Amorites and the Hittites and the Perizzites and the Canaanites and the Hivites and the Jebusites live, whom I
       will sweep away. <verse eID="Exod.23.23"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.23.24" osisID="Exod.23.24"/> You must not bow down to their gods nor worship them, nor do as they
       do; you must demolish them and break their obelisks. <verse eID="Exod.23.24"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.23.25" osisID="Exod.23.25"/> You shall wor­ship the Eternal your God, and then I will bless your
       food and water, and I will free you from disease; <verse eID="Exod.23.25"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.23.26" osisID="Exod.23.26"/> no animal shall drop her young or be barren in your country, and I
       will give you a full term of life; <verse eID="Exod.23.26"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.23.27" osisID="Exod.23.27"/> I will send a panic in front of you, routing all the nations you
       reach, until your enemies all turn their backs in flight before you; <verse eID="Exod.23.27"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.23.28" osisID="Exod.23.28"/> I will send hornets in front of you to drive out the Hivites and the
       Canaanites and the Hittites before you; <verse eID="Exod.23.28"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.23.29" osisID="Exod.23.29"/> I will not drive them out in one year, lest the country be left
       desolate and wild beasts multiply against you; <verse eID="Exod.23.29"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.23.30" osisID="Exod.23.30"/> I will drive them out before you little by little, till your own
       numbers grow and till you hold the land; <verse eID="Exod.23.30"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.23.31" osisID="Exod.23.31"/>I will fix your frontiers from the Reed Sea as far as to the
       Philis­tine sea-coast, and from the des­ert to the Euphrates, for I will put the natives in your power and you shall
       drive them out to make room for you; <verse eID="Exod.23.31"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.23.32" osisID="Exod.23.32"/> you must never make any compact with them nor with their gods; <verse eID="Exod.23.32"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.23.33" osisID="Exod.23.33"/> they must not live within your land, lest they make you sin against
       me; for if you worship their gods it will endanger you. <verse eID="Exod.23.33"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eId="Exod.23"/>
    <chapter osisId="Exod.24" sId="Exod.24"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Exod.24.3" osisID="Exod.24.3"/>Then Moses went and told the people all the orders and regulations of
       the Eternal, and the people all answered, with one voice, <q>Whatever the Eter­nal has ordered, that will we do.</q> <verse eID="Exod.24.3"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.24.4" osisID="Exod.24.4"/> So Moses wrote down all that the Eternal had said; and next morning he
       erected an altar at the foot of the moun­tain and twelve standing-stones, one for each of the twelve clans of
       Israel. <verse eID="Exod.24.4"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.24.5" osisID="Exod.24.5"/> He sent the youth of Israel to offer the burnt-offer­ings and to
       sacrifice the recom­pense-offerings of oxen to the Eternal, <verse eID="Exod.24.5"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.24.6" osisID="Exod.24.6"/> while Moses himself took half of the blood and put it into basins,
       splashing the other half on the altar. <verse eID="Exod.24.6"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.24.7" osisID="Exod.24.7"/> Then he took the scroll of the compact and read it aloud to the people,
       who said, <q>Whatever the Eternal has ordered, that will we do obedi­ently.</q> <verse eID="Exod.24.7"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.24.8" osisID="Exod.24.8"/> Then Moses took and splashed the blood on the peo­ple, saying, <q>There
       is the blood of the compact which the Eter­nal has made with you, on all these terms!</q>] <verse eID="Exod.24.8"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <hi type="italic">
       <verse sID="Exod.24.1" osisID="Exod.24.1"/>Moses was told to go up to the Eternal, along with Aaron, Nadab, Abihu,
        and seventy of the sheikhs of Israel; they were to worship at a distance, <verse eID="Exod.24.1"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.24.2" osisID="Exod.24.2"/> while Moses alone was to draw near; the rest were not to draw near,
        nor were the people to accom­pany Moses. <verse eID="Exod.24.2"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.24.9" osisID="Exod.24.9"/> So Moses went up, with Aaron, Nadab, Abihu, and seventy of the sheikhs
        of Israel; <verse eID="Exod.24.9"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.24.10" osisID="Exod.24.10"/> they saw the God of Israel, through something like a pave­ment of
        blue sapphire under his feet, clear as the sky itself. <verse eID="Exod.24.10"/>
       <verse sID="Exod.24.11" osisID="Exod.24.11"/> The Eternal did not strike down these headmen of Israel; they had a
        vision of God and they ate and drank at their sacrifice. <verse eID="Exod.24.11"/>
      </hi>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Exod.24.12" osisID="Exod.24.12"/>[Then the Eternal said to Moses, <q>Come up beside me on the mountain,
       and I will give you the stone tablets with the directions and orders I have in­scribed for the guidance of the
       <milestone type="pb" n="89"/>
       people.</q> <verse eID="Exod.24.12"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.24.13" osisID="Exod.24.13"/> Moses rose and went up the mountain of God with his attendant Joshua,
       telling the sheikhs to wait below for them till they returned. <verse eID="Exod.24.13"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.24.14" osisID="Exod.24.14"/> <q>You have Aaron and Hur,</q> he said; <q>any­one with a dispute can
       take it to them.</q> <verse eID="Exod.24.14"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.24.15" osisID="Exod.24.15"/> Then Moses went up the mountain], which was covered with the cloud. <verse eID="Exod.24.15"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.24.16" osisID="Exod.24.16"/> The radi­ance of the Eternal rested on the mountain of Sinai; for six
       days the cloud covered it, and on the seventh day he called from the cloud to Moses <verse eID="Exod.24.16"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.24.17" osisID="Exod.24.17"/> (the Eternal’s radiance looked to the Israelites like blazing fire on
       the top of the mountain). <verse eID="Exod.24.17"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.24.18" osisID="Exod.24.18"/>
       Moses entered the cloud and went up the moun­tain and Moses was on the mountain for forty days and forty nights]. <verse eID="Exod.24.18"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eId="Exod.24"/>
    <chapter osisId="Exod.25" sId="Exod.25"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Exod.25.1" osisID="Exod.25.1"/>The Eternal said to Moses, <verse eID="Exod.25.1"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.25.2" osisID="Exod.25.2"/><q>Tell the Israelites to raise a special offering for me; take it from
       every man who has a willing mind. <verse eID="Exod.25.2"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.25.3" osisID="Exod.25.3"/> This is what you are to take from them: gold, silver, and bronze, <verse eID="Exod.25.3"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.25.4" osisID="Exod.25.4"/> violet, purple, and scarlet yarn, fine linen, goats’ hair, <verse eID="Exod.25.4"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.25.5" osisID="Exod.25.5"/> rams’ skins dyed red, leather, acacia wood, <verse eID="Exod.25.5"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.25.6" osisID="Exod.25.6"/> oil for the lamps, spices for the anointing oil and for the fragrant
       incense powder, <verse eID="Exod.25.6"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.25.7" osisID="Exod.25.7"/> beryls and jewels to be set on the apron and on the sacred pouch. <verse eID="Exod.25.7"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.25.8" osisID="Exod.25.8"/> And let them make me a shrine, that I may dwell among them; <verse eID="Exod.25.8"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.25.9" osisID="Exod.25.9"/> you must make it exactly as I show you, after the pattern of the
       Dwelling and of its furniture. <verse eID="Exod.25.9"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.25.10" osisID="Exod.25.10"/> They must also make me an ark of acacia wood, four feet long, and two
       and a half feet broad and high; <verse eID="Exod.25.10"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.25.11" osisID="Exod.25.11"/> you must overlay it with pure gold, outside and inside, and run a
       moulding of gold round it. <verse eID="Exod.25.11"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.25.12" osisID="Exod.25.12"/> You must cast four rings of gold for it and fasten them on its four
       supports, two rings on one side and two rings on the other; <verse eID="Exod.25.12"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.25.13" osisID="Exod.25.13"/> then you must make poles of acacia wood, over­laid with gold, <verse eID="Exod.25.13"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.25.14" osisID="Exod.25.14"/> and put the poles through the rings at the side of the ark, to carry
       the ark; <verse eID="Exod.25.14"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.25.15" osisID="Exod.25.15"/> the poles must rest in the rings, they must never be taken out. <verse eID="Exod.25.15"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.25.16" osisID="Exod.25.16"/> Inside the ark you must place the laws I give you. <verse eID="Exod.25.16"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.25.17" osisID="Exod.25.17"/> You shall also make a cover of pure gold, four feet long and two and
       a half feet wide. <verse eID="Exod.25.17"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.25.18" osisID="Exod.25.18"/> Make also two golden kherubs, of beaten work, for the two ends of
       the cover, <verse eID="Exod.25.18"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.25.19" osisID="Exod.25.19"/> one kherub at one end and the other kherub at the other, the kherubs
       to be of one piece with the cover; <verse eID="Exod.25.19"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.25.20" osisID="Exod.25.20"/> the wings of the kherubs are to be outstretched, overshadowing the
       cover, and the kherubs must turn to one another, facing the cover.</q><verse eID="Exod.25.20"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Exod.25.21" osisID="Exod.25.21"/><q>You must place the cover on the ark, and inside the ark you must place
       the laws I give you. <verse eID="Exod.25.21"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.25.22" osisID="Exod.25.22"/> There, at the cover between the two kherubs upon the ark with its
       laws, will I meet you and tell you all the orders I have to give you for the Israelites.</q><verse eID="Exod.25.22"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Exod.25.23" osisID="Exod.25.23"/>You shall also make a table of acacia wood, three feet long, a foot
       and a half wide, and two feet three inches high; <verse eID="Exod.25.23"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.25.24" osisID="Exod.25.24"/> overlay it with pure gold and run a moulding of gold round it; <verse eID="Exod.25.24"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.25.25" osisID="Exod.25.25"/> make a frame for it all round, three inches wide, and run a moulding
       of gold all round the frame. <verse eID="Exod.25.25"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.25.26" osisID="Exod.25.26"/> You must make four rings of gold for the table, and put the rings at
       the four corners, on the feet of the table; <verse eID="Exod.25.26"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.25.27" osisID="Exod.25.27"/> the rings must lie close to the frame, to receive the poles for
       carrying the table. <verse eID="Exod.25.27"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.25.28" osisID="Exod.25.28"/> Make poles of acacia wood, overlaid with gold, that the table may be
       carried. <verse eID="Exod.25.28"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.25.29" osisID="Exod.25.29"/> Also you must make the table dishes, the saucers, the flagons, and
       the
       <milestone type="pb" n="90"/>
       chalices, for pouring the libations, all of pure gold. <verse eID="Exod.25.29"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.25.30" osisID="Exod.25.30"/> On the table you must always keep my Presence-bread. <verse eID="Exod.25.30"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Exod.25.31" osisID="Exod.25.31"/>You shall also make a lampstand of pure gold, beaten work all of it,
       both pedestal and shaft; its cups, both calyxes and flow­ers, are all to be of one piece with it. <verse eID="Exod.25.31"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.25.32" osisID="Exod.25.32"/> Six branches are to rise from its sides, three branches from one side
       of the lampstand and three from the other; <verse eID="Exod.25.32"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.25.33" osisID="Exod.25.33"/> each branch is to bear three cups like almond-blos­soms, each cup with
       a calyx and a flower, each branch upon the lampstand; <verse eID="Exod.25.33"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.25.34" osisID="Exod.25.34"/> on the main shaft of the lampstand there are to be four cups like
       almond-blossoms, each with its calyx and flower, <verse eID="Exod.25.34"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.25.35" osisID="Exod.25.35"/> and also a calyx under each pair of the six branches on the
       lampstand, <verse eID="Exod.25.35"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.25.36" osisID="Exod.25.36"/> these calyxes and their branches being of one piece with it, the
       whole forming a single piece of pure beaten gold work. <verse eID="Exod.25.36"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.25.37" osisID="Exod.25.37"/>You must then make the seven lamps for it and fix them on, so that
       they shine in front of it. <verse eID="Exod.25.37"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.25.38" osisID="Exod.25.38"/>The snuffers and ash-trays are to be gold. <verse eID="Exod.25.38"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.25.39" osisID="Exod.25.39"/> You must use ninety-six pounds of pure gold for the lampstand and all
       these fittings. <verse eID="Exod.25.39"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.25.40" osisID="Exod.25.40"/> And see that you make everything according to the pat­tern shown you
       on the moun­tain. <verse eID="Exod.25.40"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eId="Exod.25"/>
    <chapter osisId="Exod.26" sId="Exod.26"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Exod.26.1" osisID="Exod.26.1"/>Also you must furnish the Dwelling with ten curtains, made of fine
       twined linen, violet, purple, and scarlet, and em­broidered with designs of kherubs; <verse eID="Exod.26.1"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.26.2" osisID="Exod.26.2"/> each curtain is to be forty-two feet long, by six feet broad, all the
       curtains measuring the same. <verse eID="Exod.26.2"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.26.3" osisID="Exod.26.3"/> Five curtains are to be joined together, and so are the other five. <verse eID="Exod.26.3"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.26.4" osisID="Exod.26.4"/> You must put loops of violet on the edge of the outermost curtain in
       the first set, and also on the edge of the outermost curtain in the second set, <verse eID="Exod.26.4"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.26.5" osisID="Exod.26.5"/> fifty loops to each curtain, loops to be opposite each other. <verse eID="Exod.26.5"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.26.6" osisID="Exod.26.6"/> You must then make fifty golden clasps and join the curtains by the
       clasps, to form a single Dwelling. <verse eID="Exod.26.6"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.26.7" osisID="Exod.26.7"/> You must also make curtains of goats’ hair for the tent over the
       Dwelling, eleven curtains, <verse eID="Exod.26.7"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.26.8" osisID="Exod.26.8"/> each curtain forty-five feet long by six feet broad, all the curtains
       measuring the same. <verse eID="Exod.26.8"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.26.9" osisID="Exod.26.9"/> Join five of the curtains, then join the other six, doubling the sixth
       of the cur­tains to hang in front of the tent. <verse eID="Exod.26.9"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.26.10" osisID="Exod.26.10"/> You must put fifty loops on the edge of the outermost curtain in the
       first set, and also on the edge of the outermost curtain in the second set; <verse eID="Exod.26.10"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.26.11" osisID="Exod.26.11"/> then make fifty n bronze clasps, put the clasps into the loops, and
       join the tent together, to make it one. <verse eID="Exod.26.11"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.26.12" osisID="Exod.26.12"/> The curtain that is left over, the half of the curtain that is
       doubled back, is to hang over the back of the Dwelling, <verse eID="Exod.26.12"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.26.13" osisID="Exod.26.13"/> while the spare foot and a half of the ten cur­tains on each side is
       to hang over the sides of the Dwelling as a covering. <verse eID="Exod.26.13"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.26.14" osisID="Exod.26.14"/> Also, you must make a wrapper of rams’ skins dyed red and of leather,
       to cover up the tent itself. <verse eID="Exod.26.14"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Exod.26.15" osisID="Exod.26.15"/>You must make upright frames for the Dwelling out of acacia wood; <verse eID="Exod.26.15"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.26.16" osisID="Exod.26.16"/> each frame is to be fifteen feet high, by two feet three inches
       broad. <verse eID="Exod.26.16"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.26.17" osisID="Exod.26.17"/> Two pegs are to be clamped to the foot of each frame in the Dwelling. <verse eID="Exod.26.17"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.26.18" osisID="Exod.26.18"/> The frames for the Dwelling are to be as follows: twenty frames for
       the southern side, <verse eID="Exod.26.18"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.26.19" osisID="Exod.26.19"/> with forty silver pedestals under the twenty frames, two pedestals
       under each frame to receive its two pegs, and so on. <verse eID="Exod.26.19"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.26.20" osisID="Exod.26.20"/>
       Twenty frames 20 for the second side, the north
       <milestone type="pb" n="91"/> 
        side, of the Dwelling, <verse eID="Exod.26.20"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.26.21" osisID="Exod.26.21"/> with their forty silver pedestals, two pedestals to each frame. <verse eID="Exod.26.21"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.26.22" osisID="Exod.26.22"/> For the back of the Dwelling, the western side, you must make six
       frames, <verse eID="Exod.26.22"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.26.23" osisID="Exod.26.23"/> with two frames for the corners at the back, <verse eID="Exod.26.23"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.26.24" osisID="Exod.26.24"/> each of these two frames forming a double support and running right
       up to the top-most ring at the corners--<verse eID="Exod.26.24"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.26.25" osisID="Exod.26.25"/>eight frames in all, with their sixteen silver pedestals, two
       pedestals to each frame. <verse eID="Exod.26.25"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.26.26" osisID="Exod.26.26"/> You must also make bars of acacia wood, five for the frames on the
       one side of the Dwelling <verse eID="Exod.26.26"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.26.27" osisID="Exod.26.27"/> and five for the frames on the other side of the Dwelling, with five
       for the frames on the back or western side of the Dwelling; <verse eID="Exod.26.27"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.26.28" osisID="Exod.26.28"/> the middle bar is to run right along the frames, from end to end. <verse eID="Exod.26.28"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.26.29" osisID="Exod.26.29"/> You must overlay the frames with gold, and make gold rings on them
       for the bars, overlaying the bars also with gold. <verse eID="Exod.26.29"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.26.30" osisID="Exod.26.30"/> So shall you erect the Dwelling after the standard shown you on the
       mountain. <verse eID="Exod.26.30"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Exod.26.31" osisID="Exod.26.31"/>You must also make a cur­tain of fine twined linen, violet, purple,
       and scarlet, and em­broidered with designs of kherubs, <verse eID="Exod.26.31"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.26.32" osisID="Exod.26.32"/> hanging it by golden hooks on four columns of acacia wood overlaid
       with gold and resting on four silver pedestals. <verse eID="Exod.26.32"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.26.33" osisID="Exod.26.33"/> This curtain is to be hung inside the clasps, and you must place
       in­side it the ark with the laws, the curtain dividing off the sacred place from the most sacred. <verse eID="Exod.26.33"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.26.34" osisID="Exod.26.34"/> On the ark inside the most sacred place, you must put the cover. <verse eID="Exod.26.34"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.26.35" osisID="Exod.26.35"/>The table is to be placed outside the curtain, with the lampstand
       opposite the table on the south side of the Dwelling--the table being on the north side. <verse eID="Exod.26.35"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.26.36" osisID="Exod.26.36"/> You must also make a veil for the entrance into the Dwelling, of
       fine twined linen, violet, purple, and scarlet, decorated work; <verse eID="Exod.26.36"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.26.37" osisID="Exod.26.37"/> make five columns of acacia wood for the veil, overlaying them with
       gold, make golden hooks for them, and cast five bronze pedestals for them. <verse eID="Exod.26.37"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eId="Exod.26"/>
    <chapter osisId="Exod.27" sId="Exod.27"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Exod.27.1" osisID="Exod.27.1"/>You must make an altar of acacia wood, a square altar, seven and a
       half feet long, seven and a half feet broad, and four and a half feet high. <verse eID="Exod.27.1"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.27.2" osisID="Exod.27.2"/> Put knobs at the four corners, mak­ing them of one piece with the
       altar, and overlay the whole of it with bronze. <verse eID="Exod.27.2"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.27.3" osisID="Exod.27.3"/> You must make all its fittings of bronze, the pans for removing the
       ashes, the shovels, the bowls, the prongs, and the fire-pans. <verse eID="Exod.27.3"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.27.4" osisID="Exod.27.4"/> Also you must make a bronze grating of network, with four bronze
       rings at its four corners, <verse eID="Exod.27.4"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.27.5" osisID="Exod.27.5"/> and place this grating underneath the ledge of the altar, so that it
       comes halfway up the altar. <verse eID="Exod.27.5"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.27.6" osisID="Exod.27.6"/> Make poles of acacia wood for the altar, overlaying them with bronze, <verse eID="Exod.27.6"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.27.7" osisID="Exod.27.7"/> and place the poles in the rings, to run along both sides of the altar
       and let it be carried. <verse eID="Exod.27.7"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.27.8" osisID="Exod.27.8"/> The altar itself you must make hollow, planking it in. Let it be made
       on the pattern shown you on the mountain. <verse eID="Exod.27.8"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Exod.27.9" osisID="Exod.27.9"/>In making the courtyard for the Dwelling, have hangings of fine twined
       linen, a hundred and fifty feet long, for its southern side, <verse eID="Exod.27.9"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.27.10" osisID="Exod.27.10"/> with twenty columns and twenty pedestals of bronze, the hooks and
       the rods for the col­umns being silver.
      <verse eID="Exod.27.10"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.27.11" osisID="Exod.27.11"/> So for the north side, hangings a hundred and fifty feet long,
       with twenty columns and twenty pedestals of bronze, the hooks and the rods for the columns being of silver.
      <verse eID="Exod.27.11"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.27.12" osisID="Exod.27.12"/> For the breadth of the courtyard on its western side there shall be
       hangings seventy-
       <milestone type="pb" n="92"/> 
       five feet long, with ten columns and ten pedestals. <verse eID="Exod.27.12"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.27.13" osisID="Exod.27.13"/> The eastern side of the courtyard shall be seventy-five feet broad; <verse eID="Exod.27.13"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.27.14-Exod.27.15" osisID="Exod.27.14 Exod.27.15"/> on each side of the entrance there shall be hangings twenty-two and
       a half feet long, with three col­umns and three pedestals for them, <verse eID="Exod.27.14-Exod.27.15"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.27.16" osisID="Exod.27.16"/> and the entrance to the courtyard shall have a veil of fine twined
       linen, violet, purple, and scarlet, thirty feet long, decorated work, with four col­umns and four pedestals for
       them. <verse eID="Exod.27.16"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.27.17" osisID="Exod.27.17"/> The columns round the courtyard are to be ringed with silver; their
       hooks are to be sil­ver and their pedestals are to be bronze. <verse eID="Exod.27.17"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.27.18" osisID="Exod.27.18"/> The courtyard is to be a hundred and fifty feet long, seventy-five
       feet broad, and seven and a half feet high, hung round with fine twined linen; the pedestals are to be bronze, <verse eID="Exod.27.18"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.27.19" osisID="Exod.27.19"/> and all the tools used for erecting the Dwelling, like all the
       tent-pegs and such fittings for the court­yard, are to be bronze. <verse eID="Exod.27.19"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Exod.27.20" osisID="Exod.27.20"/>You must order the Israelites to provide you with clear oil, from
       crushed olives, for lighting purposes, that you may fix up a lamp to burn regularly; <verse eID="Exod.27.20"/>
      <verse sID="Exod.27.21" osisID="Exod.27.21"/>Aaron and his sons are to arrange this, evening and morning, before
       the Eternal inside the Trysting tent, outside the curtains that hang in front of the shrine. This is to be a
       standing order, age after age, to be kept by the Israelites. <verse eID="Exod.27.21"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eId="Exod.27"/>
   </div>
