   <div type="book" osisID="Gen">
    <milestone type="pb" n="1"/>
    <p>
     <chapter osisId="Gen.2" sId="Gen.2"/>
      <verse osisID="Gen.2.4" sID="Gen.2.4"/><hi type="small-caps">This</hi> is the story of how the universe was formed. <verse eId="Gen.2.4"/>
     <chapter eId="Gen.2"/>
     <chapter osisId="Gen.1" sId="Gen.1"/>
      <verse sID="Gen.1.1" osisID="Gen.1.1"/>When God began to form the universe, <verse eID="Gen.1.1"/>
      <verse sID="Gen.1.2" osisID="Gen.1.2"/> the world was void and vacant, darkness lay over the abyss; but
       the spirit of God was hovering over the waters, <verse eID="Gen.1.2"/>
      <verse sID="Gen.1.3" osisID="Gen.1.3"/>God said, <q>Let there be light,</q> and there was light. <verse eid="Gen.1.3"/>
      <verse sID="Gen.1.4" osisID="Gen.1.4"/>God saw that the light was good, and he separated the light from the darkness;<verse eid="Gen.1.4"/>
      <verse sID="Gen.1.5" osisID="Gen.1.5"/>God called the light Day and the darkness he called Night. Evening came and
       morn­ing came, making one day. <verse eid="Gen.1.5"/>
      <verse osisID="Gen.1.6" sID="Gen.1.6"/>Then God said, <q>Let there be a Vault between the waters, to divide them</q>;<verse eID="Gen.1.6"/>
      <verse osisID="Gen.1.7" sID="Gen.1.7"/>so God made the Vault, dividing the waters un­der the Vault from the waters <verse eID="Gen.1.7"/>
      <verse osisID="Gen.1.8" sID="Gen.1.8"/> above the Vault, and God called the Vault heaven. Evening came and morning
       came, making the second day. <verse eID="Gen.1.8"/>
      <verse osisID="Gen.1.9" sID="Gen.1.9"/> Then God said, <q>Let the waters below the heaven be gathered into one place, to
       let dry land appear.</q> <verse eID="Gen.1.9"/>
      <verse osisID="Gen.1.10" sID="Gen.1.10"/> And so it was. God called the dry land Earth, and the gath­ered waters he called Sea. <verse eID="Gen.1.10"/>
      <verse osisID="Gen.1.11" sID="Gen.1.11"/>
       God saw that it was good. And God said, <q>Let the earth put out verdure, plants that bear seed and trees yielding fruit of
       every kind, fruit with seed in it.</q>
      <verse eID="Gen.1.11"/>
      <verse osisID="Gen.1.12" sID="Gen.1.12"/> And so it was; the earth brought forth verdure, plants bearing seed of every kind
       and trees yielding fruit of every kind,
       <milestone type="column" n="2"/>
       fruit with seed in it. God saw that it was good.
      <verse eID="Gen.1.12"/>
      <verse osisID="Gen.1.13" sID="Gen.1.13"/> Evening came and morning came, making the third day. <verse eID="Gen.1.13"/>
      <verse osisID="Gen.1.14" sID="Gen.1.14"/> Then God said, <q>Let there be lights in the Vault of heaven to separate day from
       night, to mark out the sacred seasons, the days and the years;
      <verse eID="Gen.1.14"/>
      <verse osisID="Gen.1.15" sID="Gen.1.15"/> let them shine in the Vault of heaven, to shed light on the earth</q>; and so it was. <verse eID="Gen.1.15"/>
      <verse osisID="Gen.1.16" sID="Gen.1.16"/> For God made the two great lights, the greater light to rule the day, the lesser
       light to­gether with the stars to rule the night; <verse eID="Gen.1.16"/>
      <verse osisID="Gen.1.17" sID="Gen.1.17"/> God set them in the Vault of heaven to shed light upon earth, <verse eID="Gen.1.17"/>
      <verse osisID="Gen.1.18" sID="Gen.1.18"/> to rule the day and the night, and to separate light from darkness. And God
       saw that it was good. <verse eID="Gen.1.18"/>
      <verse osisID="Gen.1.19" sID="Gen.1.19"/> Evening came and morning came, making the fourth day. <verse eID="Gen.1.19"/>
      <verse osisID="Gen.1.20" sID="Gen.1.20"/>
       Then God said, <q>Let the waters teem with shoals of living crea­tures, and let birds fly over the earth under the open Vault of heaven.</q>
      <verse eID="Gen.1.20"/>
      <verse osisID="Gen.1.21" sID="Gen.1.21"/> So God formed the great sea-monsters and every kind of living creature that moves,
       with which the waters teem, and also every kind of winged bird. God saw that it was good,
      <verse eID="Gen.1.21"/>
      <verse osisID="Gen.1.22" sID="Gen.1.22"/> and God blessed them; <q>be fruitful,</q> he said, <q>multiply, and fill the waters
       of the sea: let the birds multiply on earth.</q> <verse eID="Gen.1.22"/>
      <verse osisID="Gen.1.23" sID="Gen.1.23"/> Evening came and morning came, making the fifth day. <verse eID="Gen.1.23"/>
    </p>
    <p>
      <verse osisID="Gen.1.24" sID="Gen.1.24"/> Then God said, <q>Let the earth
       <milestone type="pb" n="2"/>
       bring forth every kind of living creature, animals, reptiles, and wild beasts.</q> And so it was.
      <verse eID="Gen.1.24"/>
      <verse osisID="Gen.1.25" sID="Gen.1.25"/> God made every kind of wild beast, every kind of animal, and every kind of reptile;
       and God saw that it was good. <verse eID="Gen.1.25"/>
      <verse osisID="Gen.1.26" sID="Gen.1.26"/> Then said God, <q>Let us make man in our own likeness, to resemble us, with mastery
       over the fish in the sea, the birds of the air, the animals, every wild beast of the earth, and every rep­tile that crawls on
       earth.</q> <verse eID="Gen.1.26"/>
      <verse osisID="Gen.1.27" sID="Gen.1.27"/> So God formed man in his own likeness, in the likeness of God he formed him, male
       and female he formed both. <verse eID="Gen.1.27"/>
      <verse osisID="Gen.1.28" sID="Gen.1.28"/> And God blessed them; God said to them, <q>Be fruitful, multiply, fill the earth
       and subdue it, mastering the fish in the sea, the birds of the air, and every living crea­ture that crawls on earth.</q> <verse eID="Gen.1.28"/>
      <verse osisID="Gen.1.29" sID="Gen.1.29"/> God also said, <q>See, I give you every plant that bears seed all over the earth,
       and every tree with seed in its fruit; be that your food. <verse eID="Gen.1.29"/>
      <verse osisID="Gen.1.30" sID="Gen.1.30"/> To every wild beast on earth, to every bird of the air, and to every living
       creature that crawls on earth, I give all the green growth for food.</q> And so it was. <verse eID="Gen.1.30"/>
      <verse osisID="Gen.1.31" sID="Gen.1.31"/> God saw all that he had made, and very good it was. Evening came and morning came,
       making the sixth day. <verse eID="Gen.1.31"/>
    </p>
     <chapter eId="Gen.1"/>
     <chapter osisId="Gen.2" sId="Gen.2"/>
      <p>
       <verse osisID="Gen.2.1" sID="Gen.2.1"/> Thus was the universe and its array all finished. <verse eId="Gen.2.1"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.2.2" sID="Gen.2.2"/> On the seventh day God ceased his work, he desisted from working on the seventh day; <verse eId="Gen.2.2"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.2.3" sID="Gen.2.3"/> so God blessed and consecrated the seventh day, because on it he desisted from all
        his work of creation. <verse eId="Gen.2.3"/>
      </p>
      <hi type="italic">
       <p>
       <milestone type="column" n="2"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.2.4" sID="Gen.2.4"/> At the time when God the Eternal made earth and heaven, <verse eId="Gen.2.4"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.2.5" sID="Gen.2.5"/> there was as yet no shrub on earth, and no plant had sprung up; for God the
         Eternal had not sent rain on earth, and there was no one to till the soil— <verse eId="Gen.2.5"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.2.6" sID="Gen.2.6"/> though a mist used to rise from the earth and water all the surface of the ground. <verse eId="Gen.2.6"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.2.7" sID="Gen.2.7"/> Then God the Eternal moulded man from the dust of the ground, breathing into his
         nostrils the breath of life; this was how man became a living being. <verse eId="Gen.2.7"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.2.8" sID="Gen.2.8"/> In the land of Eden, to the far east, God the Eternal then planted a park, where
         he put the man whom he had moulded. <verse eId="Gen.2.8"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.2.9" sID="Gen.2.9"/> And from the ground God the Eter­nal made all sorts of trees to grow that were
         delightful to see and good to eat, with the tree of life and the tree that yields knowl­edge of good and evil in the
         cen­tre of the park. <verse eId="Gen.2.9"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.2.10" sID="Gen.2.10"/> From Eden a river flowed to water the park, which on leaving the park branched
         into four streams; <verse eId="Gen.2.10"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.2.11" sID="Gen.2.11"/> the name of the first is Pison (the one which flows all round the land of
         Havilah, where there is gold—<verse eId="Gen.2.11"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.2.12" sID="Gen.2.12"/> fine gold in that land—with pearls and beryls), <verse eId="Gen.2.12"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.2.13" sID="Gen.2.13"/> the name of the second is Gihon (the one which flows all round the land of Ethiopia), <verse eId="Gen.2.13"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.2.14" sID="Gen.2.14"/> the name of the third is Hiddekel (the one which flows west of Assyria), and the
         fourth river is the Eu­phrates. <verse eId="Gen.2.14"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.2.15" sID="Gen.2.15"/>God the Eternal took man and put him in the park of Eden, to till it and to guard it.<verse eId="Gen.2.15"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.2.16" sID="Gen.2.16"/> And God the Eternal laid a command upon the man: <q>You are free to eat from any
         tree in the park,</q> he said,<q> <verse eId="Gen.2.16"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.2.17" sID="Gen.2.17"/> but you must not eat from the tree that yields knowledge of good and evil, for
         on the day you eat from that tree you shall die.</q> <verse eId="Gen.2.17"/>
       </p>
       <p>
        <verse osisID="Gen.2.18" sID="Gen.2.18"/> Then said God the Eternal, <q>It is not good for man to be alone; I will make a
         helper to suit him.</q> <verse eId="Gen.2.18"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.2.19" sID="Gen.2.19"/> So from the ground God shaped every wild beast and every bird
        <milestone type="pb" n="3"/>
         of the air, bringing them to the man to see what he would call them; whatever the man called any living creature, that
         was to be its name. <verse eId="Gen.2.19"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.2.20" sID="Gen.2.20"/> So the man named all the animals and the birds and every wild beast, but no
         helper could be found to suit man himself. <verse eId="Gen.2.20"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.2.21" sID="Gen.2.21"/>Then God the Eternal made a deep sleep to fall upon the man; while he slept, he
         took one of his ribs, closing up the flesh in its place; <verse eId="Gen.2.21"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.2.22" sID="Gen.2.22"/> the rib he had taken from the man God the Eternal shaped into a woman, and
         brought her to the man. <verse eId="Gen.2.22"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.2.23" sID="Gen.2.23"/> Then said the man,
         <lg>
          <l> This, this at last, is bone of my bones, </l>
          <l> and flesh of my own flesh:</l>
          <l> this shall be called Wo-man, </l>
          <l> for from man was she taken! </l>
         </lg>
        <verse eId="Gen.2.23"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.2.24" sID="Gen.2.24"/> (This is why a man leaves his father and mother and cleaves to his wife, till
         they become one flesh.) <verse eId="Gen.2.24"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.2.25" sID="Gen.2.25"/> Both of them, the man and his wife, were naked, but they felt no shame. <verse eId="Gen.2.25"/>
       </p>
      </hi>
     <chapter eId="Gen.2"/>
     <chapter osisId="Gen.3" sId="Gen.3"/>
      <hi>
       <p>
        <verse osisID="Gen.3.1" sID="Gen.3.1"/> Now the serpent was cun­ning, more cunning than any creature that God the Eternal
         had made; he said to the woman, <q>And so God has said that you are not to eat fruit from any tree in the park?</q> <verse eId="Gen.3.1"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.3.2" sID="Gen.3.2"/>
         The woman said to the serpent, <q>We can eat fruit from the trees in the park,<verse eId="Gen.3.2"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.3.3" sID="Gen.3.3"/> but, as for the tree in the centre of the park, God has said, <q>You must not eat
        from it, you must not touch it, lest you die.</q> </q> <verse eId="Gen.3.3"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.3.4" sID="Gen.3.4"/> <q>No,</q> said the serpent to the woman, <q>you shall not die; <verse eId="Gen.3.4"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.3.5" sID="Gen.3.5"/>
         God knows that on the day you eat from it your eyes will be opened and you will be like gods, knowing good and evil.</q>
        <verse eId="Gen.3.5"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.3.6" sID="Gen.3.6"/> So, when the woman saw that the tree was good to eat and delight­ful to see,
         desirable to look upon, she took some of the fruit and
         <milestone type="column" n="2"/>
         ate it; she also gave some to her husband, and he ate. <verse eId="Gen.3.6"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.3.7" sID="Gen.3.7"/> Then the eyes of both were opened, and they realized that they were naked; so they
         stitched some fig-leaves together and made them­selves girdles. <verse eId="Gen.3.7"/>
       </p>
       <p>
        <verse osisID="Gen.3.8" sID="Gen.3.8"/> In the cool of the day, when they heard the sound of God the Eternal walking in
         the park, the man and his wife hid from the presence of God the Eternal among the trees of the park; <verse eId="Gen.3.8"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.3.9" sID="Gen.3.9"/> but God the Eternal called to the man and asked him, <q>Where are you?</q> <verse eId="Gen.3.9"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.3.10" sID="Gen.3.10"/>
         <q>I heard thy sound within the park,</q>he answered, <q>and I was afraid, because I was naked; so I hid myself.</q> <verse eId="Gen.3.10"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.3.11" sID="Gen.3.11"/>He said, <q>Who told you that you were naked? Have you been eating from the tree
         which I forbade you to eat?</q> <verse eId="Gen.3.11"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.3.12" sID="Gen.3.12"/> The man is said, <q>The woman thou gavest me as a companion, she gave me some
         fruit from the tree, and I ate it.</q> <verse eId="Gen.3.12"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.3.13" sID="Gen.3.13"/> Then God the Eternal said to the woman, <q>What is this that you have done?</q>
        The wom­an said, <q>I ate because the ser­pent beguiled me.</q> <verse eId="Gen.3.13"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.3.14" sID="Gen.3.14"/>
         So God the Eternal said to the serpent,<q>Since you have done this,
         <lq>
          <l>
           A curse on you of all creatures! a curse
          </l>
          <l>
           on you of all beasts! 
          </l>
          <l>
           On your belly shall you crawl
          </l>
          <l>
           and eat dust all your days! <verse eId="Gen.3.14"/>
          </l>
          <l>
           <verse osisID="Gen.3.15" sID="Gen.3.15"/> And I will set a feud between you and the woman,
          </l>
          <l>
           between your brood and hers:
          </l>
          <l>
           they shall strike at your head,
          </l>
          <l>
           and you shall strike at their heel. <verse eId="Gen.3.15"/>
          </l>
         </lq></q>
        <verse osisID="Gen.3.16" sID="Gen.3.16"/> To the woman he said,<q>
         <lq>
          <l>
           I will make child-birth a sore pain for you,
          </l>
          <l>
           you shall have pangs in bearing;
          </l>
          <l>
           yet you shall crave to have your husband,
          </l>
          <l>
            and he shall master you.
          </l>
         </lq></q>
        <verse eId="Gen.3.16"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.3.17" sID="Gen.3.17"/> To the man he said, <q>Since you have listened to what your wife
         <milestone type="pb" n="4"/>
         said, eating from the tree of which I forbade you to eat,
         <lq>
          <l>
           Cursed is the ground on your ac­count,
          </l>
          <l>
           you shall suffer all your life, as you win food from it;
          </l>
        <verse eId="Gen.3.17"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.3.18" sID="Gen.3.18"/>
          <l>
           thorns and thistles shall it bear for you,
          </l>
          <l>
           and you must eat plants of the field;
          </l>
        <verse eId="Gen.3.18"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.3.19" sID="Gen.3.19"/>
          <l>
           in the sweat of your brow you shall earn your food,
          </l>
          <l>
           till you return to the ground from which you were taken;
          </l>
          <l>
           for dust you are, and you return to dust.
          </l>
        </lq></q>
        <verse eId="Gen.3.19"/>
       </p>
      </hi>
      <p>
       <verse osisID="Gen.3.20" sID="Gen.3.20"/> [[The man called the name of his wife Eve (Life), because she was the mother of
        all living persons.]] <verse eId="Gen.3.20"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.3.21" sID="Gen.3.21"/> [[And God the Eternal made skin tunics for the man and his wife, and clothed
        them.]] <verse eId="Gen.3.21"/>
       <hi type="italic">
        <verse osisID="Gen.3.22" sID="Gen.3.22"/>Then said God the Eternal, <q>Man has become like one of us, he knows good and
         evil. He might reach his hand now to the tree of life also, and by eating of it live for ever!</q> <verse eId="Gen.3.22"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.3.23" sID="Gen.3.23"/> So God the Eternal expelled him from the park of Eden, to till the ground from
         which he had been taken; <verse eId="Gen.3.23"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.3.24" sID="Gen.3.24"/> he drove the man out, and set kherubs at the east of the park of Eden, with the
         blade of a sword flashing in every direc­tion, to guard the path to the tree of life.
        <verse eId="Gen.3.24"/>
       </hi>
      </p>
     <chapter eId="Gen.3"/>
     <chapter osisId="Gen.4" sId="Gen.4"/>
      <hi type="italic">
       <p>
        <verse osisID="Gen.4.1" sID="Gen.4.1"/> Now the man had inter­course with his wife Eve; she conceived and bore Cain (Got),
         saying, “I have got a man from the Eternal.” <verse eId="Gen.4.1"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.4.2" sID="Gen.4.2"/> Next she bore his brother Abel. Abel was a shepherd, while Cain was a farmer. <verse eId="Gen.4.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
        <verse osisID="Gen.4.3" sID="Gen.4.3"/> In course of time, Cain brought some produce of the ground as a present to the
         Eternal, <verse eId="Gen.4.3"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.4.4" sID="Gen.4.4"/> while Abel brought some of the first­born from his flock, that is, some fat slices
         from them. The Eter­nal favoured Abel and his pres­-
         <milestone type="column" n="2"/>
         ent;
        <verse eId="Gen.4.4"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.4.5" sID="Gen.4.5"/> he did not favour Cain and his. So Cain was furious and downcast. <verse eId="Gen.4.5"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.4.6" sID="Gen.4.6"/> <q>Why are you furious?</q> said the Eternal to Cain, <q>why are you downcast? <verse eId="Gen.4.6"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.4.7" sID="Gen.4.7"/> If your heart is honest, you would surely look bright? If you are sullen, sin is
         lying in wait for you, eager to be at you—yet you ought to master it.</q> <verse eId="Gen.4.7"/>
       </p>
       <p>
        <verse osisID="Gen.4.8" sID="Gen.4.8"/> But Cain quarrelled with his brother Abel, and, when they were out in the open
         country, Cain attacked his brother Abel and killed him. <verse eId="Gen.4.8"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.4.9" sID="Gen.4.9"/> Then the Eternal asked Cain, <q>Where is your brother Abel?</q> <q>How do I
         know?</q> said Cain; <q>am I a shep­herd to my brother?</q>
        <verse eId="Gen.4.9"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.4.10" sID="Gen.4.10"/> He answered, <q>What have you done? Listen, your brother s blood is crying to
         me from the soil! <verse eId="Gen.4.10"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.4.11" sID="Gen.4.11"/>
         And now you are cursed off the coun­try that has opened to swallow down the brothers blood you shed;
        <verse eId="Gen.4.11"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.4.12" sID="Gen.4.12"/>
         after this, the fields will not yield you their produce, when you till them; you must go stumbling and straying over the earth.</q>
        <verse eId="Gen.4.12"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.4.13" sID="Gen.4.13"/> Cain said to the Eternal, <q>My punishment is more than I can bear. <verse eId="Gen.4.13"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.4.14" sID="Gen.4.14"/> Thou art expelling me from the country, banishing me from thy sight; I must go
         stum­bling and straying over the earth, and anyone who catches me will kill me.</q> <verse eId="Gen.4.14"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.4.15" sID="Gen.4.15"/> So the Eternal said to him, <q>Well then, whoever kills Cain, seven times over
         shall the murder be avenged</q>; and the Eternal set a mark on Cain, to prevent anyone from catching and killing him.
        <verse eId="Gen.4.15"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.4.16" sID="Gen.4.16"/> Then Cain left the presence of the Eternal to stay in Nod (Wonderland), east
         of Eden. <verse eId="Gen.4.16"/>
       </p>
       <p>
        <verse osisID="Gen.4.17" sID="Gen.4.17"/> When Cain had intercourse with his wife, she conceived and bore Hanok; Cain
         built a town and called it after his son Hanok. <verse eId="Gen.4.17"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.4.18" sID="Gen.4.18"/> Irad was born to Hanok, and
         <milestone type="pb" n="5"/>
         Irad was the father of Mehujael, Mehujael the father of Methu- shael, and Methushael the father of Lemek. <verse eId="Gen.4.18"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.4.19" sID="Gen.4.19"/> Lemek married two wives; the name of one was Adah, the name of the other Zillah. <verse eId="Gen.4.19"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.4.20" sID="Gen.4.20"/> (Adah bore Jabal, the ancestor of shepherds who live in tents: <verse eId="Gen.4.20"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.4.21" sID="Gen.4.21"/> his brother’s name was Jubal, the ancestor of all who play the lyre and the
         pipe. <verse eId="Gen.4.21"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.4.22" sID="Gen.4.22"/>Zillah bore Tubal-Cain, the smith who forged bronze and iron tools, and
         Tubal-Cain’s sister was Naamah.) <verse eId="Gen.4.22"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.4.23" sID="Gen.4.23"/> Lemek said to his wives,<q>
         <lg>
          <l> Adah and Zillah, listen to me, </l>
          <l> O ’wives of Lemek, hear what I say: </l>
          <l> The man who wounds me, him I slay, </l>
          <l> I slay a boy for a blow: </l>
          <verse eId="Gen.4.23"/>
          <verse osisID="Gen.4.24" sID="Gen.4.24"/>
          <l> if Cain be avenged seven times, </l>
          <l>
           then seventy and seven times Lemek!
          </l>
         </lg> </q>
        <verse eId="Gen.4.24"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.4.25" sID="Gen.4.25"/>Adam again had intercourse with his wife, who bore a son and called him Seth,
         saying, <q>God has set up another child for me instead of Abel, whom Cain killed.</q>
        <verse eId="Gen.4.25"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.4.26" sID="Gen.4.26"/> Seth also had a son born to him, called Enosh; he was the first to worship the
         Eternal by name. <verse eId="Gen.4.26"/>
       </p>
      </hi>
     <chapter eId="Gen.4"/>
     <chapter osisId="Gen.5" sId="Gen.5"/>
      <p>
       <verse osisID="Gen.5.1" sID="Gen.5.1"/> Here is the list of Adam’s descendants. When God formed man, he made him to
        resemble God; <verse eId="Gen.5.1"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.5.2" sID="Gen.5.2"/> male and female, he formed them both and blessed them, calling them human on the
        day when they were formed. <verse eId="Gen.5.2"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.5.3" sID="Gen.5.3"/> After living a hundred and thirty years Adam became the father of a son resembling
        him­self, in his own likeness, whom he called Seth;
       <verse eId="Gen.5.3"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.5.4" sID="Gen.5.4"/> Adam lived eight hundred years after the birth of Seth, and was the father of
        sons and daughters. <verse eId="Gen.5.4"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.5.5" sID="Gen.5.5"/>
        Thus Adam lived for nine hundred and thirty years in all; then he died.
       <verse eId="Gen.5.5"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.5.6" sID="Gen.5.6"/>
        After living a hundred and five years Seth became 
        <milestone type="column" n="2"/>
       <verse eId="Gen.5.6"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.5.7" sID="Gen.5.7"/> the father of Enosh; Seth lived eight hundred and seven years after the birth of
        Enosh, and was the father of sons and daughters. <verse eId="Gen.5.7"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.5.8" sID="Gen.5.8"/> Thus Seth lived for nine hundred and twelve years in all; then he died. <verse eId="Gen.5.8"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.5.9" sID="Gen.5.9"/> After living ninety years Enosh be­came the father of Kenan; <verse eId="Gen.5.9"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.5.10" sID="Gen.5.10"/> Enosh lived eight hundred and fifteen years after the birth of Kenan, and was
        the father of sons and daughters. <verse eId="Gen.5.10"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.5.11" sID="Gen.5.11"/> Thus Enosh lived for nine hundred and five years in all; then he died. <verse eId="Gen.5.11"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.5.12" sID="Gen.5.12"/> After living seventy years Kenan became the father of Mahalalel; <verse eId="Gen.5.12"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.5.13" sID="Gen.5.13"/> Kenan lived eight hundred and forty years after the birth of Mahalalel, and was
        the father of sons and daughters. <verse eId="Gen.5.13"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.5.14" sID="Gen.5.14"/> Thus Kenan lived for nine hundred and ten years in all; then he died. <verse eId="Gen.5.14"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.5.15" sID="Gen.5.15"/> After living sixty-five years Mahalalel became the father of Jared; <verse eId="Gen.5.15"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.5.16" sID="Gen.5.16"/> Mahalalel lived eight hundred and thirty years after the birth of Jared, and was
        the father of sons and daughters. <verse eId="Gen.5.16"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.5.17" sID="Gen.5.17"/> Thus Mahalalel lived for eight hundred and ninety-five years in all; then he
        died. <verse eId="Gen.5.17"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.5.18" sID="Gen.5.18"/> After living a hundred and sixty-two years Jared became the father of Hanok; <verse eId="Gen.5.18"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.5.19" sID="Gen.5.19"/> Jared lived eight hundred years after the birth of Hanok, and was the father of
        sons and daughters. <verse eId="Gen.5.19"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.5.20" sID="Gen.5.20"/> Thus Jared lived for nine hundred and sixty-two years in all; then he died. <verse eId="Gen.5.20"/>
      </p>
      <p>
       <verse osisID="Gen.5.21" sID="Gen.5.21"/>
        After living sixty-five years Hanok became the father of Me­thuselah.
       <verse eId="Gen.5.21"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.5.22" sID="Gen.5.22"/>
        For three hundred years Hanok lived close to God, after the birth of Methuselah, and was the father of sons and daughters.
       <verse eId="Gen.5.22"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.5.23" sID="Gen.5.23"/> Thus Hanok lived for three hundred and sixty-five years in all; <verse eId="Gen.5.23"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.5.24" sID="Gen.5.24"/>Hanok lived close to God, and then he disappeared,
        <milestone type="pb" n="6"/>
        for God took him away. <verse eId="Gen.5.24"/>
      </p>
      <p>
       <verse osisID="Gen.5.25" sID="Gen.5.25"/> After living a hundred and eighty-seven years Methuselah became the father of Lemek; <verse eId="Gen.5.25"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.5.26" sID="Gen.5.26"/> Methuselah lived seven hun­dred and eighty-two years after the birth of Lemek, and
        was the father of sons and daughters. <verse eId="Gen.5.26"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.5.27" sID="Gen.5.27"/> Thus Methuselah lived for nine hundred and sixty-nine years in all; then he died. <verse eId="Gen.5.27"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.5.28" sID="Gen.5.28"/> After liv­ing a hundred and eighty-two years Lemek became the father of a son, <verse eId="Gen.5.28"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.5.29" sID="Gen.5.29"/> whom he called Noah, saying, <q>Now we shall <q>know a</q> relief from our
        labour and from our toil on the ground that the Eternal cursed.</q>
       <verse eId="Gen.5.29"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.5.30" sID="Gen.5.30"/> Lemek lived five hundred and ninety-five years after the birth of Noah, and was
        the father of sons and daughters. <verse eId="Gen.5.30"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.5.31" sID="Gen.5.31"/> Thus Lemek lived for seven hundred and seventy-seven years in all; then he died. <verse eId="Gen.5.31"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.5.32" sID="Gen.5.32"/> After living five hundred years Noah became the father of Shem, Ham, and Japheth. <verse eId="Gen.5.32"/>
      </p>
     <chapter eId="Gen.5"/>
     <chapter osisId="Gen.6" sId="Gen.6"/>
      <hi type="italic">
       <p>
        <verse osisID="Gen.6.1" sID="Gen.6.1"/> Now when men began to multiply over all the world and had daughters born to them, <verse eId="Gen.6.1"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.6.2" sID="Gen.6.2"/> the angels noticed that the daughters of men were beauti­ful, and they married any
         one of them that they chose. <verse eId="Gen.6.2"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.6.3" sID="Gen.6.3"/> So the Eternal said, <q>Human creatures are but flesh; my spirit is not to be
         immortal in them; they shall not live more than a hundred 4 and twenty years.</q> <verse eId="Gen.6.3"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.6.4" sID="Gen.6.4"/> (It was in these days that the Nephilim giants arose on earth, as well as
         afterwards whenever angels had intercourse with the daughters of men and had children born to them; these were the heroes
         who were famous in the days of old.) <verse eId="Gen.6.4"/>
       </p>
       <p>
        <verse osisID="Gen.6.5" sID="Gen.6.5"/> When the Eternal saw that the wickedness of man on earth was great, and that man’s
         mind was never bent on anything but evil, <verse eId="Gen.6.5"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.6.6" sID="Gen.6.6"/> the Eternal was sorry that he
        <milestone type="column" n="2"/>
        had ever made man on the earth; it was a grief to him. <verse eId="Gen.6.6"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.6.7" sID="Gen.6.7"/>So the Eternal said, <q>I will blot him off the earth, this man that I have formed—
         man and beast and reptile and bird; I am sorry that I ever made them.</q> <verse eId="Gen.6.7"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.6.8" sID="Gen.6.8"/> However, Noah had found favour with the Eternal. <verse eId="Gen.6.8"/>
       </p>
      </hi>
      <p>
       <verse osisID="Gen.6.9" sID="Gen.6.9"/> Here are the descendants of Noah. Noah was an upright man, blameless among the men
        of his day; Noah lived close to God. <verse eId="Gen.6.9"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.6.10" sID="Gen.6.10"/> Noah was the father of 10 three sons, Shem, Ham, and Japheth. <verse eId="Gen.6.10"/>
      </p>
      <p>
       <verse osisID="Gen.6.11" sID="Gen.6.11"/> Now in God's sight the earth was corrupt, the earth was full of insolence and
        outrage; <verse eId="Gen.6.11"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.6.12" sID="Gen.6.12"/> God saw that the earth was corrupt, for every human being upon earth had
        corrupted his life. <verse eId="Gen.6.12"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.6.13" sID="Gen.6.13"/> So God said to Noah, <q>I have re­solved to put an end to every human being, for
        they have filled the earth with insolence and out­rage; I will destroy them and the earth together. <verse eId="Gen.6.13"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.6.14" sID="Gen.6.14"/> Build a barge of cypress wood, build cabins inside the barge, and cover it with
        pitch, inside and outside. <verse eId="Gen.6.14"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.6.15" sID="Gen.6.15"/> This is how you are to build it: the barge is to be four hundred and fifty feet
        long, sev­enty-five feet broad, and forty- five feet high; <verse eId="Gen.6.15"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.6.16" sID="Gen.6.16"/> you must put windows in the barge, eighteen inches from the roof, and make a door
        in the side of the barge; also put three decks in it. <verse eId="Gen.6.16"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.6.17" sID="Gen.6.17"/> For I am sending a deluge of water on the earth, to destroy every liv­ing
        creature under heaven; every thing on earth shall perish. <verse eId="Gen.6.17"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.6.18" sID="Gen.6.18"/>
        But I will make a compact of my own with you; you shall enter the barge, you and your sons and your wife and your sons’ wives along with you.
       <verse eId="Gen.6.18"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.6.19" sID="Gen.6.19"/>
        And you shall 19 take into the barge two living creatures of every kind, to keep
        <milestone type="pb" n="7"/>
        them alive along with you; one is to be a male, and one a female. <verse eId="Gen.6.19"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.6.20" sID="Gen.6.20"/>
        Two of every kind, bird, beast, and reptile, are to join you, that they may be kept alive.
       <verse eId="Gen.6.20"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.6.21" sID="Gen.6.21"/> Go and gather anything in the shape of food, to be food for you and for them.</q> <verse eId="Gen.6.21"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.6.22" sID="Gen.6.22"/> Noah did so; he did all that God had ordered him. <verse eId="Gen.6.22"/>
      </p>
     <chapter eId="Gen.6"/>
   </div>
