   <div type="book" osisID="Gen">
    <milestone type="pb" n="1"/>
    <p>
     <chapter osisId="Gen.2" sId="Gen.2"/>
      <verse osisID="Gen.2.4" sID="Gen.2.4"/><hi type="small-caps">This</hi> is the story of how the universe was formed. <verse eId="Gen.2.4"/>
     <chapter eId="Gen.2"/>
     <chapter osisId="Gen.1" sId="Gen.1"/>
      <verse sID="Gen.1.1" osisID="Gen.1.1"/>When God began to form the universe, <verse eID="Gen.1.1"/>
      <verse sID="Gen.1.2" osisID="Gen.1.2"/> the world was void and vacant, darkness lay over the abyss; but
       the spirit of God was hovering over the waters, <verse eID="Gen.1.2"/>
      <verse sID="Gen.1.3" osisID="Gen.1.3"/>God said, <q>Let there be light,</q> and there was light. <verse eid="Gen.1.3"/>
      <verse sID="Gen.1.4" osisID="Gen.1.4"/>God saw that the light was good, and he separated the light from the darkness;<verse eid="Gen.1.4"/>
      <verse sID="Gen.1.5" osisID="Gen.1.5"/>God called the light Day and the darkness he called Night. Evening came and
       morn­ing came, making one day. <verse eid="Gen.1.5"/>
      <verse osisID="Gen.1.6" sID="Gen.1.6"/>Then God said, <q>Let there be a Vault between the waters, to divide them</q>;<verse eID="Gen.1.6"/>
      <verse osisID="Gen.1.7" sID="Gen.1.7"/>so God made the Vault, dividing the waters un­der the Vault from the waters <verse eID="Gen.1.7"/>
      <verse osisID="Gen.1.8" sID="Gen.1.8"/> above the Vault, and God called the Vault heaven. Evening came and morning
       came, making the second day. <verse eID="Gen.1.8"/>
      <verse osisID="Gen.1.9" sID="Gen.1.9"/> Then God said, <q>Let the waters below the heaven be gathered into one place, to
       let dry land appear.</q> <verse eID="Gen.1.9"/>
      <verse osisID="Gen.1.10" sID="Gen.1.10"/> And so it was. God called the dry land Earth, and the gath­ered waters he called Sea. <verse eID="Gen.1.10"/>
      <verse osisID="Gen.1.11" sID="Gen.1.11"/>
       God saw that it was good. And God said, <q>Let the earth put out verdure, plants that bear seed and trees yielding fruit of
       every kind, fruit with seed in it.</q>
      <verse eID="Gen.1.11"/>
      <verse osisID="Gen.1.12" sID="Gen.1.12"/> And so it was; the earth brought forth verdure, plants bearing seed of every kind
       and trees yielding fruit of every kind,
       <milestone type="column" n="2"/>
       fruit with seed in it. God saw that it was good.
      <verse eID="Gen.1.12"/>
      <verse osisID="Gen.1.13" sID="Gen.1.13"/> Evening came and morning came, making the third day. <verse eID="Gen.1.13"/>
      <verse osisID="Gen.1.14" sID="Gen.1.14"/> Then God said, <q>Let there be lights in the Vault of heaven to separate day from
       night, to mark out the sacred seasons, the days and the years;
      <verse eID="Gen.1.14"/>
      <verse osisID="Gen.1.15" sID="Gen.1.15"/> let them shine in the Vault of heaven, to shed light on the earth</q>; and so it was. <verse eID="Gen.1.15"/>
      <verse osisID="Gen.1.16" sID="Gen.1.16"/> For God made the two great lights, the greater light to rule the day, the lesser
       light to­gether with the stars to rule the night; <verse eID="Gen.1.16"/>
      <verse osisID="Gen.1.17" sID="Gen.1.17"/> God set them in the Vault of heaven to shed light upon earth, <verse eID="Gen.1.17"/>
      <verse osisID="Gen.1.18" sID="Gen.1.18"/> to rule the day and the night, and to separate light from darkness. And God
       saw that it was good. <verse eID="Gen.1.18"/>
      <verse osisID="Gen.1.19" sID="Gen.1.19"/> Evening came and morning came, making the fourth day. <verse eID="Gen.1.19"/>
      <verse osisID="Gen.1.20" sID="Gen.1.20"/>
       Then God said, <q>Let the waters teem with shoals of living crea­tures, and let birds fly over the earth under the open Vault of heaven.</q>
      <verse eID="Gen.1.20"/>
      <verse osisID="Gen.1.21" sID="Gen.1.21"/> So God formed the great sea-monsters and every kind of living creature that moves,
       with which the waters teem, and also every kind of winged bird. God saw that it was good,
      <verse eID="Gen.1.21"/>
      <verse osisID="Gen.1.22" sID="Gen.1.22"/> and God blessed them; <q>be fruitful,</q> he said, <q>multiply, and fill the waters
       of the sea: let the birds multiply on earth.</q> <verse eID="Gen.1.22"/>
      <verse osisID="Gen.1.23" sID="Gen.1.23"/> Evening came and morning came, making the fifth day. <verse eID="Gen.1.23"/>
    </p>
    <p>
      <verse osisID="Gen.1.24" sID="Gen.1.24"/> Then God said, <q>Let the earth
       <milestone type="pb" n="2"/>
       bring forth every kind of living creature, animals, reptiles, and wild beasts.</q> And so it was.
      <verse eID="Gen.1.24"/>
      <verse osisID="Gen.1.25" sID="Gen.1.25"/> God made every kind of wild beast, every kind of animal, and every kind of reptile;
       and God saw that it was good. <verse eID="Gen.1.25"/>
      <verse osisID="Gen.1.26" sID="Gen.1.26"/> Then said God, <q>Let us make man in our own likeness, to resemble us, with mastery
       over the fish in the sea, the birds of the air, the animals, every wild beast of the earth, and every rep­tile that crawls on
       earth.</q> <verse eID="Gen.1.26"/>
      <verse osisID="Gen.1.27" sID="Gen.1.27"/> So God formed man in his own likeness, in the likeness of God he formed him, male
       and female he formed both. <verse eID="Gen.1.27"/>
      <verse osisID="Gen.1.28" sID="Gen.1.28"/> And God blessed them; God said to them, <q>Be fruitful, multiply, fill the earth
       and subdue it, mastering the fish in the sea, the birds of the air, and every living crea­ture that crawls on earth.</q> <verse eID="Gen.1.28"/>
      <verse osisID="Gen.1.29" sID="Gen.1.29"/> God also said, <q>See, I give you every plant that bears seed all over the earth,
       and every tree with seed in its fruit; be that your food. <verse eID="Gen.1.29"/>
      <verse osisID="Gen.1.30" sID="Gen.1.30"/> To every wild beast on earth, to every bird of the air, and to every living
       creature that crawls on earth, I give all the green growth for food.</q> And so it was. <verse eID="Gen.1.30"/>
      <verse osisID="Gen.1.31" sID="Gen.1.31"/> God saw all that he had made, and very good it was. Evening came and morning came,
       making the sixth day. <verse eID="Gen.1.31"/>
    </p>
     <chapter eId="Gen.1"/>
     <chapter osisId="Gen.2" sId="Gen.2"/>
      <p>
       <verse osisID="Gen.2.1" sID="Gen.2.1"/> Thus was the universe and its array all finished. <verse eId="Gen.2.1"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.2.2" sID="Gen.2.2"/> On the seventh day God ceased his work, he desisted from working on the seventh day; <verse eId="Gen.2.2"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.2.3" sID="Gen.2.3"/> so God blessed and consecrated the seventh day, because on it he desisted from all
        his work of creation. <verse eId="Gen.2.3"/>
      </p>
      <hi type="italic">
       <p>
       <milestone type="column" n="2"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.2.4" sID="Gen.2.4"/> At the time when God the Eternal made earth and heaven, <verse eId="Gen.2.4"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.2.5" sID="Gen.2.5"/> there was as yet no shrub on earth, and no plant had sprung up; for God the
         Eternal had not sent rain on earth, and there was no one to till the soil— <verse eId="Gen.2.5"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.2.6" sID="Gen.2.6"/> though a mist used to rise from the earth and water all the surface of the ground. <verse eId="Gen.2.6"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.2.7" sID="Gen.2.7"/> Then God the Eternal moulded man from the dust of the ground, breathing into his
         nostrils the breath of life; this was how man became a living being. <verse eId="Gen.2.7"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.2.8" sID="Gen.2.8"/> In the land of Eden, to the far east, God the Eternal then planted a park, where
         he put the man whom he had moulded. <verse eId="Gen.2.8"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.2.9" sID="Gen.2.9"/> And from the ground God the Eter­nal made all sorts of trees to grow that were
         delightful to see and good to eat, with the tree of life and the tree that yields knowl­edge of good and evil in the
         cen­tre of the park. <verse eId="Gen.2.9"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.2.10" sID="Gen.2.10"/> From Eden a river flowed to water the park, which on leaving the park branched
         into four streams; <verse eId="Gen.2.10"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.2.11" sID="Gen.2.11"/> the name of the first is Pison (the one which flows all round the land of
         Havilah, where there is gold—<verse eId="Gen.2.11"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.2.12" sID="Gen.2.12"/> fine gold in that land—with pearls and beryls), <verse eId="Gen.2.12"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.2.13" sID="Gen.2.13"/> the name of the second is Gihon (the one which flows all round the land of Ethiopia), <verse eId="Gen.2.13"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.2.14" sID="Gen.2.14"/> the name of the third is Hiddekel (the one which flows west of Assyria), and the
         fourth river is the Eu­phrates. <verse eId="Gen.2.14"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.2.15" sID="Gen.2.15"/>God the Eternal took man and put him in the park of Eden, to till it and to guard it.<verse eId="Gen.2.15"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.2.16" sID="Gen.2.16"/> And God the Eternal laid a command upon the man: <q>You are free to eat from any
         tree in the park,</q> he said,<q> <verse eId="Gen.2.16"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.2.17" sID="Gen.2.17"/> but you must not eat from the tree that yields knowledge of good and evil, for
         on the day you eat from that tree you shall die.</q> <verse eId="Gen.2.17"/>
       </p>
       <p>
        <verse osisID="Gen.2.18" sID="Gen.2.18"/> Then said God the Eternal, <q>It is not good for man to be alone; I will make a
         helper to suit him.</q> <verse eId="Gen.2.18"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.2.19" sID="Gen.2.19"/> So from the ground God shaped every wild beast and every bird
        <milestone type="pb" n="3"/>
         of the air, bringing them to the man to see what he would call them; whatever the man called any living creature, that
         was to be its name. <verse eId="Gen.2.19"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.2.20" sID="Gen.2.20"/> So the man named all the animals and the birds and every wild beast, but no
         helper could be found to suit man himself. <verse eId="Gen.2.20"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.2.21" sID="Gen.2.21"/>Then God the Eternal made a deep sleep to fall upon the man; while he slept, he
         took one of his ribs, closing up the flesh in its place; <verse eId="Gen.2.21"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.2.22" sID="Gen.2.22"/> the rib he had taken from the man God the Eternal shaped into a woman, and
         brought her to the man. <verse eId="Gen.2.22"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.2.23" sID="Gen.2.23"/> Then said the man,
         <lg>
          <l> This, this at last, is bone of my bones, </l>
          <l> and flesh of my own flesh:</l>
          <l> this shall be called Wo-man, </l>
          <l> for from man was she taken! </l>
         </lg>
        <verse eId="Gen.2.23"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.2.24" sID="Gen.2.24"/> (This is why a man leaves his father and mother and cleaves to his wife, till
         they become one flesh.) <verse eId="Gen.2.24"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.2.25" sID="Gen.2.25"/> Both of them, the man and his wife, were naked, but they felt no shame. <verse eId="Gen.2.25"/>
       </p>
      </hi>
     <chapter eId="Gen.2"/>
     <chapter osisId="Gen.3" sId="Gen.3"/>
      <hi>
       <p>
        <verse osisID="Gen.3.1" sID="Gen.3.1"/> Now the serpent was cun­ning, more cunning than any creature that God the Eternal
         had made; he said to the woman, <q>And so God has said that you are not to eat fruit from any tree in the park?</q> <verse eId="Gen.3.1"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.3.2" sID="Gen.3.2"/>
         The woman said to the serpent, <q>We can eat fruit from the trees in the park,<verse eId="Gen.3.2"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.3.3" sID="Gen.3.3"/> but, as for the tree in the centre of the park, God has said, <q>You must not eat
        from it, you must not touch it, lest you die.</q> </q> <verse eId="Gen.3.3"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.3.4" sID="Gen.3.4"/> <q>No,</q> said the serpent to the woman, <q>you shall not die; <verse eId="Gen.3.4"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.3.5" sID="Gen.3.5"/>
         God knows that on the day you eat from it your eyes will be opened and you will be like gods, knowing good and evil.</q>
        <verse eId="Gen.3.5"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.3.6" sID="Gen.3.6"/> So, when the woman saw that the tree was good to eat and delight­ful to see,
         desirable to look upon, she took some of the fruit and
         <milestone type="column" n="2"/>
         ate it; she also gave some to her husband, and he ate. <verse eId="Gen.3.6"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.3.7" sID="Gen.3.7"/> Then the eyes of both were opened, and they realized that they were naked; so they
         stitched some fig-leaves together and made them­selves girdles. <verse eId="Gen.3.7"/>
       </p>
       <p>
        <verse osisID="Gen.3.8" sID="Gen.3.8"/> In the cool of the day, when they heard the sound of God the Eternal walking in
         the park, the man and his wife hid from the presence of God the Eternal among the trees of the park; <verse eId="Gen.3.8"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.3.9" sID="Gen.3.9"/> but God the Eternal called to the man and asked him, <q>Where are you?</q> <verse eId="Gen.3.9"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.3.10" sID="Gen.3.10"/>
         <q>I heard thy sound within the park,</q>he answered, <q>and I was afraid, because I was naked; so I hid myself.</q> <verse eId="Gen.3.10"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.3.11" sID="Gen.3.11"/>He said, <q>Who told you that you were naked? Have you been eating from the tree
         which I forbade you to eat?</q> <verse eId="Gen.3.11"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.3.12" sID="Gen.3.12"/> The man is said, <q>The woman thou gavest me as a companion, she gave me some
         fruit from the tree, and I ate it.</q> <verse eId="Gen.3.12"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.3.13" sID="Gen.3.13"/> Then God the Eternal said to the woman, <q>What is this that you have done?</q>
        The wom­an said, <q>I ate because the ser­pent beguiled me.</q> <verse eId="Gen.3.13"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.3.14" sID="Gen.3.14"/>
         So God the Eternal said to the serpent,<q>Since you have done this,
         <lq>
          <l>
           A curse on you of all creatures! a curse
          </l>
          <l>
           on you of all beasts! 
          </l>
          <l>
           On your belly shall you crawl
          </l>
          <l>
           and eat dust all your days! <verse eId="Gen.3.14"/>
          </l>
          <l>
           <verse osisID="Gen.3.15" sID="Gen.3.15"/> And I will set a feud between you and the woman,
          </l>
          <l>
           between your brood and hers:
          </l>
          <l>
           they shall strike at your head,
          </l>
          <l>
           and you shall strike at their heel. <verse eId="Gen.3.15"/>
          </l>
         </lq></q>
        <verse osisID="Gen.3.16" sID="Gen.3.16"/> To the woman he said,<q>
         <lq>
          <l>
           I will make child-birth a sore pain for you,
          </l>
          <l>
           you shall have pangs in bearing;
          </l>
          <l>
           yet you shall crave to have your husband,
          </l>
          <l>
            and he shall master you.
          </l>
         </lq></q>
        <verse eId="Gen.3.16"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.3.17" sID="Gen.3.17"/> To the man he said, <q>Since you have listened to what your wife
         <milestone type="pb" n="4"/>
         said, eating from the tree of which I forbade you to eat,
         <lq>
          <l>
           Cursed is the ground on your ac­count,
          </l>
          <l>
           you shall suffer all your life, as you win food from it;
          </l>
        <verse eId="Gen.3.17"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.3.18" sID="Gen.3.18"/>
          <l>
           thorns and thistles shall it bear for you,
          </l>
          <l>
           and you must eat plants of the field;
          </l>
        <verse eId="Gen.3.18"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.3.19" sID="Gen.3.19"/>
          <l>
           in the sweat of your brow you shall earn your food,
          </l>
          <l>
           till you return to the ground from which you were taken;
          </l>
          <l>
           for dust you are, and you return to dust.
          </l>
        </lq></q>
        <verse eId="Gen.3.19"/>
       </p>
      </hi>
      <p>
       <verse osisID="Gen.3.20" sID="Gen.3.20"/> [[The man called the name of his wife Eve (Life), because she was the mother of
        all living persons.]] <verse eId="Gen.3.20"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.3.21" sID="Gen.3.21"/> [[And God the Eternal made skin tunics for the man and his wife, and clothed
        them.]] <verse eId="Gen.3.21"/>
       <hi type="italic">
        <verse osisID="Gen.3.22" sID="Gen.3.22"/>Then said God the Eternal, <q>Man has become like one of us, he knows good and
         evil. He might reach his hand now to the tree of life also, and by eating of it live for ever!</q> <verse eId="Gen.3.22"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.3.23" sID="Gen.3.23"/> So God the Eternal expelled him from the park of Eden, to till the ground from
         which he had been taken; <verse eId="Gen.3.23"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.3.24" sID="Gen.3.24"/> he drove the man out, and set kherubs at the east of the park of Eden, with the
         blade of a sword flashing in every direc­tion, to guard the path to the tree of life.
        <verse eId="Gen.3.24"/>
       </hi>
      </p>
     <chapter eId="Gen.3"/>
     <chapter osisId="Gen.4" sId="Gen.4"/>
      <hi type="italic">
       <p>
        <verse osisID="Gen.4.1" sID="Gen.4.1"/> Now the man had inter­course with his wife Eve; she conceived and bore Cain (Got),
         saying, “I have got a man from the Eternal.” <verse eId="Gen.4.1"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.4.2" sID="Gen.4.2"/> Next she bore his brother Abel. Abel was a shepherd, while Cain was a farmer. <verse eId="Gen.4.2"/>
       </p>
       <p>
        <verse osisID="Gen.4.3" sID="Gen.4.3"/> In course of time, Cain brought some produce of the ground as a present to the
         Eternal, <verse eId="Gen.4.3"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.4.4" sID="Gen.4.4"/> while Abel brought some of the first­born from his flock, that is, some fat slices
         from them. The Eter­nal favoured Abel and his pres­-
         <milestone type="column" n="2"/>
         ent;
        <verse eId="Gen.4.4"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.4.5" sID="Gen.4.5"/> he did not favour Cain and his. So Cain was furious and downcast. <verse eId="Gen.4.5"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.4.6" sID="Gen.4.6"/> <q>Why are you furious?</q> said the Eternal to Cain, <q>why are you downcast? <verse eId="Gen.4.6"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.4.7" sID="Gen.4.7"/> If your heart is honest, you would surely look bright? If you are sullen, sin is
         lying in wait for you, eager to be at you—yet you ought to master it.</q> <verse eId="Gen.4.7"/>
       </p>
       <p>
        <verse osisID="Gen.4.8" sID="Gen.4.8"/> But Cain quarrelled with his brother Abel, and, when they were out in the open
         country, Cain attacked his brother Abel and killed him. <verse eId="Gen.4.8"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.4.9" sID="Gen.4.9"/> Then the Eternal asked Cain, <q>Where is your brother Abel?</q> <q>How do I
         know?</q> said Cain; <q>am I a shep­herd to my brother?</q>
        <verse eId="Gen.4.9"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.4.10" sID="Gen.4.10"/> He answered, <q>What have you done? Listen, your brother s blood is crying to
         me from the soil! <verse eId="Gen.4.10"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.4.11" sID="Gen.4.11"/>
         And now you are cursed off the coun­try that has opened to swallow down the brothers blood you shed;
        <verse eId="Gen.4.11"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.4.12" sID="Gen.4.12"/>
         after this, the fields will not yield you their produce, when you till them; you must go stumbling and straying over the earth.</q>
        <verse eId="Gen.4.12"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.4.13" sID="Gen.4.13"/> Cain said to the Eternal, <q>My punishment is more than I can bear. <verse eId="Gen.4.13"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.4.14" sID="Gen.4.14"/> Thou art expelling me from the country, banishing me from thy sight; I must go
         stum­bling and straying over the earth, and anyone who catches me will kill me.</q> <verse eId="Gen.4.14"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.4.15" sID="Gen.4.15"/> So the Eternal said to him, <q>Well then, whoever kills Cain, seven times over
         shall the murder be avenged</q>; and the Eternal set a mark on Cain, to prevent anyone from catching and killing him.
        <verse eId="Gen.4.15"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.4.16" sID="Gen.4.16"/> Then Cain left the presence of the Eternal to stay in Nod (Wonderland), east
         of Eden. <verse eId="Gen.4.16"/>
       </p>
       <p>
        <verse osisID="Gen.4.17" sID="Gen.4.17"/> When Cain had intercourse with his wife, she conceived and bore Hanok; Cain
         built a town and called it after his son Hanok. <verse eId="Gen.4.17"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.4.18" sID="Gen.4.18"/> Irad was born to Hanok, and
         <milestone type="pb" n="5"/>
         Irad was the father of Mehujael, Mehujael the father of Methu- shael, and Methushael the father of Lemek. <verse eId="Gen.4.18"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.4.19" sID="Gen.4.19"/> Lemek married two wives; the name of one was Adah, the name of the other Zillah. <verse eId="Gen.4.19"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.4.20" sID="Gen.4.20"/> (Adah bore Jabal, the ancestor of shepherds who live in tents: <verse eId="Gen.4.20"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.4.21" sID="Gen.4.21"/> his brother’s name was Jubal, the ancestor of all who play the lyre and the
         pipe. <verse eId="Gen.4.21"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.4.22" sID="Gen.4.22"/>Zillah bore Tubal-Cain, the smith who forged bronze and iron tools, and
         Tubal-Cain’s sister was Naamah.) <verse eId="Gen.4.22"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.4.23" sID="Gen.4.23"/> Lemek said to his wives,<q>
         <lg>
          <l> Adah and Zillah, listen to me, </l>
          <l> O ’wives of Lemek, hear what I say: </l>
          <l> The man who wounds me, him I slay, </l>
          <l> I slay a boy for a blow: </l>
          <verse eId="Gen.4.23"/>
          <verse osisID="Gen.4.24" sID="Gen.4.24"/>
          <l> if Cain be avenged seven times, </l>
          <l>
           then seventy and seven times Lemek!
          </l>
         </lg> </q>
        <verse eId="Gen.4.24"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.4.25" sID="Gen.4.25"/>Adam again had intercourse with his wife, who bore a son and called him Seth,
         saying, <q>God has set up another child for me instead of Abel, whom Cain killed.</q>
        <verse eId="Gen.4.25"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.4.26" sID="Gen.4.26"/> Seth also had a son born to him, called Enosh; he was the first to worship the
         Eternal by name. <verse eId="Gen.4.26"/>
       </p>
      </hi>
     <chapter eId="Gen.4"/>
     <chapter osisId="Gen.5" sId="Gen.5"/>
      <p>
       <verse osisID="Gen.5.1" sID="Gen.5.1"/> Here is the list of Adam’s descendants. When God formed man, he made him to
        resemble God; <verse eId="Gen.5.1"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.5.2" sID="Gen.5.2"/> male and female, he formed them both and blessed them, calling them human on the
        day when they were formed. <verse eId="Gen.5.2"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.5.3" sID="Gen.5.3"/> After living a hundred and thirty years Adam became the father of a son resembling
        him­self, in his own likeness, whom he called Seth;
       <verse eId="Gen.5.3"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.5.4" sID="Gen.5.4"/> Adam lived eight hundred years after the birth of Seth, and was the father of
        sons and daughters. <verse eId="Gen.5.4"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.5.5" sID="Gen.5.5"/>
        Thus Adam lived for nine hundred and thirty years in all; then he died.
       <verse eId="Gen.5.5"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.5.6" sID="Gen.5.6"/>
        After living a hundred and five years Seth became 
        <milestone type="column" n="2"/>
       <verse eId="Gen.5.6"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.5.7" sID="Gen.5.7"/> the father of Enosh; Seth lived eight hundred and seven years after the birth of
        Enosh, and was the father of sons and daughters. <verse eId="Gen.5.7"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.5.8" sID="Gen.5.8"/> Thus Seth lived for nine hundred and twelve years in all; then he died. <verse eId="Gen.5.8"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.5.9" sID="Gen.5.9"/> After living ninety years Enosh be­came the father of Kenan; <verse eId="Gen.5.9"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.5.10" sID="Gen.5.10"/> Enosh lived eight hundred and fifteen years after the birth of Kenan, and was
        the father of sons and daughters. <verse eId="Gen.5.10"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.5.11" sID="Gen.5.11"/> Thus Enosh lived for nine hundred and five years in all; then he died. <verse eId="Gen.5.11"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.5.12" sID="Gen.5.12"/> After living seventy years Kenan became the father of Mahalalel; <verse eId="Gen.5.12"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.5.13" sID="Gen.5.13"/> Kenan lived eight hundred and forty years after the birth of Mahalalel, and was
        the father of sons and daughters. <verse eId="Gen.5.13"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.5.14" sID="Gen.5.14"/> Thus Kenan lived for nine hundred and ten years in all; then he died. <verse eId="Gen.5.14"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.5.15" sID="Gen.5.15"/> After living sixty-five years Mahalalel became the father of Jared; <verse eId="Gen.5.15"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.5.16" sID="Gen.5.16"/> Mahalalel lived eight hundred and thirty years after the birth of Jared, and was
        the father of sons and daughters. <verse eId="Gen.5.16"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.5.17" sID="Gen.5.17"/> Thus Mahalalel lived for eight hundred and ninety-five years in all; then he
        died. <verse eId="Gen.5.17"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.5.18" sID="Gen.5.18"/> After living a hundred and sixty-two years Jared became the father of Hanok; <verse eId="Gen.5.18"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.5.19" sID="Gen.5.19"/> Jared lived eight hundred years after the birth of Hanok, and was the father of
        sons and daughters. <verse eId="Gen.5.19"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.5.20" sID="Gen.5.20"/> Thus Jared lived for nine hundred and sixty-two years in all; then he died. <verse eId="Gen.5.20"/>
      </p>
      <p>
       <verse osisID="Gen.5.21" sID="Gen.5.21"/>
        After living sixty-five years Hanok became the father of Me­thuselah.
       <verse eId="Gen.5.21"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.5.22" sID="Gen.5.22"/>
        For three hundred years Hanok lived close to God, after the birth of Methuselah, and was the father of sons and daughters.
       <verse eId="Gen.5.22"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.5.23" sID="Gen.5.23"/> Thus Hanok lived for three hundred and sixty-five years in all; <verse eId="Gen.5.23"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.5.24" sID="Gen.5.24"/>Hanok lived close to God, and then he disappeared,
        <milestone type="pb" n="6"/>
        for God took him away. <verse eId="Gen.5.24"/>
      </p>
      <p>
       <verse osisID="Gen.5.25" sID="Gen.5.25"/> After living a hundred and eighty-seven years Methuselah became the father of Lemek; <verse eId="Gen.5.25"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.5.26" sID="Gen.5.26"/> Methuselah lived seven hun­dred and eighty-two years after the birth of Lemek, and
        was the father of sons and daughters. <verse eId="Gen.5.26"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.5.27" sID="Gen.5.27"/> Thus Methuselah lived for nine hundred and sixty-nine years in all; then he died. <verse eId="Gen.5.27"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.5.28" sID="Gen.5.28"/> After liv­ing a hundred and eighty-two years Lemek became the father of a son, <verse eId="Gen.5.28"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.5.29" sID="Gen.5.29"/> whom he called Noah, saying, <q>Now we shall <q>know a</q> relief from our
        labour and from our toil on the ground that the Eternal cursed.</q>
       <verse eId="Gen.5.29"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.5.30" sID="Gen.5.30"/> Lemek lived five hundred and ninety-five years after the birth of Noah, and was
        the father of sons and daughters. <verse eId="Gen.5.30"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.5.31" sID="Gen.5.31"/> Thus Lemek lived for seven hundred and seventy-seven years in all; then he died. <verse eId="Gen.5.31"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.5.32" sID="Gen.5.32"/> After living five hundred years Noah became the father of Shem, Ham, and Japheth. <verse eId="Gen.5.32"/>
      </p>
     <chapter eId="Gen.5"/>
     <chapter osisId="Gen.6" sId="Gen.6"/>
      <hi type="italic">
       <p>
        <verse osisID="Gen.6.1" sID="Gen.6.1"/> Now when men began to multiply over all the world and had daughters born to them, <verse eId="Gen.6.1"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.6.2" sID="Gen.6.2"/> the angels noticed that the daughters of men were beauti­ful, and they married any
         one of them that they chose. <verse eId="Gen.6.2"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.6.3" sID="Gen.6.3"/> So the Eternal said, <q>Human creatures are but flesh; my spirit is not to be
         immortal in them; they shall not live more than a hundred 4 and twenty years.</q> <verse eId="Gen.6.3"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.6.4" sID="Gen.6.4"/> (It was in these days that the Nephilim giants arose on earth, as well as
         afterwards whenever angels had intercourse with the daughters of men and had children born to them; these were the heroes
         who were famous in the days of old.) <verse eId="Gen.6.4"/>
       </p>
       <p>
        <verse osisID="Gen.6.5" sID="Gen.6.5"/> When the Eternal saw that the wickedness of man on earth was great, and that man’s
         mind was never bent on anything but evil, <verse eId="Gen.6.5"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.6.6" sID="Gen.6.6"/> the Eternal was sorry that he
        <milestone type="column" n="2"/>
        had ever made man on the earth; it was a grief to him. <verse eId="Gen.6.6"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.6.7" sID="Gen.6.7"/>So the Eternal said, <q>I will blot him off the earth, this man that I have formed—
         man and beast and reptile and bird; I am sorry that I ever made them.</q> <verse eId="Gen.6.7"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.6.8" sID="Gen.6.8"/> However, Noah had found favour with the Eternal. <verse eId="Gen.6.8"/>
       </p>
      </hi>
      <p>
       <verse osisID="Gen.6.9" sID="Gen.6.9"/> Here are the descendants of Noah. Noah was an upright man, blameless among the men
        of his day; Noah lived close to God. <verse eId="Gen.6.9"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.6.10" sID="Gen.6.10"/> Noah was the father of 10 three sons, Shem, Ham, and Japheth. <verse eId="Gen.6.10"/>
      </p>
      <p>
       <verse osisID="Gen.6.11" sID="Gen.6.11"/> Now in God's sight the earth was corrupt, the earth was full of insolence and
        outrage; <verse eId="Gen.6.11"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.6.12" sID="Gen.6.12"/> God saw that the earth was corrupt, for every human being upon earth had
        corrupted his life. <verse eId="Gen.6.12"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.6.13" sID="Gen.6.13"/> So God said to Noah, <q>I have re­solved to put an end to every human being, for
        they have filled the earth with insolence and out­rage; I will destroy them and the earth together. <verse eId="Gen.6.13"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.6.14" sID="Gen.6.14"/> Build a barge of cypress wood, build cabins inside the barge, and cover it with
        pitch, inside and outside. <verse eId="Gen.6.14"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.6.15" sID="Gen.6.15"/> This is how you are to build it: the barge is to be four hundred and fifty feet
        long, sev­enty-five feet broad, and forty- five feet high; <verse eId="Gen.6.15"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.6.16" sID="Gen.6.16"/> you must put windows in the barge, eighteen inches from the roof, and make a door
        in the side of the barge; also put three decks in it. <verse eId="Gen.6.16"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.6.17" sID="Gen.6.17"/> For I am sending a deluge of water on the earth, to destroy every liv­ing
        creature under heaven; every thing on earth shall perish. <verse eId="Gen.6.17"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.6.18" sID="Gen.6.18"/>
        But I will make a compact of my own with you; you shall enter the barge, you and your sons and your wife and your sons’ wives along with you.
       <verse eId="Gen.6.18"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.6.19" sID="Gen.6.19"/>
        And you shall 19 take into the barge two living creatures of every kind, to keep
        <milestone type="pb" n="7"/>
        them alive along with you; one is to be a male, and one a female. <verse eId="Gen.6.19"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.6.20" sID="Gen.6.20"/>
        Two of every kind, bird, beast, and reptile, are to join you, that they may be kept alive.
       <verse eId="Gen.6.20"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.6.21" sID="Gen.6.21"/> Go and gather anything in the shape of food, to be food for you and for them.</q> <verse eId="Gen.6.21"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.6.22" sID="Gen.6.22"/> Noah did so; he did all that God had ordered him. <verse eId="Gen.6.22"/>
      </p>
     <chapter eId="Gen.6"/>
     <chapter osisId="Gen.7" sId="Gen.7"/>
      <hi type="italic">
       <p>
        <verse osisID="Gen.7.1" sID="Gen.7.1"/>Then said the Eternal to Noah, <q>Go into the barge, you and all your household, for
         I have adjudged you, among all the men of to-day, to be upright before me. <verse eId="Gen.7.1"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.7.2" sID="Gen.7.2"/>
         Take seven pairs, male and female, of every clean animal, and one pair, male and female, of the unclean animals, and
         seven pairs, male and female, <verse eId="Gen.7.2"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.7.3" sID="Gen.7.3"/> of the birds of the air, to maintain life over all the world. <verse eId="Gen.7.3"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.7.4" sID="Gen.7.4"/> For after seven days I will make it rain on earth for forty days and forty nights,
         and I will blot off the earth every living creature that I ever made.</q>
        <verse eId="Gen.7.4"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.7.5" sID="Gen.7.5"/> Noah did all that the Eternal ordered him.<verse eId="Gen.7.5"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.7.10" sID="Gen.7.10"/> At the end of the seven days, the waters of the deluge covered the earth; <verse eId="Gen.7.10"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.7.7" sID="Gen.7.7"/> and Noah went into the barge along with his sons and his wife and his sons’
         wives, driven by the waters of the deluge. <verse eId="Gen.7.7"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.7.8 Gen.7.9" sID="Gen.7.8-Gen.7.9" n="8-9"/>
         Pairs of animals clean and unclean, of birds and of reptiles, male and female, ac­companied Noah into the barge, as God had ordered Noah.
        <verse eId="Gen.7.8-Gen.7.9"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.7.16" sID="Gen.7.16"/> Then the Eternal shut him in. <verse eId="Gen.7.16"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.7.12" sID="Gen.7.12"/> For forty days and forty nights rain fell upon the earth; <verse eId="Gen.7.12"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.7.17" sID="Gen.7.17"/> the waters rose, lifting the barge and raising it above the earth. <verse eId="Gen.7.17"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.7.22" sID="Gen.7.22"/> Every­thing with the breath of life in its nostrils, whatever was on the dry
         land, died; <verse eId="Gen.7.22"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.7.23" sID="Gen.7.23"/> the Eternal blot­ted every living creature off the earth, men, beasts, reptiles,
         and birds; they were blotted off the earth, till only Noah and his
         <milestone type="column" n="2"/>
         company inside the barge were left. <verse eId="Gen.7.23"/>
       </p>
      </hi>
      <p>
       <verse osisID="Gen.7.6" sID="Gen.7.6"/>Noah was six hundred years old when the deluge of water flooded the earth. <verse eId="Gen.7.6"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.7.11" sID="Gen.7.11"/>In the six hundredth year of Noah’s life, in the second month, on the seventeenth
        day of the month, on that day the fountains of the great abyss all burst, and the sluices of heaven were opened;
       <verse eId="Gen.7.11"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.7.13" sID="Gen.7.13"/> on that very day Noah, with Shem and Ham and Japheth, Noah’s sons, and Noah’s
        wife, and the three wives of his sons, went into the barge, <verse eId="Gen.7.13"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.7.14" sID="Gen.7.14"/> with every kind of beast, with every kind of animal, with every reptile that
        crawls on earth, and with every kind of bird and winged creature; <verse eId="Gen.7.14"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.7.15" sID="Gen.7.15"/> they accompanied Noah into the barge, pairs of every living creature, male and
        female, <verse eId="Gen.7.15"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.7.16" sID="Gen.7.16"/> entering, as God had or­dered him. <verse eId="Gen.7.16"/>
      </p>
      <p>
       <verse osisID="Gen.7.17" sID="Gen.7.17"/>The deluge covered the earth for forty days. The waters swelled and rose high on
        the earth, and the barge floated on the surface of the waters; <verse eId="Gen.7.17"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.7.18" sID="Gen.7.18"/> the waters swelled mightily on the earth, <verse eId="Gen.7.18"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.7.19" sID="Gen.7.19"/> till every high mountain under heaven was covered-- <verse eId="Gen.7.19"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.7.20" sID="Gen.7.20"/> the waters swelling twenty-two feet higher, till the moun­tains were covered, <verse eId="Gen.7.20"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.7.21" sID="Gen.7.21"/> and every living creature perished, bird, beast, and animal, every reptile that
        crawls on earth, and every man. <verse eId="Gen.7.21"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.7.24" sID="Gen.7.24"/> For a hundred and fifty days the waters swelled over the earth. <verse eId="Gen.7.24"/>
      </p>
     <chapter eId="Gen.7"/>
     <chapter osisId="Gen.8" sId="Gen.8"/>
      <p>
       <verse osisID="Gen.8.1" sID="Gen.8.1"/>But God remembered Noah and all the living creatures and the animals that were with
        him in the barge; God made a wind blow over the earth, till the waters abated; <verse eId="Gen.8.1"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.8.2" sID="Gen.8.2"/> also, the fountains of the abyss and the sluices of heaven were closed: <verse eId="Gen.8.2"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.8.3" sID="Gen.8.3"/> and at the end of the hundred
        <milestone type="pb" n="8"/>
        and fifty days, the waters began to subside. <verse eId="Gen.8.3"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.8.4" sID="Gen.8.4"/> In the seventh month, on the seventeenth day of the month, the barge grounded on
        the mountains of Armenia. <verse eId="Gen.8.4"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.8.5" sID="Gen.8.5"/> Till the tenth month the waters steadily subsided, and on the first day of the
        tenth month the tops of the mountains were seen; <verse eId="Gen.8.5"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.8.13" sID="Gen.8.13"/> on the first day of the first month of the six hundred and first year, the
        waters had dried off the earth; <verse eId="Gen.8.13"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.8.14" sID="Gen.8.14"/> on the twenty-seventh day of the second month, the earth it­self was dry. <verse eId="Gen.8.14"/>
      </p>
      <hi type="italic">
       <p>
        <verse osisID="Gen.8.6" sID="Gen.8.6"/> At the end of forty days the <verse eId="Gen.8.6"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.8.2" sID="Gen.8.2"/> from heaven ceased, <verse eId="Gen.8.2"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.8.3" sID="Gen.8.3"/> and the waters went hack steadily from the earth. <verse eId="Gen.8.3"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.8.6" sID="Gen.8.6"/> Then Noah opened the window he had made in the barge, <verse eId="Gen.8.6"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.8.7" sID="Gen.8.7"/> and sent out a raven, which went flying here and there till the waters had dried
         off the earth. <verse eId="Gen.8.7"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.8.8" sID="Gen.8.8"/> He waited seven days and then sent out a dove, to see if the waters had drained
         off the earth; <verse eId="Gen.8.8"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.8.9" sID="Gen.8.9"/> but, as the dove could find no rest for the sole of her foot, she flew back to
         him in the barge; he put his hand out, caught her and took her in beside him in the barge. <verse eId="Gen.8.9"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.8.10" sID="Gen.8.10"/> After waiting seven days more, he sent the dove out of the barge again; <verse eId="Gen.8.10"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.8.11" sID="Gen.8.11"/> in the evening the dove came back to him, and there, in her beak, was the fresh
         leaf of an olive! So Noah knew that the waters were drained off the earth. <verse eId="Gen.8.11"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.8.12" sID="Gen.8.12"/> After waiting seven days more, he sent out the dove, but she never came back to
         him. <verse eId="Gen.8.12"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.8.13" sID="Gen.8.13"/> Then Noah removed the cover­ing of the barge and looked out. There lay the
         surface of the ground, all dry! <verse eId="Gen.8.13"/>
       </p>
      </hi>
      <p>
       <verse osisID="Gen.8.15" sID="Gen.8.15"/>Then said God to Noah, <verse eId="Gen.8.15"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.8.16" sID="Gen.8.16"/> <q>Leave the barge, you and your wife and your sons and your sons’ wives, <verse eId="Gen.8.16"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.8.17" sID="Gen.8.17"/> and take out every
        <milestone type="column" n="2"/>
        living thing that is with you, every creature, bird and beast and reptile, that they may swarm on earth and be fruitful
        and multiply on earth.</q> <verse eId="Gen.8.17"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.8.18" sID="Gen.8.18"/> So Noah came out, along with his sons and his wife and his sons’ wives; <verse eId="Gen.8.18"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.8.19" sID="Gen.8.19"/> also every beast, every reptile, every fowl, everything that moves on earth, all
        came out of the barge, arranged in families. <verse eId="Gen.8.19"/>
      </p>
      <hi type="italic">
       <p>
        <verse osisID="Gen.8.20" sID="Gen.8.20"/>Then Noah built an altar to the Eternal; he took some clean beasts and birds of
         every kind and burned them in sacrifice on the altar, <verse eId="Gen.8.20"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.8.21" sID="Gen.8.21"/> and when the Eternal smelt the soothing fragrance, the Eternal said to himself,
         <q>Never again will I curse the ground, though the bent of man's mind is indeed towards evil from his youth; never again
         will I destroy every living creature as I have done. <verse eId="Gen.8.21"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.8.22" sID="Gen.8.22"/> So long as earth remains, seedtime and harvest, cold and heat, summer and
         winter, day and night, shall never cease.</q> <verse eId="Gen.8.22"/>
       </p>
      </hi>
     <chapter eId="Gen.8"/>
     <chapter osisId="Gen.9" sId="Gen.9"/>
      <p>
       <verse osisID="Gen.9.1" sID="Gen.9.1"/>And God blessed Noah and his sons, bidding them, <q>Be fruitful and multiply and
        replen­ish the earth. <verse eId="Gen.9.1"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.9.2" sID="Gen.9.2"/>The dread of you and terror of you shall be on every beast of the earth and every
        bird of the air; for they are now in your power, with every reptile of the land and ev­ery fish within the sea. <verse eId="Gen.9.2"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.9.3" sID="Gen.9.3"/> Every moving thing that is alive is to be food for you; I give you them all, as
        once I gave you the green growth. <verse eId="Gen.9.3"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.9.4" sID="Gen.9.4"/>Only, you must never eat flesh with the life (that is, the blood) in it. <verse eId="Gen.9.4"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.9.5" sID="Gen.9.5"/>And I will avenge the shedding of your own life-blood; I will avenge it on any
        beast, I will avenge man’s life on man, upon his brother-man; <verse eId="Gen.9.5"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.9.6" sID="Gen.9.6"/>
        whoever sheds human blood, by human hands shall his own blood be shed—
        <milestone type="pb" n="9"/>
        for God made man in his own likeness. <verse eId="Gen.9.6"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.9.7" sID="Gen.9.7"/> As for you, be fruitful and multiply; breed freely on earth and subdue it.</q> <verse eId="Gen.9.7"/>
      </p>
      <p>
       <verse osisID="Gen.9.8" sID="Gen.9.8"/> Then said God to Noah and also to his sons, <verse eId="Gen.9.8"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.9.9" sID="Gen.9.9"/> <q>I now ratify my compact with you and your descendants, <verse eId="Gen.9.9"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.9.10" sID="Gen.9.10"/> and with every liv­ing creature in your company, with any bird or beast or animal
        whatsoever that leaves the barge, with every beast of the earth: <verse eId="Gen.9.10"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.9.11" sID="Gen.9.11"/> I ratify my compact with you, that never again shall all living creatures be
        swept away by the waters of the deluge, that never again shall there be a deluge to destroy the earth. <verse eId="Gen.9.11"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.9.12" sID="Gen.9.12"/> Here,</q> said God, <q>is the symbol of the com­pact that I make with you and all
        the living creatures in your company for endless generations: <verse eId="Gen.9.12"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.9.13" sID="Gen.9.13"/> in the clouds I set my rainbow, as a symbol of the compact between myself and
        the earth; <verse eId="Gen.9.13"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.9.14" sID="Gen.9.14"/> whenever I cloud over the earth, once the rainbow appears in the clouds, <verse eId="Gen.9.14"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.9.15" sID="Gen.9.15"/> then I will remem­ber my compact with you and every living creature whatso­ever,
        and the waters shall never again become a deluge to destroy every creature. <verse eId="Gen.9.15"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.9.16" sID="Gen.9.16"/> When the rainbow appears in the clouds, I will look at it to remind me of the
        lasting compact between God and every living creature whatsoever upon earth. <verse eId="Gen.9.16"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.9.17" sID="Gen.9.17"/> This,</q> God said to Noah, <q>is the sym­bol of the compact that I ratify
        between myself and every crea­ture upon earth.</q> <verse eId="Gen.9.17"/>
      </p>
      <hi type="italic">
       <p>
        <verse osisID="Gen.9.18" sID="Gen.9.18"/>The sons of Noah who came out of the barge were Shem, Ham, and Japheth
         [[; Ham was the father of Canaan]]. <verse eId="Gen.9.18"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.9.19" sID="Gen.9.19"/> These three were the sons of Noah, and from them people spread all over the
         earth. <verse eId="Gen.9.19"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.9.20" sID="Gen.9.20"/> Noah the farmer was the first man to plant a vineyard; <verse eId="Gen.9.20"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.9.21" sID="Gen.9.21"/> he
        <milestone type="column" n="2"/>
        drank some of the wine and, be­coming drunk, lay uncovered in­side his tent. <verse eId="Gen.9.21"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.9.22" sID="Gen.9.22"/> When [[Ham the father of]] Canaan saw his fa­ther naked, he told his two
         brothers outside; <verse eId="Gen.9.22"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.9.23" sID="Gen.9.23"/> Shem and Japheth then took a plaid, which they laid over their shoulders,
         and walking backwards they covered up the nakedness of their father; as their faces were turned back, they did not see
         their father's nakedness. <verse eId="Gen.9.23"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.9.24" sID="Gen.9.24"/> When Noah wakened from his wine and learned what his youngest son had done, <verse eId="Gen.9.24"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.9.25" sID="Gen.9.25"/>
         he said,<q>
         <lg>
          <l>
            A curse on Canaan!
          </l>
          <l>
            May he be slave and thrall to his brothers!
          </l>
         </lg></q>
        <verse eId="Gen.9.25"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.9.26" sID="Gen.9.26"/>He added,<q>
         <lg>
          <l>
            O thou Eternal, bless the tents of Shem!
          </l>
          <l>
            let Canaan be his slave!
          </l>
          <verse eId="Gen.9.26"/>
          <verse osisID="Gen.9.27" sID="Gen.9.27"/>
          <l>
           May God enlarge Japheth!
          </l>
          <l>
           May he be welcome in the tents of Shem,
          </l>
          <l>
           and have Canaan as his slave!”
          </l>
          <verse eId="Gen.9.27"/>
         </lg></q>
       </p>
      </hi>
      <p>
       <verse osisID="Gen.9.28" sID="Gen.9.28"/>After the deluge Noah lived three hundred and fifty years.<verse eId="Gen.9.28"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.9.29" sID="Gen.9.29"/> Thus Noah lived for nine hundred and fifty years in all; and then he died. <verse eId="Gen.9.29"/>
      </p>
     <chapter eId="Gen.9"/>
     <chapter osisId="Gen.10" sId="Gen.10"/>
      <p>
       <verse osisID="Gen.10.1" sID="Gen.10.1"/>Here are the descendants of Shem, Ham, and Japheth, the sons of Noah (they had
        sons born after the deluge):<verse eId="Gen.10.1"/>
      </p>
      <p>
       <verse osisID="Gen.10.2" sID="Gen.10.2"/>The descendants of Japheth were the Cimmerians, Magog, the Medes, the Ionians,
        Tubal, Meshek, and Tiras; <verse eId="Gen.10.2"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.10.3" sID="Gen.10.3"/> the descendants of the Cimmerians were Ashkenaz, Riphath, and Togarmah; <verse eId="Gen.10.3"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.10.4" sID="Gen.10.4"/> he descendants of the Ionians were Elishah, Tartessus, Cyprus, and Rhodes <verse eId="Gen.10.4"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.10.5" sID="Gen.10.5"/> from whom the seaboard nations spread. Such were the sons of Japheth, according
        to their lands, languages, and na­tional families.<verse eId="Gen.10.5"/>
      </p>
      <p>
       <verse osisID="Gen.10.6" sID="Gen.10.6"/>The descendants of Ham were Ethiopia, Egypt, Put, and Canaan;<verse eId="Gen.10.6"/>
       <milestone type="pb" n="10"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.10.7" sID="Gen.10.7"/> the descendants of Ethio­pia were Seba, Havilah, Sabta, Raamah, and Sabteca; the
        de­scendants of Raamah were Sheba and Dedan. <verse eId="Gen.10.7"/>
       <hi type="italic">
        <verse osisID="Gen.10.8" sID="Gen.10.8"/> Ethiopia produced Nimrod, the first man on earth to be a despot
        <verse eId="Gen.10.8"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.10.9" sID="Gen.10.9"/> (he was a mighty hunter before the Eter­nal; hence the proverb, <q>Like Nimrod,
         a mighty hunter before the Eternal</q>). <verse eId="Gen.10.9"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.10.10" sID="Gen.10.10"/> His empire at first was Babylon, Vruk, Akkad, and Kalneh, in the land of
         Shinar; <verse eId="Gen.10.10"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.10.11" sID="Gen.10.11"/> from which he pushed out into Assyria, building the great city
         of Nineveh and its suburbs, also Kalah, <verse eId="Gen.10.11"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.10.12" sID="Gen.10.12"/> and Resen which lies between Nineveh and Kalah. <verse eId="Gen.10.12"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.10.13" sID="Gen.10.13"/> From Egypt sprang Lud, the Anamin, the Libyans, the Naphtuhim, <verse eId="Gen.10.13"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.10.14" sID="Gen.10.14"/> Pathros, the Casluhim, and Crete (from which the Philistines came). <verse eId="Gen.10.14"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.10.15" sID="Gen.10.15"/>From Canaan sprang Sidon first of all, then the Hittites
        <verse eId="Gen.10.15"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.10.16" sID="Gen.10.16"/> [[the Jebusites, the Amorites, the Girgashites, <verse eId="Gen.10.16"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.10.17" sID="Gen.10.17"/> the Hivites, the Arkites, the Sinites, <verse eId="Gen.10.17"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.10.18" sID="Gen.10.18"/> the Arvadites, the Zemarites, and the Hamathites]]; after that the Canaanite
         families spread abroad, <verse eId="Gen.10.18"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.10.19" sID="Gen.10.19"/> their territory ex­tending from Sidon in the direc­tion of Gerar, as far as
         Gaza, and as far as Lesha in the direction of Sodom and Gomorrah and Admah and Zeboiim. <verse eId="Gen.10.19"/>
       </hi>
      </p>
      <p>
       <verse osisID="Gen.10.20" sID="Gen.10.20"/>Such were the descendants of Ham, according to their national clans,
        languages, and lands. <verse eId="Gen.10.20"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.10.22" sID="Gen.10.22"/> descendants of Shem were Elam, Assyria, Arpachshad, the
        Lydians, and Aram; <verse eId="Gen.10.22"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.10.23" sID="Gen.10.23"/> and the de­scendants of Aram were Uz, Hul, Gether, and Mash. <verse eId="Gen.10.23"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.10.31" sID="Gen.10.31"/> Such were the descendants of Shem, according to their national clans,
        languages, and lands. <verse eId="Gen.10.31"/>
      </p>
      <p>
       <hi type="italic">
        <verse osisID="Gen.10.21" sID="Gen.10.21"/> Shem, the ancestor of all the Hebrews, the older brother of Japheth, had also
         descendants; <verse eId="Gen.10.21"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.10.24" sID="Gen.10.24"/>from Arpachshad sprang Shelah, and from Shelah Eber. <verse eId="Gen.10.24"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.10.25" sID="Gen.10.25"/>Two sons were born to Eber, one called Peleg (Division) because the
         in­habitants of the earth were di­vided up in his day, and his brother called Joktan.<verse eId="Gen.10.25"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.10.26" sID="Gen.10.26"/> From Joktan sprang Almodad, Sheleph, Hazarmdveth, Jerah, <verse eId="Gen.10.26"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.10.27" sID="Gen.10.27"/> Hadoram, Uzal, Diklah, <verse eId="Gen.10.27"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.10.28" sID="Gen.10.28"/> Obal, Abimael, Sheba, <verse eId="Gen.10.28"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.10.29" sID="Gen.10.29"/> Ophir, Havilah, and Jobab; all these were de­scendants of Joktan, <verse eId="Gen.10.29"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.10.30" sID="Gen.10.30"/> who lived between Massa and Sephar, to­wards the hill-country of the East. <verse eId="Gen.10.30"/>
       </hi>
      </p>
      <p>
       <verse osisID="Gen.10.32" sID="Gen.10.32"/>Such were the national clans descended from Noah, according to their origin,
        from whom the nations on earth spread after the deluge.<verse eId="Gen.10.32"/>
      </p>
     <chapter eId="Gen.10"/>
     <chapter osisId="Gen.11" sId="Gen.11"/>
      <hi type="italic">
       <p>
        <verse osisID="Gen.11.1" sID="Gen.11.1"/>In the days when the whole earth had one language and one vocabulary, <verse eId="Gen.11.1"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.11.2" sID="Gen.11.2"/>there was a migration from the east, and men came upon a plain in the land of
         Shinar, where they settled. <verse eId="Gen.11.2"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.11.3" sID="Gen.11.3"/>Then they said to one another, <q>Come on, let us make bricks, and give them a
         good burning.</q> Then, as they had bricks for stone and asphalt for mortar, <verse eId="Gen.11.3"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.11.4" sID="Gen.11.4"/>they said, <q>Come on, let us make a name for ourselves by building a city and a
         tower whose top reaches to heaven; it will keep us from being scattered all over the wide earth.</q> <verse eId="Gen.11.4"/>
       </p>
       <p>
        <verse osisID="Gen.11.5" sID="Gen.11.5"/>Down came the Eternal to see the city and the tower which hu­man beings had
         built. <verse eId="Gen.11.5"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.11.6" sID="Gen.11.6"/>
         <q>They are one people,</q> said the Eternal, <q>and they have one language; if this is what they do, to start with,
         nothing that they ever un­dertake will prove too hard for them. <verse eId="Gen.11.6"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.11.7" sID="Gen.11.7"/> Come, let us go down and make a babble of their lan­guage on the spot, so that
         they cannot understand one another’s speech.</q> <verse eId="Gen.11.7"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.11.8" sID="Gen.11.8"/>
         Thus did the Eternal 
        <milestone type="pb" n="11"/>
         scatter them all over the wide earth; they gave up building the city. <verse eId="Gen.11.8"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.11.9" sID="Gen.11.9"/>
         Hence it was called Baby­lon, because it was there that the Eternal made a babble of the language of the whole earth,
         and there that the Eternal scattered men all over the wide earth. <verse eId="Gen.11.9"/>
       </p>
      </hi>
      <p>
       <verse osisID="Gen.11.10" sID="Gen.11.10"/>These are the descendants of Shem. When Shem was a hun­dred years old, he
        became the father of Arpachshad, two years the flood; <verse eId="Gen.11.10"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.11.11" sID="Gen.11.11"/> Shem lived five hundred years after the birth of Arpachshad, and was the
        father of sons and daughters. <verse eId="Gen.11.11"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.11.12" sID="Gen.11.12"/> After living thirty-five years Arpach­shad became the father of Shelah;<verse eId="Gen.11.12"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.11.13" sID="Gen.11.13"/> Arpachshad lived four hundred and three years after the birth of Shelah,
        and was the father of sons and daughters. <verse eId="Gen.11.13"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.11.14" sID="Gen.11.14"/>After living thirty years Shelah became the father of Eber; <verse eId="Gen.11.14"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.11.15" sID="Gen.11.15"/>Shelah lived four hundred and three years after the birth of Eber, and was the
        father of sons and daughters. <verse eId="Gen.11.15"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.11.16" sID="Gen.11.16"/> After living thirty-four years Eber became the father of Peleg; <verse eId="Gen.11.16"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.11.17" sID="Gen.11.17"/>Eber lived four hundred and thirty years after the birth of Peleg, and was the
        father of sons and daughters. <verse eId="Gen.11.17"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.11.18" sID="Gen.11.18"/> After living thirty years Peleg became the father of Reu; <verse eId="Gen.11.18"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.11.19" sID="Gen.11.19"/>Peleg lived two hundred and nine years after the birth of Reu, and was the
        father of sons and daughters. <verse eId="Gen.11.19"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.11.20" sID="Gen.11.20"/>After living thirty-two years Reu became the father of Serug; <verse eId="Gen.11.20"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.11.21" sID="Gen.11.21"/> Reu lived two hundred and seven years after the birth of Serug, and was the
        father of sons and daughters. <verse eId="Gen.11.21"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.11.22" sID="Gen.11.22"/>After living thirty years Serug became the father of Nahor;<verse eId="Gen.11.22"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.11.23" sID="Gen.11.23"/> Serug lived two hundred years after the birth of Nahor, and was the father of
        sons and daughters. <verse eId="Gen.11.23"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.11.24" sID="Gen.11.24"/> After living twen­ty-nine years Nahor became the
        <milestone type="column" n="2"/>
        father of Terah; <verse eId="Gen.11.24"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.11.25" sID="Gen.11.25"/> Nahor lived a hundred and nineteen years after the birth of Terah, and was the
        father of sons and daughters. <verse eId="Gen.11.25"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.11.26" sID="Gen.11.26"/> After living seventy years Terah became the father of Abram, Nahor, and Haran. <verse eId="Gen.11.26"/>
      </p>
      <p>
       <verse osisID="Gen.11.27" sID="Gen.11.27"/>Now these are the descendants of Terah: Terah was the father of Abram, Nahor,
        and Haran, while Haran was the father of Lot. <verse eId="Gen.11.27"/>
       <hi type="italic">
        <verse osisID="Gen.11.28" sID="Gen.11.28"/>Haran died during the lifetime of his father in Chaldean Ur, the land of his
         birth. <verse eId="Gen.11.28"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.11.29" sID="Gen.11.29"/> Abram and Nahor married; Abram’s wife was called Sarai, and Nahor’s wife,
         called Milkah, was the daughter of Haran the father of Milkah and Iskah. <verse eId="Gen.11.29"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.11.30" sID="Gen.11.30"/> Sarai was barren, she had no children. <verse eId="Gen.11.30"/>
       </hi>
       <verse osisID="Gen.11.31" sID="Gen.11.31"/> Then Terah took Abram his son, and Lot his grandson, Haran’s son, and Sarai
        his daughter-in-law, the wife of his son Abram, and led them from Chaldean Ur to reach the land of Canaan. But when they
        reached Harran, they stayed there, <verse eId="Gen.11.31"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.11.32" sID="Gen.11.32"/>
        and in Harran Terah died at the age of two hundred and five. <verse eId="Gen.11.32"/>
      </p>
     <chapter eId="Gen.11"/>
     <chapter osisId="Gen.12" sId="Gen.12"/>
      <p>
       <hi type="italic">
        <verse osisID="Gen.12.1" sID="Gen.12.1"/>Said the Eternal to in Abram, <q>Leave your country, leave your kindred, leave
         your father’s house, for a land that I will show to you; <verse eId="Gen.12.1"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.12.2" sID="Gen.12.2"/> I will make a great nation of you and bless you and make you famous for your
         bliss; <verse eId="Gen.12.2"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.12.3" sID="Gen.12.3"/> those who bless you, I will bless, and anyone who curses you I will curse, till
         all nations of the world seek bliss such as yours.</q>
        <verse eId="Gen.12.3"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.12.4" sID="Gen.12.4"/> So Abram went away, as the Eternal had told him, and with him went Lot. <verse eId="Gen.12.4"/>
       </hi>
      </p>
      <p>
       <verse osisID="Gen.12.5" sID="Gen.12.5"/>When Abram moved out of Harran, he was seventy-five years old; he took Sarai his
        wife and Lot his nephew, with all
        <milestone type="pb" n="11"/>
        the property and the serfs they had acquired in Harran; off they started for the land of Canaan, and to the land of Canaan
        came.
       <verse eId="Gen.12.5"/>
       <hi type="italic">
        <verse osisID="Gen.12.6" sID="Gen.12.6"/> Abram passed on through the land as far as the oracular oak at the shrine of
         Shechem. The Canaanites still occupied the country, <verse eId="Gen.12.6"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.12.7" sID="Gen.12.7"/> but the Eternal appeared to Abram and said, <q>I give this land to your
         descendants.</q> He built an altar on the spot to the Eternal who had appeared to him; <verse eId="Gen.12.7"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.12.8" sID="Gen.12.8"/> then he moved on to the hill east of Beth-el, and pitched his tent be­tween Beth-el
         on the west and Ai on the east; there also he built an altar to the Eternal, and worshipped the Eternal.
        <verse eId="Gen.12.8"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.12.9" sID="Gen.12.9"/>
         Then Abram travelled on, still south­ward.
        <verse eId="Gen.12.9"/>
       </hi>
      </p>
      <p>
       <hi type="italic">
        <verse osisID="Gen.12.10" sID="Gen.12.10"/>There was a famine in the land, and, as the famine was severe in the land,
         Abram went down to stay in Egypt. <verse eId="Gen.12.10"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.12.11" sID="Gen.12.11"/> As he neared Egypt, he said to Sarai his wife, <q>Come, I know you are a
         handsome-looking woman; <verse eId="Gen.12.11"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.12.12" sID="Gen.12.12"/> when the Egyptians see you, they will say, <q>This is his wife,</q> and they
         will kill me and let you live. <verse eId="Gen.12.12"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.12.13" sID="Gen.12.13"/> Do say you are my sister, that I may be kindly treated for your sake, and
         that my life may be spared on your account.</q> <verse eId="Gen.12.13"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.12.14" sID="Gen.12.14"/> When Abram entered Egypt, the Egyptians did notice that the woman was very
         handsome; <verse eId="Gen.12.14"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.12.15" sID="Gen.12.15"/>the courtiers of the Pharaoh saw her and praised her to the Pha­raoh, and, the
         woman was taken to the palace of the Pharaoh, <verse eId="Gen.12.15"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.12.16" sID="Gen.12.16"/> who treated Abram kindly for her sake, presenting him with sheep, oxen,
         he-asses, male and female slaves, she-asses, and camels. <verse eId="Gen.12.16"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.12.17" sID="Gen.12.17"/>But the Eternal struck the Pharaoh and his household with severe diseases on
         account of Sarai the wife of Abram. <verse eId="Gen.12.17"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.12.18" sID="Gen.12.18"/> So
         <milestone type="pb" n="12"/>
         the Pharaoh called Abram and said to him, <q>What is this you have done to me? Why did you not tell me that she was your
         wife? <verse eId="Gen.12.18"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.12.19" sID="Gen.12.19"/>Why did you say, <q>She is my sister,</q> and so move me to marry her? See,
         there is your wife! Take her and be­gone!</q>
        <verse eId="Gen.12.19"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.12.20" sID="Gen.12.20"/> And the Pharaoh gave him an escort, who led him away with his wife and all
         that he had; <verse eId="Gen.12.20"/>
       </hi>
      </p>
     <chapter eId="Gen.12"/>
     <chapter osisId="Gen.13" sId="Gen.13"/>
      <p>
       <hi type="italic">
        <verse osisID="Gen.13.1" sID="Gen.13.1"/> so Abram left Egypt, along with his wife and all that he had, accompanied by
         Lot, and went up to the Negeb. <verse eId="Gen.13.1"/>
       </hi>
      </p>
      <p>
       <hi type="italic">
        <verse osisID="Gen.13.2" sID="Gen.13.2"/> Abram was very rich in cattle, silver and gold; <verse eId="Gen.13.2"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.13.3" sID="Gen.13.3"/>he travelled on from the Negeb to Beth-el, <verse eId="Gen.13.3"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.13.4" sID="Gen.13.4"/> to the site of the altar he had erected there at the first, and there he
         worshipped the Eternal. <verse eId="Gen.13.4"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.13.5" sID="Gen.13.5"/> Lot, who accompanied Abram, also had flocks and herds and tents. <verse eId="Gen.13.5"/>
       </hi>
      </p>
      <p>
       <verse osisID="Gen.13.6" sID="Gen.13.6"/>Now the country could not support them both together; their possessions were so
        large that they could not live side by side. <verse eId="Gen.13.6"/>
       <hi type="italic">
        <verse osisID="Gen.13.7" sID="Gen.13.7"/>A dispute arose between the herdsmen of Abram and the herdsmen of Lot.
         (The Ca­naanites and the Perizzites still lived in the country.) <verse eId="Gen.13.7"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.13.8" sID="Gen.13.8"/> So Abram said to Lot, <q>Let us have no dispute, you and I, my herds­men and
         your herdsmen; we are kinsmen. <verse eId="Gen.13.8"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.13.9" sID="Gen.13.9"/>The whole land lies before you, does it not? Pray, separate; if you go to the
         left, I will go to the right, or, if you go to the right, I will go to the left.</q> <verse eId="Gen.13.9"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.13.10" sID="Gen.13.10"/>Then Lot, looking round, noticed that the whole of the Jor­dan basin was well
         watered in every direction (that was before the Eternal destroyed Sodom and Gomorrah); it was like the Eternal’s own
         park, like the land of Egypt on the way to Zoan.
        <verse eId="Gen.13.10"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.13.11" sID="Gen.13.11"/> So Lot chose all the Jordan basin.
       </hi>
        Lot went east, and they parted company;<verse eId="Gen.13.11"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.13.12" sID="Gen.13.12"/>
        Abram lived
        <milestone type="pb" n="13"/>
        in the land of Canaan, while Lot lived in the towns of the Jordan basin,
       <hi type="italic">
        moving his tent up country towards Sodom.
        <verse eId="Gen.13.12"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.13.13" sID="Gen.13.13"/> (The men of Sodom were vicious, they sinned openly against the Eter­nal.) <verse eId="Gen.13.13"/>
       </hi>
      </p>
      <p>
       <hi type="italic">
        <verse osisID="Gen.13.14" sID="Gen.13.14"/>After Lot had parted from him, the Eternal said to Abram,
         <q>Look abroad now from where you are, north, south, east, and west; <verse eId="Gen.13.14"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.13.15" sID="Gen.13.15"/> the land you see, I give it all to you and to your descend­edants for all
         time. <verse eId="Gen.13.15"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.13.16" sID="Gen.13.16"/> I will make your descendants as numerous as the dust on the ground, so that
         if the dust of the ground could be counted your descendants could be counted.<verse eId="Gen.13.16"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.13.17" sID="Gen.13.17"/> Up, traverse the length and breadth of the land, for I give it to you.</q> <verse eId="Gen.13.17"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.13.18" sID="Gen.13.18"/> Then Abram moved his tent and went to live beside Mamre’s oaks at Hebron,
         where he built an altar to the Eternal. <verse eId="Gen.13.18"/>
       </hi>
      </p>
     <chapter eId="Gen.13"/>
     <chapter osisId="Gen.14" sId="Gen.14"/>
      <p>
       <verse osisID="Gen.14.1" sID="Gen.14.1"/>Now it was during the reign of Amraphel king of Shinar that Arioch king of
        Ellasar, Kedorlaomer king of Elam, and Tidal king of the Guti, <verse eId="Gen.14.1"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.14.2" sID="Gen.14.2"/>joined him in attacking Bera king of Sodom, Birsha king of Gomorrah, Shinab king
        of Admah, Shemeber king of Zeboiim, and the king of Bela (that is, Zoar), <verse eId="Gen.14.2"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.14.3" sID="Gen.14.3"/> all of whom formed a league in the valley of Siddim (that is, the Salt Sea);<verse eId="Gen.14.3"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.14.4" sID="Gen.14.4"/>for twelve years they had paid homage to Kedorlaomer, but when they rebelled in
        the thirteenth year, <verse eId="Gen.14.4"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.14.5" sID="Gen.14.5"/> Kedorlaomer and his fellow-kings came in the fourteenth year and routed the
        Titans at Ashteroth-karnaim, the Zuzim at Ham, the Emim on the plain of Kiriathaim, <verse eId="Gen.14.5"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.14.6" sID="Gen.14.6"/> and the troglodytes in their high­lands of Seir, driving them as far as El-paran
        which lies close
        <milestone type="column" n="2"/>
        to the desert. <verse eId="Gen.14.6"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.14.7" sID="Gen.14.7"/> They then turned back to En-Mishpat (that is, Kadesh), ravaging all the coun­try
        of the Amalekites and of the Amorites who inhabited Hazazon-tamar. <verse eId="Gen.14.7"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.14.8" sID="Gen.14.8"/> Out marched the king of Sodom, the king of Gomorrah, the king of Admah, the king
        of Zeboiim, and the king of Bela (that is, Zoar) to confront them in the valley of Siddim, <verse eId="Gen.14.8"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.14.9" sID="Gen.14.9"/>facing Kedorlaomer king of Elam, Tidal king of the Guti, Amraphel king of Shinar,
        and Arioch king of Ellasar—four kings against five. <verse eId="Gen.14.9"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.14.10" sID="Gen.14.10"/>The valley of Siddim was all petroleum wells, and, when the kings of Sodom and
        Gomorrah fled, some people fell in, while the survivors fled to the hills. <verse eId="Gen.14.10"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.14.11" sID="Gen.14.11"/>
        The four kings captured all the possessions and all the provi­sions of Sodom and Gomorrah and went away;
       <verse eId="Gen.14.11"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.14.12" sID="Gen.14.12"/>
        they also carried off Lot, the son of Abram’s kinsman, who lived in Sodom, and his possessions.<verse eId="Gen.14.12"/>
      </p>
      <p>
       <verse osisID="Gen.14.13" sID="Gen.14.13"/>Then one of the survivors went and told Abram the He­brew, who was living
        beside the oaks of Mamre the Amorite (a kinsman of Eshcol and of Aner, who were allies of Abram). <verse eId="Gen.14.13"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.14.14" sID="Gen.14.14"/> As soon as Abram heard that his kinsman had been taken pris­oner, he called out
        his trusty fol­lowers, retainers born in his own household, three hundred and eighteen of them, and went in pursuit as far
        as Dan, <verse eId="Gen.14.14"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.14.15" sID="Gen.14.15"/> where, dividing his forces by night, he routed the enemy and chased them as
        far as Hobah to the north of Damascus. <verse eId="Gen.14.15"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.14.16" sID="Gen.14.16"/>He recovered all the possessions, and also recovered his kinsman Lot with his
        possessions, besides the women and the people. <verse eId="Gen.14.16"/>
      </p>
      <p>
       <verse osisID="Gen.14.17" sID="Gen.14.17"/>On returning from his defeat of Kedorlaomer and the other
        <milestone type="pb" n="14"/>
        kings, he was met by the king of Sodom in the valley of Shaveh (that is, the King’s valley); <verse eId="Gen.14.17"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.14.18" sID="Gen.14.18"/>Melkizedek, king of Salem, brought out bread and wine, and, as a priest of God
       Most High, <verse eId="Gen.14.18"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.14.19" sID="Gen.14.19"/> he blessed him saying, <q>
        <lg>
         <l> Blessed be Abram by God Most High, </l>
         <l> Creator of heaven and earth! </l>
       <verse eId="Gen.14.19"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.14.20" sID="Gen.14.20"/>
         <l> And blessed be God Most High, </l>
         <l> who has put your foes into your hand! </l>
        </lg></q>
        Abram gave him a tenth of all the spoil.
       <verse eId="Gen.14.20"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.14.21" sID="Gen.14.21"/> But, when the king of Sodom said to Abram, <q>Take the goods yourself, and
        let me have the prisoners,</q>
       <verse eId="Gen.14.21"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.14.22" sID="Gen.14.22"/> Abram an­swered the king of Sodom, :<q>By this hand raised to the Eternal, God
        Most High, Creator of heaven and earth, I swear I will not take a thread or string of yours! <verse eId="Gen.14.22"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.14.23" sID="Gen.14.23"/>
        I will not have you say that, <q>I made Abram rich.</q> <verse eId="Gen.14.23"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.14.24" sID="Gen.14.24"/> Nothing for me—except what the troops have eaten; but let my comrades, let
        Aner, Eshcol, and Mamre, have their share of the spoil!</q> <verse eId="Gen.14.24"/>
      </p>
     <chapter eId="Gen.14"/>
     <chapter osisId="Gen.15" sId="Gen.15"/>
      <p>
       <verse osisID="Gen.15.1" sID="Gen.15.1"/>[After this the Eternal said to Abram in a vision, <q>Fear not, Abram, I
        will shield you. Rich your reward shall be.</q><verse eId="Gen.15.1"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.15.2" sID="Gen.15.2"/> <q>O Lord Eternal,</q> said Abram, <q>but what canst thou give me, when I am
        going to die childless, and my heir is a Damascene, Eliezer?</q>] <verse eId="Gen.15.2"/>
       <hi type="italic">
        <verse osisID="Gen.15.3" sID="Gen.15.3"/>And Abram said, <q>Thou hast not given me a child; yon slave born in my house
         will be heir to me!</q> <verse eId="Gen.15.3"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.15.4" sID="Gen.15.4"/> Then said the Eter­nal to him, <q>He shall not be heir to you; a son of your own body
         be heir to you.</q> <verse eId="Gen.15.4"/>
       </hi>
       <verse osisID="Gen.15.5" sID="Gen.15.5"/> [Then he took him outside and said, <q>Look up to the sky and num­ber the
        stars if you can</q>; adding, <q>such shall be the number of your descendants.</q>] <verse eId="Gen.15.5"/>
       <hi type="italic">
        <verse osisID="Gen.15.6" sID="Gen.15.6"/>Abram be­lieved the Eternal, who counted
         <milestone type="column" n="2"/>
         his trust as real religion,<verse eId="Gen.15.6"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.15.7" sID="Gen.15.7"/>and said to him, <q>I am the Eternal who brought you from Chaldean Ur to give
         you possession of this land.</q> <verse eId="Gen.15.7"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.15.8" sID="Gen.15.8"/> <q>Lord Eternal,</q> he said, <q>how can I be sure I shall possess it?</q> <verse eId="Gen.15.8"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.15.9" sID="Gen.15.9"/> So he said to him, <q>Take a three-year old heifer, a three-year old she-goat,
         a three-year old ram, a turtle-dove, and a young pigeon.</q> <verse eId="Gen.15.9"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.15.10" sID="Gen.15.10"/> Taking all these, he cut them in two, and put each piece opposite the other.
         (He did not cut the birds in two.) <verse eId="Gen.15.10"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.15.11" sID="Gen.15.11"/>When the birds of prey swooped on the carcases, Abram drove them off. <verse eId="Gen.15.11"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.15.12" sID="Gen.15.12"/>Then, as the sun was going down, a trance came over Abram, a great hor­ror of
         a darkness came over him; <verse eId="Gen.15.12"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.15.13" sID="Gen.15.13"/> and the Eternal said to him, <q>Be sure of this: your de­scendants shall reside in a
         land that is not their own, in subjec­tion to people who will treat them harshly for four hundred years; <verse eId="Gen.15.13"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.15.14" sID="Gen.15.14"/> but I will punish the nation that held them in slavery, and then they shall
         get away with ample possessions. <verse eId="Gen.15.14"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.15.15" sID="Gen.15.15"/>(As for 15 yourself, you shall join your fathers in peace, you shall be
         buried in a ripe old age.) <verse eId="Gen.15.15"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.15.16" sID="Gen.15.16"/> In the fourth generation they shall come back here—for the guilt of the Amorites
         is not yet full.</q> <verse eId="Gen.15.16"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.15.17" sID="Gen.15.17"/> When the sun went down, when it turned dark, there was a smok­ing furnace and
         a blazing torch that passed between the pieces! <verse eId="Gen.15.17"/>
       </hi>
      </p>
      <hi type="italic">
       <p>
        <verse osisID="Gen.15.18" sID="Gen.15.18"/>That day the Eternal made a compact with Abram. <q>To your descendants,</q>
         he said, <q>I am giv­ing this land, from the river of Egypt to the great Euphrates river--<verse eId="Gen.15.18"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.15.19" sID="Gen.15.19"/> Kenites, Kenizzites, Kadmonites, <verse eId="Gen.15.19"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.15.20" sID="Gen.15.20"/> Hittites, Perizzites, Titans, <verse eId="Gen.15.20"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.15.21" sID="Gen.15.21"/> Amorites, Canaanites, Girgashites, and Jebusites!</q> <verse eId="Gen.15.21"/>
       </p>
      </hi>
     <chapter eId="Gen.15"/>
     <chapter osisId="Gen.16" sId="Gen.16"/>
      <hi type="italic">
       <p>
        <verse osisID="Gen.16.1" sID="Gen.16.1"/>Abrams wife Sarai had borne him no children;
         <milestone type="pb" n="15"/>
         but, as she had an Egyptian a maid called Hagar, <verse eId="Gen.16.1"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.16.2" sID="Gen.16.2"/> Sarai said to Abram, <q>See, the Eternal has kept me from having children!
         Do go in to my maid; per­haps I may get a family by means of her.</q> <verse eId="Gen.16.2"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.16.3" sID="Gen.16.3"/> Abram obeyed Sarai. So, after Abram had been living ten years in the land of
         Canaan, his wife Sarai took her maid, Hagar the Egyptian, and gave her in marriage to Abram her husband. <verse eId="Gen.16.3"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.16.4" sID="Gen.16.4"/> When he went in to Hagar, she conceived; and as soon as she found that she had
         conceived, she looked down upon her mistress. <verse eId="Gen.16.4"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.16.5" sID="Gen.16.5"/> Said Sarai to Abram, <q>May this wrong I suffer fall on you! I put my maid
         into your arms, and as soon as she found she had con­ceived, she looked down upon me! The Eternal punish you and avenge
         me!</q> <verse eId="Gen.16.5"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.16.6" sID="Gen.16.6"/><q>Your maid is in your power,</q> said Abram to Sarai, <q>do what you like
         with her.</q> Sarai treated her harshly, and she ran away.<verse eId="Gen.16.6"/>
       </p>
      </hi>
      <p>
       <hi type="italic">
        <verse osisID="Gen.16.7" sID="Gen.16.7"/> When the angel of the Eternal came upon her be­side a spring in the desert, at
         the spring on the road to Shur,
        <verse eId="Gen.16.7"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.16.8" sID="Gen.16.8"/> he said to her, <q>Hagar, Sarai’s maid, where have you come from, and where
         are you going?</q> She answered, <q>I am running away from Sarai, my mistress. <verse eId="Gen.16.8"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.16.9" sID="Gen.16.9"/> </q><q>Go back to your mistress,</q> said the angel of the Eternal, <q>submit
         to her.</q> <verse eId="Gen.16.9"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.16.10" sID="Gen.16.10"/> And the angel of the Eternal added, <q>I will mul­tiply your descendants till
         their number cannot be counted, so many shall they be. <verse eId="Gen.16.10"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.16.11" sID="Gen.16.11"/>You are with child,</q> said the angel of the Eternal, <q>you shall bear a
         son and call him Ishmael (God-hear)--for the Eternal has heard of your ill-treatment. <verse eId="Gen.16.11"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.16.12" sID="Gen.16.12"/>
         <lg>
          <l> He shall be a wild-ass of a man, </l>
          <l> his hand against everyone, </l>
          <milestone type="column" n="2"/>
          <l> and everyone’s hand against him, </l>
          <l> defying all his kinsmen. </l>
         </lg>
         </q>
        <verse eId="Gen.16.12"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.16.13" sID="Gen.16.13"/> So she named the Eternal who had spoken to her, <q>God Seen.</q>
         <q>Even here in the desert,</q> she said to herself, <q>have I seen God, and lived after my vision?</q> <verse eId="Gen.16.13"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.16.14" sID="Gen.16.14"/> Hence the well was called Beer-lahai-roi (well of life and vision);
         it is between Kadesh and Bered. <verse eId="Gen.16.14"/>
       </hi>
       <verse osisID="Gen.16.15" sID="Gen.16.15"/> Hagar bore a son to Abram, and Abram called his son, born of Hagar, by the
        name of Ish­mael. <verse eId="Gen.16.15"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.16.16" sID="Gen.16.16"/> Abram was eighty-six, when Hagar bore Ishmael to him. <verse eId="Gen.16.16"/>
      </p>
     <chapter eId="Gen.16"/>
     <chapter osisId="Gen.17" sId="Gen.17"/>
      <p>
       <verse osisID="Gen.17.1" sID="Gen.17.1"/>When Abram was ninety-nine, the Eternal appeared to Abram and said, <q>I am God
        Almighty; live ever mindful of my presence, and so be blameless; <verse eId="Gen.17.1"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.17.2" sID="Gen.17.2"/> I will make my compact with you and multiply your descendants greatly.</q> <verse eId="Gen.17.2"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.17.3" sID="Gen.17.3"/> Abram fell on his face; and God continued, <verse eId="Gen.17.3"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.17.4" sID="Gen.17.4"/><q>As for me, my compact is made with you, and you shall be the father of many
        a nation; <verse eId="Gen.17.4"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.17.5" sID="Gen.17.5"/> no longer shall your name be Abram, but Abraham (Many-father), for I have
        ap­pointed you to be the father of many a nation;
       <verse eId="Gen.17.5"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.17.6" sID="Gen.17.6"/>I will make you most fruitful, I will make na­tions out of you, and kings shall
        spring from you. <verse eId="Gen.17.6"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.17.7" sID="Gen.17.7"/> And I will ratify my compact for all time, between me and yourself and your
        descendants from genera­tion to generation, engaging to be a God to you and to your de­scendants after you. <verse eId="Gen.17.7"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.17.8" sID="Gen.17.8"/>Also, I will give you and your descend­ants after you the land where you are
        residing, the whole of the land of Canaan, as a pos­session for all time; and I will be their God.</q> <verse eId="Gen.17.8"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.17.9" sID="Gen.17.9"/> God said to Abraham, <q>As for you, you must keep my compact, you
        <milestone type="pb" n="16"/>
        and your descendants after you from generation to generation. <verse eId="Gen.17.9"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.17.10" sID="Gen.17.10"/> The compact which you are to keep, the compact between me and yourself and
        your descend­ants after you, is this: every male among you is to be circumcised. <verse eId="Gen.17.10"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.17.11" sID="Gen.17.11"/> You are to be cir­cumcised in the flesh of your foreskin; that is to mark the
        compact between us. <verse eId="Gen.17.11"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.17.12" sID="Gen.17.12"/> Every male among you, from genera­tion to generation, is to be cir­cumcised
        when he is eight days old, with every slave, whether born in your household or bought from any foreigner--<verse eId="Gen.17.12"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.17.13" sID="Gen.17.13"/>he who is born in your household and he who is bought with your money must be
        circumcised; so shall my compact be cut in your flesh as a compact lasting for all time. <verse eId="Gen.17.13"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.17.14" sID="Gen.17.14"/> Any uncircumcised male, who is not circumcised in the flesh of his foreskin,
        he shall be outlawed from his kinsfolk; he has broken my compact.</q> <verse eId="Gen.17.14"/>
      </p>
      <p>
       <verse osisID="Gen.17.15" sID="Gen.17.15"/>And God said to Abraham, <q>As for your wife Sarai, you are not to call her
        Sarai but Sarah (princess). <verse eId="Gen.17.15"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.17.16" sID="Gen.17.16"/>I will bless her, and give you a son from her; I will bless her and make
        nations of her--kings of peoples shall come from her.</q> <verse eId="Gen.17.16"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.17.17" sID="Gen.17.17"/> Abraham fell on his face; he laughed, saying to himself, <q>Shall a man who
        is a hundred become a father? Sarah is ninety now, and shall she become a mother?</q> <verse eId="Gen.17.17"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.17.18" sID="Gen.17.18"/> Then said Abraham to God, <q>Oh that Ishmael might be under thy care!</q> <verse eId="Gen.17.18"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.17.19" sID="Gen.17.19"/> But God said, <q></q>Nay, Sarah your wife shall indeed bear you a son; you
        must call him Isaac (Laughter), and I will ratify my compact with him to be a compact for all time with his descendants
        after him. <verse eId="Gen.17.19"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.17.20" sID="Gen.17.20"/> As for Ishmael, I have heard what you say; I have a
        <milestone type="column" n="2"/>
        blessing for him, I will make him fruitful and multiply his race
        greatly; twelve princes shall be born of him, and I will make him a great nation. <verse eId="Gen.17.20"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.17.21" sID="Gen.17.21"/> Nevertheless I will ratify my com­pact with Isaac, whom Sarah will bear to you
        when the time comes round next year.” <verse eId="Gen.17.21"/>
      </p>
      <p>
       <verse osisID="Gen.17.22" sID="Gen.17.22"/>Then God ceased talking to him, and leaving Abraham went up to heaven. <verse eId="Gen.17.22"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.17.23" sID="Gen.17.23"/> That very day Abraham took Ishmael his son, and every male in his household,
        both the slaves born in his household and those bought with his money, and circum­cised the flesh of their foreskins, as
        God had told him. <verse eId="Gen.17.23"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.17.24" sID="Gen.17.24"/> Abraham was ninety-nine when he was circumcised in the flesh of his foreskin,
       <verse eId="Gen.17.24"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.17.25" sID="Gen.17.25"/> and Ishmael his son was thirteen when he was cir­cumcised in the flesh of his
        foreskin. <verse eId="Gen.17.25"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.17.26" sID="Gen.17.26"/>That very day Abraham was circumcised with Ish­mael his son, <verse eId="Gen.17.26"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.17.27" sID="Gen.17.27"/>and all the men of his household, the slaves born in his household and those
        bought from foreigners with his money, were circumcised along with him. <verse eId="Gen.17.27"/>
      </p>
     <chapter eId="Gen.17"/>
     <chapter osisId="Gen.18" sId="Gen.18"/>
      <hi type="italic">
       <p>
        <verse osisID="Gen.18.1" sID="Gen.18.1"/>As he sat at the door of his tent at noon, the Eternal appeared him beside the
         Mamre-oaks. <verse eId="Gen.18.1"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.18.2" sID="Gen.18.2"/>He raised his eyes, and there stood three men be­fore him! When he saw them, he
         ran from the door of the tent to welcome them, and bowed to the ground, <verse eId="Gen.18.2"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.18.3" sID="Gen.18.3"/> saying, <q>Pray, sirs, if I have found favour with you, do not pass by your
         servant; since you have come to your humble servant,<verse eId="Gen.18.3"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.18.4" sID="Gen.18.4"/>  have a little water brought to wash your feet; then lie down under the tree <verse eId="Gen.18.4"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.18.5" sID="Gen.18.5"/> till I fetch a bite of food, to refresh you; after that you can go on.</q>
         <q>Do as you propose,</q> they said. <verse eId="Gen.18.5"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.18.6" sID="Gen.18.6"/>So Abraham hurried inside the
         <milestone type="pb" n="17"/>
         tent and said to Sarah, <q>Quick, bring a bushel
         of meal, knead it and make some rolls.</q> <verse eId="Gen.18.6"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.18.7" sID="Gen.18.7"/> Then Abraham ran to the herd and took a tender, plump calf, which he handed to
         his slave, who hurried to dress it. <verse eId="Gen.18.7"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.18.8" sID="Gen.18.8"/> Taking curds and milk and the veal he had dressed, he placed them before the
         men, and stood beside them under the tree as they ate. <verse eId="Gen.18.8"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.18.9" sID="Gen.18.9"/>Then they asked him, <q>Where is your wife Sarah?</q> <q>Inside the tent
         there,</q> he said. <verse eId="Gen.18.9"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.18.10" sID="Gen.18.10"/> <q>Well,</q> said the Eternal, <q>I will come back to you next spring, when
         your wife Sarah shall have a son.</q>
         Sarah was listening behind the tent-door. <verse eId="Gen.18.10"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.18.11" sID="Gen.18.11"/>She and Abraham were old, well on in years, and the custom of women had
         ceased with Sarah. <verse eId="Gen.18.11"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.18.12" sID="Gen.18.12"/> So Sarah laughed to herself. <q>Marriage-bliss for a worn old creature like
         me, with an old husband!</q> <verse eId="Gen.18.12"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.18.13" sID="Gen.18.13"/> The Eternal said to Abraham, <q>Why did Sarah laugh and ask, <q>Is an old
         woman like me really going to bear a child?</q> <verse eId="Gen.18.13"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.18.14" sID="Gen.18.14"/>
         Is anything too hard for the Eternal? Next spring I will return to you, when the time comes round and Sarah 
         has a son.</q><verse eId="Gen.18.14"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.18.15" sID="Gen.18.15"/> Then Sarah denied it; she said, <q>I did not laugh</q>--for she was afraid.
         <q>Nay,</q> he said, <q>but you did laugh.</q> <verse eId="Gen.18.15"/>
       </p>
       <p>
        <verse osisID="Gen.18.16" sID="Gen.18.16"/>Then the men went away, gazing towards Sodom.
         (Abraham went to escort them, <verse eId="Gen.18.16"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.18.17" sID="Gen.18.17"/> and the Eternal thought, <q>Shall I hide from Abraham what I am going
         to do, <verse eId="Gen.18.17"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.18.18" sID="Gen.18.18"/>seeing that Abraham is to become a large and powerful na­tion, and that all
         nations of the world are to seek bliss like his? <verse eId="Gen.18.18"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.18.19" sID="Gen.18.19"/>I have chosen him that he may charge his sons and his house­hold after him to
         follow the di­rections of the Eternal by doing what is good and right, so that the Eternal may fulfil for Abraham what
         he has promised.</q>) <verse eId="Gen.18.19"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.18.20" sID="Gen.18.20"/> Then said the Eternal, <q>Loud is the outcry against Sodom and Gomorrah, and
         their sin must be heavy indeed; <verse eId="Gen.18.20"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.18.21" sID="Gen.18.21"/>we will go down and see if their deeds answer to the outcry that has reached
         us; we would find out whether it is so.</q><verse eId="Gen.18.21"/>
       </p>
       <p>
        <verse osisID="Gen.18.22" sID="Gen.18.22"/>So the men turned away towards Sodom, while Abraham remained standing before
         the Eternal. <verse eId="Gen.18.22"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.18.23" sID="Gen.18.23"/> Then Abraham went nearer and said, <q>Wilt thou really sweep away good and
         bad together? <verse eId="Gen.18.23"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.18.24" sID="Gen.18.24"/>Suppose there are fifty good folk in the town; wilt thou really sweep away
         the place, and not forgive it for the sake of the fifty good folk in it? <verse eId="Gen.18.24"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.18.25" sID="Gen.18.25"/> Far be it from thee to act like that, to slay good and bad to­gether, letting
         the good fare as the bad fare! Far be that from thee! Shall not the Judge of all the earth be just?</q> <verse eId="Gen.18.25"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.18.26" sID="Gen.18.26"/> The Eternal said, <q>If I can find fifty good folk in the town of Sodom, I
         will forgive the whole place for their sake.</q> <verse eId="Gen.18.26"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.18.27" sID="Gen.18.27"/> Then Abraham went on, <q>Here am I venturing to speak to the Lord, I who am
         mere dust and dross! <verse eId="Gen.18.27"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.18.28" sID="Gen.18.28"/> Suppose five are wanting out of the fifty good folk, wilt thou sweep away
         the whole town for lack of five?</q> He replied, <q>I will not sweep it away, if I can find forty-five in it.</q> <verse eId="Gen.18.28"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.18.29" sID="Gen.18.29"/> Once more he asked him, <q>Perhaps forty may be found in it.</q>
         <q>I will spare it,</q> he said, <q>for the sake of the forty.</q> <verse eId="Gen.18.29"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.18.30" sID="Gen.18.30"/> Then he said, <q>Oh let not the Lord be angry, let me say one word: sup­pose
         thirty are found in it?</q> <q>I will spare it,</q> he answered, <q>if I can find thirty there.</q> <verse eId="Gen.18.30"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.18.31" sID="Gen.18.31"/> And he said, <q>Here am I venturing to speak to the Lord: suppose there are
         twenty found in it?</q> <q>I will not sweep it away,</q> he replied,
         <milestone type="pb" n="18"/>
         <q>for the sake of the twenty</q> <verse eId="Gen.18.31"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.18.32" sID="Gen.18.32"/> Then he said, <q>Oh let not the Lord be angry, let me say one word more:
         suppose ten are to be found in it?</q> <q>I will not sweep it away,</q> he replied, <q>for the sake of the ten.</q> <verse eId="Gen.18.32"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.18.33" sID="Gen.18.33"/> The Eternal went away, as soon as he ceased talking to Abraham, and Abra­ham
         went home. <verse eId="Gen.18.33"/>
       </p>
      </hi>
     <chapter eId="Gen.18"/>
     <chapter osisId="Gen.19" sId="Gen.19"/>
      <hi type="italic">
       <p>
        <verse osisID="Gen.19.1" sID="Gen.19.1"/>In the evening two of the angels reached Sodom. Lot was sitting at the gateway
         of Sodom, and when Lot saw them he rose to welcome them, bowing his face to the ground <verse eId="Gen.19.1"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.19.2" sID="Gen.19.2"/>and saying, <q>Pray step aside, sirs, into the house of your servant to pass
         the night and wash your feet; you can rise early and go on your way.</q> <q>No,</q> they said, <q>we will stay in the
         open square all night.</q> <verse eId="Gen.19.2"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.19.3" sID="Gen.19.3"/> However, as he pressed them, they turned with him and entered his house, where
         he made a feast for them, baking unleavened bread, of which they ate.
        <verse eId="Gen.19.3"/>
       </p>
       <p>
        <verse osisID="Gen.19.4" sID="Gen.19.4"/>They had not lain down to rest before all the townsmen, the inhabitants of
         Sodom, beset the house, young and old from every quarter, <verse eId="Gen.19.4"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.19.5" sID="Gen.19.5"/> shouting to Lot, <q>Where are the men who came to visit you to-night?
         Bring them out to us that we may rape them.</q> <verse eId="Gen.19.5"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.19.6" sID="Gen.19.6"/> Lot went out to them and shut the door behind him. <verse eId="Gen.19.6"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.19.7" sID="Gen.19.7"/> <q>Pray, friends,</q> he said, <q>be not so wicked. <verse eId="Gen.19.7"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.19.8" sID="Gen.19.8"/> See, I have two daugh­ters, virgins; let me bring them out, and you can do as
         you please with them, but pray let these men alone--they have sheltered under my roof!</q> <verse eId="Gen.19.8"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.19.9" sID="Gen.19.9"/> <q>Out of the way!</q> said the crowd. <q>The fellow settled among us as a
         stranger, and he would lay down the law for us!</q> <q>We’ll treat you worse than them!</q> So they mobbed Lot and were
         on the
         <milestone type="column" n="2"/>
         point of breaking into the house, <verse eId="Gen.19.9"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.19.10" sID="Gen.19.10"/> when the men put out their hands, pulled Lot inside, and closed the door. <verse eId="Gen.19.10"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.19.11" sID="Gen.19.11"/> Then they plagued the townsfolk at the door with blindness, young and old
         alike, till they tired them­selves out with groping for the door. <verse eId="Gen.19.11"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.19.12" sID="Gen.19.12"/> The men said to Lot, <q>If you have anyone else in the place, sons-in-law,
         daughters, anyone belonging to you in the town, get them away, for we intend to sweep this place to ruin. <verse eId="Gen.19.12"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.19.13" sID="Gen.19.13"/> The outcry against it has be­come loud before the Eternal, and the Eternal
         has sent us to sweep it away.</q> <verse eId="Gen.19.13"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.19.14" sID="Gen.19.14"/> So Lot went out and told his sons-in-law, the men who were to marry his
         daughters. <q>Up and away</q>, he said, <q>for the Eternal is about to sweep the town to ruin.</q>
         However, his sons-in-law thought he was merely jesting. <verse eId="Gen.19.14"/>
       </p>
       <p>
        <verse osisID="Gen.19.15" sID="Gen.19.15"/>When dawn appeared, the angels urged Lot. <q>Be off with your wife and your
         daughters who are beside you,</q> they urged, <q>lest you are swept away when the town is punished.</q> <verse eId="Gen.19.15"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.19.16" sID="Gen.19.16"/>He hesitated. But the men seized him and his wife and his two daughters by
         the hand; thanks to the Eternal’s pity for him, they got him away and left him outside the town. <verse eId="Gen.19.16"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.19.17" sID="Gen.19.17"/> When they had got the party outside, one of them said to him, <q>Now, fly
         for your life; never look be­hind you, stay nowhere on the basin of the plain, but fly to the hills, lest you are swept
         away.</q> <verse eId="Gen.19.17"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.19.18" sID="Gen.19.18"/><q>Oh no, sir!</q> said Lot, <verse eId="Gen.19.18"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.19.19" sID="Gen.19.19"/><q>now that your servant has found favour with you, and you have shown me
         great mercy in saving my life, since I cannot make my es­cape to yonder hills, for fear that the disaster overtakes me
         and kills me--<verse eId="Gen.19.19"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.19.20" sID="Gen.19.20"/>pray now, yonder
         <milestone type="pb" n="19"/>
         town is near enough for my flight. It is small, oh, let me es­cape to it (is it not small?) and so preserve my life!</q>
        <verse eId="Gen.19.20"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.19.21" sID="Gen.19.21"/>He re­plied, <q>I grant this request of yours also, I will not sweep away the
         town of which you speak. <verse eId="Gen.19.21"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.19.22" sID="Gen.19.22"/> Make haste and escape to it, for I can do nothing till you reach it.</q>
         (Hence the name of the town was called Zoar, or Small.) <verse eId="Gen.19.22"/>
       </p>
      </hi>
      <p>
       <hi type="italic">
        <verse osisID="Gen.19.23" sID="Gen.19.23"/>The sun had risen on the earth when Lot reached Zoar, <verse eId="Gen.19.23"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.19.24" sID="Gen.19.24"/>and then the Eternal rained sulphur and fire from heaven on Sodom and
         Gomorrah, <verse eId="Gen.19.24"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.19.25" sID="Gen.19.25"/> sweeping away these towns and all the Jordan basin, with all the inhabitants
         of the towns and whatever grew on the ground. <verse eId="Gen.19.25"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.19.26" sID="Gen.19.26"/> (But Lot’s wife looked back, and became a pillar of salt.)<verse eId="Gen.19.26"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.19.27" sID="Gen.19.27"/> In the morning when Ab­raham rose and went to the spot where he had stood
         before the Eternal, <verse eId="Gen.19.27"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.19.28" sID="Gen.19.28"/> he looked in the direc­tion of Sodom and Gomorrah, and there was steam
         rising from the land like vapour from a furnace! <verse eId="Gen.19.28"/>
       </hi>
       <verse osisID="Gen.19.29" sID="Gen.19.29"/>So it was that when God destroyed the towns in the Jor­dan basin, God
        remembered Abraham and sent Lot away from the overthrow of the towns in one of which Lot resided. <verse eId="Gen.19.29"/>
      </p>
      <p>
       <hi type="italic">
        <verse osisID="Gen.19.30" sID="Gen.19.30"/>Lot went up from Zoar and stayed in the hills, accompanied by his two
         daughters--for he was afraid to stay in Zoar; so he lived with his two daughters in a cave. <verse eId="Gen.19.30"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.19.31" sID="Gen.19.31"/>The elder said to the younger, <q>Our father is an old
         man, and there is not a man on earth left to marry us in the usual way. <verse eId="Gen.19.31"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.19.32" sID="Gen.19.32"/> Come, let us make our father drunk, and we will lie
         with him, so as to preserve our race through our father.</q>
        <verse eId="Gen.19.32"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.19.33" sID="Gen.19.33"/> So that night they made their father drunk; then the
         elder daughter went in and lay with her father, though he never
         <milestone type="column" n="2"/>
         knew when she lay down or when
         she rose. <verse eId="Gen.19.33"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.19.34" sID="Gen.19.34"/> In the morning the elder daughter said to the
         younger, <q>I lay with my father last night; let us make him drunk again to-night; then you go in
         and lie with him, that we may preserve our race through our father.</q>
        <verse eId="Gen.19.34"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.19.35" sID="Gen.19.35"/> So that night again they made their father drunk, and
         the younger daughter got up and lay with him, although he never knew when she lay down and when
         she rose. <verse eId="Gen.19.35"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.19.36" sID="Gen.19.36"/> In this way both the daughters of Lot were with child
         by their father. <verse eId="Gen.19.36"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.19.37" sID="Gen.19.37"/> The elder bore a son, whom she called Moab
         (From-father); he is the ancestor of the modern Moabites. <verse eId="Gen.19.37"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.19.38" sID="Gen.19.38"/> The younger also bore a son, whom she called
         Benammi (Son-of-my-father’s-kin); he is the ancestor of the modern Ammonites. <verse eId="Gen.19.38"/>
       </hi>
      </p>
     <chapter eId="Gen.19"/>
     <chapter osisId="Gen.20" sId="Gen.20"/>
      <p>
       <verse osisID="Gen.20.1" sID="Gen.20.1"/>[Abraham travelled on towards the Negeb, staying between
        Kadesh and Shur, and also stopping at Gerar. <verse eId="Gen.20.1"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.20.2" sID="Gen.20.2"/> He said that his wife Sarah was his sister, and so
        Abimelek the king of Gerar sent and took Sarah. <verse eId="Gen.20.2"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.20.3" sID="Gen.20.3"/> But God came to Abimelek in a dream by night,
        saying, <q>You are a dead man; for this woman whom you have taken is a married woman.</q> <verse eId="Gen.20.3"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.20.4" sID="Gen.20.4"/> Now Abimelek had not touched her. So he said,
        <q>Lord, wilt thou slay innocent folk? <verse eId="Gen.20.4"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.20.5" sID="Gen.20.5"/> Did he not tell me himself, <q>She is my sister,</q> and
        she herself said, <q>He is my brother</q>? I did it in all simplicity and innocence.</q> <verse eId="Gen.20.5"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.20.6" sID="Gen.20.6"/> Then God said to him in the dream, <q>I know you did it
        in all simplicity; it was I who kept you from committing a sin against me; for I would not let
        you touch her. <verse eId="Gen.20.6"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.20.7" sID="Gen.20.7"/> But now restore the man’s wife--for he is a prophet and
        he will intercede for you,
        <milestone type="pb" n="19"/>
        so that you may recover. If you do not restore her at once, know this, you shall die, you and
        all yours.</q>
       <verse eId="Gen.20.7"/>
      </p>
      <p>
       <verse osisID="Gen.20.8" sID="Gen.20.8"/>Next morning Abimelek rose, summoned all his officials,
        and told them everything. On hearing it, the men were terrified.
       <verse eId="Gen.20.8"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.20.9" sID="Gen.20.9"/> Then Abimelek summoned Abraham and said to him, <q>What have I done to you? How
        have I sinned against you, that you should involve me and my realm in a great sin? You have done to me what ought never to
        be done.</q>
       <verse eId="Gen.20.9"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.20.10" sID="Gen.20.10"/> Abimelek added, <q>What possessed you to do this?</q><verse eId="Gen.20.10"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.20.11" sID="Gen.20.11"/> <q>Because,</q> said Abraham, <q>I thought there was no religion here, and the
        people would kill me for the sake of my wife.
       <verse eId="Gen.20.11"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.20.12" sID="Gen.20.12"/>Besides, she really is my sister, a daughter to my father; only, she was not the
        daughter of my mother, and so she became my wife.
       <verse eId="Gen.20.12"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.20.13" sID="Gen.20.13"/>And when God sent me wandering from my father’s house, I said to her, <q>You must
        do me this kindness; wherever we go, say that I am your brother.</q></q>
       <verse eId="Gen.20.13"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.20.14" sID="Gen.20.14"/>Then Abimelek made a present of sheep, oxen, and slaves, male and female, to
        Abraham and restored his wife Sarah to him. <verse eId="Gen.20.14"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.20.15" sID="Gen.20.15"/>
        <q>There lies my land be­fore you,</q> said Abimelek; <q>reside wherever you please.</q> <verse eId="Gen.20.15"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.20.16" sID="Gen.20.16"/>He said to Sarah, <q>Look, I have given your brother a hundred and forty pounds
        in silver as compensation for all that has happened to you; in the eyes of all men your honour is cleared.</q> <verse eId="Gen.20.16"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.20.17" sID="Gen.20.17"/> Then Abraham prayed to God, and God cured Abimelek and his wife and his
        concubines, so that they now bore children <verse eId="Gen.20.17"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.20.18" sID="Gen.20.18"/> (for the Eternal had entirely closed the wombs of all in Abimelek’s household,
        on account of Sarah, Abraham’s wife.)] <verse eId="Gen.20.18"/>
      </p>
     <chapter eId="Gen.20"/>
     <chapter osisId="Gen.21" sId="Gen.21"/>
      <p>
       <verse osisID="Gen.21.1" sID="Gen.21.1"/>
        <hi type="italic">
         Now the Eternal dealt with Sarah as he had said,
        </hi>
       <verse eId="Gen.21.1"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.21.2" sID="Gen.21.2"/>the Eternal did for Sarah what he had promised, and Sarah conceived; she bore a
        son for Abraham’s old age,<verse eId="Gen.21.2"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.21.3" sID="Gen.21.3"/> when the time came round of which God had told him. Abraham called the son born
        to him by Sarah, Isaac, <verse eId="Gen.21.3"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.21.4" sID="Gen.21.4"/> and when Isaac was eight days old, Abraham circumcised his son, as God had ordered him. <verse eId="Gen.21.4"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.21.5" sID="Gen.21.5"/> Abraham was a hundred years old when his son Isaac was born. <verse eId="Gen.21.5"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.21.6" sID="Gen.21.6"/> [So Sarah said, <q>God has prepared laughter for me</q>; <verse eId="Gen.21.6"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.21.7" sID="Gen.21.7"/> she said,
        <q><lq>
         <l> Think of anyone telling Abraham, </l>
         <l> <q>Sarah is suckling a child</q>! </l>
         <l> I have borne him a son for his old age, </l>
         <l> and all who hear it will laugh over me! </l>
        </lq></q>
       <verse eId="Gen.21.7"/>
      </p>
      <p>
       <verse osisID="Gen.21.8" sID="Gen.21.8"/>When the child grew up and was weaned, Abraham held a great feast on the day of
        his weaning. <verse eId="Gen.21.8"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.21.9" sID="Gen.21.9"/> But Sarah noticed the son of Hagar the Egyptian, whom she had borne to Abraham,
        playing along with her son Isaac; <verse eId="Gen.21.9"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.21.10" sID="Gen.21.10"/>so she told Abraham, <q>Put away that slave-girl and her boy; the son of
        that slave- girl is not to be heir along with my son, with Isaac.</q> <verse eId="Gen.21.10"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.21.11" sID="Gen.21.11"/> Now Abraham resented this keenly, on account of his boy. <verse eId="Gen.21.11"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.21.12" sID="Gen.21.12"/> But God said to Abraham, <q>Do not resent it on account of the lad and
        your slave-girl; listen to Sarah’s bidding, for it is through Isaac that your name shall be carried on. <verse eId="Gen.21.12"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.21.13" sID="Gen.21.13"/> I will make another nation out of the son of your slave-girl, because he is
        your child.</q> <verse eId="Gen.21.13"/>
      </p>
      <p>
       <verse osisID="Gen.21.14" sID="Gen.21.14"/>Next morning Abraham rose and gave Hagar some food and a waterskin; he put
        the boy upon her shoulder and sent her off. She went away and wandered in the desert of Beersheba; <verse eId="Gen.21.14"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.21.15" sID="Gen.21.15"/>and
        <milestone type="pb" n="20"/>
        when the water in the skin was done, she threw the child under a bush,<verse eId="Gen.21.15"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.21.16" sID="Gen.21.16"/>and sat down about a bowshot from him, saying to herself, <q>I cannot bear to see
        the child dying.</q>But, as she sat opposite him, the boy wept aloud, <verse eId="Gen.21.16"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.21.17" sID="Gen.21.17"/>and God heard his cry; then the angel of God called from heaven to Hagar,
        <q>Hagar, what is the matter with you? Fear not, for God has heard the cry of the boy where he is lying. <verse eId="Gen.21.17"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.21.18" sID="Gen.21.18"/> Come, lift the boy and hold him, for I will make him a great nation.</q> <verse eId="Gen.21.18"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.21.19" sID="Gen.21.19"/>And God opened her eyes; she saw a well of water. Then she went and filled
        the skin with water, and gave the boy a drink. <verse eId="Gen.21.19"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.21.20" sID="Gen.21.20"/> God was with him; he grew up to be an archer in the desert,
       <verse eId="Gen.21.20"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.21.21" sID="Gen.21.21"/> living in the desert of Paran, and his mother got a wife for him from
        the land of Egypt.] <verse eId="Gen.21.21"/>
      </p>
      <p>
       <verse osisID="Gen.21.14" sID="Gen.21.14"/>Next morning Abraham rose and gave Hagar some food and a waterskin; he put
        the boy upon her shoulder and sent her off. She went away and wandered in the desert of Beersheba; <verse eId="Gen.21.14"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.21.15" sID="Gen.21.15"/>and
        <milestone type="pb" n="21"/>
        when the water in the skin was done, she threw the child under a bush,<verse eId="Gen.21.15"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.21.16" sID="Gen.21.16"/>and sat down about a bowshot from him, saying to herself, <q>I cannot bear to see
        the child dying.</q>But, as she sat opposite him, the boy wept aloud, <verse eId="Gen.21.16"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.21.17" sID="Gen.21.17"/>and God heard his cry; then the angel of God called from heaven to Hagar,
        <q>Hagar, what is the matter with you? Fear not, for God has heard the cry of the boy where he is lying. <verse eId="Gen.21.17"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.21.18" sID="Gen.21.18"/> Come, lift the boy and hold him, for I will make him a great nation.</q> <verse eId="Gen.21.18"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.21.19" sID="Gen.21.19"/>And God opened her eyes; she saw a well of water. Then she went and filled
        the skin with water, and gave the boy a drink. <verse eId="Gen.21.19"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.21.20" sID="Gen.21.20"/> God was with him; he grew up to be an archer in the desert, <verse eId="Gen.21.20"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.21.21" sID="Gen.21.21"/> living in the desert of Paran, and his mother got a wife for him from the land of Egypt.] <verse eId="Gen.21.21"/>
      </p>
      <p>
       <verse osisID="Gen.21.22" sID="Gen.21.22"/>[Now at that time Abimelek and Phicol his general said to Abraham, <q>God
        is with you in all that you do! <verse eId="Gen.21.22"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.21.23" sID="Gen.21.23"/> Come now, swear here to me by God that you will not be false to me nor to
        my son nor to my descendants, but that, as I have treated you kindly, so you will treat me and the land where you are
        living.</q> <verse eId="Gen.21.23"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.21.24" sID="Gen.21.24"/> <q>I will swear it,</q>” said Abraham; <verse eId="Gen.21.24"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.21.27" sID="Gen.21.27"/> so Abraham gave a present of sheep and oxen to Abimelek, and the two men 
        made a compact. <verse eId="Gen.21.27"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.21.31" sID="Gen.21.31"/> Hence the spot was called Beersheba (Oath-well) because the two men swore
        an oath there.] <verse eId="Gen.21.31"/>
      </p>
      <p>
       <hi type="italic">
        <verse osisID="Gen.21.25" sID="Gen.21.25"/>Whenever Abraham complained to Abimelek about some well of water
         which Abimelek’s slaves had seized, <verse eId="Gen.21.25"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.21.26" sID="Gen.21.26"/>Abimelek would reply, <q>I do not know who did this; you never told me about
         it; I never heard of it till to-day.</q>
        <verse eId="Gen.21.26"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.21.28" sID="Gen.21.28"/> Then Abraham set
         <milestone type="column" n="2"/>
         apart seven ewe lambs of the flock. <verse eId="Gen.21.28"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.21.29" sID="Gen.21.29"/> And when Abimelek asked Abraham, <q>What are these seven ewe lambs that
         you have set apart?</q> <verse eId="Gen.21.29"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.21.30" sID="Gen.21.30"/> he replied, <q>You will accept these seven ewe lambs from me, in token
         of the fact that it was I who dug these wells.</q> <verse eId="Gen.21.30"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.21.32" sID="Gen.21.32"/> So they made a compact at Beersheba. Abimelek and Phicol his general
         left to return to the Philistine country, <verse eId="Gen.21.32"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.21.33" sID="Gen.21.33"/> while Abraham planted a tamarisk at Beersheba and there worshipped
         the Eternal, the everlasting God. <verse eId="Gen.21.33"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.21.34" sID="Gen.21.34"/> For many a day Abraham lived in the Philistine country. <verse eId="Gen.21.34"/>
       </hi>
      </p>
     <chapter eId="Gen.21"/>
     <chapter osisId="Gen.22" sId="Gen.22"/>
      <p>
       <verse osisID="Gen.22.1" sID="Gen.22.1"/>[After this God put eyey Abraham to the test. <q>Abraham,</q> he said,
        and Abraham answered, <q>Here I am.</q> <verse eId="Gen.22.1"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.22.2" sID="Gen.22.2"/>And he said, <q>Take your son, your only son, the son you love, take
        Isaac and go to the district of Moriah; there offer him in sacrifice on one of the hills which I will name to you.</q> <verse eId="Gen.22.2"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.22.3" sID="Gen.22.3"/> Next morning Abraham rose and saddled his ass, taking with him two of his
        servants and his son Isaac; he cut wood for burning the sacrifice, and started for the spot of which God had told him. <verse eId="Gen.22.3"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.22.4" sID="Gen.22.4"/> On the third day Abraham looked up and saw the spot at a distance.<verse eId="Gen.22.4"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.22.5" sID="Gen.22.5"/> Then Abraham said to his servants, <q>You stay here with the ass; the lad and
        I are going yonder to worship, and then we will come back to you.</q> <verse eId="Gen.22.5"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.22.6" sID="Gen.22.6"/> So Abraham took the wood for burning the sacrifice and laid it on his son
        Isaac, he himself carrying the fire and the knife. The two went off together. <verse eId="Gen.22.6"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.22.7" sID="Gen.22.7"/><q>My father,</q> said Isaac to his father Abraham. <q>Yes, my boy,</q>
        he said. <q>Here are the fire and the wood,</q> said Isaac, <q>but where is the sheep for the sacrifice?</q> <verse eId="Gen.22.7"/>
        <milestone type="pb" n="22"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.22.8" sID="Gen.22.8"/>Abraham answered, <q>God will provide himself with a sheep for the sacrifice,
        my boy.</q> So the two went on together, <verse eId="Gen.22.8"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.22.9" sID="Gen.22.9"/>and reached the spot of which God had told him. Here Abraham built the altar,
        arranged the wood, and, binding his son Isaac, laid him upon the wood on the altar. <verse eId="Gen.22.9"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.22.10" sID="Gen.22.10"/> Then Abraham put out his hand and lifted the knife to cut the throat of
        his son. <verse eId="Gen.22.10"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.22.11" sID="Gen.22.11"/> But the angel of God called to him from heaven, <q>Abraham, Abraham!</q>
        He said, <q>Here I am.</q> <verse eId="Gen.22.11"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.22.12" sID="Gen.22.12"/> The angel said, <q>Do not lay hands on the lad, do nothing to him;
        I now know that you revere God, since you have not grudged me your son, your only son.</q> <verse eId="Gen.22.12"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.22.13" sID="Gen.22.13"/> Then looking up Abraham glanced round, and there was a ram caught in the
        brushwood by its horns! So Abraham took the ram and offered it as a sacrifice instead of his son; <verse eId="Gen.22.13"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.22.14" sID="Gen.22.14"/> and Abraham called the spot Yahweh-yireh— as the saying goes, to this day,
        <q>God provides on the hill.</q>] <verse eId="Gen.22.14"/>
      </p>
      <p>
       <verse osisID="Gen.22.15" sID="Gen.22.15"/>[[Then the angel of the Eternal called a second time to Abraham from heaven, <verse eId="Gen.22.15"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.22.16" sID="Gen.22.16"/> saying, <q>I swear by myself,</q> says the Eternal, <q>since you have done this,
        since you have not grudged your son, your only son, <verse eId="Gen.22.16"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.22.17" sID="Gen.22.17"/>that I will indeed bless you, I will indeed make your descendants as
        numerous as the stars in the sky and the sand on the sea-shore;your descendants shall conquer the seats of their foes, <verse eId="Gen.22.17"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.22.18" sID="Gen.22.18"/>and all nations on earth shall seek bliss like theirs—and all because you
        have obeyed my word.</q>]] <verse eId="Gen.22.18"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.22.19" sID="Gen.22.19"/> [So Abraham went back to his servants, and they started together for
        Beersheba where Abraham lived.] <verse eId="Gen.22.19"/>
      </p>
      <p>
       <hi type="italic">
        <verse osisID="Gen.22.20" sID="Gen.22.20"/>After this Abraham was told that Milkah had borne children to his
         brother Nahor, <verse eId="Gen.22.20"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.22.21" sID="Gen.22.21"/> Uz the eldest, Buz his brother, Kemuel (the ancestor of the Aramaeans), <verse eId="Gen.22.21"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.22.22" sID="Gen.22.22"/> Kesed, Hazo, Pildash, Jidlaph, and Bethuel <verse eId="Gen.22.22"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.22.23" sID="Gen.22.23"/> (the father of Rebekah). These eight were borne by Milkah to Abraham's brother
         Nahor; <verse eId="Gen.22.23"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.22.24" sID="Gen.22.24"/> his concubine, who was called. Reumah, also bore him Tebah, Gaham, Tahash, and
         Maakah. <verse eId="Gen.22.24"/>
       </hi>
      </p>
     <chapter eId="Gen.22"/>
     <chapter osisId="Gen.23" sId="Gen.23"/>
      <p>
       <verse osisID="Gen.23.1" sID="Gen.23.1"/>Sarah lived a hundred and twenty-seven years; these were the years of Sarah's
        life. <verse eId="Gen.23.1"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.23.2" sID="Gen.23.2"/>Sarah died at Kiriatharba (that is, Hebron) in the land of Canaan. After going
        indoors to wail and weep for Sarah,
       <verse eId="Gen.23.2"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.23.3" sID="Gen.23.3"/>Abraham rose from mourning beside his dead and said to the Hittites,
       <verse eId="Gen.23.3"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.23.4" sID="Gen.23.4"/>
        <q> I am a foreigner, residing among you; let me have a burying-place among you, that I may bury my dead out of
         sight.</q> <verse eId="Gen.23.4"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.23.5" sID="Gen.23.5"/> The Hittites answered Abraham, <verse eId="Gen.23.5"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.23.6" sID="Gen.23.6"/> <q>Pray listen to us, my lord; you are a great prince among us, bury your
        dead in the choicest of our sepulchres; not a man of us would grudge you his sepulchre for burying your dead.</q> <verse eId="Gen.23.6"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.23.7" sID="Gen.23.7"/> Abraham rose and bowed to the Hit­tites, the natives of the land; <verse eId="Gen.23.7"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.23.8" sID="Gen.23.8"/> he addressed them, saying, <q>If it is your will that I should bury my dead
        out of sight, listen to me; speak for me to Ephron the son of Zohar,<verse eId="Gen.23.8"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.23.9" sID="Gen.23.9"/> and ask him to give me the cave at Makpelah that belongs to him, at the corner
        of his field; let him sell it to me in your presence for its full value, that I may have it as a burying-place.</q>
       <verse eId="Gen.23.9"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.23.10" sID="Gen.23.10"/> Ephron was sitting among the Hittites. So Ephron the Hittite answered
        Abraham in presence of the Hittites, of all the citizens of his town. <verse eId="Gen.23.10"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.23.11" sID="Gen.23.11"/><q>No, my lord,</q> he said, <q>listen to me; I give you the field, I
        <milestone type="pb" n="23"/>
        give you the cave in the field; before the sons of my people I give it to you; bury your dead there.</q>
       <verse eId="Gen.23.11"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.23.12" sID="Gen.23.12"/>Then Abraham bowed low before the natives, <verse eId="Gen.23.12"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.23.13" sID="Gen.23.13"/> and said to Ephron in presence of the natives, <q>If only you would--ah,
        now, listen to me! I will pay for the field; take the money for it, and I will bury my dead there.</q> <verse eId="Gen.23.13"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.23.14" sID="Gen.23.14"/>Ephron answered Abraham, <verse eId="Gen.23.14"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.23.15" sID="Gen.23.15"/> <q>Pray listen to me, my lord; a bit of land worth fifty pounds, what is
        a trifle like that between me and you? So bury your dead.</q> <verse eId="Gen.23.15"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.23.16" sID="Gen.23.16"/> Abraham listened to what Ephron said, and weighed out for Ephron the sum he
        had named in presence of the Hittites, fifty pounds in current silver ingots. <verse eId="Gen.23.16"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.23.17" sID="Gen.23.17"/> Thus the field of Ephron at Makpelah, east of Mamre, the field, the cave in
        the field, and all the trees in the field and on its bor­ders, <verse eId="Gen.23.17"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.23.18" sID="Gen.23.18"/> were conveyed over to Abraham as his property, in presence of the Hittites,
        before all the citizens of Ephron’s town. <verse eId="Gen.23.18"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.23.19" sID="Gen.23.19"/> After that, Abraham buried his wife Sarah in the cave of the field at
        Makpelah, east of Mamre (that is, Hebron) in the land of Canaan; <verse eId="Gen.23.19"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.23.20" sID="Gen.23.20"/>the field and the cave in it were conveyed over to Abraham as his own
        property and burying-place by the Hittites. <verse eId="Gen.23.20"/>
      </p>
     <chapter eId="Gen.23"/>
     <chapter osisId="Gen.24" sId="Gen.24"/>
      <p>
       <hi type="italic">
        <verse osisID="Gen.24.1" sID="Gen.24.1"/>Now Abraham was old, well advanced in years, the Eternal had 
         prospered Abraham in every way, <verse eId="Gen.24.1"/>
     <chapter eId="Gen.24"/>
     <chapter osisId="Gen.25" sId="Gen.25"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.25.5" sID="Gen.25.5"/> and to Isaac Abraham gave all his prop­erty. <verse eId="Gen.25.5"/>
     <chapter eId="Gen.25"/>
     <chapter osisId="Gen.24" sId="Gen.24"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.24.2" sID="Gen.24.2"/>Then Abraham said to the oldest servant in his household, the man who took
         charge of all that he had, <q>Pray, place your hand under my thigh, <verse eId="Gen.24.2"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.24.3" sID="Gen.24.3"/>and I will make you swear an oath by the Eternal, God of heaven and God of
         earth, that
         <milestone type="column" n="2"/>
         you will never marry my son to a daughter of the Canaanites among whom I am living; <verse eId="Gen.24.3"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.24.4" sID="Gen.24.4"/> no, you must go to my own country and kindred, and choose a wife for my son
         Isaac.</q> <verse eId="Gen.24.4"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.24.5" sID="Gen.24.5"/> <q>But,</q> said the servant, <q>suppose the woman is unwilling to follow me]
         to this land; am I to take your son back to the land from which you came?</q> <verse eId="Gen.24.5"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.24.6" sID="Gen.24.6"/> Abraham said to him, <q>Beware of taking my son back! <verse eId="Gen.24.6"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.24.7" sID="Gen.24.7"/>The Eternal, God of heaven and God of earth, who brought me away from my
         father’s house and from the land of my birth, who talked to me, who swore to me that he would give this land to my
         descendants, the Eternal will send his angel before you, and provide you with a wife for my son yonder. <verse eId="Gen.24.7"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.24.8" sID="Gen.24.8"/> If the woman is unwilling to follow you, then you are free from this oath of
         mine. Only, you must never take my son back there.</q> <verse eId="Gen.24.8"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.24.9" sID="Gen.24.9"/> Then the servant put his hand under the thigh of his master Abraham and swore
         as he was told to swear. <verse eId="Gen.24.9"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.24.10" sID="Gen.24.10"/> He took ten of his master’s camels to carry a present from his master’s
         treasures, and started for Mesopotamia, for the town of Nahor. <verse eId="Gen.24.10"/>
       </hi>
      </p>
      <p>
       <hi type="italic">
        <verse osisID="Gen.24.11" sID="Gen.24.11"/>Outside the town he made the camels kneel beside the well of water at the
         evening hour, when women come out to draw water. <verse eId="Gen.24.11"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.24.12" sID="Gen.24.12"/><q>O Eternal,</q> he said, <q>God of my master Abraham, pray let me succeed
         to-day, pray be kind to my master Abraham. <verse eId="Gen.24.12"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.24.13" sID="Gen.24.13"/>Here I stand, beside the fountain! The daughters of the citizens are coming
         out to draw water. <verse eId="Gen.24.13"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.24.14" sID="Gen.24.14"/> Now may the maiden to whom I say, <q>Pray lower your pitcher, that I may
         drink,</q> the maiden who an­swers, <q>Drink, and let me give a drink to your camels also</q>--may she be the maiden
         thou hast
        <milestone type="pb" n="24"/>
         allotted to thy servant Isaac! So shall I know that thou hast been kind to my master.</q> <verse eId="Gen.24.14"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.24.15" sID="Gen.24.15"/> Ere he had done speaking, out came Rebekah, a daughter of Bethuel the son
         of Milkah (the wife of Abra­ham’s brother Nahor). She car­ried her pitcher on her shoulder; <verse eId="Gen.24.15"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.24.16" sID="Gen.24.16"/> she was a beautiful girl, unmar­ried, and a virgin. Down she stepped to the
         fountain and filled her pitcher; as she came up, <verse eId="Gen.24.16"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.24.17" sID="Gen.24.17"/> the servant ran to meet her, say­ing, <q>Pray let me drink a little water
         from your pitcher.</q> <verse eId="Gen.24.17"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.24.18" sID="Gen.24.18"/><q>Drink, sir,</q> she said, and low­ering the pitcher rapidly to her hand,
         she gave him a drink. <verse eId="Gen.24.18"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.24.19" sID="Gen.24.19"/>When she had finished giving him a drink, she said, <q>Let me draw water for
         your camels also, till they have enough,</q> <verse eId="Gen.24.19"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.24.20" sID="Gen.24.20"/> So she quickly emptied her pitcher into the trough, and ran again to the
         well to draw water, doing this for all his camels. <verse eId="Gen.24.20"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.24.21" sID="Gen.24.21"/>The man gazed at her in silence, to see if the Eternal had made his errand
         successful or not. <verse eId="Gen.24.21"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.24.22" sID="Gen.24.22"/> When the camels had finished drinking, he took a golden nose-ring weighing
         a quarter of an ounce, and two golden bracelets weighing five ounces, <verse eId="Gen.24.22"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.24.23" sID="Gen.24.23"/> and asked her, <q>Whose daughter are you? Pray tell me. Is there a place
         for me to put up in, at your father’s house?</q> <verse eId="Gen.24.23"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.24.24" sID="Gen.24.24"/>She said to him, <q>I am the daughter of Bethuel the son of Milkah, whom she
         bore to Nahor.</q> <verse eId="Gen.24.24"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.24.25" sID="Gen.24.25"/> She added, <q>We have ample straw and fodder, and there is a place for you
         to put up in.</q> <verse eId="Gen.24.25"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.24.26" sID="Gen.24.26"/> The man bowed his head, adoring the Eternal. <verse eId="Gen.24.26"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.24.27" sID="Gen.24.27"/><q>Blessed be the Eter­nal</q> he said, <q>the God of my master Abraham, who
         has not ceased to be kind and true to my master! And as for myself, the Eternal has led me straight to the house of my
         master’s kins­folk.</q> <verse eId="Gen.24.27"/>
       </hi>
      </p>
      <p>
       <hi type="italic">
        <verse osisID="Gen.24.28" sID="Gen.24.28"/>Then the girl ran and told her mother's household about it.<verse eId="Gen.24.28"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.24.29" sID="Gen.24.29"/>Now Rebekah had a brother called Laban. Laban ran out to the man at the
         fountain <verse eId="Gen.24.29"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.24.30" sID="Gen.24.30"/> (he had seen the nose-ring, and the bracelets on his sister’s hands, and
         heard his sister Rebekah telling what the man had said to her). When he reached the man, there he was, standing
         beside the camels at the fountain! <verse eId="Gen.24.30"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.24.31" sID="Gen.24.31"/><q>Come in,</q>” he said, <q>you whom the Eternal has blessed! Why stand
         outside? I have the house all ready, and a place cleared for the camels.</q> <verse eId="Gen.24.31"/>
       </hi>
      </p>
      <p>
       <hi type="italic">
        <verse osisID="Gen.24.32" sID="Gen.24.32"/>So the man went indoors and unshackled the camels, while Laban brought straw
         and fodder for the camels and water for the man and his companions to wash their feet. <verse eId="Gen.24.32"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.24.33" sID="Gen.24.33"/> Then food was set before him; but he said, <q>I will not eat, till I have
         told my er­rand.</q> <q>Say on,</q> said Laban. <verse eId="Gen.24.33"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.24.34" sID="Gen.24.34"/> And he said, <q>I am Abraham’s servant. <verse eId="Gen.24.34"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.24.35" sID="Gen.24.35"/> The Eternal has richly blessed my master, so that he is a great man; he has
         given him flocks and herds, silver and gold, male and female slaves, camels and asses. <verse eId="Gen.24.35"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.24.36" sID="Gen.24.36"/> When Sarah my master's wife was old, she bore a son to my master, and he
         has given this son all his property. <verse eId="Gen.24.36"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.24.37" sID="Gen.24.37"/> My master made me swear this, <q>you must never marry my son to a daughter
         of the Canaanites in whose land I am living; <verse eId="Gen.24.37"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.24.38" sID="Gen.24.38"/> no, you must go to my father’s house­hold and my own kindred, to get a wife
         for my son.</q> <verse eId="Gen.24.38"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.24.39" sID="Gen.24.39"/> <q>But,</q> I said to my master, <q>suppose the woman is unwilling to
         follow me.</q> <verse eId="Gen.24.39"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.24.40" sID="Gen.24.40"/> He answered, <q>The Eternal, of whose presence I am ever mindful, will send
         his angel along with you and make your journey
         <milestone type="pb" n="25"/>
         a success, till you get a wife for my son from my own kindred and my father’s house, <verse eId="Gen.24.40"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.24.41" sID="Gen.24.41"/> and then you shall be free from your oath to me; when you reach my kin­dred--
         if they will not let you have her, you are free from your oath to me!</q> <verse eId="Gen.24.41"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.24.42" sID="Gen.24.42"/> To-day I came to the fountain and prayed, <q>O Eternal, God of my master
         Abraham, if thou really makest my errand a success, <verse eId="Gen.24.42"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.24.43" sID="Gen.24.43"/> grant that, as I stand here beside the foun­tain, the maiden who
         comes out to draw water, and to whom I say, <q>Pray let me have a little water to drink out of your pitcher,</q> <verse eId="Gen.24.43"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.24.44" sID="Gen.24.44"/> the maiden who an­swers, <q>Drink yourself, and let me draw water also for
         your camels</q>--may she be the woman whom the Eternal has allotted to my master’s son!</q> <verse eId="Gen.24.44"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.24.45" sID="Gen.24.45"/> Ere I had done saying this to myself, out came Rebekah with her pitcher on
         her shoulder; she stepped down to the fountain and drew water, and when I said, <q>Pray let me have a little water to
         drink,</q> <verse eId="Gen.24.45"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.24.46" sID="Gen.24.46"/>she lowered her pitcher rapidly from her shoulder, saying, <q>Drink, and let
         me give your camels a drink also!</q> So I drank, and she made the camels also drink. <verse eId="Gen.24.46"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.24.47" sID="Gen.24.47"/> I asked her, <q>Whose daughter are you?</q> She said, <q>I am the daughter
         of Bethuel, Nahor’s son, whom Milkah bore!</q> Then I put the ring on her nose and the bracelets on her hands; <verse eId="Gen.24.47"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.24.48" sID="Gen.24.48"/> I bowed my head, adoring the Eternal, blessing the Eternal, the God of my
         master Abraham, who had led me by the right road to win my master’s kins­man’s daughter for his son. <verse eId="Gen.24.48"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.24.49" sID="Gen.24.49"/> Now, tell me whether or no you will deal kindly and straightfor­wardly with
         my master, so that I may know what to do next.</q> <verse eId="Gen.24.49"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.24.50" sID="Gen.24.50"/> Laban and his household replied, <q>This comes from the Eternal; we dare
         not say yes or no to you. <verse eId="Gen.24.50"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.24.51" sID="Gen.24.51"/> Here is Rebekah, take her and go; let her be the wife of your master’s son,
         as the Eternal has signified.</q> <verse eId="Gen.24.51"/>
       </hi>
      </p>
      <p>
       <hi type="italic">
        <verse osisID="Gen.24.52" sID="Gen.24.52"/>When Abraham’s servant heard this, he bowed to the ground before the
         Eternal; <verse eId="Gen.24.52"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.24.53" sID="Gen.24.53"/>then he took out jewels of silver, jew­els of gold, and garments, which he
         gave to Rebekah; he also pre­sented costly gifts to her brother and her mother. <verse eId="Gen.24.53"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.24.54" sID="Gen.24.54"/> He and his men ate and drank and stayed all night. When they rose in the
         morning, he said, <q>Send me back to my master.</q> <verse eId="Gen.24.54"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.24.55" sID="Gen.24.55"/> Her brother and her mother said, <q>Let the girl re­main with us for a week
         or ten days; and then she can go.</q> <verse eId="Gen.24.55"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.24.56" sID="Gen.24.56"/> But he replied, <q>Do not hinder me: the Eternal has made my errand a
         success; send me away, that l may return to my master.</q> <verse eId="Gen.24.56"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.24.57" sID="Gen.24.57"/><q>We will call the girl,</q> they said, <q>and ask herself.</q> <verse eId="Gen.24.57"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.24.58" sID="Gen.24.58"/> So they called Rebekah, and asked her, <q>Will you go with this man?</q>
         She replied, <q>I will.</q> <verse eId="Gen.24.58"/>
       </hi>
      </p>
      <p>
       <hi type="italic">
        <verse osisID="Gen.24.59" sID="Gen.24.59"/>So they sent off their sister Rebekah, with her nurse and Abraham’s servant
         and his men, <verse eId="Gen.24.59"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.24.60" sID="Gen.24.60"/> blessing Rebekah in these words,
         <q><lg>
          <l> Sister, may you be the mother of myriads! </l>
          <l> May your descendants conquer all who hate them! </l>
         </lg></q>
        <verse eId="Gen.24.60"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.24.61" sID="Gen.24.61"/> Then Rebekah and her maidens started, riding on camels, after the man.
         Thus the servant took Rebekah and went off. <verse eId="Gen.24.61"/>
       </hi>
      </p>
      <p>
       <hi type="italic">
        <verse osisID="Gen.24.62" sID="Gen.24.62"/>Now Isaac had come across the desert as far as Beer-lahairoi (for he lived
         in the south country). <verse eId="Gen.24.62"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.24.63" sID="Gen.24.63"/> It was evening, and he had gone out to mourn in the fields; as he looked
         up, he saw there were camels coming. <verse eId="Gen.24.63"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.24.64" sID="Gen.24.64"/>
         When Rebekah looked up and saw Isaac, she alighted from her
         <milestone type="pb" n="26"/>
         camel <verse eId="Gen.24.64"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.24.65" sID="Gen.24.65"/> and asked the servant, <q>Who is yonder man walking in the fields to meet
         us?</q> The servant said, <q>It is my master.</q> Then she took her veil and covered herself. <verse eId="Gen.24.65"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.24.66" sID="Gen.24.66"/> The servant told Isaac all that he had done, <verse eId="Gen.24.66"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.24.67" sID="Gen.24.67"/> and Isaac took her inside his tent; Rebekah became his wife, and he loved
         her. So Isaac consoled himself after his mother’s death.
        <verse eId="Gen.24.67"/>
       </hi>
      </p>
     <chapter eId="Gen.24"/>
     <chapter osisId="Gen.25" sId="Gen.25"/>
      <p>
       <hi type="italic">
        <verse osisID="Gen.25.1" sID="Gen.25.1"/>Abraham married another wife, called Keturah; <verse eId="Gen.25.1"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.25.2" sID="Gen.25.2"/> she bore him Zimran, Jokshan, Me­dan, Midian, Ishbak, and Shuah.<verse eId="Gen.25.2"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.25.3" sID="Gen.25.3"/> Jokshan was the father of Sheba and Dedan, and from Dedan sprang the
         Asshurim, the Letushim, and the Leummim. <verse eId="Gen.25.3"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.25.4" sID="Gen.25.4"/>From Midian sprang Ephah, Epher, Hanok, Abida, and Eldaah. All these were
         Keturah’s children. <verse eId="Gen.25.4"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.25.6" sID="Gen.25.6"/>To the sons of his concubines Abraham gave presents, and sent them away
         eastward to the land of Kedem, before he died, to leave no burden upon his son Isaac. <verse eId="Gen.25.6"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.25.11" sID="Gen.25.11"/> Isaac lived at Beer-lahairoi. <verse eId="Gen.25.11"/>
       </hi>
      </p>
      <p>
       <verse osisID="Gen.25.7" sID="Gen.25.7"/>The years that Abraham lived were a hundred and seventy-five;<verse eId="Gen.25.7"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.25.8" sID="Gen.25.8"/>he breathed his last, dying in a ripe old age, an old man, after a full life,
        and was gath­ered to his father’s kindred. <verse eId="Gen.25.8"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.25.9" sID="Gen.25.9"/> Isaac and Ishmael his sons buried him in the cave at Makpelah, in the field
        of Ephron the Hittite, the son of Zohar, that lies east of Mamre, <verse eId="Gen.25.9"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.25.10" sID="Gen.25.10"/> the field that Abraham had bought from the Hittites. There Abraham was
        buried, with his wife Sarah. <verse eId="Gen.25.10"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.25.11" sID="Gen.25.11"/> And after Abraham’s death God blessed his son Isaac. <verse eId="Gen.25.11"/>
      </p>
      <p>
       <verse osisID="Gen.25.12" sID="Gen.25.12"/>Here are the descendants of Ishmael the son of Abraham, whom Hagar, the
        Egyptian, Sarah’s maid, bore to Abraham; <verse eId="Gen.25.12"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.25.13" sID="Gen.25.13"/> here are the names of Ishmael’s sons, according to their genealo­gies.
        Nebaioth the eldest, then Kedar, Adbeel, Mibsam, <verse eId="Gen.25.13"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.25.14" sID="Gen.25.14"/> Mishma, Dumah, Massa, <verse eId="Gen.25.14"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.25.15" sID="Gen.25.15"/> Hadad, Tema, Jetur, Naphish, and Kedemah: <verse eId="Gen.25.15"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.25.16" sID="Gen.25.16"/> these are Ishmael’s sons, in the order of their vil­lages and encampments,
        twelve sheikhs with their clans. <verse eId="Gen.25.16"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.25.17" sID="Gen.25.17"/>The years of Ishmael’s life were a hundred and thirty-seven; he breathed
        his last, died, and was gathered to his father’s kin­dred. <verse eId="Gen.25.17"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.25.18" sID="Gen.25.18"/>
        <hi type="italic">
         The Ishmaelites lived between Havilah and Shur on the east of Egypt; they
         settled to the east of all their kinsmen.
        </hi>
       <verse eId="Gen.25.18"/>
      </p>
      <p>
       <verse osisID="Gen.25.19" sID="Gen.25.19"/>Here are the descendants of Isaac, Abraham’s son. Abra­ham was the father of
        Isaac, <verse eId="Gen.25.19"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.25.20" sID="Gen.25.20"/> and Isaac was forty years old when he married Rebekah, the daughter of
        Bethuel the Ara­maean (belonging to Paddan-aram) and the sister of Laban the Aramaean. <verse eId="Gen.25.20"/>
       <hi type="italic">
        <verse osisID="Gen.25.21" sID="Gen.25.21"/> Isaac besought the Eternal on behalf of his wife, for she was barren;
         the Eternal yielded to his entreaty, and his wife Rebekah conceived. <verse eId="Gen.25.21"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.25.22" sID="Gen.25.22"/> Twins were struggling in her womb, and she cried, <q>Why has this befallen
         me?</q> So she went to consult the Eternal. <verse eId="Gen.25.22"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.25.23" sID="Gen.25.23"/> And the Eternal told her,
         <q><lg>
          <l> In your womb lie nations twain, </l>
          <l> rival races from their birth; </l>
          <l> one the mastery shall gain, </l>
          <l> the younger o’er the older reign.” </l>
         </lg></q>
        <verse eId="Gen.25.23"/>
       </hi>
      </p>
      <p>
       <hi type="italic">
        <verse osisID="Gen.25.24" sID="Gen.25.24"/>When the time of her delivery came round, twins there were in her womb! <verse eId="Gen.25.24"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.25.25" sID="Gen.25.25"/> The first came out tawny, and hairy all over, like a mantle of hair; so
         they called him Esau (Hairy). <verse eId="Gen.25.25"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.25.26" sID="Gen.25.26"/> Then his brother came out, with his hand grasping Esau’s heel; so he was
         called Jacob (Heel-catcher). (Isaac was sixty years old when she bore them.)
        <verse eId="Gen.25.26"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.25.27" sID="Gen.25.27"/>
         The boys grew up; Esau was a skilful hunter, a man who lived in the open; Jacob was a quiet man, living in
         <milestone type="pb" n="27"/>
         tents. <verse eId="Gen.25.27"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.25.28" sID="Gen.25.28"/> Isaac was fond of Esau, for Esau’s venison was to his taste, but Rebekah
         was fond of Jacob. <verse eId="Gen.25.28"/>
       </hi>
      </p>
      <p>
       <hi type="italic">
        <verse osisID="Gen.25.29" sID="Gen.25.29"/>One day Jacob was cooking some food, when Esau came in famishing from the
         country; <verse eId="Gen.25.29"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.25.30" sID="Gen.25.30"/>Esau said to Jacob, <q>Let me have a bite of that red omelet there! I am
         famishing.</q> (Hence he was called Edom or Red.) <verse eId="Gen.25.30"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.25.31" sID="Gen.25.31"/> Jacob said, <q>First of all, sell me your birthright.</q><verse eId="Gen.25.31"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.25.32" sID="Gen.25.32"/>Esau an­swered, <q>Here am I dying of hunger! What good will the
         birthright be to me?</q> <verse eId="Gen.25.32"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.25.33" sID="Gen.25.33"/><q>Swear to me first of all,</q> said Jacob. So Esau swore to him, and,
         after he had sold his birthright to Jacob, Jacob gave Esau bread and stewed lentils; <verse eId="Gen.25.33"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.25.34" sID="Gen.25.34"/> Esau ate and drank, got up and went away--so little store did Esau set by
         his birthright. <verse eId="Gen.25.34"/>
       </hi>
      </p>
     <chapter eId="Gen.25"/>
     <chapter osisId="Gen.26" sId="Gen.26"/>
      <p>
       <hi type="italic">
        <verse osisID="Gen.26.1" sID="Gen.26.1"/>When a famine visited the land (in addition to the first famine during
         Abrahams life-time), Isaac went to Gerar, to Abimelek the king of the Philistines. <verse eId="Gen.26.1"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.26.2" sID="Gen.26.2"/>The Eternal ap­peared to him, saying, <q>[[Do not go down into Egypt; stay in
         the land of which I shall tell you.]] <verse eId="Gen.26.2"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.26.3" sID="Gen.26.3"/> Reside in this land, and I will be with you and bless you</q>
       </hi>
        <q>[[forto you and your descendants I give all this region; I will ratify the oath I swore to your father Abraham,
       <verse eId="Gen.26.3"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.26.4" sID="Gen.26.4"/>and I will make your descendants as numerous as the stars in the sky, and give
        all this region to your descendants, and all nations of the world shall seek bliss like theirs. <verse eId="Gen.26.4"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.26.5" sID="Gen.26.5"/> For Abra­ham obeyed my word and did his duty to me, following my orders, my
        rules and regulations]].</q> <verse eId="Gen.26.5"/>
       <hi type="italic">
        <verse osisID="Gen.26.6" sID="Gen.26.6"/> So Isaac stayed at Gerar. <verse eId="Gen.26.6"/>
       </hi>
      </p>
      <p>
       <hi type="italic">
        <verse osisID="Gen.26.7" sID="Gen.26.7"/>When the men of the place asked him about his wife, he said, <q>She is my sister</q>
         (for he was afraid to say, <q>She is my wife,</q> in case, he thought, the men of the place would kill him on account of
         Rebekah--she was so beautiful). <verse eId="Gen.26.7"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.26.8" sID="Gen.26.8"/> Now, after he had been there for some time, Abimelek the king of the Philistines
         was looking out of a window one day, and there he saw Isaac fondling his wife Rebekah! <verse eId="Gen.26.8"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.26.9" sID="Gen.26.9"/> Then Abimelek summoned Isaac. <q>So she is really your wife,</q> he said; <q>why
         did you say, <q>She is my sister?</q></q> Isaac answered, <q>Because I thought I might be killed on her account.</q> <verse eId="Gen.26.9"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.26.10" sID="Gen.26.10"/> Abimelek said, <q>What do you mean by this? One of my people plight easily have
         lain with your wife, and then you would have made us incur guilt!</q> <verse eId="Gen.26.10"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.26.11" sID="Gen.26.11"/>So Abimelek laid injunctions on all the people, saying, <q>Whoever touches this
         man or his wife shall be put to death.</q> <verse eId="Gen.26.11"/>
       </hi>
      </p>
      <p>
       <hi type="italic">
        <verse osisID="Gen.26.12" sID="Gen.26.12"/>Isaac sowed a crop in that country and reaped in the same year a hundredfold. The
         Eternal blessed him;<verse eId="Gen.26.12"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.26.13" sID="Gen.26.13"/>he grew rich and increased till he became very rich,<verse eId="Gen.26.13"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.26.14" sID="Gen.26.14"/>with property in flocks and herds and a large household. The Philistines became
         jealous of him. <verse eId="Gen.26.14"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.26.16" sID="Gen.26.16"/> So Abimelek said to Isaac, <q>Leave us; you are too great a man for us.</q> <verse eId="Gen.26.16"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.26.17" sID="Gen.26.17"/> Then Isaac left them and settled down to live in the valley of Gerar.
        <verse eId="Gen.26.17"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.26.15" sID="Gen.26.15"/>As the Philistines had choked with earth all the wells dug by his father’s slaves
         during the lifetime of his father Abraham, <verse eId="Gen.26.15"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.26.18" sID="Gen.26.18"/> Isaac re-opened the wells dug during the lifetime of his father Abraham, since
         the Philistines had stopped them after Abraham’s death. He called them by the names given by his father. <verse eId="Gen.26.18"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.26.19" sID="Gen.26.19"/>As Isaac’s slaves were digging in the valley, they came upon
         <milestone type="pb" n="28"/>
         a well of running water; <verse eId="Gen.26.19"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.26.20" sID="Gen.26.20"/> when the herdsmen of Gerar quarrelled with Isaac’s herdsmen, saying, <q>This
         water belongs to us,</q> he called the well Esek (quarrel) because they had quarrelled with him. <verse eId="Gen.26.20"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.26.21" sID="Gen.26.21"/>Another well was then dug, and over that they quarrelled too; so he called it
         Sitnah (Feud).<verse eId="Gen.26.21"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.26.22" sID="Gen.26.22"/>Changing his quarters, he dug another well; they did not quarrel over that, so he
         called it Rehoboth (Room)--<q>surely,</q> he said, <q>the Eternal has made room for us now, so that we can prosper in the 
         land.</q> <verse eId="Gen.26.22"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.26.23" sID="Gen.26.23"/> He then made his way up to Beersheba, <verse eId="Gen.26.23"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.26.24" sID="Gen.26.24"/>and that very night the Eternal appeared to him, saying, <q>I am the God of your
         father Abraham: fear not, I am with you and I will bless you and multiply your descendants, for the sake of my servant
         Abraham.</q> <verse eId="Gen.26.24"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.26.25" sID="Gen.26.25"/> There he built an altar, worshipped the Eternal, and pitched his tent;
         there also Isaac’s slaves dug a well. <verse eId="Gen.26.25"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.26.26" sID="Gen.26.26"/> Then Abimelek came to him from Gerar, with his vizier Ahuzzath and his general
         Phicol. <verse eId="Gen.26.26"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.26.27" sID="Gen.26.27"/> <q>Why come to me,</q> said Isaac, <q>when you hate me? You sent me away from
         you.</q> <verse eId="Gen.26.27"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.26.28" sID="Gen.26.28"/> They replied, <q>We have seen clearly that the Eternal is with you; so we
         thought, Let there be an oath between us--between us and yourself; let us make a compact with you, <verse eId="Gen.26.28"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.26.29" sID="Gen.26.29"/> that you will not injure us, as we have never touched you, but have only done
         good to you and sent you away in peace. And now you are blessed by the Eternal!</q><verse eId="Gen.26.29"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.26.30" sID="Gen.26.30"/>Then he made a banquet for them. They ate and drank, <verse eId="Gen.26.30"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.26.31" sID="Gen.26.31"/>and rising early next morning they swore their oath; Isaac sent them on their way,
         and they left him on terms of peace. <verse eId="Gen.26.31"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.26.32" sID="Gen.26.32"/> That very day Isaac’s slaves came and told him about a well they had dug; <q>we
         have found water,</q> they cried. <verse eId="Gen.26.32"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.26.33" sID="Gen.26.33"/> So Isaac called it Shibah (Oathwell); to this day the town is called Beersheba. <verse eId="Gen.26.33"/>
       </hi>
      </p>
      <p>
       <verse osisID="Gen.26.34" sID="Gen.26.34"/>When Esau was forty years old, he married Judith the daughter of Beeri the
        Hittite and Basemath the daughter of Elon the Hittite-- <verse eId="Gen.26.34"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.26.35" sID="Gen.26.35"/> which was a bitter disappointment to Isaac and Rebekah. <verse eId="Gen.26.35"/>
      </p>
     <chapter eId="Gen.26"/>
     <chapter osisId="Gen.27" sId="Gen.27"/>
      <p>
       <hi type="italic">
        <verse osisID="Gen.27.1" sID="Gen.27.1"/>Now when Isaac was an old man, his eyes so dim that he could not see, he
         called his older son Esau and said to him, <q>My son.</q> Esau answered, <q>Here I am.</q> <verse eId="Gen.27.1"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.27.2" sID="Gen.27.2"/>He went on: <q>I am an old man now, I know not how soon I may die. <verse eId="Gen.27.2"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.27.3" sID="Gen.27.3"/> Pray take your hunting weapons, your quiver and your bow, and go out into
         the country to get me some venison; <verse eId="Gen.27.3"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.27.4" sID="Gen.27.4"/>make me a tasty dish, such as I love, and bring it for me to eat, so that I
         can give you my blessing before I die.</q> <verse eId="Gen.27.4"/>
       </hi>
      </p>
      <p>
       <hi type="italic">
        <verse osisID="Gen.27.5" sID="Gen.27.5"/>Rebekah was listening while Isaac spoke to his son Esau; and when Esau went
         off to the coun­try to hunt for venison to give his father, <verse eId="Gen.27.5"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.27.6" sID="Gen.27.6"/> Rebekah said to her son Jacob, <q>I heard your father telling your brother
         Esau <verse eId="Gen.27.6"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.27.7" sID="Gen.27.7"/> to get him some venison and make a tasty dish, so that he could eat and
         then bless him in presence of the Eternal before he died. <verse eId="Gen.27.7"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.27.8" sID="Gen.27.8"/> Now, my son, do exactly as I tell you. <verse eId="Gen.27.8"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.27.9" sID="Gen.27.9"/> Go to the flock and fetch me two tender kids from the goats; I will make
         them into a tasty dish, such as your father loves, <verse eId="Gen.27.9"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.27.10" sID="Gen.27.10"/> and you can take it for your father to eat, so that he may bless you
         before he dies.</q> <verse eId="Gen.27.10"/>
       </hi>
      </p>
      <p>
       <verse osisID="Gen.27.11" sID="Gen.27.11"/>[But Jacob said to his mother Rebekah, <q>My brother Esau is a hairy man,
        and I am smooth. <verse eId="Gen.27.11"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.27.12" sID="Gen.27.12"/>Perhaps my father will feel me,
        <milestone type="pb" n="29"/>
        and then it will look as if I were mocking him; that will draw a curse, and not a blessing, upon me.</q> <verse eId="Gen.27.12"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.27.13" sID="Gen.27.13"/> His mother said to him, <q>On me be any curse meant for you, my son! Only
        do what I tell you. Go and fetch the kids.</q>] <verse eId="Gen.27.13"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.27.14" sID="Gen.27.14"/> So he went and fetched them for his mother, and his mother made a tasty
        dish, such as his father loved. <verse eId="Gen.27.14"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.27.15" sID="Gen.27.15"/>Then Rehekah took the best robes of Esau her older son, which she had lying
        beside her in the house, and dressed Jacob her younger son in them; <verse eId="Gen.27.15"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.27.16" sID="Gen.27.16"/> she [spread the skins of the kids over his hands and over the smooth part
        of his neck, and] <verse eId="Gen.27.16"/>
       <hi type="italic">
        <verse osisID="Gen.27.17" sID="Gen.27.17"/>put the tasty dish and the bread she had prepared into the hands of her
         son Jacob. <verse eId="Gen.27.17"/>
       </hi>
      </p>
      <p>
       <hi type="italic">
        <verse osisID="Gen.27.18" sID="Gen.27.18"/>He went to his father, saying, <q>My father.</q> Isaac said, <q>Yes? who are
         you, my son?</q> <verse eId="Gen.27.18"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.27.19" sID="Gen.27.19"/> Jacob answered his father, <q>I am Esau, your first-born, I have done as
         you told me; pray sit up and eat some of my venison, that you may give me your blessing.</q> <verse eId="Gen.27.19"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.27.20" sID="Gen.27.20"/> <q>My son,</q> said, Isaac, <q>how quickly you have found it!</q>
         <q>Yes,</q> he said, <q>the Eternal your God brought it to me.</q>
        <verse eId="Gen.27.20"/>
       </hi>
       <verse osisID="Gen.27.21" sID="Gen.27.21"/> [Isaac said to Jacob, <q>Pray come close, that I may feel you, my son, to
        see if you are really my son Esau or not.</q> <verse eId="Gen.27.21"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.27.22" sID="Gen.27.22"/>So Jacob went up to his father Isaac, who felt him and said, <q>The voice
        is Jacob’s voice, but the hands are the hands of Esau.</q> <verse eId="Gen.27.22"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.27.23" sID="Gen.27.23"/>He did not recognize him, for his hands were hairy, like his brother
        Esau’s. So he blessed him.] <verse eId="Gen.27.23"/>
       <hi type="italic">
        <verse osisID="Gen.27.24" sID="Gen.27.24"/> He said, <q>So you are my son Esau?</q> <q>Yes,</q> he answered. <verse eId="Gen.27.24"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.27.25" sID="Gen.27.25"/><q>Then bring me my son’s venison,</q> he said; <q>I will eat, and then
         give you my blessing.</q> Jacob brought it and he ate, brought him wine and he drank; <verse eId="Gen.27.25"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.27.26" sID="Gen.27.26"/> then his father Isaac said, <q>Come here, my son, and kiss me.</q>
        <verse eId="Gen.27.26"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.27.27" sID="Gen.27.27"/> He went up and kissed him. Isaac smelt his robes, and blessed him, saying,
         <q>Ah, the smell of my son is like the smell of a field blessed by the Eternal.
        <verse eId="Gen.27.27"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.27.28" sID="Gen.27.28"/>
         <lg>
          <l> God grant you dew from heaven </l>
          <l> and rich soil upon earth— </l>
          <l> corn and wine in plenty! </l>
        <verse eId="Gen.27.28"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.27.29" sID="Gen.27.29"/>
          <l> May nations be your servants, </l>
          <l> and races bow before you! </l>
          <l> Be master of your kinsmen, </l>
          <l> and may your mother’s sons bow before you! </l>
          <l> A curse on him who curses you, </l>
          <l> a blessing on him who blesses you! </l>
         </lg></q>
        <verse eId="Gen.27.29"/>
       </hi>
      </p>
      <p>
       <hi type="italic">
        <verse osisID="Gen.27.30" sID="Gen.27.30"/>No sooner had Isaac finished blessing Jacob--indeed Jacob had just left his
         father Isaac--when his brother Esau returned from the hunt. <verse eId="Gen.27.30"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.27.31" sID="Gen.27.31"/> He too made a tasty dish and brought it to his father, saying, <q>Let my father
         sit up and eat his son’s venison, that you may give me your blessing.</q> <verse eId="Gen.27.31"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.27.32" sID="Gen.27.32"/> <q>Who are you?</q> said Isaac his father. <q>Your son</q> he answered, <q>your
         oldest son, Esau!</q> <verse eId="Gen.27.32"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.27.33" sID="Gen.27.33"/> This made Isaac tremble violently. [<q>Then who was it,</q> he asked, <q>who got
         venison and brought it to me? I ate it all before you came, and blessed him! Ay, and he shall be blessed.</q> <verse eId="Gen.27.33"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.27.34" sID="Gen.27.34"/> When Esau heard what his father said, he raised a loud and bitter wail. <q>My
         father,</q> he cried, <q>bless me, bless me too!</q>] <verse eId="Gen.27.34"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.27.35" sID="Gen.27.35"/> <q>But,</q> he said, <q>your brother stole in and took away your blessing.</q><verse eId="Gen.27.35"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.27.36" sID="Gen.27.36"/> Esau answered, <q>Is it because his name is Jacob that he has twice over­reached
         me? He cheated me out of my birthright, and now he has cheated me out of my blessing!</q> Then he said, <q>Have you not kept
         a blessing for me?</q> <verse eId="Gen.27.36"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.27.37" sID="Gen.27.37"/> Isaac answered, <q>I have made him your master, I have
         <milestone type="pb" n="30"/>
         appointed all his kinsmen to be his servants, I have given him corn and wine for his support. My son,
         what can I do for you?</q> <verse eId="Gen.27.37"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.27.38" sID="Gen.27.38"/> Esau said to his father, <q>My father, is that your only blessing? O my
         father, bless me, bless me too!</q> And Esau wept aloud. <verse eId="Gen.27.38"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.27.39" sID="Gen.27.39"/> Then his father Isaac answered: <q>
         <lg>
          <l> Far from rich soil on earth shall you live, </l>
          <l> far from the dew of heaven on high; <verse eId="Gen.27.39"/> </l>
          <l> <verse osisID="Gen.27.40" sID="Gen.27.40"/> you shall live by the sword and serve your brother; </l>
          <l> but when you grow restive, his yoke you shall break. <verse eId="Gen.27.40"/> </l>
         </lg></q>
       </hi>
      </p>
      <p>
       <hi type="italic">
        <verse osisID="Gen.27.41" sID="Gen.27.41"/>Esau had a hatred of Jacob on account of the blessing he had got from his father;
         Esau muttered, <q>It will soon be time to mourn for my father, and then I will murder my brother Jacob.</q> <verse eId="Gen.27.41"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.27.42" sID="Gen.27.42"/> When Rebekah was told what her elder son Esau was saying, she sent for her
         younger son Jacob and said to him, <q>Here is your brother Esau consoling himself with the thought of murdering you! <verse eId="Gen.27.42"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.27.43" sID="Gen.27.43"/> Now, my son, do what I tell you; be off, fly to my brother Laban in Harran, <verse eId="Gen.27.43"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.27.44" sID="Gen.27.44"/> and stay awhile with him till your brother's anger is diverted till your
         brother’s fury is diverted, <verse eId="Gen.27.44"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.27.45" sID="Gen.27.45"/> and he forgets what you have done to him; then I will send and fetch you back.
         Why should I be bereft of you both at once?</q> <verse eId="Gen.27.45"/>
       </hi>
      </p>
      <p>
        <verse osisID="Gen.27.46" sID="Gen.27.46"/>Then Rebekah said to Isaac, <q>These Hittite women tire me to death. If Jacob
         marries a Hittite like these women, some native girl, what good is life to me?</q> <verse eId="Gen.27.46"/>
       <chapter eId="Gen.27"/>
       <chapter osisId="Gen.28" sId="Gen.28"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.28.1" sID="Gen.28.1"/> So Isaac called Jacob, blessed him, and gave him this charge: <q>You are not to
         marry any Canaanite woman; <verse eId="Gen.28.1"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.28.2" sID="Gen.28.2"/> be up and off to Paddan-aram, to the house of Bethuel your mother’s father, and
         get a wife there, among the daughters of Laban your mother’s brother. <verse eId="Gen.28.2"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.28.3" sID="Gen.28.3"/>God Almighty bless you and make you fruitful and multiply you till you become a
         group of nations! <verse eId="Gen.28.3"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.28.4" sID="Gen.28.4"/> May he grant you and your descendants the blessing of Abraham, that you may own
         the land where you reside, the land God gave to Abraham.</q> <verse eId="Gen.28.4"/>
      </p>
      <p>
       <verse osisID="Gen.28.5" sID="Gen.28.5"/>So Isaac sent Jacob away, and he went to Paddan-aram, to Laban the son of Bethuel the
        Aramaean, the brother of Rebekah, Jacob’s and Esau’s mother. <verse eId="Gen.28.5"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.28.6" sID="Gen.28.6"/> When Esau found that Isaac had blessed Jacob and sent him off to get a wife in Paddan-aram,
        charging him, as he blessed him, that he was not to marry a Canaanite woman, <verse eId="Gen.28.6"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.28.7" sID="Gen.28.7"/> and that Jacob had gone off to Paddan-aram in obedience to his father and mother, <verse eId="Gen.28.7"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.28.8" sID="Gen.28.8"/> Esau saw that his father did not care for Canaanite women; <verse eId="Gen.28.8"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.28.9" sID="Gen.28.9"/> so he went to Ishmael and, in addition to the wives he had, married Mahalath the daughter of
        Abraham’s son Ishmael, the sister of Nebaioth. <verse eId="Gen.28.9"/>
      </p>
      <p>
       <hi type="italic">
        <verse osisID="Gen.28.10" sID="Gen.28.10"/>Setting out from Beersheba, Jacob travelled toward Harran. <verse eId="Gen.28.10"/>
       </hi>
       <verse osisID="Gen.28.11" sID="Gen.28.11"/>[He happened to reach a certain place where he stayed all night, as the sun had set;
        taking a stone, he put it under his head and lay down to sleep. <verse eId="Gen.28.11"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.28.12" sID="Gen.28.12"/> He had a dream. There stood a flight of steps rising from earth, till it reached
        high heaven! And there were God’s angels ascending it and descending!] <verse eId="Gen.28.12"/>
       <hi type="italic">
        <verse osisID="Gen.28.13" sID="Gen.28.13"/> And the Eternal stood beside him, saying, <q>I am the Eternal, the God of your ancestor
         Abraham and the God of Isaac; to you and to your descendants I give this land where you are lying. <verse eId="Gen.28.13"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.28.14" sID="Gen.28.14"/> Your
         <milestone type="pb" n="31"/>
         descendants shall be as numerous as the dust on the ground, you shall extend west and east and north and south, and all nations of
         the world shall seek bliss such as yours and your descendants. <verse eId="Gen.28.14"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.28.15" sID="Gen.28.15"/>I am with you, I will guard you wherever you go, and I will bring you back to this land;
         I will never leave you till I have done what I have promised you.</q> <verse eId="Gen.28.15"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.28.16" sID="Gen.28.16"/>Then Jacob woke up and said, <q>The Eternal must be here, and I never knew it!</q> <verse eId="Gen.28.16"/>
       </hi>
       <verse osisID="Gen.28.17" sID="Gen.28.17"/> [He was terrified, and he said, <q>What an awesome place! This is a very dwelling
        of God, a very opening into heaven!</q> <verse eId="Gen.28.17"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.28.18" sID="Gen.28.18"/> So Jacob rose in the morning and, taking the stone he had put under his head, he
        erected it as a pillar, 14  pouring oil upon it.]
       <verse eId="Gen.28.18"/>
       <hi type="italic">
        <verse osisID="Gen.28.19" sID="Gen.28.19"/> He called the place Beth-el (God’s dwell­ing), though the first name of the town
         had been Luz. <verse eId="Gen.28.19"/>
       </hi>
      </p>
      <p>
       <verse osisID="Gen.28.20" sID="Gen.28.20"/> [Then Jacob made a vow. He said, <q>If God will be with me and guard me on this
        journey, giving me food to eat and clothes to wear, <verse eId="Gen.28.20"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.28.21" sID="Gen.28.21"/> so that I return to my father’s house safe and sound, then [[the Eternal shall be my
        God <verse eId="Gen.28.21"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.28.22" sID="Gen.28.22"/> and]] this stone which I have erected as a pillar shall be God’s dwelling, and
        I will give thee faithfully a tenth of all that thou givest me.</q> <verse eId="Gen.28.22"/>
      </p>
     <chapter eId="Gen.28"/>
     <chapter osisId="Gen.29" sId="Gen.29"/>
      <p>
       <verse osisID="Gen.29.1" sID="Gen.29.1"/>Then Jacob travelled on till he reached the land of the East.] <verse eId="Gen.29.1"/>
       <hi type="italic">
        <verse osisID="Gen.29.2" sID="Gen.29.2"/> As he looked, he saw a well in the open country, with three flocks of sheep lying beside it. <verse eId="Gen.29.2"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.29.3" sID="Gen.29.3"/> (From this well men used to water the flocks; a heavy stone lay on the mouth
         of the well, and when the flocks gathered, they used to roll the stone off the well and water the sheep; after which
         they replaced the stone on the mouth of the well.) <verse eId="Gen.29.3"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.29.4" sID="Gen.29.4"/>Jacob said to the herdsmen, <q>My friends, where do you come from?</q>
         <q>From Harran,</q> they replied. <verse eId="Gen.29.4"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.29.5" sID="Gen.29.5"/> He said to them, <q>Do you know Laban the son of Nahor?</q> <q>Yes,</q> they replied. <verse eId="Gen.29.5"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.29.6" sID="Gen.29.6"/> <q>Is he well? said Jacob.</q> <q>Yes,</q> they replied, <q>and here is his daughter
         Rachel coming unth the sheep!</q> <verse eId="Gen.29.6"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.29.7" sID="Gen.29.7"/><q>Why,</q> said Jacob, <q>the sun is still high, it is not time yet for you to collect
         your cattle; water the sheep yourselves, go and attend to them!</q> <verse eId="Gen.29.7"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.29.8" sID="Gen.29.8"/> <q>We cannot do that,</q> they answered, <q>till the flocks have all gathered,
         and the stone is rolled off the mouth of the well. Then we water the sheep.</q> <verse eId="Gen.29.8"/>
       </hi>
      </p>
      <p>
       <hi type="italic">
        <verse osisID="Gen.29.9" sID="Gen.29.9"/>He was still talking to them when Rachel came up with her father’s sheep (for
         she was a shepherdess). <verse eId="Gen.29.9"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.29.10" sID="Gen.29.10"/> So when Jacob saw Rachel the daughter of his mother s brother Laban, and the
         sheep of his mother’s brother Laban, Jacob went forward and, rolling the stone off the mouth of the well, watered the flock
         of his mother’s brother Laban. <verse eId="Gen.29.10"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.29.11" sID="Gen.29.11"/> Then Jacob kissed Rachel and wept aloud. <verse eId="Gen.29.11"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.29.12" sID="Gen.29.12"/> When he told Rachel that he was her father’s nephew and Rebekah’s son, she ran to
         tell her father, <verse eId="Gen.29.12"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.29.13" sID="Gen.29.13"/> and as soon as Laban heard the news about Jacob, his sister’s son, he ran to
         meet him, embraced him, kissed him over and again, and took him home. Jacob told Laban everything, <verse eId="Gen.29.13"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.29.14" sID="Gen.29.14"/> and Laban said to him, <q>You are my own bone and flesh.</q> He stayed with him
         for a whole month. <verse eId="Gen.29.14"/>
       </hi>
      </p>
      <p>
       <hi type="italic">
        <verse osisID="Gen.29.15" sID="Gen.29.15"/>Then Laban said to him, <q>Are you to serve me for nothing, because you are my kinsman?
         Tell me what your wage is to be.</q> <verse eId="Gen.29.15"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.29.16" sID="Gen.29.16"/> Now Laban had two daughters, the elder called Leah and the younger called Rachel; <verse eId="Gen.29.16"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.29.17" sID="Gen.29.17"/> Leah had dull eyes, but Rachel was lovely
         <milestone type="pb" n="32"/>
         and handsome. <verse eId="Gen.29.17"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.29.18" sID="Gen.29.18"/> As Jacob loved Rachel, he said, <q>I will serve you seven years for Rachel, your
         younger daughter.</q> <verse eId="Gen.29.18"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.29.19" sID="Gen.29.19"/> <q>Better let you have her than a stranger,</q> said Laban; <q>stay on with me.</q> <verse eId="Gen.29.19"/>
       </hi>
      </p>
      <p>
       <hi type="italic">
        <verse osisID="Gen.29.20" sID="Gen.29.20"/>Jacob served seven years for Rachel; they seemed to him only a few days,
         such was his love for her. <verse eId="Gen.29.20"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.29.21" sID="Gen.29.21"/>Then Jacob said to Laban, <q>Let me have my wife, that I may go in to her;
         the time is up</q>. <verse eId="Gen.29.21"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.29.22" sID="Gen.29.22"/> So Laban gathered all the natives and gave a banquet; <verse eId="Gen.29.22"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.29.23" sID="Gen.29.23"/> during the evening he took his daughter Leah and brought her to Jacob, who
         went in to her. <verse eId="Gen.29.23"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.29.24" sID="Gen.29.24"/> (Laban gave his maidservant Zilpah to his daughter Leah as her maid.) <verse eId="Gen.29.24"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.29.25" sID="Gen.29.25"/>In the morning he found it was Leah! So he said to Laban, <q>What is this
         you have done? Did I not serve you for Rachel? Why then have you cheated me?</q> <verse eId="Gen.29.25"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.29.26" sID="Gen.29.26"/> Laban answered, <q>It is not the custom in our country to marry the younger
         daughter before the older. <verse eId="Gen.29.26"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.29.27" sID="Gen.29.27"/>Complete this girl’s marriage-week; then we will let you have the other for
         another seven years service.</q> <verse eId="Gen.29.27"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.29.28" sID="Gen.29.28"/> Jacob did so; he completed his marriage-week, and then Laban gave him his
         daughter Rachel in marriage. <verse eId="Gen.29.28"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.29.29" sID="Gen.29.29"/> (Laban gave his maid­servant Bilhah to his daughter Rachel as her maid.) <verse eId="Gen.29.29"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.29.30" sID="Gen.29.30"/> Jacob went in to Rachel also, but he loved Rachel more than Leah. <verse eId="Gen.29.30"/>
       </hi>
      </p>
      <p>
       <hi type="italic">
        <verse osisID="Gen.29.31" sID="Gen.29.31"/>Then he served Laban for another seven years. The Eternal saw that Leah was
         disliked, so he opened her womb, while Rachel remained barren. <verse eId="Gen.29.31"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.29.32" sID="Gen.29.32"/> Leah conceived and bore a son, whom she called Reuben (Lookson)—saying, 
         <q>The Eternal has indeed looked on my trouble! Now my husband will love me!</q> <verse eId="Gen.29.32"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.29.33" sID="Gen.29.33"/> Again she conceived and bore a son; she said, <q>The Eternal has indeed heard
         that I am disliked, so he has given me this other son,</q> and she called him Simeon (Heard). <verse eId="Gen.29.33"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.29.34" sID="Gen.29.34"/> Again she conceived and bore a son. <q>Now,</q> she said, <q>my husband will
         at last be attached to me, when I have borne three sons to him</q>--so his name was Levi (Attached). <verse eId="Gen.29.34"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.29.35" sID="Gen.29.35"/> Again she conceived and bore a son. <q>This time,</q> she said, <q>I will praise
         the Eternal,</q> so she called him Judah (Praise). Then she ceased to bear children. <verse eId="Gen.29.35"/>
       </hi>
      </p>
     <chapter eId="Gen.29"/>
     <chapter osisId="Gen.30" sId="Gen.30"/>
      <p>
       <verse osisID="Gen.30.1" sID="Gen.30.1"/>[When Rachel found that she was bearing no children to Jacob, she grew jealous of
        her sister. <q>Give me children,</q> she said to Jacob, <q>or I will die!</q>
       <verse eId="Gen.30.1"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.30.2" sID="Gen.30.2"/>Jacob was furious with Rachel. <q>Am I in the place of God,</q> he asked, <q>who
        has withheld fruit from your womb?</q> <verse eId="Gen.30.2"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.30.3" sID="Gen.30.3"/> She answered, <q>There is my maid Bilhah! Go in to her, that her children may
        be mine, that I may get a family by means of her.</q> <verse eId="Gen.30.3"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.30.4" sID="Gen.30.4"/> So she gave him her maid Bilhah in marriage, and when Jacob went in to her, <verse eId="Gen.30.4"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.30.5" sID="Gen.30.5"/> Bilhah conceived and bore Jacob a son. <verse eId="Gen.30.5"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.30.6" sID="Gen.30.6"/> <q>God has decided in my favour,</q> said Rachel; <q>he has listened to me and given
        me a son.</q> So she called him Dan (Decision).]
       <verse eId="Gen.30.6"/>
       <hi type="italic">
        <verse osisID="Gen.30.7" sID="Gen.30.7"/> Again Bilhah, Rachel’s maid, conceived and bore Jacob another son. <verse eId="Gen.30.7"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.30.8" sID="Gen.30.8"/><q>I have had God’s own bout with my sister,</q> said Rachel, <q>and I have won.</q>
         So she called him Naphtali (Bout). <verse eId="Gen.30.8"/>
       </hi>
      </p>
      <p>
       <hi type="italic">
        <verse osisID="Gen.30.9" sID="Gen.30.9"/>When Leah found that she ceased to have children, she took her maid Zilpah and
         gave her in marriage to Jacob. <verse eId="Gen.30.9"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.30.10" sID="Gen.30.10"/> Zilpah, Leah’s maid, bore a son for Leah, <verse eId="Gen.30.10"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.30.11" sID="Gen.30.11"/> who cried, <q>I am in luck!</q> and called him Gad (Luck). <verse eId="Gen.30.11"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.30.12" sID="Gen.30.12"/>Zilpah, Leah’s maid, bore Jacob another son, <verse eId="Gen.30.12"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.30.13" sID="Gen.30.13"/> and Leah cried,
         <milestone type="pb" n="33"/>
         <q>Happy am I! women will call me happy.</q> So she named him Asher (Happy).
        <verse eId="Gen.30.13"/>
       </hi>
      </p>
      <p>
       <hi type="italic">
        <verse osisID="Gen.30.14" sID="Gen.30.14"/>During wheat-harvest Reuben found some love-apples in the field and brought
         them to his mother Leah. Rachel said, <q>Do give me some of your boy’s love-apples.</q> <verse eId="Gen.30.14"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.30.15" sID="Gen.30.15"/> But Leah answered, <q>Is it a trifling matter that you have taken away my husband?
         And now you want to take my boy’s love-apples!</q> <q>Give me some of your boy’s love-apples,</q> said Rachel, <q>and you
         can lie with him to-night.</q> <verse eId="Gen.30.15"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.30.16" sID="Gen.30.16"/> When Jacob came home from the field in the evening, Leah went out to meet him,
         saying, <q>You must come in to me; I have hired you at the price of my boy’s love-apples.</q> So he lay with her that night.<verse eId="Gen.30.16"/>
       </hi>
       <verse osisID="Gen.30.17" sID="Gen.30.17"/> [God listened to Leah, and she conceived and bore Jacob a fifth son.<verse eId="Gen.30.17"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.30.18" sID="Gen.30.18"/><q>God has given me my hire,</q> said Leah, <q>because I gave my maid to my husband.</q>
        So she called him Issachar (Hireman). <verse eId="Gen.30.18"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.30.19" sID="Gen.30.19"/> Again Leah conceived and bore Jacob a sixth son. <verse eId="Gen.30.19"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.30.20" sID="Gen.30.20"/> <q>God has given me a fine dowry,</q> she said: <q>my husband will dwell with
        me at last, now that I have borne him six sons.</q> So she called him Zebulun (Dwelling). <verse eId="Gen.30.20"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.30.21" sID="Gen.30.21"/> Afterwards she bore a daughter, and called her Dinah; <verse eId="Gen.30.21"/>
      </p>
      <p>
       <verse osisID="Gen.30.22" sID="Gen.30.22"/>Then God remembered Rachel, God listened to her and opened her womb,<verse eId="Gen.30.22"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.30.23" sID="Gen.30.23"/>so that she conceived and bore a son. She said, <q>God has removed my reproach,</q>]<verse eId="Gen.30.23"/>
       <hi type="italic">
        <verse osisID="Gen.30.24" sID="Gen.30.24"/>and called him Joseph (Add), saying, <q>May the Eternal add another son to me!</q> <verse eId="Gen.30.24"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.30.25" sID="Gen.30.25"/>It was after Rachel had given birth to Joseph, that Jacob said to Laban,
         <q>Let me leave you for my own home and country. <verse eId="Gen.30.25"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.30.26" sID="Gen.30.26"/> Let me have my wives and children, for whom I have served you, and go my way.
         You know all the service I have rendered you.</q> <verse eId="Gen.30.26"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.30.27" sID="Gen.30.27"/> Laban said to him, <q>If I have found favour with you, stay; I have noted the
         omens and seen that the Eternal has blessed me for your sake.</q> <verse eId="Gen.30.27"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.30.28" sID="Gen.30.28"/> He added, <q>Fix your own wage, and I will pay it.</q> <verse eId="Gen.30.28"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.30.29" sID="Gen.30.29"/> Jacob answered, <q>You know yourself how I have served you, and how your stock
         has fared under my charge. <verse eId="Gen.30.29"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.30.30" sID="Gen.30.30"/>Little you had before I came, and now it has multiplied abundantly; wherever I
         have turned, the Eternal has blessed you. But when am I to make some provision for my own household?</q>
        <verse eId="Gen.30.30"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.30.31" sID="Gen.30.31"/> Laban said, <q>What am I to give you?</q> <q>Nothing at all,</q> said
         Jacob; <q>let me go on feeding and tend­ing your stock, if you will simply do this for me: <verse eId="Gen.30.31"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.30.32" sID="Gen.30.32"/> to-day, as I go over all your stock, I will set apart all the speckled
         and spot­ted animals, and my pay shall consist of any black sheep or any speckled and spotted goat hereafter born. <verse eId="Gen.30.32"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.30.33" sID="Gen.30.33"/> In this way my honesty will tell, when you come to cast your eye over my
         share; any goat in my lot, that is not speckled and spotted, any sheep that is not black, you may con­sider to have
         been stolen.</q> <verse eId="Gen.30.33"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.30.34" sID="Gen.30.34"/> <q>Good,</q> said Laban, <q>so be it.</q>
        <verse eId="Gen.30.34"/>
       </hi>
      </p>
      <p>
       <hi type="italic">
        <verse osisID="Gen.30.35" sID="Gen.30.35"/>Then Laban that very day set apart the striped and spotted he-goats and
         all the speckled and spotted she-goats—every animal that had a white tinge, and all the black sheep; he put them in
         charge of his sons, <verse eId="Gen.30.35"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.30.36" sID="Gen.30.36"/> at a distance of three days’ march from Jacob. The rest of Laban’s stock
         was fed by Jacob. <verse eId="Gen.30.36"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.30.37" sID="Gen.30.37"/> But Jacob took fresh boughs of poplar, almond, and plane, and peeled
         white streaks in them, exposing the white of the boughs. <verse eId="Gen.30.37"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.30.38" sID="Gen.30.38"/> These
         <milestone type="pb" n="34"/>
         peeled, sticks he laid in front of the flocks, in the runnels of the watering-troughs at which the flocks drank; <verse eId="Gen.30.38"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.30.39" sID="Gen.30.39"/>they bred when they came to drink, and as they bred in front of the
         sticks they brought forth young that were striped, speckled, and spotted. <verse eId="Gen.30.39"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.30.40" sID="Gen.30.40"/> These lambs Jacob kept separate [[turning the faces of the flocks to the
         striped and black animals in Labans flock]], he kept his own droves apart, instead of adding them to Laban’s stock. <verse eId="Gen.30.40"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.30.41" sID="Gen.30.41"/> Jacob also used to lay the sticks in the runnels only when the stronger
         animals came to breed, that they might breed in sight of the sticks; <verse eId="Gen.30.41"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.30.42" sID="Gen.30.42"/> when the weaker animals came, he did not put in the sticks. In this way,
         the weaker lambs fell to Laban, the stronger to Jacob, <verse eId="Gen.30.42"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.30.43" sID="Gen.30.43"/> who grew ex­tremely rich, with large flocks, male and female slaves,
         camels, and asses. <verse eId="Gen.30.43"/>
       </hi>
      </p>
     <chapter eId="Gen.30"/>
     <chapter osisId="Gen.31" sId="Gen.31"/>
      <p>
       <hi type="italic">
        <verse osisID="Gen.31.1" sID="Gen.31.1"/>But he heard Labans sons muttering, <q>Jacob has got hold of all our fathers property; he
         has acquired all this wealth from what our father had.</q> <verse eId="Gen.31.1"/>
       </hi>
       <verse osisID="Gen.31.2" sID="Gen.31.2"/>[Jacob also saw that Laban’s looks were not friendly as they were before.]<verse eId="Gen.31.2"/>
       <hi type="italic">
        <verse osisID="Gen.31.3" sID="Gen.31.3"/> And the Eternal said to Jacob, <q>Return to the land of your fathers and to your kinsfolk;
         I will be with you.</q>
        <verse eId="Gen.31.3"/>
       </hi>
       <verse osisID="Gen.31.4" sID="Gen.31.4"/> [So Jacob summoned Rachel and Leah to his flock in the field, <verse eId="Gen.31.4"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.31.5" sID="Gen.31.5"/> and said to them, <q>I see that your father’s looks are not friendly as
        they were before. However, the God of my fathers has always been with me. <verse eId="Gen.31.5"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.31.6" sID="Gen.31.6"/>You know your­selves that I have served your father to the best of my power. <verse eId="Gen.31.6"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.31.7" sID="Gen.31.7"/> Your father has taken advan­tage of me and changed my wages over and again;
        yet God did not allow him to injure me, <verse eId="Gen.31.7"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.31.8" sID="Gen.31.8"/> for, whenever he said, <q>The speckled animals are to be your wage,</q>
        then all the flock bore speckled young, and whenever he said, <q>The striped are to be your wage,</q> then all the
        flock bore striped young. <verse eId="Gen.31.8"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.31.9" sID="Gen.31.9"/> In this way God has taken the stock from your father and given it to me. <verse eId="Gen.31.9"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.31.10" sID="Gen.31.10"/> When the stock was breeding, I raised my eyes in a dream and saw that the
        he-goats that leaped on the she-goats were striped, speckled, and mottled. <verse eId="Gen.31.10"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.31.11" sID="Gen.31.11"/> The angel of God said to me in the dream, <q>Jacob!</q> <q>Yes,</q>
        said I. <verse eId="Gen.31.11"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.31.12" sID="Gen.31.12"/>And he said, <q>Raise your eyes, look! all the he-goats that leap on the
        she-goats are striped, speckled, and mottled--for I have seen all Laban’s treatment of you. <verse eId="Gen.31.12"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.31.13" sID="Gen.31.13"/> I am the God of Beth-el, where you poured oil on a pillar, where you made
        a vow to me. Now up and away from this land, return to the land of your birth.</q></q> <verse eId="Gen.31.13"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.31.14" sID="Gen.31.14"/> Rachel and Leah replied, <q>What share or possession is left for us in
        our father’s house? <verse eId="Gen.31.14"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.31.15" sID="Gen.31.15"/> Does he not treat us like aliens? He has sold us, and he goes on to spend
        all the price of our marriage! <verse eId="Gen.31.15"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.31.16" sID="Gen.31.16"/> All the wealth that God has taken from our father now belongs to us and
        to our children; so do whatever God tells you.</q>
       <verse eId="Gen.31.16"/>
      </p>
      <p>
       <verse osisID="Gen.31.17" sID="Gen.31.17"/>Then Jacob started to mount his sons and his wives on camels, <verse eId="Gen.31.17"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.31.18" sID="Gen.31.18"/> driving off all his cattle, and all the stock he had gathered, the cattle
        he had acquired in Paddan-aram, in order to reach his father Isaac in the land of Ca­naan. <verse eId="Gen.31.18"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.31.19" sID="Gen.31.19"/>As Laban had gone to the sheep-shearing, Rachel stole the household gods
        that be­longed to her father, <verse eId="Gen.31.19"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.31.20" sID="Gen.31.20"/> and Jacob outwitted Laban the Aramaean, never letting him know that he
        fled; <verse eId="Gen.31.20"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.31.21" sID="Gen.31.21"/> he fled with all that he had, got across the Euphrates, and
        <milestone type="pb" n="35"/>
        turned towards the hill-country of Gilead. <verse eId="Gen.31.21"/>
      </p>
      <p>
       <verse osisID="Gen.31.22" sID="Gen.31.22"/>Three days later, Laban was told that Jacob had fled. <verse eId="Gen.31.22"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.31.23" sID="Gen.31.23"/> So he took his kinsmen and pursued him for seven days, overtaking him in
        the hill-country of Gilead. <verse eId="Gen.31.23"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.31.24" sID="Gen.31.24"/> (In a dream by night God came to Laban the Ara­maean, saying, <q>Beware of
        saying a single word to Jacob.</q>) <verse eId="Gen.31.24"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.31.25" sID="Gen.31.25"/> When Laban came up on Jacob, Jacob had encamped on the hill of Mizpah;
        so Laban and his kinsmen encamped on the hill of Gilead. <verse eId="Gen.31.25"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.31.26" sID="Gen.31.26"/>Laban said to Jacob, <q>What do you mean by stealing away without telling
        me, carrying my daughters off as if they were prisoners of war? <verse eId="Gen.31.26"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.31.27" sID="Gen.31.27"/> Why did you flee in secret and deceive me, instead of telling me? I would
        have sent you off with mirth and music, with tambourine and lyre! <verse eId="Gen.31.27"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.31.28" sID="Gen.31.28"/> Why did you not let me kiss my grand­children and my daughters? That was a
        senseless thing to do. <verse eId="Gen.31.28"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.31.29" sID="Gen.31.29"/> I have it in my power to injure you, but the God of your father told me
        last night, <q>Beware of saying a single word to Jacob.</q> <verse eId="Gen.31.29"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.31.30" sID="Gen.31.30"/> You are off, forsooth, because you yearned for your father’s house! Then
        why did you steal my gods?</q> <verse eId="Gen.31.30"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.31.31" sID="Gen.31.31"/> Jacob an­swered, <q>I fled secretly because I was afraid; I thought you
        would take your daughters from me, by force.
       <verse eId="Gen.31.31"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.31.32" sID="Gen.31.32"/> As for your gods, he shall die with whom you find them! In presence of
        our kins­men, pick out whatever is yours among my belongings, and take it</q>(for Jacob had no idea that Rachel had
        stolen the gods).
       <verse eId="Gen.31.32"/>
      </p>
      <p>
       <verse osisID="Gen.31.33" sID="Gen.31.33"/> So Laban went into Jacob’s tent and Leah’s tent and the tent of the two
        maids, and found nothing. From Leah’s tent he went into Rachel’s. <verse eId="Gen.31.33"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.31.34" sID="Gen.31.34"/> Now Rachel had taken the household gods and put them in the camel’s
        saddle, on which she was riding. As Laban felt all about the tent, and could not find them, <verse eId="Gen.31.34"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.31.35" sID="Gen.31.35"/>she said to her father, <q>Let not my lord be angry at me for not rising
        before you, but the custom of women is on me.</q> So he did not find the household gods, for all his search. <verse eId="Gen.31.35"/>
      </p>
      <p>
       <verse osisID="Gen.31.36" sID="Gen.31.36"/>Then Jacob angrily reproached Laban. Said Jacob to Laban, <q>What is my
        crime, what is my sin, that you have hotly pursued me? <verse eId="Gen.31.36"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.31.37" sID="Gen.31.37"/> After your groping among all my goods, what goods have you found that
        belong to your household? Down with it here, in front of your kinsmen and mine, that they may judge be­tween us two! <verse eId="Gen.31.37"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.31.38" sID="Gen.31.38"/> These twenty years I have been with you; your ewes and she-goats have
        never miscarried, and I never ate the rams of your flock. <verse eId="Gen.31.38"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.31.39" sID="Gen.31.39"/> What wild beasts tore, I never laid be­fore you; I made good the loss of
        it myself; you held me re­sponsible for anything stolen by night or by day. <verse eId="Gen.31.39"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.31.40" sID="Gen.31.40"/> And this was my lot, to be worn out by heat during the day and by frost
        at night, to lose my sleep. <verse eId="Gen.31.40"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.31.41" sID="Gen.31.41"/> These twenty years I have been a member of your household; fourteen years
        I served you for your two daughters and six years for your flock, and you changed my wages over and again. <verse eId="Gen.31.41"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.31.42" sID="Gen.31.42"/> Unless my father’s God, the God of Abraham, the Awe of Isaac, had been on
        my side, you would in­deed have sent me off empty-handed. But God saw my plight and my toil, and last night he checked
        you.</q>
       <verse eId="Gen.31.42"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.31.43" sID="Gen.31.43"/> Laban answered, <q>The girls are my daughters, the children are my
        grandchildren, the flocks are
        <milestone type="pb" n="36"/>
        my flocks, and all that you see is mine. But--what can I do to-day for these daughters of mine and for the children
        they have borne? <verse eId="Gen.31.43"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.31.44" sID="Gen.31.44"/> Come, let us make a compact, you and I, let us have a witness between us.</q> <verse eId="Gen.31.44"/>
      </p>
      <p>
       <verse osisID="Gen.31.45" sID="Gen.31.45"/>So he took a boulder, and erected it as a pillar.] <verse eId="Gen.31.45"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.31.46" sID="Gen.31.46"/> Jacob said to his men, <q>Gather stones</q>; they did so and built a
        cairn. Then they ate together on the cairn. <verse eId="Gen.31.46"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.31.47" sID="Gen.31.47"/>(Witness-cairn they called it, Laban in Aramaic, Jacob in Hebrew.) <verse eId="Gen.31.47"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.31.48" sID="Gen.31.48"/><q>This cairn,</q> said Laban, <q>is a witness between you and me
        to-day</q>; so he called it Galeed (Witness-cairn); <verse eId="Gen.31.48"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.31.49" sID="Gen.31.49"/> and also Mizpah (Watch-post), say­ing, <q>May the Eternal keep a watchful
        eye upon us, when we are out of one another's sight! <verse eId="Gen.31.49"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.31.50" sID="Gen.31.50"/> If you ill-treat my daughters, or if you marry other wives, then, though
        there is no man, here is God to interfere!</q> <verse eId="Gen.31.50"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.31.51" sID="Gen.31.51"/> [And Laban said to Jacob, <q>Look at this cairn, look at the pillar I
        have set up between myself and you. <verse eId="Gen.31.51"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.31.52" sID="Gen.31.52"/> This cairn be witness, this pillar be witness, that I will not pass it to
        attack you, and you shall not pass this cairn and pillar to attack me. <verse eId="Gen.31.52"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.31.53" sID="Gen.31.53"/> The God of Abraham and the God of Nahor judge between us!</q> Jacob swore
        it by the Awe of his father Isaac. <verse eId="Gen.31.53"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.31.54" sID="Gen.31.54"/>Then, killing a victim for sacri­fice on the hill, Jacob called his kinsmen
        to a meal; they ate and then they stayed all night on the hill. <verse eId="Gen.31.54"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.31.55" sID="Gen.31.55"/> Next morning Laban rose, kissed his grandchildren and his daughters, gave
        them his blessing, and went away home. <verse eId="Gen.31.55"/>
       <chapter eId="Gen.31"/>
       <chapter osisId="Gen.32" sId="Gen.32"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.32.1" sID="Gen.32.1"/>Jacob went his way, and encountered the angels of God; <verse eId="Gen.32.1"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.32.2" sID="Gen.32.2"/> on seeing them, Jacob said, <q>This is God’s camp</q>--so he called the
        spot Mahanaim (Camps).] <verse eId="Gen.32.2"/>
      </p>
      <p>
       <hi type="italic">
        <verse osisID="Gen.32.3" sID="Gen.32.3"/>Now Jacob sent messengers ahead to his brother Esau in the land of Seir,
         the country of Edom, <verse eId="Gen.32.3"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.32.4" sID="Gen.32.4"/> with these instructions: <q>You shall say to my lord Esau, <q>Your servant
         Jacob says: I have been residing with Laban until now; <verse eId="Gen.32.4"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.32.5" sID="Gen.32.5"/> I have oxen, asses, flocks, and slaves both male and fe­male, and I hereby
         send to tell my lord, in hope of finding fa­vour with you.</q></q> <verse eId="Gen.32.5"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.32.6" sID="Gen.32.6"/> The messengers came back to Jacob re­porting that they had gone to his
         brother Esau, who was al­ready on the way to meet him with four hundred men. <verse eId="Gen.32.6"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.32.7" sID="Gen.32.7"/> Jacob was terrified and anxious; he di­vided his party, with the flocks
         and the herds and the camels, into two companies, <verse eId="Gen.32.7"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.32.8" sID="Gen.32.8"/> thinking that if Esau attacked and over­powered one company, the sur­viving
         company might escape. <verse eId="Gen.32.8"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.32.9" sID="Gen.32.9"/> Then Jacob prayed, <q>God of my father Abraham, God of my fa­ther Isaac,
         O Eternal who didst say to me, <q>Return to your coun­try and your kindred, and I will do you good,</q> <verse eId="Gen.32.9"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.32.10" sID="Gen.32.10"/> I do not deserve all the kindness and loyalty with which thou hast
         treated thy serv­ant; stick in hand I crossed the Jordan here, and now I am two companies! <verse eId="Gen.32.10"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.32.11" sID="Gen.32.11"/> O save me from the power of my brother, from Esau! I am afraid of him
         attacking me and overpowering me, slaying our women and children. <verse eId="Gen.32.11"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.32.12" sID="Gen.32.12"/> Thou didst promise, <q>I will indeed do you good, and make your
         de­scendants like the sand of the sea, past counting for number.</q></q> <verse eId="Gen.32.12"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.32.13" sID="Gen.32.13"/> There Jacob remained for the night. <verse eId="Gen.32.13"/>
       </hi>
      </p>
      <p>
       <verse osisID="Gen.32.14" sID="Gen.32.14"/>[From his possessions he se­lected a present for his brother Esau, namely, <verse eId="Gen.32.14"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.32.15" sID="Gen.32.15"/> two hundred she-goats and twenty he-goats, two hundred ewes and twenty
        rams, thirty milch camels with their
        <milestone type="pb" n="37"/>
        colts, forty cows and ten bul­locks, twenty she-asses and ten foals.
       <verse eId="Gen.32.15"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.32.16" sID="Gen.32.16"/> These he entrusted to his slaves, each herd separately, telling his
        slaves to move across ahead of him, leaving a space between herd and herd. <verse eId="Gen.32.16"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.32.17" sID="Gen.32.17"/> He gave this order to those in the very front: <q>When my brother Esau
        meets you and asks to whom you belong and where you are going, and whose are the beasts you are driving, <verse eId="Gen.32.17"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.32.18" sID="Gen.32.18"/> say, <q>They belong to your servant Jacob; they are a present for my
        lord Esau; and Jacob himself is just behind us.</q></q> <verse eId="Gen.32.18"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.32.19" sID="Gen.32.19"/> He also gave orders to the second and the third, and to all the others
        who drove the herds, telling them what they were to say to Esau when they came across him; <verse eId="Gen.32.19"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.32.20" sID="Gen.32.20"/><q>Say, <q>here is your servant Jacob just behind us!</q></q>(He thought
        to himself, <q>I will ap­pease him with the present in front, and then I can get access to his presence; perhaps he
        will receive me.</q>) <verse eId="Gen.32.20"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.32.21" sID="Gen.32.21"/> So the present moved ahead of him, while he passed the night in the
        encamp­ment.] <verse eId="Gen.32.21"/>
      </p>
      <p>
       <hi type="italic">
        <verse osisID="Gen.32.22" sID="Gen.32.22"/>That night he rose, took his two wives, his two maidserv­ants, and his
         eleven children, [and crossed the ford of the Jabbok. <verse eId="Gen.32.22"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.32.23" sID="Gen.32.23"/> He took them] and made them cross the stream, along with all that he
         had. <verse eId="Gen.32.23"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.32.24" sID="Gen.32.24"/> Jacob was left alone, and a man struggled with him till break of day;<verse eId="Gen.32.24"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.32.25" sID="Gen.32.25"/>when the man found that he could not master him, he struck the hollow of
         his thigh, so that Jacob’s thigh was sprained in the wrestle. <verse eId="Gen.32.25"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.32.26" sID="Gen.32.26"/> Then he said, <q>Let me go, for the day is breaking.</q> <q>I will
         not,</q> said Jacob, <q>unless you bless me</q> <verse eId="Gen.32.26"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.32.27" sID="Gen.32.27"/><q>What is your name?</q> said the man. <q>Jacob.</q> he answered.
        <verse eId="Gen.32.27"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.32.28" sID="Gen.32.28"/> <q>Then your name shall be Jacob no longer,</q> said the man, <q>but
         Israel (Striver-with-God), for you have striven with God and men, and won.</q> <verse eId="Gen.32.28"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.32.29" sID="Gen.32.29"/><q>Tell me what name you bear,</q> said Jacob. <q>Why ask my name?</q>
         he answered, and blessed him on the spot. <verse eId="Gen.32.29"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.32.30" sID="Gen.32.30"/> Jacob named the spot Peniel (God’s-face), saying, <q>I have seen God
         face to face, and yet I am alive!</q> <verse eId="Gen.32.30"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.32.31" sID="Gen.32.31"/> The sun rose upon him as he passed Peniel, and he limped on ac­count of
         his thigh. <verse eId="Gen.32.31"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.32.32" sID="Gen.32.32"/> (To this day the Israelites never eat any ten­don of the hip on the
         hollow of an animal’s thigh, because One struck the tendon of the hip on the hollow of Jacob’s thigh.) <verse eId="Gen.32.32"/>
       </hi>
      </p>
     <chapter eId="Gen.32"/>
     <chapter osisId="Gen.33" sId="Gen.33"/>
      <p>
       <hi type="italic">
        <verse osisID="Gen.33.1" sID="Gen.33.1"/>When Jacob looked up, there was Esau coming with four hundred men! So he
         assigned the children to Leah and to Rachel and to the two maids, <verse eId="Gen.33.1"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.33.2" sID="Gen.33.2"/> putting the maids and their children in front, then Leah and her children,
         with Ra­chel and Joseph in the rear. <verse eId="Gen.33.2"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.33.3" sID="Gen.33.3"/> He passed on before them bowing seven times to the earth till he reached
         his brother, <verse eId="Gen.33.3"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.33.4" sID="Gen.33.4"/> and Esau ran to meet him and embraced him, falling on his neck and kiss­ing
         him, while they wept to­gether. <verse eId="Gen.33.4"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.33.5" sID="Gen.33.5"/> On looking up Esau noticed the women and children. <q>Who are these with
         you?</q> he asked. And Jacob said, <q>The children whom God has gra­ciously given to your servant.</q>
        <verse eId="Gen.33.5"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.33.6" sID="Gen.33.6"/> Then the maids came up with their children and bowed; <verse eId="Gen.33.6"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.33.7" sID="Gen.33.7"/> Leah and her children also came up and bowed; after that, Joseph and
         Rachel came up and bowed. <verse eId="Gen.33.7"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.33.8" sID="Gen.33.8"/> Esau said, <q>And what was the meaning of all yon company that I met?</q>
         <q>It was to win my lord’s favour,</q> said Jacob.
        <verse eId="Gen.33.8"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.33.9" sID="Gen.33.9"/> <q>I have plenty,</q> said Esau; “keep what you have, my brother.”
         <milestone type="pb" n="38"/>
        <verse eId="Gen.33.9"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.33.10" sID="Gen.33.10"/> But Jacob answered, <q>No, if I have found favour with you, pray accept
         my present, for I have had access to your presence as to the presence of God, himself and found a welcome. <verse eId="Gen.33.10"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.33.11" sID="Gen.33.11"/> Pray take the gift I have brought you; God has been generous to me, and
         I have plenty.</q> So he urged him, and Esau took it. <verse eId="Gen.33.11"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.33.12" sID="Gen.33.12"/> Then said Esau, <q>Let us travel together on our way; I will march in
         front.</q> <verse eId="Gen.33.12"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.33.13" sID="Gen.33.13"/> But Jacob said, <q>My lord knows that the children are young, and I have
         to think of the young in my flocks and herds; if they are overdriven for a single day, the flocks will all die. <verse eId="Gen.33.13"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.33.14" sID="Gen.33.14"/> Pray let my lord go ahead of his servant, and I will advance gradually,
         suiting my pace to the cattle in front of me and to the children, till I reach my lord at Seir.</q>
        <verse eId="Gen.33.14"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.33.15" sID="Gen.33.15"/> <q>Let me leave some of my men with you,</q> said Esau. But Jacob said,
         <q>What is the use of that, so please my lord?</q> <verse eId="Gen.33.15"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.33.16" sID="Gen.33.16"/> Then Esau started that very day to go back to Seir; <verse eId="Gen.33.16"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.33.17" sID="Gen.33.17"/> Jacob moved to Sukkoth, where he built himself a house and put up booths
         for his cattle. Hence the place was called Sukkoth (Booths). <verse eId="Gen.33.17"/>
       </hi>
      </p>
      <p>
       <verse osisID="Gen.33.18" sID="Gen.33.18"/>When Jacob came from Paddan-aram he arrived safe and sound at the town of
        Shechem in the land of Canaan, camping to the east of the town. <verse eId="Gen.33.18"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.33.19" sID="Gen.33.19"/> [For a hundred ingots he bought the piece of ground on which he had
        pitched his tent, from the clan of Hamor, the founder of Shechem. <verse eId="Gen.33.19"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.33.20" sID="Gen.33.20"/> There he put up an altar, which he called <q>El, God of Israel.</q>] <verse eId="Gen.33.20"/>
      </p>
     <chapter eId="Gen.33"/>
     <chapter osisId="Gen.34" sId="Gen.34"/>
      <p>
       <verse osisID="Gen.34.1" sID="Gen.34.1"/>Now Dinah, the daughter whom Leah bore to Jacob, went to visit the women of
        the district. <verse eId="Gen.34.1"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.34.2" sID="Gen.34.2"/> Shechem, the son of Hamor the Hivite, who was the local chief, saw her; <verse eId="Gen.34.2"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.34.4" sID="Gen.34.4"/> and She­chem said to his father Hamor, <q>Get me this girl for my wife.</q> <verse eId="Gen.34.4"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.34.6" sID="Gen.34.6"/> So Hamor, the father of Shechem, went to have a talk with Jacob. <verse eId="Gen.34.6"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.34.8" sID="Gen.34.8"/>Hamor’s words were: <q>My son Shechem has set his heart on your daughter;
        pray let him have her in marriage. <verse eId="Gen.34.8"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.34.10" sID="Gen.34.10"/> Intermarry with us, give us your daughters and take our daughters; you
        can live along with us, the country will be open to you, stay and trade here, and get property.</q> <verse eId="Gen.34.10"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.34.13" sID="Gen.34.13"/> But the sons of Jacob answered She­chem and his father Hamor craftily; <verse eId="Gen.34.13"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.34.14" sID="Gen.34.14"/>they said, <q>We cannot do such a thing. To give our sister to a man who
        is uncir­cumcised!--that would be a disgrace to us. <verse eId="Gen.34.14"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.34.15" sID="Gen.34.15"/> Only on this condition will we make terms with you, if you become as we
        are, every male among you getting circumcised; <verse eId="Gen.34.15"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.34.16" sID="Gen.34.16"/> then we will give you our daughters and take your daughters, we will live
        along with you and become one people. <verse eId="Gen.34.16"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.34.17" sID="Gen.34.17"/> If you will not listen to us and get circum­cised, then we will retire
        with our daughter.</q> <verse eId="Gen.34.17"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.34.18" sID="Gen.34.18"/> Their proposal pleased Hamor and Shechem the son of Hamor. <verse eId="Gen.34.18"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.34.20" sID="Gen.34.20"/> Hamor and his son Shechem went to the council of the town and dis­cussed
        it with the citizens. <verse eId="Gen.34.20"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.34.21" sID="Gen.34.21"/><q>These men,</q> they said, <q>are quite friendly; let them live in the
        country and trade, for the country is large enough; let us marry their daughters and give them our daughters. <verse eId="Gen.34.21"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.34.22" sID="Gen.34.22"/> But they will agree to live along with us and to become one people only
        on this condition, that every male among us gets circumcised, as they are circumcised. <verse eId="Gen.34.22"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.34.23" sID="Gen.34.23"/> Well, their cattle and possessions and all their beasts will become ours,
        will they not? Only let us come
        <milestone type="pb" n="39"/>
        to terms with them, and they will live along with us.</q> <verse eId="Gen.34.23"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.34.24" sID="Gen.34.24"/> The citizens all agreed to what Hamor and his son Shechem urged, and
        every male citizen got circumcised. <verse eId="Gen.34.24"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.34.25" sID="Gen.34.25"/> On the third day, when they were sore, the sons of Jacob fell on them in
        their pain, murdered every male in the town,
       <verse eId="Gen.34.25"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.34.27" sID="Gen.34.27"/> and sacked it, <verse eId="Gen.34.27"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.34.28" sID="Gen.34.28"/> seizing their flocks and herds and asses, whatever was in the town or in
        the fields, <verse eId="Gen.34.28"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.34.29" sID="Gen.34.29"/> and carry­ing off as booty all their posses­sions, their children and
        their wives. <verse eId="Gen.34.29"/>
     <chapter eId="Gen.34"/>
     <chapter osisId="Gen.35" sId="Gen.35"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.35.5" sID="Gen.35.5"/> As they rode off, a panic fell upon the sur­rounding towns, and no one
        pur­sued the sons of Jacob. <verse eId="Gen.35.5"/>
     <chapter eId="Gen.35"/>
      </p>
     <chapter eId="Gen.34"/>
      <p>
       <hi type="italic">
        <verse osisID="Gen.34.3" sID="Gen.34.3"/> Now Shechem the son of Hamor had his heart set on Dinah the daughter of
         Jacob; <verse eId="Gen.34.3"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.34.2" sID="Gen.34.2"/> he lay with her and dishonoured her, <verse eId="Gen.34.2"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.34.3" sID="Gen.34.3"/> but he loved the girl and consoled her. <verse eId="Gen.34.3"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.34.5" sID="Gen.34.5"/> Jacob heard that he had violated his daughter Di­nah, but, as his sons were
         out in the open country with his cattle, he said nothing till they came home.
        <verse eId="Gen.34.5"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.34.7" sID="Gen.34.7"/>
         However, the sons of Jacob heard it and came back from the country, distressed and enraged that the man had
         com­mitted an immoral scandal in Israel by lying with Jacob’s daughter—a thing that ought never to be done!
        <verse eId="Gen.34.7"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.34.11" sID="Gen.34.11"/> Shechem said to her father and her brothers, <q>Let me have your
         goodwill! I will pay any sum you mention <verse eId="Gen.34.11"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.34.12" sID="Gen.34.12"/> ask as large a price and presents as you like, and I will give what­ever
         you may claim; only, give me the girl in marriage.</q> <verse eId="Gen.34.12"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.34.19" sID="Gen.34.19"/> The young man did not hesitate to do as they demanded, though he was the
         highest member of his family--so charmed was he with Jacob’s daughter. <verse eId="Gen.34.19"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.34.25" sID="Gen.34.25"/> But two of the sons of Jacob, Simeon and Levi, brothers of Dinah, each
         took his sword, got into the town unsuspected, <verse eId="Gen.34.25"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.34.26" sID="Gen.34.26"/> and cut Hamor and his son Shechem to pieces; then they took Dinah from
         Shechem’s house and got away. <verse eId="Gen.34.26"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.34.30" sID="Gen.34.30"/> Jacob said to Simeon and Levi, <q>You have undone me, you have brought
         me into bad odour among the natives, the Canaanites and the Perizzites; my num­bers are few, and they will mus­ter to
         attack me, till I am de­stroyed, I and my family!</q> <verse eId="Gen.34.30"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.34.31" sID="Gen.34.31"/> Their answer was, <q>Should he have treated our sister like a harlot?</q> <verse eId="Gen.34.31"/>
       </hi>
      </p>
     <chapter eId="Gen.34"/>
     <chapter osisId="Gen.35" sId="Gen.35"/>
      <p>
       <verse osisID="Gen.35.1" sID="Gen.35.1"/>[God said to Jacob, <q>Move up to Beth-el and stay there; make an altar
        there to the God who appeared to you when you fled from your brother Esau.</q> <verse eId="Gen.35.1"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.35.2" sID="Gen.35.2"/> So Jacob said to his household and all his people, <q>Put away your
        foreign gods, wash yourselves clean, and change your clothing; <verse eId="Gen.35.2"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.35.3" sID="Gen.35.3"/> let us move up to Beth-el, where I shall make an altar to the God who
        answered me in the hour of my distress and accompanied me on my journey.</q> <verse eId="Gen.35.3"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.35.4" sID="Gen.35.4"/> Then they handed over to Jacob all their foreign gods, with their amulets
        of ear-rings; Jacob buried them below the sacred oak at She­chem. <verse eId="Gen.35.4"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.35.6" sID="Gen.35.6"/> When Jacob reached Luz (that is, Beth-el) in the land of Canaan, he and all
        his people, <verse eId="Gen.35.6"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.35.7" sID="Gen.35.7"/> he built an altar there, calling the spot <q>The God of Beth-el,</q>
        because God had been revealed to him there when he fled from his brother. <verse eId="Gen.35.7"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.35.8" sID="Gen.35.8"/> Deborah, Rebekah’s nurse, died and was buried under the sacred oak below
        Beth-el; hence its name Weeping-oak. <verse eId="Gen.35.8"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.35.14" sID="Gen.35.14"/> Jacob erected a pillar, a pillar of stone there, pouring on it a
        libation of wine and also oil.] <verse eId="Gen.35.14"/>
      </p>
      <p>
       <verse osisID="Gen.35.9" sID="Gen.35.9"/>When Jacob came from Paddan
        <milestone type="pb" n="40"/>
        -aram, God again appeared to him and blessed him.
       <verse eId="Gen.35.9"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.35.10" sID="Gen.35.10"/><q>Jacob is your name,</q> said God, <q>but Jacob it shall be no longer;
        Israel is to be your name.</q>
       <verse eId="Gen.35.10"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.35.11" sID="Gen.35.11"/> So he called him Israel. <q>I am God Almighty,</q> said God;
        <q>be fruit­ful and multiply; a nation, a group of nations, shall come from you, and kings shall be born of you; <verse eId="Gen.35.11"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.35.12" sID="Gen.35.12"/> also I will give you and your descendants after you the land that I gave
        to Abraham and Isaac.</q> <verse eId="Gen.35.12"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.35.13" sID="Gen.35.13"/> Then God went up to heaven from the spot at which he spoke to him. <verse eId="Gen.35.13"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.35.15" sID="Gen.35.15"/> And Jacob gave the name of Beth-el to the spot at which God spoke to him. <verse eId="Gen.35.15"/>
      </p>
      <p>
       <verse osisID="Gen.35.16" sID="Gen.35.16"/>[From Beth-el they moved on, and they were still some dis­tance from
        Ephrath, when Rachel felt the pains of childbirth. She had hard labour, <verse eId="Gen.35.16"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.35.17" sID="Gen.35.17"/> but, in the midst of her hard labour, the midwife said to her, <q>Fear
        not, you are going to have another son.</q> <verse eId="Gen.35.17"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.35.18" sID="Gen.35.18"/> As her life went from her (for she died), she called the child Benoni
        (Son- of-my-sorrow), but his father called him Benjamin (Fortune-son). <verse eId="Gen.35.18"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.35.19" sID="Gen.35.19"/> Rachel died and was buried on the way to Ephrath (that is, Bethlehem), <verse eId="Gen.35.19"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.35.20" sID="Gen.35.20"/> and Jacob erected a pillar at her grave, the Pillar of Rachel’s Grave to
        this day.] <verse eId="Gen.35.20"/>
       <hi type="italic">
        <verse osisID="Gen.35.21" sID="Gen.35.21"/> Then Israel moved on and; pitched his tent on the other side of
         Flocktower. <verse eId="Gen.35.21"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.35.22" sID="Gen.35.22"/> It was when Is­rael lived there that Reuben went and lay with Bilhah, his
         father’s concubine; and when Is­rael heard...
        <verse eId="Gen.35.22"/>
       </hi>
      </p>
      <p>
       <verse osisID="Gen.35.27" sID="Gen.35.27"/>Then Jacob went to his father Isaac at Mamre, at Kirjath-arba (that is,
        Hebron), where Abraham and Isaac had stayed. <verse eId="Gen.35.27"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.35.28" sID="Gen.35.28"/> The life of Isaac lasted for a hundred and eighty years; <verse eId="Gen.35.28"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.35.29" sID="Gen.35.29"/> then Isaac breathed his last, died, and was gathered to his father’s
        kindred, an old man, after a full life. He was buried by his sons Esau and Jacob.
       <verse eId="Gen.35.29"/>
      </p>
     <chapter eId="Gen.35"/>
     <chapter osisId="Gen.36" sId="Gen.36"/>
      <p>
       <verse osisID="Gen.36.1" sID="Gen.36.1"/>Here are the descendants of Esau (that is, Edom). <verse eId="Gen.36.1"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.36.2" sID="Gen.36.2"/> Esau took his wives from among the Canaanite women, Adah the daughter of
        Elon the Hittite, Oholibamah the daughter of Anah (son of Zibeon the Hivite), <verse eId="Gen.36.2"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.36.3" sID="Gen.36.3"/> and Basemath, the daughter of Ishmael, sister of Nebaioth. <verse eId="Gen.36.3"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.36.4" sID="Gen.36.4"/> Adah bore Eliphaz to Esau, Basemath bore Reuel,
        and Oholibamah bore Jeush,<verse eId="Gen.36.4"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.36.5" sID="Gen.36.5"/> Jalam, and Korah; these are the sons born to Esau in the land of Canaan. <verse eId="Gen.36.5"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.36.6" sID="Gen.36.6"/>Then Esau, taking his wives, his sons, his daugh­ters, and all his serfs,
        with his cattle and all his stock and all the property he had gathered in the land of Canaan, went away from his
        brother Jacob into the land of Seir; <verse eId="Gen.36.6"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.36.7" sID="Gen.36.7"/> for their possessions were so large that they could not live together, the
        land where they resided could not support their cattle. <verse eId="Gen.36.7"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.36.8" sID="Gen.36.8"/> So Esau lived in the hill-country of Seir (Esau means Edom). <verse eId="Gen.36.8"/>
      </p>
      <p>
       <verse osisID="Gen.36.9" sID="Gen.36.9"/>Here are the descendants of 9 Esau the ancestor of the Edom­ites in the
        hill-country of Seir; <verse eId="Gen.36.9"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.36.10" sID="Gen.36.10"/> here are the names of Esau’s sons--Eliphaz the son of Esau’s wife Adah,
        and Reuel the son of Esau’s wife Basemath. <verse eId="Gen.36.10"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.36.11" sID="Gen.36.11"/> The sons of Eliphaz were Teman, Omar, Zepho, Gatam, and Kenaz. <verse eId="Gen.36.11"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.36.12" sID="Gen.36.12"/> (Eliphaz, Esau’s son, had Timna as his concubine, and she bore Amalek to
        Eliphaz.) These were the descendants of Esau’s wife Adah. <verse eId="Gen.36.12"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.36.13" sID="Gen.36.13"/> Here are the sons of Reuel; Nahath, Zerah, Shammah, and Mizzah; these
        were the descendants of Esau’s wife Basemath.
       <verse eId="Gen.36.13"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.36.14" sID="Gen.36.14"/> And here are the sons of Esau’s wife
        <milestone type="pb" n="41"/>
        Oholibamah, the daughter of Anah (son of Zibeon); she bore Jeush, Jalam, and Korah to Esau. <verse eId="Gen.36.14"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.36.15" sID="Gen.36.15"/> Here are the chief­tains among the sons of Esau. Of the sons of Eliphaz,
        the first­born of Esau, the chieftain of Teman, the chieftain of Omar, the chieftain of Zepho, the chieftain of
        Kenaz, <verse eId="Gen.36.15"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.36.16" sID="Gen.36.16"/> the chieftain of Gatam, and the chieftain of Amalek--all chieftains from
        Eliphaz in the land of Edom, descended from Adah. <verse eId="Gen.36.16"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.36.17" sID="Gen.36.17"/> Here are the descendants of Esau’s son Reuel: the chieftain of Nahath,
        the chieftain of Zerah, the chief­tain of Shammah, and the chief­tain of Mizzah--these are the chieftains from Reuel
        in the land of Edom, descended from Esau’s wife Basemath. <verse eId="Gen.36.17"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.36.18" sID="Gen.36.18"/> And here are the descendants of Esau’s wife Oholibamah: the chieftain of
        Jeush, the chieftain of Jalam, and the chieftain of Korah--chieftains descended from Esau’s wife Oholibamah, the
        daughter of Anah. <verse eId="Gen.36.18"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.36.19" sID="Gen.36.19"/> Such were the sons of Esau (that is, Edom), such were the Edomite
        chieftains. <verse eId="Gen.36.19"/>
      </p>
      <p>
       <verse osisID="Gen.36.20" sID="Gen.36.20"/>Here are the sons of Seir the troglodyte, the natives of the country :
        Lotan, Shobal, Zibeon, Anah, <verse eId="Gen.36.20"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.36.21" sID="Gen.36.21"/> Dishon, Ezer, and Rishan; these were the troglodyte chieftains, the
        Seirites in the land of Edom. <verse eId="Gen.36.21"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.36.22" sID="Gen.36.22"/> Lotan’s chil­dren were Hori and Hemam; Lotan’s sister was Timna. <verse eId="Gen.36.22"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.36.23" sID="Gen.36.23"/> Shobal’s children were Alvan, Manahath, Ebal, Shepho, and Onam. <verse eId="Gen.36.23"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.36.24" sID="Gen.36.24"/> Zibeon’s children were Aiah and Anah (the Anah who dis­covered the hot
        springs in the desert, as he was herding his father’s asses). <verse eId="Gen.36.24"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.36.25" sID="Gen.36.25"/> Anah’s children were Dishon and Oholibamah. <verse eId="Gen.36.25"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.36.26" sID="Gen.36.26"/> Dishon’s children were Hemdan, Eshban, Ithran, and Keran. <verse eId="Gen.36.26"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.36.27" sID="Gen.36.27"/> Ezer’s children were Bilham, Zaavan, and Akan. <verse eId="Gen.36.27"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.36.28" sID="Gen.36.28"/> Rishan’s children Were Uz and Aran. <verse eId="Gen.36.28"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.36.29" sID="Gen.36.29"/> Here are the troglodyte chieftains: the chieftain of Lotan, the
        chieftain of Shobal, the chieftain of Zibeon, the chief­tain of Anah, <verse eId="Gen.36.29"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.36.30" sID="Gen.36.30"/>
        the chieftain of Dishon, the chieftain of Ezer, and the chieftain of Rishan; such were the troglodyte chief­tains in
        the order of their clans, within the land of Seir. <verse eId="Gen.36.30"/>
      </p>
      <p>
       <verse osisID="Gen.36.31" sID="Gen.36.31"/>Here are the kings who reigned in the land of Edom, before any king
        reigned over the Israelites. <verse eId="Gen.36.31"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.36.32" sID="Gen.36.32"/> Bela the son of Beor reigned in Edom; the name of his capital was
        Dinhabah. <verse eId="Gen.36.32"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.36.33" sID="Gen.36.33"/> Bela died and was succeeded by Jobab the son of Zerah of Busaireh. <verse eId="Gen.36.33"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.36.34" sID="Gen.36.34"/> Jobab died and was succeeded by Husham from the Temanite country. <verse eId="Gen.36.34"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.36.35" sID="Gen.36.35"/> Husham died and was succeeded by Hadad the son of Bedad, who defeated the
        Midianites in the open country of Moab; the name of his capital was Avith. <verse eId="Gen.36.35"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.36.36" sID="Gen.36.36"/> Hadad died and was succeeded by Samlah of Masrekah. <verse eId="Gen.36.36"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.36.37" sID="Gen.36.37"/> Samlah died and was succeeded by Saul from Rahaba on the Eu­phrates. <verse eId="Gen.36.37"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.36.38" sID="Gen.36.38"/> Saul died and was succeeded by Baal-hanan the son of Achbor. <verse eId="Gen.36.38"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.36.39" sID="Gen.36.39"/> Baal-hanan the son of Achbor died and was suc­ceeded by Hadar; the name of
        his capital was Pau, and his wife was called Mehetabel, the daughter of Matred, who was the daughter of Mezahab.
       <verse eId="Gen.36.39"/>
      </p>
      <p>
       <verse osisID="Gen.36.40" sID="Gen.36.40"/>Here are the names of the chieftains descended from Esau, in the order of
        their peoples and places: the chieftain of Timna, the chieftain of Alvah, the chief­tain of Jetheth, <verse eId="Gen.36.40"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.36.41" sID="Gen.36.41"/> the chieftain of Oholibamah, the chieftain of Elath, the chieftain of
        Punon, <verse eId="Gen.36.41"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.36.42" sID="Gen.36.42"/> the chieftain of Kenaz, the
        <milestone type="pb" n="42"/>
        chieftain of Teman, the chieftain of Mibzar, <verse eId="Gen.36.42"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.36.43" sID="Gen.36.43"/> the chieftain of Magdiel, and the chieftain of Iram. Such were the
        chieftains of Edom, as they were placed in the land they held--that is, the land of Esau, the ancestor of the
        Edomites. <verse eId="Gen.36.43"/>
      </p>
     <chapter eId="Gen.36"/>
     <chapter osisId="Gen.37" sId="Gen.37"/>
      <p>
       <verse osisID="Gen.37.1" sID="Gen.37.1"/>Now Jacob was living in the land where his father had resided, in the land
        of Canaan. <verse eId="Gen.37.1"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.37.2" sID="Gen.37.2"/> Here are the descendants of Jacob. <verse eId="Gen.37.2"/>
     <chapter eId="Gen.37"/>
     <chapter osisId="Gen.35" sId="Gen.35"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.35.22" sID="Gen.35.22"/> Jacob had twelve sons; <verse eId="Gen.35.22"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.35.23" sID="Gen.35.23"/> Leah’s sons were Reuben (Jacob’s first-born), Simeon, Levi, Judah,
        Issachar, and Zebulun; <verse eId="Gen.35.23"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.35.24" sID="Gen.35.24"/> Rachel’s sons were Joseph and Benjamin; <verse eId="Gen.35.24"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.35.25" sID="Gen.35.25"/> the sons of Bilhah, Rachel’s maid, were Dan and Naphtali, <verse eId="Gen.35.25"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.35.26" sID="Gen.35.26"/> the sons of of Zilpah, Leah’s maid, were Gad and Asher. These were the
        sons born to Jacob in Paddan-aram. <verse eId="Gen.35.26"/>
     <chapter eId="Gen.35"/>
     <chapter osisId="Gen.37" sId="Gen.37"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.37.2" sID="Gen.37.2"/> Now Joseph, who was seventeen,
        <hi type="italic">
          was a shepherd-lad along with his brothers,
          the sons of Bilhah and of Zilpah, his father’s wives. He gave a bad report of them to his father. <verse eId="Gen.37.2"/>
         <verse osisID="Gen.37.3" sID="Gen.37.3"/> Is­rael loved Joseph more than all his sons, as the son of his old age; he
          had a tunic with long sleeves made for him. <verse eId="Gen.37.3"/>
         <verse osisID="Gen.37.4" sID="Gen.37.4"/> And as his brothers saw that their father loved him better than all the
          others, they hated him and could not say a civil word to him. <verse eId="Gen.37.4"/>
        </hi>
       <verse osisID="Gen.37.5" sID="Gen.37.5"/> [Joseph had a dream, which he told his brothers, and it made them hate him
        worse than ever. <verse eId="Gen.37.5"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.37.6" sID="Gen.37.6"/> He said to them, <q>Do listen to this dream I have had. <verse eId="Gen.37.6"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.37.7" sID="Gen.37.7"/> Methought, as we were binding sheaves in the field, my sheaf stood up,
        while your sheaves all around did homage to it!</q> <verse eId="Gen.37.7"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.37.8" sID="Gen.37.8"/>His brothers answered, <q>And are you to be king over us? You to lord it
        over us!</q> They hated him worse than ever, for what he dreamed and what he said. <verse eId="Gen.37.8"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.37.9" sID="Gen.37.9"/> He had another dream which he told his brothers. <q>Listen,</q> he said,
        <q>I have had another dream! The sun, the moon, and the eleven stars were doing homage to me!</q> <verse eId="Gen.37.9"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.37.10" sID="Gen.37.10"/> When he told this to his father and his brothers, his father reproved
        him, saying, <q>What is this dream of yours? Am I and your mother and your brothers actually to bow before you to
        the earth?</q> <verse eId="Gen.37.10"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.37.11" sID="Gen.37.11"/> His brothers bore him malice, but his father kept mind of what he said.] <verse eId="Gen.37.11"/>
      </p>
      <p>
       <hi type="italic">
        <verse osisID="Gen.37.12" sID="Gen.37.12"/>His brothers had gone to herd their fathers flocks at Shechem. <verse eId="Gen.37.12"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.37.13" sID="Gen.37.13"/> So Israel said to Joseph, <q>Are not your brothers herding the flocks
         at Shechem? Come, I will send you to them.</q> <q>I am ready,</q> said Joseph. <verse eId="Gen.37.13"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.37.14" sID="Gen.37.14"/> <q>Well, go,</q> said Israel, <q>see if all is well with your brothers
         and with the flocks, and bring me word.</q> So he sent him from the valley of Hebron, and to Shechem Joseph came. <verse eId="Gen.37.14"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.37.15" sID="Gen.37.15"/> A man found him wandering about the country and asked him what he
         wanted. <verse eId="Gen.37.15"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.37.16" sID="Gen.37.16"/> He said, <q>I am in search of my brothers. Pray tell me where they are
         shepherding.</q> <verse eId="Gen.37.16"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.37.17" sID="Gen.37.17"/> The man said, <q>They have gone from here; I heard them saying, <q>Let
         us move to Dothan.</q></q> Then Jo­seph went after his brothers, and in Dothan he found them. <verse eId="Gen.37.17"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.37.18" sID="Gen.37.18"/> But they saw him at a distance and, long before he came up, they plotted
         to murder him.
        <verse eId="Gen.37.18"/>
       </hi>
       <verse osisID="Gen.37.19" sID="Gen.37.19"/>[They said to each other, <q>Here’s the dreamer! <verse eId="Gen.37.19"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.37.20" sID="Gen.37.20"/> Come on, let us kill him and fling him into one of the pits. We can
        say that a wild beast devoured him. Then we’ll see what becomes of his dreams!</q>]<verse eId="Gen.37.20"/>
       <hi type="italic">
        <verse osisID="Gen.37.21" sID="Gen.37.21"/> When Judah heard this, however, he rescued him from their hands,
         saying, <q>No, we must not kill him outright.</q>
        <verse eId="Gen.37.21"/>
       </hi>
       <milestone type="pb" n="43"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.37.22" sID="Gen.37.22"/> [Said Reuben, <q>Shed no blood; fling him into this pit out in the open,
        but no violence!</q> (his idea being to rescue him and restore him to his father). <verse eId="Gen.37.22"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.37.23" sID="Gen.37.23"/> So when Joseph reached his brothers, they stripped him of his tunic (the
        tunic with long sleeves), <verse eId="Gen.37.23"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.37.24" sID="Gen.37.24"/> and flung him into the pit, which was empty; there was no water in it. <verse eId="Gen.37.24"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.37.25" sID="Gen.37.25"/>
        Then they sat down to their food.]
      </p>
      <p>
       <hi type="italic">
         On looking up, there they saw a caravan of Ishmaelites on the way from Gilead to Egypt, carrying resin and balsam
         and fragrant gum on their camels! <verse eId="Gen.37.25"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.37.26" sID="Gen.37.26"/>Then said Judah to his brothers, <q>What is the good of killing our brother
         and covering up his blood? <verse eId="Gen.37.26"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.37.27" sID="Gen.37.27"/> Come on, let us sell him to the Ishmaelites, instead of doing him
         violence! He is our brother, our own flesh!</q> <verse eId="Gen.37.27"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.37.28" sID="Gen.37.28"/>To this his brothers agreed, and they sold Joseph to the Ishmaelites for
         fifty shillings,
       </hi>
        [Some Midianite traders passed, who pulled Joseph out of the pit, and took him away to Egypt. <verse eId="Gen.37.28"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.37.29" sID="Gen.37.29"/> So, when Reuben went back to the pit, there was no Joseph in the pit!
        He tore his dress, <verse eId="Gen.37.29"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.37.30" sID="Gen.37.30"/> and went back to his brothers, crying, <q>The boy is gone! Whatever
        is to become of me?</q>] <verse eId="Gen.37.30"/>
      </p>
      <p>
       <hi type="italic">
        <verse osisID="Gen.37.31" sID="Gen.37.31"/>As for Joseph’s tunic, they dipped it in the blood of a goat they
         had killed; <verse eId="Gen.37.31"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.37.32" sID="Gen.37.32"/> then, taking it to their father, they said, <q>We found this
         tunic; see if it is your son’s or not.</q> <verse eId="Gen.37.32"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.37.33" sID="Gen.37.33"/> Jacob recognized it. <q>It is my son’s tunic,</q> he said;
         <q>some wild beast has devoured him. Joseph must have been torn to pieces.</q> <verse eId="Gen.37.33"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.37.34" sID="Gen.37.34"/> So Jacob tore his dress, girdled him­self with sackcloth, and
         mourned for his son many a day; <verse eId="Gen.37.34"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.37.35" sID="Gen.37.35"/> his sons and his daughters all tried to console him, but he would
         not be consoled. <q>No,</q> he said, <q>I will go down mourning to my son in death.</q> Thus did his father
         weep for him. <verse eId="Gen.37.35"/>
       </hi>
       <verse osisID="Gen.37.36" sID="Gen.37.36"/> [Meantime the Midianites sold him in Egypt to Potiphar, one of the
        Pharaoh’s officials, who was governor of the prison.] <verse eId="Gen.37.36"/>
      </p>
     <chapter eId="Gen.37"/>
     <chapter osisId="Gen.38" sId="Gen.38"/>
      <p>
       <hi type="italic">
        <verse osisID="Gen.38.1" sID="Gen.38.1"/>It happened about then that Judah withdrew from his
         brothers and joined an Adullamite called Hirah. <verse eId="Gen.38.1"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.38.2" sID="Gen.38.2"/> There he saw Bathshua a Canaanite; he married her and went in to her,<verse eId="Gen.38.2"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.38.3" sID="Gen.38.3"/> and she conceived; she bore a son and called him Er. <verse eId="Gen.38.3"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.38.4" sID="Gen.38.4"/> Again she conceived and bore a son, whom she called Onan. <verse eId="Gen.38.4"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.38.5" sID="Gen.38.5"/> Once more she bore a son, calling him Shelah (she was at Kezib when
         she bore him). <verse eId="Gen.38.5"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.38.6" sID="Gen.38.6"/> Judah chose a wife for Er, called Tamar; <verse eId="Gen.38.6"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.38.7" sID="Gen.38.7"/> but Er, Judah’s first-born, was a wicked man before the Eternal, and
         the Eternal cut him off. <verse eId="Gen.38.7"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.38.8" sID="Gen.38.8"/> Then said Judah to Onan, <q>Go in to your brother’s widow, do your
         duty to her as a husband’s brother, and produce a child for your brother.</q> <verse eId="Gen.38.8"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.38.9" sID="Gen.38.9"/> But, as Onan knew that the child would not belong to him, he used to
         spill the seed on the ground whenever he went in to his brother’s widow, to avoid producing a child for his
         brother. <verse eId="Gen.38.9"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.38.10" sID="Gen.38.10"/> What he did was wicked before the Eternal, who cut him off also. <verse eId="Gen.38.10"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.38.11" sID="Gen.38.11"/> So Judah said to Tamar, <q>Stay on as a widow in your father’s
         house, till my son Shelah grows up.</q> (He was afraid that Shelah might die like his brothers.) Tamar
         went to stay in her father’s house.
        <verse eId="Gen.38.11"/>
       </hi>
      </p>
      <p>
       <hi type="italic">
        <verse osisID="Gen.38.12" sID="Gen.38.12"/>In course of time Bathshua, Judah’s wife, died; and, after
         Judah had consoled himself, he went to look after his sheep-shearers at Timna, along with his
         companion, Hirah the Adullamite. <verse eId="Gen.38.12"/>
        <milestone type="pb" n="44"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.38.13" sID="Gen.38.13"/> Tamar was told that her father-in-law had gone to Timna
         for the sheep-shearing. <verse eId="Gen.38.13"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.38.14" sID="Gen.38.14"/> Now she knew Shelah had grown up, and yet she was not his
         wife; so laying aside her widow’s dress, she wrapped herself up in a veil and sat at the entrance to Enaim on 
         the road to Timna. <verse eId="Gen.38.14"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.38.15" sID="Gen.38.15"/> When Judah saw her, he thought she was a harlot, since her face was
         veiled. <verse eId="Gen.38.15"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.38.16" sID="Gen.38.16"/> So he stepped aside to her by the roadside, saying, <q>Pray, let me
         come in to you</q> (little knowing that she was his daughter-in-law). <verse eId="Gen.38.16"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.38.17" sID="Gen.38.17"/> <q>What will you give me,</q> she asked, <q>for coming in to me?</q>
         <q>I will send you a kid from my flock of goats,</q> he said. <q>Will you give me a pledge till 16  you send
         it?</q> <verse eId="Gen.38.17"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.38.18" sID="Gen.38.18"/><q>What pledge?</q> <q>Your signet-ring,</q> she said, <q>your cord for
         it, and the stick in your hand.</q> So he gave them to her and went in to her, and she conceived by him. <verse eId="Gen.38.18"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.38.19" sID="Gen.38.19"/>Then she got up and went away, removing her veil and putting on her
         widow’s dress. <verse eId="Gen.38.19"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.38.20" sID="Gen.38.20"/> Judah sent his companion the Adullamite with the kid, to get back the
         pledge from the woman, but she was not to be found. <verse eId="Gen.38.20"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.38.21" sID="Gen.38.21"/> He asked the natives, <q>Where is yon temple-prostitute who was by the
         road­side at Enaim?</q> They answered, <q>There has been none here.</q> <verse eId="Gen.38.21"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.38.22" sID="Gen.38.22"/> So he went back and told Judah, <q>I cannot find her; the natives say
         that no temple-prostitute has been there.</q> <verse eId="Gen.38.22"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.38.23" sID="Gen.38.23"/> <q>Well,</q> said Judah, <q>let her keep the pledge, lest we are
         brought into con­tempt; I did send the kid, and you could not find the woman.</q>
        <verse eId="Gen.38.23"/>
       </hi>
      </p>
      <p>
       <hi type="italic">
        <verse osisID="Gen.38.24" sID="Gen.38.24"/>About three months later Ju­dah was told that his daughter-in-law Tamar
         had been playing the harlot and was with child by whoredom. <q>Bring her out and burn her,</q> said Judah. <verse eId="Gen.38.24"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.38.25" sID="Gen.38.25"/> But as she was being led out, she sent a message to her father-in-law:
         <q>I am with child by the man to whom these belong. Look,</q> she said, <q>note whom they belong to, this
         signet-ring, this cord and stick!</q> <verse eId="Gen.38.25"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.38.26" sID="Gen.38.26"/> When Judah recognized them, he said, <q>She is in the right against me,
         for I did not marry her to my son Shelah.</q> So he had no further intercourse with her. <verse eId="Gen.38.26"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.38.27" sID="Gen.38.27"/> When she was in child-birth, there were twins in her womb, <verse eId="Gen.38.27"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.38.28" sID="Gen.38.28"/> and during her labour a hand appeared; the midwife tied a scarlet
         thread on it, say­ing, <q>This one came out first.</q> <verse eId="Gen.38.28"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.38.29" sID="Gen.38.29"/> But he drew back his hand, and out came his brother. <q>What a breach
         you have made for your­self!</q> she said. So his name was Perez (Breach). <verse eId="Gen.38.29"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.38.30" sID="Gen.38.30"/> Afterwards his brother came out, with the scarlet thread on his hand;
         and his name was Zerah (Scarlet). <verse eId="Gen.38.30"/>
       </hi>
      </p>
     <chapter eId="Gen.38"/>
     <chapter osisId="Gen.39" sId="Gen.39"/>
      <p>
       <hi type="italic">
        <verse osisID="Gen.39.1" sID="Gen.39.1"/>When Joseph was taken on down to Egypt, an Egyptian [[Potiphar, one of the
         Pha­raoh’s officials, who was governor of the prison, bought him from the Ishmaelites who had brought him down. <verse eId="Gen.39.1"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.39.2" sID="Gen.39.2"/> But the Eternal was with Joseph, and he prospered; he was kept inside the
         household of his master the Egyptian, <verse eId="Gen.39.2"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.39.3" sID="Gen.39.3"/> and his master noticed that the Eter­nal was with him, and that the
         Eternal prospered everything he took in hand. <verse eId="Gen.39.3"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.39.4" sID="Gen.39.4"/> Joseph was popular with him and became his per­sonal attendant; then he
         made him his household steward, and entrusted everything to him. <verse eId="Gen.39.4"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.39.5" sID="Gen.39.5"/> From the hour that he made him his household steward in charge of
         everything, the Eter­nal blessed the house of the Egyptian for Joseph’s sake; the blessing of the Eternal rested on
         all that he had, inside the house and outside. <verse eId="Gen.39.5"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.39.6" sID="Gen.39.6"/> He left everything
         <milestone type="pb" n="45"/>
         in the hands of Joseph; not a thing did he trouble himself about, except his food. <verse eId="Gen.39.6"/>
       </hi>
      </p>
      <p>
       <hi type="italic">
        <verse osisID="Gen.39.7" sID="Gen.39.7"/>Joseph was good-looking and handsome. <verse eId="Gen.39.7"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.39.8" sID="Gen.39.8"/> By-and-by his mas­ter’s wife cast her eyes on him: <q>Lie with me,</q>
         she said. <verse eId="Gen.39.8"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.39.9" sID="Gen.39.9"/> But he refused. He said to his master’s wife, <q>My master does not
         trouble himself about anything in the household, but has left everything in my hands, so that my authority is
         equal to his own; he has kept nothing from me ex­cept yourself, for you are his wife. How then can I commit this
         great crime, and sin against God?</q><verse eId="Gen.39.9"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.39.10" sID="Gen.39.10"/>
        <verse eId="Gen.39.10"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.39.11" sID="Gen.39.11"/> Day after day she spoke to Joseph, but he would not lis­ten to her
         appeal to lie with her or to be with her. One day, when he went into the house about his work, as no man of the
         household was indoors, <verse eId="Gen.39.11"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.39.12" sID="Gen.39.12"/> she caught him by the robe, saying, <q>Lie with me.</q> But he ran off,
         leaving the robe in her hands, and got away. <verse eId="Gen.39.12"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.39.13" sID="Gen.39.13"/> When she saw he had run away, leaving his robe in her hands, <verse eId="Gen.39.13"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.39.14" sID="Gen.39.14"/> she called to her household, <q>Here is a Hebrew brought into the house
         to insult me! He came in to lie with me; I screamed,
        <verse eId="Gen.39.14"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.39.15" sID="Gen.39.15"/> and when he heard me screaming aloud he left his robe with me and ran
         off!</q> <verse eId="Gen.39.15"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.39.16" sID="Gen.39.16"/> She kept the robe beside her, till his master came home. <verse eId="Gen.39.16"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.39.17" sID="Gen.39.17"/> Then she told him this story: <q>The He­brew slave you brought to us
         came in to insult me; <verse eId="Gen.39.17"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.39.18" sID="Gen.39.18"/> but when I screamed aloud, he left his robe with me and ran out!</q> <verse eId="Gen.39.18"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.39.19" sID="Gen.39.19"/> When Joseph’s master heard what his wife said, about how his servant
         had treated her, he was furious; <verse eId="Gen.39.19"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.39.20" sID="Gen.39.20"/> Joseph’s master put him in gaol, where the royal prisoners were bound. <verse eId="Gen.39.20"/>
       </hi>
      </p>
      <p>
       <hi type="italic">
        <verse osisID="Gen.39.21" sID="Gen.39.21"/>In gaol he lay. Yet the Eter­nal was with Joseph and was kind to him,
         making him popu­lar with the gaoler, <verse eId="Gen.39.21"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.39.22" sID="Gen.39.22"/> who put Joseph in charge of all the pris­oners in the gaol, holding him
         responsible for anything they did; <verse eId="Gen.39.22"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.39.23" sID="Gen.39.23"/> the gaoler did not need to attend to anything that Joseph undertook,
         for the Eternal was with him, and whatever he did the Eternal made it prosper. <verse eId="Gen.39.23"/>
       </hi>
      </p>
     <chapter eId="Gen.39"/>
     <chapter osisId="Gen.40" sId="Gen.40"/>
      <p>
       <verse osisID="Gen.40.1" sID="Gen.40.1"/>[After this it happened a a that the cupbearer and the baker of the king
        of Egypt offended their lord the king of Egypt; <verse eId="Gen.40.1"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.40.2" sID="Gen.40.2"/> the Pharaoh was angry with his two officials, the chief cupbearer and the
        head baker, <verse eId="Gen.40.2"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.40.3" sID="Gen.40.3"/> and put them in custody in the house of the governor of the prison, the
        gaol in which Joseph was confined. <verse eId="Gen.40.3"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.40.4" sID="Gen.40.4"/> The governor of the prison appointed Joseph to attend upon them. <verse eId="Gen.40.4"/>
      </p>
      <p>
       <verse osisID="Gen.40.5" sID="Gen.40.5"/>For some time they remained in custody. Then one night they both had
        dreams, each man dreaming something with a meaning for himself, the cup­bearer and the baker of the king of Egypt
        who were confined in the gaol. <verse eId="Gen.40.5"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.40.6" sID="Gen.40.6"/> When Joseph went in, next morning, he noticed that they were downcast. <verse eId="Gen.40.6"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.40.7" sID="Gen.40.7"/> So he asked the officials of the Pharaoh who were in custody along with
        himself in his master’s house, <q>Why are you looking so downcast to-day?</q><verse eId="Gen.40.7"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.40.8" sID="Gen.40.8"/> <q>We have had a dream,</q> they said, <q>and there is no one to
        interpret it.</q> Joseph answered, <q>Do not interpretations belong to God? But pray tell me the dream.</q> <verse eId="Gen.40.8"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.40.9" sID="Gen.40.9"/> So the chief cupbearer told Joseph his dream. <q>In my dream,</q>
        he said, <q>there was a vine in front of me, <verse eId="Gen.40.9"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.40.10" sID="Gen.40.10"/> and on the vine there were three branches. It seemed to bud,
        its blossoms opened, and the clusters produced ripe grapes. <verse eId="Gen.40.10"/>
        <milestone type="pb" n="46"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.40.11" sID="Gen.40.11"/> As the Pharaoh’s cup was in my hand, I plucked the grapes, squeezed
        them into the Pharaoh’s cup, and handed the cup to the Pharaoh.</q> <verse eId="Gen.40.11"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.40.12" sID="Gen.40.12"/> <q>Here is the interpretation,</q> said Joseph; <q>the three
        branches are three days. <verse eId="Gen.40.12"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.40.13" sID="Gen.40.13"/> Within three days the Pharaoh will release you and restore you to
        your post; you will hand the Pharaoh his cup as you used to do when you were his cupbearer. <verse eId="Gen.40.13"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.40.14" sID="Gen.40.14"/> But remember me when all goes well with you; do me the kindness of
        mentioning my name to the Pharaoh and get me out of here; <verse eId="Gen.40.14"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.40.15" sID="Gen.40.15"/>for I was really kidnapped from the land of the Hebrews, and I have
        done nothing in this country for which I should be put into the dungeon.</q> <verse eId="Gen.40.15"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.40.16" sID="Gen.40.16"/> When the head baker saw that the interpretation was favourable, he
        said to Joseph, <q>In my dream I too saw something; three baskets of white bread were on my head; <verse eId="Gen.40.16"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.40.17" sID="Gen.40.17"/> in the top basket there were all sorts of pastry for the Pharaoh,
        but the birds kept eating them out of the basket on my head.</q> <verse eId="Gen.40.17"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.40.18" sID="Gen.40.18"/> <q>Here is the interpretation,</q> said Joseph; <q>the three baskets
        are three days. <verse eId="Gen.40.18"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.40.19" sID="Gen.40.19"/> Within three days the Pharaoh will release you, and hang you on a tree,
        till the birds eat the flesh off you.</q> <verse eId="Gen.40.19"/>
      </p>
      <p>
       <verse osisID="Gen.40.20" sID="Gen.40.20"/>On the third day, which was the Pharaoh’s birthday, he held a banquet
        for all his courtiers, and he did release the chief cupbearer and the head baker. <verse eId="Gen.40.20"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.40.21" sID="Gen.40.21"/> The chief cupbearer he restored to his post, where he handed the cup
        to the Pharaoh; <verse eId="Gen.40.21"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.40.22" sID="Gen.40.22"/> but the head baker he hanged. It was as Joseph had interpreted to them. <verse eId="Gen.40.22"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.40.23" sID="Gen.40.23"/> But the chief cupbearer did not remember Joseph; he forgot him. <verse eId="Gen.40.23"/>
      </p>
     <chapter eId="Gen.40"/>
     <chapter osisId="Gen.41" sId="Gen.41"/>
      <p>
       <verse osisID="Gen.41.1" sID="Gen.41.1"/>Two years passed, and the Pharaoh dreamed he was standing beside the Nile; <verse eId="Gen.41.1"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.41.2" sID="Gen.41.2"/> up came seven cows from the Nile, sleek and plump, and they grazed in the
        reed-grass. <verse eId="Gen.41.2"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.41.3" sID="Gen.41.3"/> After them seven other cows came up from the Nile, ugly and lean; they
        stood beside the rest of the cows on the bank of the Nile, <verse eId="Gen.41.3"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.41.4" sID="Gen.41.4"/> and the ugly lean cows ate up the seven cows that were sleek and plump.
        Then the Pharaoh woke up. <verse eId="Gen.41.4"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.41.5" sID="Gen.41.5"/> When he fell asleep, he had a second dream; there were seven fine ripe
        ears of corn sprouting on a single stalk! <verse eId="Gen.41.5"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.41.6" sID="Gen.41.6"/> And seven ears sprang up after them, thin and blasted by the east wind; <verse eId="Gen.41.6"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.41.7" sID="Gen.41.7"/> but the thin ears swallowed up the seven ears that were fine and full.
      </p>
      <p>
        Then the Pharaoh woke up, to find he had been dreaming. <verse eId="Gen.41.7"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.41.8" sID="Gen.41.8"/> In the morning his mind was dis­turbed; so he summoned all the magicians
        and sages in Egypt, and told them what he had dreamed, but no one could in­terpret it for the Pharaoh. <verse eId="Gen.41.8"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.41.9" sID="Gen.41.9"/> Then the chief cupbearer said to the Pharaoh, <q>I must recall my
        offences to-day, <verse eId="Gen.41.9"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.41.10" sID="Gen.41.10"/> how the Pharaoh was angry with his serv­ants and put myself and the head
        baker in custody within the house of the governor of the prison. <verse eId="Gen.41.10"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.41.11" sID="Gen.41.11"/> Now, one night we dreamed, he and I; each had a dream with a meaning
        for himself. <verse eId="Gen.41.11"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.41.12" sID="Gen.41.12"/> But there was a youth along with us, a Hebrew slave of the
        prison-governor, and when we told him our dreams, he interpreted them, telling each of us the meaning of his own
        dream. <verse eId="Gen.41.12"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.41.13" sID="Gen.41.13"/> And as he interpreted, so it fell out; I
        <milestone type="pb" n="47"/>
        was restored to my post, and the other man was hanged.</q> <verse eId="Gen.41.13"/>
      </p>
      <p>
       <verse osisID="Gen.41.14" sID="Gen.41.14"/>Then the Pharaoh sent for Jo­seph, whom they brought hur­riedly from the
        dungeon; after shaving himself and changing his clothes, he came into the Pharaoh’s presence. <verse eId="Gen.41.14"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.41.15" sID="Gen.41.15"/> <q>I have had a dream,</q> said the Pharaoh to Joseph, <q>and there
        is no one to interpret it; but I have heard about you, that you can interpret a dream whenever you hear it.</q>
       <verse eId="Gen.41.15"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.41.16" sID="Gen.41.16"/> <q>Not I!</q> said Joseph to the Pharaoh; <q>it is God’s answer that will
        answer to the Pharaoh.</q> <verse eId="Gen.41.16"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.41.17" sID="Gen.41.17"/> Then the Pharaoh said to Joseph: <q>In my dream I was standing on the bank
        of the Nile; <verse eId="Gen.41.17"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.41.18" sID="Gen.41.18"/> up came seven cows from the Nile, plump and sleek, and they grazed in the
        reed-grass.  <verse eId="Gen.41.18"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.41.19" sID="Gen.41.19"/> After them seven other cows came up, starved and very ugly and lean--I
        never saw such poor cows in all the land of Egypt.  <verse eId="Gen.41.19"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.41.20" sID="Gen.41.20"/> The lean and ugly cows ate up the first seven plump cows, <verse eId="Gen.41.20"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.41.21" sID="Gen.41.21"/> and even after they had eaten them up, you could not tell that they had
        eaten them—they were still ugly as before. Then I woke up.  <verse eId="Gen.41.21"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.41.22" sID="Gen.41.22"/> I also saw in a dream seven full ripe ears sprouting on a single stalk.<verse eId="Gen.41.22"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.41.23" sID="Gen.41.23"/> Seven ears sprang up after them, withered, thin, and blasted by the east wind, <verse eId="Gen.41.23"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.41.24" sID="Gen.41.24"/> and the thin ears swallowed up the seven ripe ears! I told all this to the
        magicians, but not one of them could tell me the meaning.</q> <verse eId="Gen.41.24"/>
      </p>
      <p>
       <verse osisID="Gen.41.25" sID="Gen.41.25"/>Joseph said to the Pharaoh, <q>The Pharaoh’s dreams mean one thing. God has
        been showing the Pharaoh what he is about to do; <verse eId="Gen.41.25"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.41.26" sID="Gen.41.26"/> the seven good cows are seven years, and the seven good ears are seven
        years--it is one and the same dream.  <verse eId="Gen.41.26"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.41.27" sID="Gen.41.27"/> The seven lean and ugly cows that came up afterwards are also seven years,
        and so are the seven empty ears blasted by the east wind; there are to be seven years of famine.  <verse eId="Gen.41.27"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.41.28" sID="Gen.41.28"/> This is what I meant when I said to the Pharaoh that God has shown the
        Pharaoh what he is going to do.  <verse eId="Gen.41.28"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.41.29" sID="Gen.41.29"/> Seven years of great plenty are coming for all the land of Egypt, <verse eId="Gen.41.29"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.41.30" sID="Gen.41.30"/> but there will be seven years of famine after them, and the plenty will all
        be forgotten in the land of Egypt; famine will consume the land, <verse eId="Gen.41.30"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.41.31" sID="Gen.41.31"/> so sore a famine that there will be no word of plenty in the land, owing to
        the famine that will follow.  <verse eId="Gen.41.31"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.41.32" sID="Gen.41.32"/> The dream was doubled for the Pharaoh because this is fixed by God, and ere
        long God will bring it about.  <verse eId="Gen.41.32"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.41.33" sID="Gen.41.33"/> Well then, let the Pharaoh look out a shrewd, intelligent man, and put him
        in control of the land of Egypt.  <verse eId="Gen.41.33"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.41.34" sID="Gen.41.34"/> Let the Pharaoh take action further by appointing food-controllers throughout
        the country, to annex a fifth of the produce of Egypt during the seven years of plenty; <verse eId="Gen.41.34"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.41.35" sID="Gen.41.35"/> let them gather all the food of the good years that are coming, and, under
        authority of the Pharaoh, store up the grain and hold it for food in the towns.  <verse eId="Gen.41.35"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.41.36" sID="Gen.41.36"/> The food will be a reserve for the land in view of the seven years of famine
        that are to befall the land of Egypt, that the country may not perish of famine.</q> <verse eId="Gen.41.36"/>
      </p>
      <p>
       <verse osisID="Gen.41.37" sID="Gen.41.37"/>This plan approved itself to the Pharaoh and all his courtiers. <verse eId="Gen.41.37"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.41.38" sID="Gen.41.38"/> The Pharaoh said to his courtiers, <q>Can we find anyone equal
        to this man, in whom is the spirit of God?</q> <verse eId="Gen.41.38"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.41.39" sID="Gen.41.39"/> Then the Pharaoh turned to Joseph: <q>As God has shown you all this,
        there is no one so shrewd and
        <milestone type="pb" n="48"/>
        intelligent as yourself.  <verse eId="Gen.41.39"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.41.40" sID="Gen.41.40"/> You shall be mayor of my palace, and all my nation shall move at your
        bidding; only on the throne shall my authority be greater than yours.<verse eId="Gen.41.40"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.41.41" sID="Gen.41.41"/> Look,</q> said the Pharaoh to Joseph, <q>I hereby appoint you over all the
        land of Egypt!</q> <verse eId="Gen.41.41"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.41.42" sID="Gen.41.42"/> And taking his signet-ring from his hand, the Pharaoh put it on Joseph’s
        hand, arraying him in fine linen robes, putting a gold chain round his neck, <verse eId="Gen.41.42"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.41.43" sID="Gen.41.43"/> and giving him his second chariot to drive in, till the people shouted,
        <q>At your service!</q> Thus he appointed him over all the land of Egypt.  <verse eId="Gen.41.43"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.41.44" sID="Gen.41.44"/> <q>I am the Pharaoh,</q> said the Pharaoh to Joseph, <q>and not a man
        shall stir hand or foot in all Egypt without your consent.</q> <verse eId="Gen.41.44"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.41.45" sID="Gen.41.45"/> The Pharaoh gave Joseph the name of Zaphenath-paneah (Life-sustainer)
        and married him to Asenath, the daughter of Potiphera, the priest at On.
      </p>
      <p>
        Then Joseph went through the land of Egypt.]
       <verse eId="Gen.41.45"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.41.46" sID="Gen.41.46"/> Joseph was thirty years old when he became prime minister to the Pharaoh,
        king of Egypt. Joseph went from the presence of the Pharaoh to go through all the land of Egypt.  <verse eId="Gen.41.46"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.41.47" sID="Gen.41.47"/> [And during the seven years of plenty, when the earth bore ample crops, <verse eId="Gen.41.47"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.41.48" sID="Gen.41.48"/> he collected all the produce of the rich years over Egypt and stored the
        grain within the towns; in every town he stored the produce of the surrounding fields.  <verse eId="Gen.41.48"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.41.49" sID="Gen.41.49"/> Joseph stored grain in huge quantities, like the sand of the sea, till
        he ceased counting it, for it was past measuring. <verse eId="Gen.41.49"/>
      </p>
      <p>
       <verse osisID="Gen.41.50" sID="Gen.41.50"/>Before the time of famine came, two sons were born to him by Asenath the
        daughter of Potiphera, the priest at On.  <verse eId="Gen.41.50"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.41.51" sID="Gen.41.51"/> The first-born Joseph called Manasseh (Forgetting) <q>for,</q> said he,
        <q>God has made me for­get all my hardships and my father’s house.</q> <verse eId="Gen.41.51"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.41.52" sID="Gen.41.52"/> The second he called Ephraim (Fruitful); <q>for God has made me fruitful
        in the land of my misfortunes.</q> <verse eId="Gen.41.52"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.41.53" sID="Gen.41.53"/> Then the seven years of plenty in the land of Egypt ended, <verse eId="Gen.41.53"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.41.54" sID="Gen.41.54"/> and, as Joseph had foretold, the seven years of famine began. There was
        a famine in every country, but there was food everywhere in Egypt.  <verse eId="Gen.41.54"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.41.55" sID="Gen.41.55"/> And when all Egypt itself grew famished, and the people cried to the
        Pharaoh for food, the Pharaoh told all the Egyptians, <q>Go to Joseph; do as he tells you.</q> <verse eId="Gen.41.55"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.41.56" sID="Gen.41.56"/> Then Joseph opened all the granaries and sold grain to the Egyptians.  <verse eId="Gen.41.56"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.41.57" sID="Gen.41.57"/> As the famine was all over the world, people from every country also came
        to Joseph in Egypt to buy grain--so severe was the famine everywhere on earth.<verse eId="Gen.41.57"/>
      </p>
     <chapter eId="Gen.41"/>
     <chapter osisId="Gen.42" sId="Gen.42"/>
      <p>
       <verse osisID="Gen.42.1" sID="Gen.42.1"/>When Jacob realized that there was grain for sale in Egypt, Jacob said to
        his sons, <q>Why stand looking at each other? <verse eId="Gen.42.1"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.42.2" sID="Gen.42.2"/>
        I hear,</q> he said, <q>there is grain for sale in Egypt; go down there and buy some for us, that we may live
        instead of dying.</q> <verse eId="Gen.42.2"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.42.3" sID="Gen.42.3"/> So Joseph’s ten brothers went down to buy grain from the Egyptians; <verse eId="Gen.42.3"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.42.4" sID="Gen.42.4"/> Jacob did not send Benjamin, Joseph’s own brother, with the rest, as he
        was afraid of him coming to harm.] <verse eId="Gen.42.4"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.42.5" sID="Gen.42.5"/> Among those who came to buy were the sons of Israel; for the famine was
        raging in the land of Canaan. <verse eId="Gen.42.5"/>
      </p>
      <p>
       <verse osisID="Gen.42.6" sID="Gen.42.6"/> Now Joseph was viceroy of the country; he it was who sold the grain to
        all the natives. [The brothers of Joseph came and bowed to the ground before
        <milestone type="pb" n="49"/>
        him.] <verse eId="Gen.42.6"/>
       <hi type="italic">
        <verse osisID="Gen.42.7" sID="Gen.42.7"/>When Joseph saw his brothers he recognized them, but he treated them like
         a stranger. He asked, <q>Where do you come from?</q> <q>From the country of Canaan,</q> they said, <q>to buy
         food.</q> <verse eId="Gen.42.7"/>
       </hi>
       <verse osisID="Gen.42.8" sID="Gen.42.8"/> [Joseph recognized his brothers, but they did not recognize him; <verse eId="Gen.42.8"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.42.9" sID="Gen.42.9"/> Joseph remembered what he had dreamed about them, and spoke harshly to
        them. <q>You are spies,</q> he said, <q>you have come to note how defenceless the land is.</q> <verse eId="Gen.42.9"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.42.10" sID="Gen.42.10"/> <q>No, my lord,</q> they said, <q>your serv­ants have come to buy food. <verse eId="Gen.42.10"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.42.11" sID="Gen.42.11"/> We are all sons of one man; we are honest men, your servants is are no
        spies.</q> <verse eId="Gen.42.11"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.42.12" sID="Gen.42.12"/> He answered, <q>No, you did come to note how defenceless the land is.</q> <verse eId="Gen.42.12"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.42.13" sID="Gen.42.13"/> They repeated, <q>Your servants are twelve brothers, sons of one man in
        the land of Canaan; the youngest is at present with our father, and there is one gone.</q> <verse eId="Gen.42.13"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.42.14" sID="Gen.42.14"/> Joseph retorted, <q>It is as I said, you are spies. <verse eId="Gen.42.14"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.42.15" sID="Gen.42.15"/> But I will test you; as sure as the Pharaoh lives, you shall not leave
        here unless your youngest brother comes here. <verse eId="Gen.42.15"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.42.16" sID="Gen.42.16"/> Send one of your number to fetch your brother, while you remain
        confined; it will be a test of your statements, and show if you are honest. Otherwise, as sure as the Pharaoh
        lives, you are spies.</q> <verse eId="Gen.42.16"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.42.17" sID="Gen.42.17"/> So he put them all in custody to­gether for three days. <verse eId="Gen.42.17"/>
      </p>
      <p>
       <verse osisID="Gen.42.18" sID="Gen.42.18"/>On the third day Joseph said to them, <q>As I am a religious man, you
        must do this at least to save your lives; <verse eId="Gen.42.18"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.42.19" sID="Gen.42.19"/> if you are honest men, let one of you re­main confined in prison, while
        you go with grain for your starving households <verse eId="Gen.42.19"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.42.20" sID="Gen.42.20"/> and bring me back your youngest brother; that will verify your
        statements and save your lives.</q> <verse eId="Gen.42.20"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.42.21" sID="Gen.42.21"/> They said to each other, <q>This misfortune has befallen us because we
        were guilty about our brother; we saw his misfortune, and we would not listen to his en­treaties.</q> <verse eId="Gen.42.21"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.42.22" sID="Gen.42.22"/> And Reuben said, <q>Did I not tell you, not to sin against the boy?
        But you would not listen to me. So, you see, there is a reckoning for his blood.</q> <verse eId="Gen.42.22"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.42.23" sID="Gen.42.23"/> They little knew that Joseph understood them, for there was an
        inter­preter at the interview. <verse eId="Gen.42.23"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.42.24" sID="Gen.42.24"/> But Joseph withdrew and broke down. On coming back, he se­lected Simeon
        and had him bound before their eyes; <verse eId="Gen.42.24"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.42.25" sID="Gen.42.25"/> then he gave orders that their bag­gage was to be filled with grain,
        that each man’s money was to be replaced in his sack, and that they were to receive pro­visions for the journey.
        This was done. <verse eId="Gen.42.25"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.42.26" sID="Gen.42.26"/> They loaded their asses with grain, and went away.] <verse eId="Gen.42.26"/>
      </p>
      <p>
       <verse osisID="Gen.42.27" sID="Gen.42.27"/>At the spot where they put up for the night, one of them opened his
        sack to get fodder for his ass, and there he saw his money, at the mouth of the sack! <verse eId="Gen.42.27"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.42.28" sID="Gen.42.28"/> He told his brothers, <q>My money has been put back! There it is,
        inside my sack!</q> At this their heart sank, and they turned trembling to one another. <verse eId="Gen.42.28"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.42.29" sID="Gen.42.29"/> [When they reached their father Jacob in the land of Canaan, they told
        him all that had happened to them. <verse eId="Gen.42.29"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.42.30" sID="Gen.42.30"/> <q>The man who is lord of the land,</q> they said, <q>talked harshly to
        us; he took us for spies and put us in cus­tody. <verse eId="Gen.42.30"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.42.31" sID="Gen.42.31"/> We said to him, <q>We are honest men, we are no spies; <verse eId="Gen.42.31"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.42.32" sID="Gen.42.32"/> we are twelve brothers, sons of our father; one is gone, and the
        youngest is at present with our father in the land of Canaan.</q> <verse eId="Gen.42.32"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.42.33" sID="Gen.42.33"/> Then the man who is lord of the
        <milestone type="pb" n="50"/>
        land said, ‘I will find out whether you are honest men in this way: leave one of your number with me, and do
        you take grain for your starving households and be off; <verse eId="Gen.42.33"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.42.34" sID="Gen.42.34"/> but bring me your youngest brother. Then I shall be sure that you are
        not spies but honest men; I will hand over your brother, and you can trade in the country.</q> <verse eId="Gen.42.34"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.42.35" sID="Gen.42.35"/> When they emptied their sacks, there was every man’s packet of money
        inside his sack! On seeing their pack­ets of money, they and their father were afraid, <verse eId="Gen.42.35"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.42.36" sID="Gen.42.36"/> saying, <q>What is this that God has done to us?</q> And Jacob their
        father said, <q>You bereave me of my children; Joseph is gone, Simeon is gone, and now you would take Benjamin.
        Look at all that I have to bear!</q> <verse eId="Gen.42.36"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.42.37" sID="Gen.42.37"/> But Reuben said to his father, <q>You may kill my two sons if I do not
        bring him back to you; put him in my charge, and I will bring him back!</q>] <verse eId="Gen.42.37"/>
      </p>
     <chapter eId="Gen.42"/>
     <chapter osisId="Gen.43" sId="Gen.43"/>
      <p>
       <hi type="italic">
        <verse osisID="Gen.43.1" sID="Gen.43.1"/>The famine was raging in the land. <verse eId="Gen.43.1"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.43.2" sID="Gen.43.2"/> So, after they had consumed the grain that they had brought from Egypt,
         their father said to them, <q>Go and buy us a little more food.</q> <verse eId="Gen.43.2"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.43.3" sID="Gen.43.3"/> <q>But,</q> said Judah, <q>the man told us strictly, <q>You cannot see
         me, unless your brother is with you.</q> <verse eId="Gen.43.3"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.43.4" sID="Gen.43.4"/> We will go and buy food, if you send our brother along with us; <verse eId="Gen.43.4"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.43.5" sID="Gen.43.5"/> but if you refuse, we will not go. The man told us, <q>You cannot see me,
         unless your brother is with you.</q></q> <verse eId="Gen.43.5"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.43.6" sID="Gen.43.6"/> <q>And why did you bring trouble on me,</q> said Israel, <q>by telling
         the man you had another brother?</q> <verse eId="Gen.43.6"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.43.7" sID="Gen.43.7"/> They said, <q>The man asked par­ticularly about us and our rela­tives; he
         said, <q>Is your father still alive? Have you another brother?</q> We answered the drift of his questions.
         How were we to know that he would say, <q>Fetch your brother?</q></q> <verse eId="Gen.43.7"/>
     <chapter eId="Gen.43"/>
     <chapter osisId="Gen.42" sId="Gen.42"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.42.38" sID="Gen.42.38"/>
         Israel said, <q>My son shall not go with you; his brother is dead, and he is the only one left. If he came to any
         harm on the road, you would bring down my grey hairs to the grave with grief.</q> <verse eId="Gen.42.38"/>
     <chapter eId="Gen.42"/>
     <chapter osisId="Gen.43" sId="Gen.43"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.43.8" sID="Gen.43.8"/><q>Send the lad with me,</q> said Judah to his father Israel; <q>let us
         start off, that we may live instead of dy­ing, we and you and our little ones. <verse eId="Gen.43.8"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.43.9" sID="Gen.43.9"/> I will stand guarantee for him; I will answer to you for him. If I fail
         to bring him back and set him before you, the last­ing blame be mine. <verse eId="Gen.43.9"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.43.10" sID="Gen.43.10"/> If we had not put off time, we could have been back by now!</q> <verse eId="Gen.43.10"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.43.11" sID="Gen.43.11"/> <q>Well,</q> said their father Israel, <q>if it is to be, then do this:
         take some of the dainties of the country in your baggage, and carry them as a present to the man, a little bal­sam,
         a little honey, resin, fra­grant gum, pistachio nuts, and almonds; <verse eId="Gen.43.11"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.43.12" sID="Gen.43.12"/> take double money with you, and carry back the money that was replaced
         in your sacks (perhaps it was by mis­take); <verse eId="Gen.43.12"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.43.13" sID="Gen.43.13"/> also take your brother and go back to the man.</q><verse eId="Gen.43.13"/>
       </hi>
       <verse osisID="Gen.43.14" sID="Gen.43.14"/><q>[And may God Almighty move the man to be kind and let your other
        brother go, as well as Ben­jamin. But if I am to be be­reaved--well, I am to be be­reaved!]</q> <verse eId="Gen.43.14"/>
      </p>
      <p>
       <hi type="italic">
        <verse osisID="Gen.43.15" sID="Gen.43.15"/>So taking this present, taking the double money, and taking Benjamin,
         the men started south for Egypt and made their way into the presence of Joseph. <verse eId="Gen.43.15"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.43.16" sID="Gen.43.16"/> When Joseph saw Benjamin with them, he said to his house-steward,
         <q>Take the men indoors, slaughter animals and make all preparations, for the men are to
         <milestone type="pb" n="51"/> 
         dine with me at noon.</q> <verse eId="Gen.43.16"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.43.17" sID="Gen.43.17"/>So he did as Joseph told him. He took the men into Joseph’s house; <verse eId="Gen.43.17"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.43.18" sID="Gen.43.18"/> but they were afraid at being taken inside Joseph’s house, thinking,
         <q>It is on ac­count of the money replaced in our sacks at our first visit; he wants to accuse us and attack us,
         to make us slaves and seize our asses!</q> <verse eId="Gen.43.18"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.43.19" sID="Gen.43.19"/> So they went up to Joseph’s house-steward and spoke to him at the
         door of the house. <verse eId="Gen.43.19"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.43.20" sID="Gen.43.20"/> <q>O my lord,</q> they said, <q>we simply came down to buy food <verse eId="Gen.43.20"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.43.21" sID="Gen.43.21"/> on our first visit, and when we opened our sacks at the spot where we
         put up, there was every man’s money in the mouth of his sack, our own money in full weight! We have brought it
         back, <verse eId="Gen.43.21"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.43.22" sID="Gen.43.22"/> and we have brought other money to buy food. We do not know who put
         our money in our sacks.</q> <verse eId="Gen.43.22"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.43.23" sID="Gen.43.23"/> <q>All right,</q> he said, <q>you need not be afraid; your God and
         the God of your father must have put treasure in your sacks, for I got your money.</q> <verse eId="Gen.43.23"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.43.24" sID="Gen.43.24"/> [[Then he brought Simeon out to them.]] Taking the men in­doors, he
         gave them water to wash their feet, and gave their asses fodder. <verse eId="Gen.43.24"/>
       </hi>
      </p>
      <p>
       <hi type="italic">
        <verse osisID="Gen.43.25" sID="Gen.43.25"/>Then they arranged their pres­ent for Joseph’s arrival at noon, for
         they had, heard they were to have a meal there. <verse eId="Gen.43.25"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.43.26" sID="Gen.43.26"/> When Joseph came home, they took their present to him in the house,
         bowing to the ground before him. <verse eId="Gen.43.26"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.43.27" sID="Gen.43.27"/>He asked how they were; he said, <q>Is your father well, the old man
         you spoke of? Is he still alive?</q> <verse eId="Gen.43.27"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.43.28" sID="Gen.43.28"/> They answered, <q>Your servant our father is well, he is still
         alive.</q> Then they bowed and did homage to him. <verse eId="Gen.43.28"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.43.29" sID="Gen.43.29"/> Looking up he saw his brother Benjamin, his mother’s son, and asked,
         <q>And is this your young­est brother, of whom you told me?</q> Then he said, <q>God be gracious to you, my
         son!</q> <verse eId="Gen.43.29"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.43.30" sID="Gen.43.30"/> His heart yearned for his brother, so he hastily sought a place to
         weep, and retired to his room, where he broke down in tears. <verse eId="Gen.43.30"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.43.31" sID="Gen.43.31"/> After washing his face, he came out, and controlling himself or­dered
         dinner to be served. <verse eId="Gen.43.31"/>
       </hi>
      </p>
      <p>
       <hi type="italic">
        <verse osisID="Gen.43.32" sID="Gen.43.32"/>Dinner was served for Joseph apart, for the men apart, and for his
         Egyptian guests apart; the Egyptians could not eat along with the Hebrews--that would, have polluted the
         Egyptians. <verse eId="Gen.43.32"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.43.33" sID="Gen.43.33"/> The men were seated in his presence in order of age, from the oldest,
         by right of birth, to the youngest--which made them stare at each other in astonish­ment. <verse eId="Gen.43.33"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.43.34" sID="Gen.43.34"/> Joseph would send portions to them from his own table, but Benjamin’s
         portions were five times as large as any of theirs. As they drank and drank deep in his company, <verse eId="Gen.43.34"/>
     <chapter eId="Gen.43"/>
     <chapter osisId="Gen.44" sId="Gen.44"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.44.1" sID="Gen.44.1"/> he ordered his house-steward, <q>Fill the men’s sacks with as much
         grain as they can hold, put every man’s money in the mouth of his sack, <verse eId="Gen.44.1"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.44.2" sID="Gen.44.2"/> and in the mouth of the youngest man’s sack, along with his corn
         money, put my goblet, the silver goblet.</q> He did as Joseph told him. <verse eId="Gen.44.2"/>
       </hi>
      </p>
      <p>
       <hi type="italic">
        <verse osisID="Gen.44.3" sID="Gen.44.3"/>Soon as day dawned, the men were sent off with their asses. <verse eId="Gen.44.3"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.44.4" sID="Gen.44.4"/>They had left the city but were not far away, when Joseph said to his steward,
         <q>Up and after the men! When you overtake them, ask them, <q>Why have you repaid injury for kindness? <verse eId="Gen.44.4"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.44.5" sID="Gen.44.5"/> Why have you stolen the silver goblet, the very goblet out of which my lord
         drinks, and with which he divines? That was a foul deed of yours!</q></q> <verse eId="Gen.44.5"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.44.6" sID="Gen.44.6"/> When he overtook them, he asked them this. <verse eId="Gen.44.6"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.44.7" sID="Gen.44.7"/> They said to him, <q>Why does my lord say such a thing? Your servants do a
         thing like that? Never! <verse eId="Gen.44.7"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.44.8" sID="Gen.44.8"/> Why, we brought you back from Canaan the money that we found in our sacks! How
         then should we steal silver or gold from your lord’s house? <verse eId="Gen.44.8"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.44.9" sID="Gen.44.9"/> If the goblet is found in possession of any of your servants, he shall die,
         and we will be slaves to my lord.</q> <verse eId="Gen.44.9"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.44.10" sID="Gen.44.10"/> <q>As you say,</q> replied the steward, <q>but he only who is found in
         possession of it shall be my slave; the rest of you shall be clear,</q> <verse eId="Gen.44.10"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.44.11" sID="Gen.44.11"/>Hurriedly they lowered all there sacks to the ground, every man opened his
         sack, <verse eId="Gen.44.11"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.44.12" sID="Gen.44.12"/> and the steward searched them, beginning with the oldest and going on to the
         youngest; in Benjamin's sack the goblet was found! <verse eId="Gen.44.12"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.44.13" sID="Gen.44.13"/> Tearing their clothes, each reloaded his ass, and back they went to the city. <verse eId="Gen.44.13"/>
       </hi>
      </p>
      <p>
       <hi type="italic">
        <verse osisID="Gen.44.14" sID="Gen.44.14"/>When Judah and his brothers reached Joseph’s house, he was still there; they
         dropped to the ground before him. <verse eId="Gen.44.14"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.44.15" sID="Gen.44.15"/> <q>What is this you have done?</q> said Joseph. <q>Don’t you know a man in
         my position is able to divine?</q><verse eId="Gen.44.15"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.44.16" sID="Gen.44.16"/> Judah answered, <q>What are we to say to my lord? What can we urge? how can
         we clear ourselves? God has discovered the iniquity of your servants; now we are slaves to my lord, we and the man in
         whose possession the goblet was found</q> <verse eId="Gen.44.16"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.44.17" sID="Gen.44.17"/><q>Far be it from me to act like that,</q> said Joseph; <q>the man in whose
         possession the goblet was found, he shall be my slave, but the rest of you can go to your father safe and sound!</q> <verse eId="Gen.44.17"/>
       </hi>
      </p>
      <p>
       <hi type="italic">
        <verse osisID="Gen.44.18" sID="Gen.44.18"/>Then Judah went up to him and said, <q>O my lord, pray let your
         servant say one word to my lord, and be not enraged at your servant, for you are like the Pharaoh himself. <verse eId="Gen.44.18"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.44.19" sID="Gen.44.19"/> My lord asked his servants, <q>Have you a father or a brother?</q> <verse eId="Gen.44.19"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.44.20" sID="Gen.44.20"/> And we told my lord, <q>We have a father, an old man, and a child
         of his old age, a young child, whose own brother is dead; he is the only child left of his mother, and his
         father loves him.</q> <verse eId="Gen.44.20"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.44.21" sID="Gen.44.21"/> You said to your servants, <q>Bring him down, that I may look at
         him.</q> <verse eId="Gen.44.21"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.44.22" sID="Gen.44.22"/> But we told my lord, <q>The boy cannot leave his father; his father
         would die if he lost him.</q> <verse eId="Gen.44.22"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.44.23" sID="Gen.44.23"/> You said to your servants, <q>Unless your brother comes along with
         you, you will never see me again.</q> <verse eId="Gen.44.23"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.44.24" sID="Gen.44.24"/> Well, when we went to your servant our father, we told him what my
         lord said; <verse eId="Gen.44.24"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.44.25" sID="Gen.44.25"/> and when our father bade us return and buy a little food, <verse eId="Gen.44.25"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.44.26" sID="Gen.44.26"/> we said, <q>We cannot go down. If our youngest brother goes with us,
         then we will go down; but not otherwise, for we cannot see the man unless our youngest brother is with us.</q> <verse eId="Gen.44.26"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.44.27" sID="Gen.44.27"/> Your servant our father said to us, <q>You know my wife bore me two
         sons; <verse eId="Gen.44.27"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.44.28" sID="Gen.44.28"/> one left me, and me-thinks he must have been torn to pieces, for I
         have never seen him again; <verse eId="Gen.44.28"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.44.29" sID="Gen.44.29"/> if you take this one too, and if he comes to harm, you will bring
         my grey hairs down to the grave with trouble.</q> <verse eId="Gen.44.29"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.44.30" sID="Gen.44.30"/> Now if I go to your servant my father without the boy, when he sees
         there is no boy, he will die, for his very soul is bound up in the boy; <verse eId="Gen.44.30"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.44.31" sID="Gen.44.31"/> and your servants will bring down the grey hairs of your servant
         our father to the grave with grief. <verse eId="Gen.44.31"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.44.32" sID="Gen.44.32"/> For your servant became guarantee for the boy to my father: I said,
         <q>If I fail to bring him back to you, then the lasting blame of my father shall be mine</q> <verse eId="Gen.44.32"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.44.33" sID="Gen.44.33"/> Well then, do let your servant remain instead of the boy as a slave
         to my lord, and
         <milestone type="pb" n="53"/> 
         let the boy return with his brothers. <verse eId="Gen.44.33"/>
        <verse osisID="Gen.44.34" sID="Gen.44.34"/> How can I go to my father without the boy? Never may I witness the
         woe that would overwhelm my father!</q> <verse eId="Gen.44.34"/>
       </hi>
      </p>
     <chapter eId="Gen.44"/>
     <chapter osisId="Gen.45" sId="Gen.45"/>
      <p>
       <verse osisID="Gen.45.1" sID="Gen.45.1"/>[Joseph could control himself no longer before all the bystanders; he
        called out, <q>Make every man withdraw.</q> No one was present when Joseph made himself known to his brothers, <verse eId="Gen.45.1"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.45.2" sID="Gen.45.2"/> although he wept so loud that the Egyptians heard of it and the
       Pharaoh’s household heard of it. <verse eId="Gen.45.2"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.45.3" sID="Gen.45.3"/> Joseph said to his brothers, <q>I am Joseph. Is my father still
        alive?</q> His brothers were so dismayed that they could not answer.] <verse eId="Gen.45.3"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.45.4" sID="Gen.45.4"/> So Joseph said to his brothers, <q>Pray come near.</q> When they came
        near, he said, <q>I am your brother Joseph whom you sold into Egypt. <verse eId="Gen.45.4"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.45.5" sID="Gen.45.5"/> [Now be not vexed or angry with yourselves that you sold me here, for
        God sent me in front of you to be a preserver of life: <verse eId="Gen.45.5"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.45.6" sID="Gen.45.6"/> the famine has been two years in the land, and there are still five
        years when there will be neither ploughing nor harvest. <verse eId="Gen.45.6"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.45.7" sID="Gen.45.7"/> God sent me in front of you to preserve your posterity alive on earth
        and make you survive to become a great company. <verse eId="Gen.45.7"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.45.8" sID="Gen.45.8"/> So it was not you but God who sent me here, and God has made me the
        Pharaoh’s prime minister, head of all his palace, and governor of all the land of Egypt. <verse eId="Gen.45.8"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.45.9" sID="Gen.45.9"/> Hasten back to my father and give him this message from his son
        Joseph: <q>God has made me lord over all Egypt; come down to me at once, <verse eId="Gen.45.9"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.45.10" sID="Gen.45.10"/> you shall stay in the land of Goshen and you shall live near me, you
        and your sons and your grandsons, your flocks and herds and all that you possess; <verse eId="Gen.45.10"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.45.11" sID="Gen.45.11"/> I will provide for you here, lest you become poor, you and your
        household and all that you possess; <verse eId="Gen.45.11"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.45.12" sID="Gen.45.12"/> for there are still five years of famine.</q> You can see for
        yourselves, my brother Benjamin can see for himself, that it is I who am speaking to you.] <verse eId="Gen.45.12"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.45.13" sID="Gen.45.13"/> You must tell my father all about my splendid position in Egypt and
        about all you have seen; make haste and bring my father here.</q> <verse eId="Gen.45.13"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.45.14" sID="Gen.45.14"/> Then he fell on the neck of his brother Benjamin and wept, and
        Benjamin wept on his neck. <verse eId="Gen.45.14"/>
       <verse osisID="Gen.45.15" sID="Gen.45.15"/> [Then he kissed all his brothers and wept as he embraced them; after
        which his brothers talked with him. <verse eId="Gen.45.15"/>
      </p>
     <chapter eId="Gen.45"/>
   </div>
