   <div type="book" osisID="Josh">
    <milestone type="pb" n="242"/>
    <chapter osisID="Josh.1" sID="Josh.1"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Josh.1.1" osisID="Josh.1.1"/>Now, after the death of Moses the servant of the Eter­nal, the Eternal said to
       Joshua the son of Nun, the attendant of Moses,
      <verse eID="Josh.1.1"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.1.2" osisID="Josh.1.2"/>
       <q>Moses my servant is dead; come, cross the Jordan here, you and all this people, into the land which I assign to them,
       to the Israelites. <verse eID="Josh.1.2"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.1.3" osisID="Josh.1.3"/> Every foot of ground you tread I assign to you, as I promised Moses; <verse eID="Josh.1.3"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.1.4" osisID="Josh.1.4"/> your frontier shall stretch from the desert to Leb­anon yonder, from the great
       River, the river Euphrates, over all the land of the Hittites, to the great Mediterranean Sea westward. <verse eID="Josh.1.4"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.1.5" osisID="Josh.1.5"/> Not a man shall be able to hold his own against you all the days of your life;
       as I was with Moses, so I will be with you; I will never fail you nor forsake you. <verse eID="Josh.1.5"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.1.6" osisID="Josh.1.6"/> Be strong, be brave, for you shall put this people in possession of the land
       which I swore to their fathers that I would give them. <verse eID="Josh.1.6"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.1.7" osisID="Josh.1.7"/> Only be strong and brave, mindful to carry out all your orders from my servant
       Moses, turning neither to the right nor to the left, so that you may succeed wherever you go. <verse eID="Josh.1.7"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.1.8" osisID="Josh.1.8"/> This law­book you shall never cease to have on your lips; you must pore over it
       day and night, that you may be mindful to carry out all that is written in it, for so shall you make your way prosperous,
       so shall you succeed. <verse eID="Josh.1.8"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.1.9" osisID="Josh.1.9"/> These are my orders: be firm and brave, never be daunted or dismayed, for the
       Eternal your God is with you wherever you go.</q>
      <verse eID="Josh.1.9"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Josh.1.10" osisID="Josh.1.10"/> Then Joshua ordered the officers of the nation <verse eID="Josh.1.10"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.1.11" osisID="Josh.1.11"/> to go through the camp and com­mand the people to <q>Prepare food, for within
       three days you are going to cross the Jordan here and enter into possession of the land which the Eternal your God assigns
       you for your very own.</q> <verse eID="Josh.1.11"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.1.12" osisID="Josh.1.12"/> Joshua also said to the Reubenites and the Gadites and the half-clan of
       Manasseh, <verse eID="Josh.1.12"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.1.13" osisID="Josh.1.13"/> <q>Remember what Moses the servant of the Eternal com­manded you when he told
       you that the Eternal your God would settle you here and give you this region. <verse eID="Josh.1.13"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.1.14" osisID="Josh.1.14"/> Your wives, your children, and your cattle shall re­main in this land which
       Moses assigned you east of the Jordan, but you must march across un­der arms in front of your kins­men, every fighting man
       among you, to assist them, <verse eID="Josh.1.14"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.1.15" osisID="Josh.1.15"/> till the Eternal settles your kinsmen like yourselves, till they get posses­sion
       of the land which the Eter­nal your God assigns to them; then you may return to your own region and occupy the land
       assigned you by Moses the servant of the Eternal on the eastern bank of the Jordan.</q> <verse eID="Josh.1.15"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.1.16" osisID="Josh.1.16"/> They answered Joshua, <q>Whatever you command us we will do, and wherever you
       send us we will go. <verse eID="Josh.1.16"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.1.17" osisID="Josh.1.17"/> As we obeyed Moses in everything, so we will obey you; only may the Eternal
       your God be with you as he was with Moses! <verse eID="Josh.1.17"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.1.18" osisID="Josh.1.18"/> Whoever rebels against your orders and will not listen to what you say by way
       of command to him, that man shall be put to death. Only be firm and brave.</q> <verse eID="Josh.1.18"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eID="Josh.1"/>
    <chapter osisID="Josh.2" sID="Josh.2"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Josh.2.1" osisID="Josh.2.1"/> From Shittim Joshua sent two men secretly as spies to explore the country and
       <milestone type="pb" n="243"/>
       specially Jericho. When they ar­rived, they went into the house of a harlot called Rahab and stayed there. <verse eID="Josh.2.1"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.2.2" osisID="Josh.2.2"/> The king of Jericho was told that two men of Israel had come in that night to
       find out about the country; <verse eID="Josh.2.2"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.2.3" osisID="Josh.2.3"/> so he sent a message to Rahab to <q>Bring out the two men who have come to you,
       who have entered your house, for they are here to find out all about the country.</q> <verse eID="Josh.2.3"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.2.4" osisID="Josh.2.4"/> The woman, who had taken the men and hid them, said, <q>Yes, the men did come to
       me, but I did not know where they came from, <verse eID="Josh.2.4"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.2.5" osisID="Josh.2.5"/> and just about the hour for shutting the town-gate, when it was dark, the men
       went off. Where they went, I do not know. Quick, pursue them, for you will overtake them.</q> <verse eID="Josh.2.5"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.2.6" osisID="Josh.2.6"/> Now she had taken them up to the roof and hidden them under some stalks of flax
       which she had arranged on the roof. <verse eID="Josh.2.6"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.2.7" osisID="Josh.2.7"/> The pursuers went by the road to the Jordan, as far as the fords, and as soon as
       they left the town the gate was shut. <verse eID="Josh.2.7"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Josh.2.8" osisID="Josh.2.8"/> The two men had not lain down, before the woman came to them on the roof <verse eID="Josh.2.8"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.2.9" osisID="Josh.2.9"/> and said, <q>I know that the Eternal has given you this country, and how the
       terror of you has fallen upon us, till all the natives are quivering before you. <verse eID="Josh.2.9"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.2.10" osisID="Josh.2.10"/> For we have heard how the Eternal dried up the water of the Reed Sea before
       you, when you left Egypt, and how you treated the two Amorite kings on the east of the Jordan, Sihon and Og, whom you
       wiped off the earth. <verse eID="Josh.2.10"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.2.11" osisID="Josh.2.11"/> As soon as we heard it, our hearts quivered and everyone became utterly
       dispirited be­cause of you, for the Eternal your God is God in heaven above and on the earth below. <verse eID="Josh.2.11"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.2.12" osisID="Josh.2.12"/> Now then, since I have dealt kindly with you, pray swear to me by the Eternal
       that you will deal kindly with my family, and give me a sure sign of it; <verse eID="Josh.2.12"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.2.13" osisID="Josh.2.13"/> swear that you will spare the lives of my father and my mother and my brothers
       and my sisters and all they have, saving us from death.</q> <verse eID="Josh.2.13"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.2.14" osisID="Josh.2.14"/> The men re­plied, <q>Our lives for yours--only you must not breathe a word
       about our errand; then we will deal kindly and honestly with you when the Eternal gives us the country.</q> <verse eID="Josh.2.14"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.2.17" osisID="Josh.2.17"/> The men told her, The men told her, <q>We will not be bound by this oath to
       you, which you have made us swear, <verse eID="Josh.2.17"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.2.18" osisID="Josh.2.18"/> unless, when we enter the country, you tie this cord of scarlet thread outside
       the win­dow through which you let us down. You must gather your father and mother and brothers and all your family
       inside your house; <verse eID="Josh.2.18"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.2.19" osisID="Josh.2.19"/> anyone who crosses the door of your house into the street, his blood be on his
       own head, we are not to blame; but if a hand is laid on anyone in­side the house, then his blood be on our head! <verse eID="Josh.2.19"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.2.20" osisID="Josh.2.20"/> But remember, if you breathe a word about our errand, we will not be bound by
       the oath you have made us swear.</q> <verse eID="Josh.2.20"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.2.21" osisID="Josh.2.21"/> <q>As you say,</q> answered the woman, <q>so be it.</q>
      <verse eID="Josh.2.21"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.2.15" osisID="Josh.2.15"/> Then she lowered them by a rope out of the window, for her house was on the
       town-wall; she stayed on the town-wall. <verse eID="Josh.2.15"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.2.16" osisID="Josh.2.16"/> She told them, <q>Get away to the hills, lest the pursuers come across you;
       hide yourselves there for three days till the pur­suers return, and then make your retreat.</q>
      <verse eID="Josh.2.16"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.2.21" osisID="Josh.2.21"/> So away they went, while she tied the scarlet cord to the window. <verse eID="Josh.2.21"/>
      <milestone type="pb" n="243"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.2.22" osisID="Josh.2.22"/> They went into the hills and stayed there for three days, till the pursuers
       returned (the pur­suers looked for them all along the road and could not find them). <verse eID="Josh.2.22"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.2.23" osisID="Josh.2.23"/> Then the two men came down from the hills and crossed over to Joshua the son
       of Nun, telling him all that had befallen them; <verse eID="Josh.2.23"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.2.24" osisID="Josh.2.24"/> they said to Joshua, <q>The Eternal has put all the country into our hands.
       The natives are all quivering before us!</q> <verse eID="Josh.2.24"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eID="Josh.2"/>
   </div>