   <div type="book" osisID="Josh">
    <milestone type="pb" n="242"/>
    <chapter osisID="Josh.1" sID="Josh.1"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Josh.1.1" osisID="Josh.1.1"/>Now, after the death of Moses the servant of the Eter­nal, the Eternal said to
       Joshua the son of Nun, the attendant of Moses,
      <verse eID="Josh.1.1"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.1.2" osisID="Josh.1.2"/>
       <q>Moses my servant is dead; come, cross the Jordan here, you and all this people, into the land which I assign to them,
       to the Israelites. <verse eID="Josh.1.2"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.1.3" osisID="Josh.1.3"/> Every foot of ground you tread I assign to you, as I promised Moses; <verse eID="Josh.1.3"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.1.4" osisID="Josh.1.4"/> your frontier shall stretch from the desert to Leb­anon yonder, from the great
       River, the river Euphrates, over all the land of the Hittites, to the great Mediterranean Sea westward. <verse eID="Josh.1.4"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.1.5" osisID="Josh.1.5"/> Not a man shall be able to hold his own against you all the days of your life;
       as I was with Moses, so I will be with you; I will never fail you nor forsake you. <verse eID="Josh.1.5"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.1.6" osisID="Josh.1.6"/> Be strong, be brave, for you shall put this people in possession of the land
       which I swore to their fathers that I would give them. <verse eID="Josh.1.6"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.1.7" osisID="Josh.1.7"/> Only be strong and brave, mindful to carry out all your orders from my servant
       Moses, turning neither to the right nor to the left, so that you may succeed wherever you go. <verse eID="Josh.1.7"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.1.8" osisID="Josh.1.8"/> This law­book you shall never cease to have on your lips; you must pore over it
       day and night, that you may be mindful to carry out all that is written in it, for so shall you make your way prosperous,
       so shall you succeed. <verse eID="Josh.1.8"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.1.9" osisID="Josh.1.9"/> These are my orders: be firm and brave, never be daunted or dismayed, for the
       Eternal your God is with you wherever you go.</q>
      <verse eID="Josh.1.9"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Josh.1.10" osisID="Josh.1.10"/> Then Joshua ordered the officers of the nation <verse eID="Josh.1.10"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.1.11" osisID="Josh.1.11"/> to go through the camp and com­mand the people to <q>Prepare food, for within
       three days you are going to cross the Jordan here and enter into possession of the land which the Eternal your God assigns
       you for your very own.</q> <verse eID="Josh.1.11"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.1.12" osisID="Josh.1.12"/> Joshua also said to the Reubenites and the Gadites and the half-clan of
       Manasseh, <verse eID="Josh.1.12"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.1.13" osisID="Josh.1.13"/> <q>Remember what Moses the servant of the Eternal com­manded you when he told
       you that the Eternal your God would settle you here and give you this region. <verse eID="Josh.1.13"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.1.14" osisID="Josh.1.14"/> Your wives, your children, and your cattle shall re­main in this land which
       Moses assigned you east of the Jordan, but you must march across un­der arms in front of your kins­men, every fighting man
       among you, to assist them, <verse eID="Josh.1.14"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.1.15" osisID="Josh.1.15"/> till the Eternal settles your kinsmen like yourselves, till they get posses­sion
       of the land which the Eter­nal your God assigns to them; then you may return to your own region and occupy the land
       assigned you by Moses the servant of the Eternal on the eastern bank of the Jordan.</q> <verse eID="Josh.1.15"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.1.16" osisID="Josh.1.16"/> They answered Joshua, <q>Whatever you command us we will do, and wherever you
       send us we will go. <verse eID="Josh.1.16"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.1.17" osisID="Josh.1.17"/> As we obeyed Moses in everything, so we will obey you; only may the Eternal
       your God be with you as he was with Moses! <verse eID="Josh.1.17"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.1.18" osisID="Josh.1.18"/> Whoever rebels against your orders and will not listen to what you say by way
       of command to him, that man shall be put to death. Only be firm and brave.</q> <verse eID="Josh.1.18"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eID="Josh.1"/>
   </div>