   <div type="book" osisID="Josh">
    <milestone type="pb" n="242"/>
    <chapter osisID="Josh.1" sID="Josh.1"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Josh.1.1" osisID="Josh.1.1"/>Now, after the death of Moses the servant of the Eter­nal, the Eternal said to
       Joshua the son of Nun, the attendant of Moses,
      <verse eID="Josh.1.1"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.1.2" osisID="Josh.1.2"/>
       <q>Moses my servant is dead; come, cross the Jordan here, you and all this people, into the land which I assign to them,
       to the Israelites. <verse eID="Josh.1.2"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.1.3" osisID="Josh.1.3"/> Every foot of ground you tread I assign to you, as I promised Moses; <verse eID="Josh.1.3"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.1.4" osisID="Josh.1.4"/> your frontier shall stretch from the desert to Leb­anon yonder, from the great
       River, the river Euphrates, over all the land of the Hittites, to the great Mediterranean Sea westward. <verse eID="Josh.1.4"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.1.5" osisID="Josh.1.5"/> Not a man shall be able to hold his own against you all the days of your life;
       as I was with Moses, so I will be with you; I will never fail you nor forsake you. <verse eID="Josh.1.5"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.1.6" osisID="Josh.1.6"/> Be strong, be brave, for you shall put this people in possession of the land
       which I swore to their fathers that I would give them. <verse eID="Josh.1.6"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.1.7" osisID="Josh.1.7"/> Only be strong and brave, mindful to carry out all your orders from my servant
       Moses, turning neither to the right nor to the left, so that you may succeed wherever you go. <verse eID="Josh.1.7"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.1.8" osisID="Josh.1.8"/> This law­book you shall never cease to have on your lips; you must pore over it
       day and night, that you may be mindful to carry out all that is written in it, for so shall you make your way prosperous,
       so shall you succeed. <verse eID="Josh.1.8"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.1.9" osisID="Josh.1.9"/> These are my orders: be firm and brave, never be daunted or dismayed, for the
       Eternal your God is with you wherever you go.</q>
      <verse eID="Josh.1.9"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Josh.1.10" osisID="Josh.1.10"/> Then Joshua ordered the officers of the nation <verse eID="Josh.1.10"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.1.11" osisID="Josh.1.11"/> to go through the camp and com­mand the people to <q>Prepare food, for within
       three days you are going to cross the Jordan here and enter into possession of the land which the Eternal your God assigns
       you for your very own.</q> <verse eID="Josh.1.11"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.1.12" osisID="Josh.1.12"/> Joshua also said to the Reubenites and the Gadites and the half-clan of
       Manasseh, <verse eID="Josh.1.12"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.1.13" osisID="Josh.1.13"/> <q>Remember what Moses the servant of the Eternal com­manded you when he told
       you that the Eternal your God would settle you here and give you this region. <verse eID="Josh.1.13"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.1.14" osisID="Josh.1.14"/> Your wives, your children, and your cattle shall re­main in this land which
       Moses assigned you east of the Jordan, but you must march across un­der arms in front of your kins­men, every fighting man
       among you, to assist them, <verse eID="Josh.1.14"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.1.15" osisID="Josh.1.15"/> till the Eternal settles your kinsmen like yourselves, till they get posses­sion
       of the land which the Eter­nal your God assigns to them; then you may return to your own region and occupy the land
       assigned you by Moses the servant of the Eternal on the eastern bank of the Jordan.</q> <verse eID="Josh.1.15"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.1.16" osisID="Josh.1.16"/> They answered Joshua, <q>Whatever you command us we will do, and wherever you
       send us we will go. <verse eID="Josh.1.16"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.1.17" osisID="Josh.1.17"/> As we obeyed Moses in everything, so we will obey you; only may the Eternal
       your God be with you as he was with Moses! <verse eID="Josh.1.17"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.1.18" osisID="Josh.1.18"/> Whoever rebels against your orders and will not listen to what you say by way
       of command to him, that man shall be put to death. Only be firm and brave.</q> <verse eID="Josh.1.18"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eID="Josh.1"/>
    <chapter osisID="Josh.2" sID="Josh.2"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Josh.2.1" osisID="Josh.2.1"/> From Shittim Joshua sent two men secretly as spies to explore the country and
       <milestone type="pb" n="243"/>
       specially Jericho. When they ar­rived, they went into the house of a harlot called Rahab and stayed there. <verse eID="Josh.2.1"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.2.2" osisID="Josh.2.2"/> The king of Jericho was told that two men of Israel had come in that night to
       find out about the country; <verse eID="Josh.2.2"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.2.3" osisID="Josh.2.3"/> so he sent a message to Rahab to <q>Bring out the two men who have come to you,
       who have entered your house, for they are here to find out all about the country.</q> <verse eID="Josh.2.3"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.2.4" osisID="Josh.2.4"/> The woman, who had taken the men and hid them, said, <q>Yes, the men did come to
       me, but I did not know where they came from, <verse eID="Josh.2.4"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.2.5" osisID="Josh.2.5"/> and just about the hour for shutting the town-gate, when it was dark, the men
       went off. Where they went, I do not know. Quick, pursue them, for you will overtake them.</q> <verse eID="Josh.2.5"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.2.6" osisID="Josh.2.6"/> Now she had taken them up to the roof and hidden them under some stalks of flax
       which she had arranged on the roof. <verse eID="Josh.2.6"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.2.7" osisID="Josh.2.7"/> The pursuers went by the road to the Jordan, as far as the fords, and as soon as
       they left the town the gate was shut. <verse eID="Josh.2.7"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Josh.2.8" osisID="Josh.2.8"/> The two men had not lain down, before the woman came to them on the roof <verse eID="Josh.2.8"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.2.9" osisID="Josh.2.9"/> and said, <q>I know that the Eternal has given you this country, and how the
       terror of you has fallen upon us, till all the natives are quivering before you. <verse eID="Josh.2.9"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.2.10" osisID="Josh.2.10"/> For we have heard how the Eternal dried up the water of the Reed Sea before
       you, when you left Egypt, and how you treated the two Amorite kings on the east of the Jordan, Sihon and Og, whom you
       wiped off the earth. <verse eID="Josh.2.10"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.2.11" osisID="Josh.2.11"/> As soon as we heard it, our hearts quivered and everyone became utterly
       dispirited be­cause of you, for the Eternal your God is God in heaven above and on the earth below. <verse eID="Josh.2.11"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.2.12" osisID="Josh.2.12"/> Now then, since I have dealt kindly with you, pray swear to me by the Eternal
       that you will deal kindly with my family, and give me a sure sign of it; <verse eID="Josh.2.12"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.2.13" osisID="Josh.2.13"/> swear that you will spare the lives of my father and my mother and my brothers
       and my sisters and all they have, saving us from death.</q> <verse eID="Josh.2.13"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.2.14" osisID="Josh.2.14"/> The men re­plied, <q>Our lives for yours--only you must not breathe a word
       about our errand; then we will deal kindly and honestly with you when the Eternal gives us the country.</q> <verse eID="Josh.2.14"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.2.17" osisID="Josh.2.17"/> The men told her, The men told her, <q>We will not be bound by this oath to
       you, which you have made us swear, <verse eID="Josh.2.17"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.2.18" osisID="Josh.2.18"/> unless, when we enter the country, you tie this cord of scarlet thread outside
       the win­dow through which you let us down. You must gather your father and mother and brothers and all your family
       inside your house; <verse eID="Josh.2.18"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.2.19" osisID="Josh.2.19"/> anyone who crosses the door of your house into the street, his blood be on his
       own head, we are not to blame; but if a hand is laid on anyone in­side the house, then his blood be on our head! <verse eID="Josh.2.19"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.2.20" osisID="Josh.2.20"/> But remember, if you breathe a word about our errand, we will not be bound by
       the oath you have made us swear.</q> <verse eID="Josh.2.20"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.2.21" osisID="Josh.2.21"/> <q>As you say,</q> answered the woman, <q>so be it.</q>
      <verse eID="Josh.2.21"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.2.15" osisID="Josh.2.15"/> Then she lowered them by a rope out of the window, for her house was on the
       town-wall; she stayed on the town-wall. <verse eID="Josh.2.15"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.2.16" osisID="Josh.2.16"/> She told them, <q>Get away to the hills, lest the pursuers come across you;
       hide yourselves there for three days till the pur­suers return, and then make your retreat.</q>
      <verse eID="Josh.2.16"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.2.21" osisID="Josh.2.21"/> So away they went, while she tied the scarlet cord to the window. <verse eID="Josh.2.21"/>
      <milestone type="pb" n="243"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.2.22" osisID="Josh.2.22"/> They went into the hills and stayed there for three days, till the pursuers
       returned (the pur­suers looked for them all along the road and could not find them). <verse eID="Josh.2.22"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.2.23" osisID="Josh.2.23"/> Then the two men came down from the hills and crossed over to Joshua the son
       of Nun, telling him all that had befallen them; <verse eID="Josh.2.23"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.2.24" osisID="Josh.2.24"/> they said to Joshua, <q>The Eternal has put all the country into our hands.
       The natives are all quivering before us!</q> <verse eID="Josh.2.24"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eID="Josh.2"/>
    <chapter osisID="Josh.3" sID="Josh.3"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Josh.3.1" osisID="Josh.3.1"/>In the morning Joshua rose; he and all the Israelites set out from Shittim and
       reached the Jordan, where they passed the night before they crossed over. <verse eID="Josh.3.1"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.3.2" osisID="Josh.3.2"/> Three days afterwards the officers went through the camp <verse eID="Josh.3.2"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.3.3" osisID="Josh.3.3"/> and gave this order to the nation: <q>When you see the ark of the compact of the
       Eter­nal your God being carried by the priestly Levites, then set out and follow it, <verse eID="Josh.3.3"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.3.4" osisID="Josh.3.4"/> so that you may learn the ford by which you are to cross; for you have never
       crossed here before. Only, you must not come close to the ark; between it and you there must be a space kept of one
       thousand yards.</q> <verse eID="Josh.3.4"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.3.5" osisID="Josh.3.5"/> Then Joshua said to the people, <q>Consecrate yourselves, for to-morrow the
       Eternal will do wonders among you.</q> <verse eID="Josh.3.5"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.3.6" osisID="Josh.3.6"/> To the priests he said, <q>Lift the ark of the compact and go in front of the
       people.</q> So they lifted the ark of the compact and went in front of the people. <verse eID="Josh.3.6"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Josh.3.7" osisID="Josh.3.7"/> The Eternal said to Joshua, <q>This day I begin to exalt you in the sight of
       Israel, to let them see that as I was with Moses so I will be with you. <verse eID="Josh.3.7"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.3.8" osisID="Josh.3.8"/> Order the priests who are carrying the ark of the compact to stand still in the
       Jordan as soon as they reach the edge of the water.</q> <verse eID="Josh.3.8"/>
    <chapter eID="Josh.3"/>
    <chapter osisID="Josh.4" sID="Josh.4"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.4.1" osisID="Josh.4.1"/> The Eternal also said to Joshua, <verse eID="Josh.4.1"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.4.2" osisID="Josh.4.2"/> <q>Take twelve men from the nation, a man from each clan,<verse eID="Josh.4.2"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.4.3" osisID="Josh.4.3"/> and order them to take twelve stones out of the Jordan from the spot where the
       feet of the priest stood firm; they must carry these stones across and place them on the spot where you spend the night.</q>
      <verse eID="Josh.4.3"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eID="Josh.4"/>
    <chapter osisID="Josh.3" sID="Josh.3"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Josh.3.9" osisID="Josh.3.9"/> Then Joshua bade the Israelites come and listen to the words of the Eternal,
       their God. <verse eID="Josh.3.9"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.3.10" osisID="Josh.3.10"/> Joshua said, <q>This is to let you see that the living God is among you, and
       that he will without fail evict before you the Canaanite and the Hittite and the Hivite and the Perizzite and the
       Girgashite and the Amorite and the Jebusite. <verse eID="Josh.3.10"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.3.11" osisID="Josh.3.11"/> See, the ark of the compact of the Lord of all the earth is crossing the
       Jordan in front of you. <verse eID="Josh.3.11"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.3.12" osisID="Josh.3.12"/> Now choose twelve men from the clans of Israel, a man from each clan. <verse eID="Josh.3.12"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.3.13" osisID="Josh.3.13"/> As soon as the soles of the feet of the priests who carry the ark of the
       compact of the Eternal, the Lord of all the earth, rest in the water of the Jordan, the waters of the Jordan shall be
       stopped; the waters which are flowing down, they shall be dammed up.</q> <verse eID="Josh.3.13"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.3.14" osisID="Josh.3.14"/> When the people left their tents to cross the Jordan, headed by the priests
       who carried the ark of the compact, <verse eID="Josh.3.14"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.3.15" osisID="Josh.3.15"/> as soon as the bearers reached the Jordan and the feet of the priests dipped
       in the water at the edge (for the Jordan overflows its banks all the time of harvest), <verse eID="Josh.3.15"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.3.16" osisID="Josh.3.16"/> the waters that flow down stopped and were dammed up at a distance, at Adamah
       (a town beside Zartan), while the waters that flow away to the sea of the Arabah (the Salt Sea) were cut off and
       <milestone type="pb" n="244"/>
       failed. In this way the people crossed, opposite Jericho. <verse eID="Josh.3.16"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.3.17" osisID="Josh.3.17"/> The priests who carried the ark of the compact of the Eternal stood still on
       dry ground in the middle of the Jordan, and all Israel crossed on dry ground until the whole nation had finished
       crossing. <verse eID="Josh.3.17"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eID="Josh.3"/>
    <chapter osisID="Josh.4" sID="Josh.4"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Josh.4.1" osisID="Josh.4.1"/>When the whole nation had finished crossing the Jordan,<verse eID="Josh.4.1"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.4.4" osisID="Josh.4.4"/> Joshua called the twelve men of Israel whom he had ready, one from each of the
       clans; <verse eID="Josh.4.4"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.4.5" osisID="Josh.4.5"/> Joshua said to them, <q>Cross in front of the ark of the Eternal your God
       through the Jordan, each of you taking a stone on his shoulder, one for each of the clans of Israel. <verse eID="Josh.4.5"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.4.6" osisID="Josh.4.6"/> They are to be a sign for your nation. When your children in after days ask what
       is the meaning of these stones, <verse eID="Josh.4.6"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.4.7" osisID="Josh.4.7"/> you shall tell them it was because the waters of the Jordan were stopped be­fore
       the ark of the compact of the Eternal, stopped when it crossed the Jordan; these stones shall be a memorial for Israel
       for all time.</q> <verse eID="Josh.4.7"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.4.8" osisID="Josh.4.8"/> The Israelites did as Joshua gave orders; they lifted twelve stones out of the
       Jordan, as the Eternal had com­manded Joshua, one for each of the clans of Israel, and carried them over along with them
       to the spot where they spent the night, laying them down there. <verse eID="Josh.4.8"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.4.9" osisID="Josh.4.9"/> [[Joshua set up twelve stones in the middle of the Jordan on the spot where the
       feet of the priests who carried the ark of the compact had stood; they are there to this day. <verse eID="Josh.4.9"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.4.10" osisID="Josh.4.10"/> For the priests who carried the ark stood in the middle of the Jordan till all
       was finished that Joshua was told by the Eternal to enjoin upon the people, all that Moses had commanded Joshua.]] The
       people hurried over, <verse eID="Josh.4.10"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.4.11" osisID="Josh.4.11"/> and when all the people had finished crossing, the ark passed over, the
       priests advancing to the front of the people. <verse eID="Josh.4.11"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.4.12" osisID="Josh.4.12"/> The Reubenites, the Gadites, and the half clan of Manasseh passed across under
       arms in front of the Israelites, as Moses had ordered them, <verse eID="Josh.4.12"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.4.13" osisID="Josh.4.13"/> about forty thousand men equipped for war, crossing under the eyes of the
       Eternal to the steppes of Jericho for battle. <verse eID="Josh.4.13"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.4.14" osisID="Josh.4.14"/> The Eternal exalted Joshua that day in the eyes of all Israel; they stood in
       awe of him as they had stood in awe of Moses all the days of his life. <verse eID="Josh.4.14"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Josh.4.15" osisID="Josh.4.15"/> Then the Eternal said to Joshua, <verse eID="Josh.4.15"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.4.16" osisID="Josh.4.16"/><q> Order the priests who carry the ark of the Presence to step up from the
       Jordan.</q> <verse eID="Josh.4.16"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.4.17" osisID="Josh.4.17"/> Joshua ordered the priests to step up from the Jordan, <verse eID="Josh.4.17"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.4.18" osisID="Josh.4.18"/> and when the priests who carried the ark of the compact of the Eternal came up
       from the Jor­dan, when the soles of the feet of the priests were lifted on to the dry ground, the waters of the Jordan
       flowed back into their place and overflowed their banks as before. <verse eID="Josh.4.18"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.4.19" osisID="Josh.4.19"/> It was on the tenth day of the first month that the people came up from the
       Jordan and encamped at Gilgal on the eastern side of Jericho. <verse eID="Josh.4.19"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.4.20" osisID="Josh.4.20"/> These twelve stones which they took out of the Jordan were set up by Joshua at
       Gilgal. <verse eID="Josh.4.20"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.4.21" osisID="Josh.4.21"/> He said to the Israelites, <q>When your children in after days ask their
       fathers what these stones mean, <verse eID="Josh.4.21"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.4.22" osisID="Josh.4.22"/> you shall tell your children that <q>Israel crossed the Jordan here on dry
       ground.</q>
      <verse eID="Josh.4.22"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.4.23" osisID="Josh.4.23"/> For the Eternal your God dried up the waters of the Jordan before you till you
       had passed across, as the Eternal your God had done
       <milestone type="pb" n="246"/>
       to the Reed Sea, which he also dried up before us till we passed across it--<verse eID="Josh.4.23"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.4.24" osisID="Josh.4.24"/> to let all the nations on earth know how strong is the hand of the Eternal,
       that they may stand in awe of the Eternal your God for all time.</q> <verse eID="Josh.4.24"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eID="Josh.4"/>
    <chapter osisID="Josh.5" sID="Josh.5"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Josh.5.1" osisID="Josh.5.1"/>Now when all the Amorite kings west of the Jordan and all the Canaanite kings by
       the Mediterranean heard how the Eternal had dried up the waters of the Jordan in front of the Israelites till they had
       got across, their hearts quivered and they were all dispirited, on account of the Israelites. <verse eID="Josh.5.1"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Josh.5.2" osisID="Josh.5.2"/> It was then that the Eternal said to Joshua, <q>Make flint knives and
       circumcise the Israelites once more.</q> <verse eID="Josh.5.2"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.5.3" osisID="Josh.5.3"/> So Joshua made flint knives and cir­cumcised the Israelites at the Hill of
       Foreskins. <verse eID="Josh.5.3"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.5.9" osisID="Josh.5.9"/> Then said the Eternal to Joshua, <q>And now I have rolled off you the scorn of
       the Egyptians.</q> Hence the name of the spot was called Rollstone (Gilgal), and is so called to this day. <verse eID="Josh.5.9"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Josh.5.4" osisID="Josh.5.4"/> [[Joshua circumcised them for this reason. All who had left Egypt, all the male
       warriors, had died during the journey through the desert after leaving Egypt. <verse eID="Josh.5.4"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.5.5" osisID="Josh.5.5"/> These who had left Egypt were circumcised, but none of the people who had been
       born in the desert after leaving Egypt had been circumcised. <verse eID="Josh.5.5"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.5.6" osisID="Josh.5.6"/> For forty years the Israelites had journeyed in the desert until the whole
       nation of war­riors who had left Egypt had perished, because they would not listen to what the Eternal said, and because
       the Eternal had sworn to them that he would not let them see the land which the Eternal had sworn to their fathers that
       he would give to us, a land abounding in milk and honey. <verse eID="Josh.5.6"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.5.7" osisID="Josh.5.7"/> So their children, whom the Eternal raised up instead of them, were circum­cised
       by Joshua, since they had never been circumcised from time to time. <verse eID="Josh.5.7"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.5.8" osisID="Josh.5.8"/> After the circumcising was over, the whole na­tion remained where they were in
       the camp till they had re­covered.]] <verse eID="Josh.5.8"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Josh.5.10" osisID="Josh.5.10"/> When the Israelites were in camp at Gilgal, they kept the passover on the
       evening of the fourteenth day of the month, on the steppes of Jericho. <verse eID="Josh.5.10"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.5.11" osisID="Josh.5.11"/> The day after the passover, they ate some of the produce of the land,
       unleavened cakes and roasted grain. <verse eID="Josh.5.11"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.5.12" osisID="Josh.5.12"/> And that very day the manna ceased, once they ate the produce of the land; the
       Israelites no longer had manna, but ate hereafter the food of the land of Canaan. <verse eID="Josh.5.12"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eID="Josh.5"/>
    <chapter osisID="Josh.6" sID="Josh.6"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Josh.6.1" osisID="Josh.6.1"/>Now Jericho had shut its gates against the Israelites; no one left the town, and
       no one entered it.
      <verse eID="Josh.6.1"/>
    <chapter eID="Josh.6"/>
    <chapter osisID="Josh.5" sID="Josh.5"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.5.13" osisID="Josh.5.13"/> Joshua was one day near Jericho, when he raised his eyes and saw a man
       standing before him, holding a drawn sword. Joshua went up to him and said, <q>Are you for us, or are you for our
       enemies?</q>
      <verse eID="Josh.5.13"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.5.14" osisID="Josh.5.14"/> <q>No,</q> he answered, <q>I am here as the captain of the host of the
       Eternal.</q> Then Joshua fell on his face to the ground and wor­shipped, saying, <q>And what has my Lord to say to his
       servant?</q> <verse eID="Josh.5.14"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.5.15" osisID="Josh.5.15"/> The captain of the host of the Eternal said to Joshua, <q>Re­move your sandals
       from your feet, for the place where you are standing is sacred.</q> Joshua did so. <verse eID="Josh.5.15"/>
    <chapter eID="Josh.5"/>
    <chapter osisID="Josh.6" sID="Josh.6"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.6.2" osisID="Josh.6.2"/> Then the Eternal said to Joshua, <q>I am putting Jericho into your hands, with
       its king and all its fighting
       <milestone type="pb" n="247"/>
       men. <verse eID="Josh.6.2"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.6.3" osisID="Josh.6.3"/> For six days you and all your men at arms shall march round the town once a day,
      <verse eID="Josh.6.3"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.6.4" osisID="Josh.6.4"/> with seven priests carrying seven rams' horns as trumpets in front of the ark.
      <verse eID="Josh.6.4"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.6.5" osisID="Josh.6.5"/> On the seventh day you shall march round the town seven times, and the priests
       shall blow a trumpet blast. As soon as they blow a long trumpet blast on the horns, whenever you hear the sound, then all
       the people must raise a mighty shout, and the wall of the town will fall down flat, till every man of you can march in,
       straight in front of him.</q> <verse eID="Josh.6.5"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.6.6" osisID="Josh.6.6"/> So Joshua the son of Nun called the priests and told them to lift the ark of the
       compact and let seven priests carry seven rams' horns as trumpets in front of the ark of the Eternal. <verse eID="Josh.6.6"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.6.7" osisID="Josh.6.7"/> Then he told the people, <q>Forward, march round the town, with the armed men in
       front of the ark of the Eternal; <verse eID="Josh.6.7"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.6.8" osisID="Josh.6.8"/> let the seven priests with the trumpets of rams' horns go ahead, in pres­ence of
       the Eternal, blowing the trumpets, and followed by the ark of the compact of the Eternal. <verse eID="Josh.6.8"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.6.9" osisID="Josh.6.9"/> Let the armed men go in front of the priests who blow the trumpets, and let the
       rear-guard follow the ark, the trumpets blowing.</q> <verse eID="Josh.6.9"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.6.10" osisID="Josh.6.10"/> To the people Joshua said, <q>You must not shout nor cry, you must not say a
       word, until I tell you to shout; then shout.</q> <verse eID="Josh.6.10"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.6.11" osisID="Josh.6.11"/> He had the ark of the Eternal car­ried round the town, going round it once;
       then all retired to the camp and passed the night there. <verse eID="Josh.6.11"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.6.12" osisID="Josh.6.12"/> Next morning Joshua rose, the priests lifted the ark of the Eternal, <verse eID="Josh.6.12"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.6.13" osisID="Josh.6.13"/> and the seven priests carrying the seven rams' horns as trumpets kept on in
       front of the ark of the Eternal, blowing a blast, preceded by the armed men, with the rear­guard after the ark, the
       trum­pets blowing as they went. <verse eID="Josh.6.13"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.6.14" osisID="Josh.6.14"/> On the second day they marched round the town once, and then retired to the
       camp. This they did for six days. <verse eID="Josh.6.14"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Josh.6.15" osisID="Josh.6.15"/> On the seventh day they rose at dawn and marched round the town seven times;
      this was the only day they marched seven times round it. <verse eID="Josh.6.15"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.6.16" osisID="Josh.6.16"/> The seventh time, when the priests blew their blast, Joshua said to the
       people, <q>Shout, for the Eternal has given you the town. <verse eID="Josh.6.16"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.6.17" osisID="Josh.6.17"/> It shall be doomed to destruction, the town and all in it; only Rahab the
       harlot shall be spared, she and all who are with her in her house, because she hid the mes­sengers whom we sent. <verse eID="Josh.6.17"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.6.18" osisID="Josh.6.18"/> As for you, hands off any of the doomed spoil, lest you desire it and take
       some of it! That would be the ruin and undoing of the camp of Israel. <verse eID="Josh.6.18"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.6.19" osisID="Josh.6.19"/> No, all the silver and gold and articles of bronze and iron are sacred to the
       Eternal and must come to the treasury of the Eternal.</q> <verse eID="Josh.6.19"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Josh.6.20" osisID="Josh.6.20"/> Then the people shouted, at the trumpet blast. And when the people heard the
       sound of the trumpet blast and raised a mighty shout, down the wall fell flat, till every man could march in, straight
       in front of him. <verse eID="Josh.6.20"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.6.21" osisID="Josh.6.21"/> In they marched and so they took the town, massacring all inside, men and
       women, old and young alike, oxen, sheep, and asses, giving no quarter. <verse eID="Josh.6.21"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.6.22" osisID="Josh.6.22"/> But Joshua said to the two men who had spied out the country, <q>Go to the
       harlot’s house and fetch the woman out, with all she has, as you swore to her.</q> <verse eID="Josh.6.22"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.6.23" osisID="Josh.6.23"/> So the young spies went and brought Rahab out, with her
       <milestone type="pb" n="248"/>
       father and mother and brothers and all she had, all her family; they placed them outside the camp of Israel. <verse eID="Josh.6.23"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.6.24" osisID="Josh.6.24"/> The town and all in it they burned up; only the silver and gold and all the
       arti­cles of bronze and iron they put into the treasury of the Eternal. <verse eID="Josh.6.24"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.6.25" osisID="Josh.6.25"/> Rahab the harlot and her family and all she had, Joshua spared; she lived
       among the Israelites, as do her descendants to this day, because she hid the mes­sengers whom Joshua sent to spy out
       Jericho. <verse eID="Josh.6.25"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.6.26" osisID="Josh.6.26"/> Joshua then laid this oath upon the people: <q>Cursed before the Eternal be
       the man who starts to rebuild this town of Jericho! At the cost of his oldest son shall he lay its foun­dation, and at the
       cost of his youngest son shall he erect its gates.</q> <verse eID="Josh.6.26"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.6.27" osisID="Josh.6.27"/> The Eternal was with Joshua, and the fame of him spread all over the land. <verse eID="Josh.6.27"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eID="Josh.6"/>
    <chapter osisID="Josh.7" sID="Josh.7"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Josh.7.1" osisID="Josh.7.1"/> But the Israelites broke faith with regard to doomed spoil; Achan the son of
       Karmi, the son of Zabdi, the son of Zerah, who belonged to the clan of Judah, took some of it, and so the anger of the
       Eternal blazed against the Israelites. <verse eID="Josh.7.1"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Josh.7.2" osisID="Josh.7.2"/> Joshua sent men from Jericho to Ai, which lies close to Bethaven on the east of
       Bethel, ordering them to go up and spy out the land. <verse eID="Josh.7.2"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.7.3" osisID="Josh.7.3"/> They went up and spied out Ai and came back to Joshua, saying, <q>All the nation
       need not go up; let only about two or three thousand men go up and attack Ai. Do not make all the nation toil up there,
       for there are few folk at Ai.</q>
      <verse eID="Josh.7.3"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.7.4" osisID="Josh.7.4"/> So about three thousand men marched up; but they ran away from the men of Ai.
      <verse eID="Josh.7.4"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.7.5" osisID="Josh.7.5"/> The men of Ai killed about thirty-six of them, and chased them from their gates
       as far as Shebarim, killing some others at the descent. The hearts of Israel quivered and became weak as water, <verse eID="Josh.7.5"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.7.6" osisID="Josh.7.6"/> and Joshua tore his clothes and fell to the ground upon his face before the ark
       of the Eternal till evening, he and the sheikhs of Israel, with dust upon their heads. <verse eID="Josh.7.6"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.7.7" osisID="Josh.7.7"/> <q>Ah, Lord Eternal,</q> said Joshua, <q>why didst thou ever bring this people
       across the Jordan, only to hand us over to the Amorites to be killed? Would that we had been content to stay on the other
       side of the Jordan. <verse eID="Josh.7.7"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.7.8" osisID="Josh.7.8"/> O Lord, what can I say, after Israel has run away from its enemies? <verse eID="Josh.7.8"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.7.9" osisID="Josh.7.9"/> The Canaanites and all the natives will hear of it, and they will surround us
       and wipe us off the earth. Then what wilt thou do for thy great honour?</q> <verse eID="Josh.7.9"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Josh.7.10" osisID="Josh.7.10"/><q>Get up,</q> said the Eternal to Joshua, <q>why are you lying on your face
       there? <verse eID="Josh.7.10"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.7.11" osisID="Josh.7.11"/> Israel has sinned; they have broken my compact which I commanded them to keep,
       they have taken some of the doomed spoil, stolen it, acted deceitfully, and hidden it among their own goods. <verse eID="Josh.7.11"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.7.12" osisID="Josh.7.12"/> That is why the Israelites cannot stand up against their enemies and why they
       run from their enemies, because they have brought themselves under doom. I will never be with you again, unless you
       remove the doomed thing from among you. <verse eID="Josh.7.12"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.7.13" osisID="Josh.7.13"/> Go and consecrate the people. Tell them to conse­crate themselves for
       to-morrow. Tell them this from the Eternal the God of Israel, <q>There is a doomed tiling among you, O Israel; you cannot
       hold your own against your enemies until you put the doomed thing away
       <milestone type="pb" n="249"/>
       from you. <verse eID="Josh.7.13"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.7.14" osisID="Josh.7.14"/> So in the morning you shall be brought before me by your clans, and the clan
       which the Eternal takes by lot shall come with its septs, and the sept which the Eternal takes by lot shall come with its
       families, and the family which the Eternal takes by lot shall come man by man. <verse eID="Josh.7.14"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.7.15" osisID="Josh.7.15"/> Then he who is taken by lot, in posses­sion of the doomed thing, shall be
       burned, he and all he has, because he has broken the compact of the Eternal, because he has committed a scandal in
       Israel.</q></q> <verse eID="Josh.7.15"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Josh.7.16" osisID="Josh.7.16"/> In the morning Joshua rose and brought Israel before the Eternal by their
       clans; the clan of Judah was taken by lot. <verse eID="Josh.7.16"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.7.17" osisID="Josh.7.17"/> Then the septs of Judah were brought, and the sept of the Zerahites was taken
       by lot; the sept of the Zerahites was brought, family by family, and the family of Zabdi was taken by lot. <verse eID="Josh.7.17"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.7.18" osisID="Josh.7.18"/> Then Zabdi brought his family man by man, and Achan the son of Karmi, the son
       of Zabdi, the son of Zerah, belonging to the clan of Judah, was taken by lot. <verse eID="Josh.7.18"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.7.19" osisID="Josh.7.19"/> Joshua said to Achan, <q>My son, pray confess to the Eternal, the God of
       Israel, own up to him; tell me what you have done, do not hide it from me.</q> <verse eID="Josh.7.19"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.7.20" osisID="Josh.7.20"/> Achan answered, <q>Truly, I have sinned against the Eternal, the God of
       Israel; this is what I did. <verse eID="Josh.7.20"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.7.21" osisID="Josh.7.21"/> When I saw among the spoil a splendid mantle from Shinar and twenty-five
       pounds in silver and a bar of gold weigh­ing twenty-five ounces, I cov­eted them and took them. The mantle is hidden in the
       ground inside my tent, with the money under it.</q> <verse eID="Josh.7.21"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Josh.7.22" osisID="Josh.7.22"/> So Joshua sent messengers, who ran to the tent, and there was the mantle hidden
       inside the tent, with the money under it! <verse eID="Josh.7.22"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.7.23" osisID="Josh.7.23"/> They took them from the tent and brought them to Joshua and all the
       Israelites, who laid them before the Eternal. <verse eID="Josh.7.23"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.7.24" osisID="Josh.7.24"/> Then Joshua and all the Israelites took Achan the son of Zerah and the silver
       and the mantle and the bar of gold and his sons and his daugh­ters and his oxen and his asses and his sheep and his tent
       and all that he had; they brought them to the valley of Achor. <verse eID="Josh.7.24"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.7.25" osisID="Josh.7.25"/> <q>Why have you undone us?</q> said Joshua. <q>The Eternal shall undo you this
       day.</q> Then all Israel stoned him; they burned them with fire and stoned them with stones, <verse eID="Josh.7.25"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.7.26" osisID="Josh.7.26"/> and over them they raised a great cairn of stones. It stands there to this
       day. Then the Eternal relented from his fierce anger. So the name of the place is called Glen-Undoing (Achor-vale) down
       to this day. <verse eID="Josh.7.26"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eID="Josh.7"/>
    <chapter osisID="Josh.8" sID="Josh.8"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Josh.8.1" osisID="Josh.8.1"/>Then said the Eternal to Joshua, <q>Fear not, neither be dismayed; take all the
       warriors with you and march up to Ai. I put into your hands the king of Ai with his people and his town and his country,
      <verse eID="Josh.8.1"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.8.2" osisID="Josh.8.2"/> and you shall treat Ai and its king as you treated Jericho and its king, except
       that you may take the spoils and cattle in it for your­selves. Lay an ambush for the town in the rear.</q> <verse eID="Josh.8.2"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Josh.8.3" osisID="Josh.8.3"/> So Joshua and all the warriors started off for Ai. Three thou­sand veterans
       Joshua picked out, and despatched them by night <verse eID="Josh.8.3"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.8.4" osisID="Josh.8.4"/> with orders to <q>Lie in ambush to the west of the town in the rear. Do not go
       too far away, but be all ready; <verse eID="Josh.8.4"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.8.5" osisID="Josh.8.5"/> I and all the troops who are with me will move against the town, and when they
       issue against us, as before, we
       <milestone type="pb" n="250"/>
       will run off, <verse eID="Josh.8.5"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.8.6" osisID="Josh.8.6"/> till we draw them away from the town, for they will think we are running from
       them as before. <verse eID="Josh.8.6"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.8.7" osisID="Josh.8.7"/> Then, as we run away, you must start out of your ambush and seize the town. The
       Eternal your God will put it into your hands. <verse eID="Josh.8.7"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.8.8" osisID="Josh.8.8"/> As soon as you have seized the town, set it on fire, and carry out the Eternal’s
       command. These are my orders.</q> <verse eID="Josh.8.8"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.8.9" osisID="Josh.8.9"/> So Joshua despatched them, and they went to the place of am­bush, remaining
       between Bethel and Ai, to the west of Ai. Joshua spent the night in the valley. <verse eID="Josh.8.9"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Josh.8.10" osisID="Josh.8.10"/> [Joshua rose in the morning and mustered the nation; then he and the sheikhs
       of Israel led them against Ai. <verse eID="Josh.8.10"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.8.11" osisID="Josh.8.11"/> All the na­tion, that is, the armed men who were with him, marched up close to
       the town and encamped on the north of Ai. Between him and Ai lay a valley. <verse eID="Josh.8.11"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.8.12" osisID="Josh.8.12"/> So Joshua took about five thousand men and put them in ambush--be­tween Bethel
       and Ai, to the west of the town. <verse eID="Josh.8.12"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.8.13" osisID="Josh.8.13"/> The main army was thus stationed to the north of the town, with the am­bush
       laid to the west. Joshua passed that night in the middle of the valley. <verse eID="Josh.8.13"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Josh.8.14" osisID="Josh.8.14"/> In the morning the townsmen rose and marched out to fight Israel. <verse eID="Josh.8.14"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.8.15" osisID="Josh.8.15"/> They beat Joshua and all Israel, who fled in the direc­tion of the desert;
      <verse eID="Josh.8.15"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.8.16" osisID="Josh.8.16"/> all the townsmen of Ai were called out to pursue them, and in their pursuit of
       Joshua they left the town unguarded. <verse eID="Josh.8.16"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.8.18" osisID="Josh.8.18"/> Then said the Eternal to Joshua, <q>Stretch out the jave­lin in your hand
       towards Ai, for I put Ai in your power.</q> And as soon as Joshua stretched out the javelin towards the town, <verse eID="Josh.8.18"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.8.19" osisID="Josh.8.19"/> the men in ambush rushed into the town and captured it, while the Israelites
       who were flying towards the desert turned upon their pursuers,
      <verse eID="Josh.8.19"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.8.20" osisID="Josh.8.20"/>
       seeing that the men in ambush had captured the town. <verse eID="Josh.8.20"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.8.24" osisID="Josh.8.24"/> When the Israelites and Joshua had finished slaughtering the townsmen of Ai
       who had run into the desert, and when they had cut them down, giving no quarter, all Israel then returned to Ai and
       sacked it. <verse eID="Josh.8.24"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.8.25" osisID="Josh.8.25"/> All the folk of Ai fell that day, both men and women, twelve thousand in all;
      <verse eID="Josh.8.25"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.8.26" osisID="Josh.8.26"/> Joshua never withdrew the hand that held his javelin until he had massacred
       all the folk of Ai. <verse eID="Josh.8.26"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.8.27" osisID="Josh.8.27"/> Only, the Israelites took the spoils and cattle of the town for themselves,
       as the Eternal had given orders to Joshua. <verse eID="Josh.8.27"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.8.28" osisID="Josh.8.28"/> Ai itself Joshua burned, making it a heap of ruins; to this day it lies
       deso­late.] <verse eID="Josh.8.28"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Josh.8.14" osisID="Josh.8.14"/> When the king of Ai saw this, he and his men made an early start; not knowing
       that an ambush had been laid behind the town they allowed themselves to be drawn away from the town, <verse eID="Josh.8.14"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.8.17" osisID="Josh.8.17"/> till not a man was left in Ai who did not go out after Israel. <verse eID="Josh.8.17"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.8.19" osisID="Josh.8.19"/> The men in ambush then came out quickly and hur­ried to set the town on fire,
      <verse eID="Josh.8.19"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.8.20" osisID="Josh.8.20"/> so that when the men of Ai turned round to look, there was smoke rising from
       the town! <verse eID="Josh.8.20"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.8.21" osisID="Josh.8.21"/> They had no chance to flee this way or that, for the pursued turned upon the
       pursuers when they saw the smoke rising from the town, <verse eID="Josh.8.21"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.8.22" osisID="Josh.8.22"/> and the men in ambush rushed from the town to join them, so that the men of Ai
       were caught between Israelites, some on one side and some on the other; they were slaughtered till not a soul escaped or
       re­mained alive. <verse eID="Josh.8.22"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.8.23" osisID="Josh.8.23"/> The king of Ai was taken alive and brought to
       <milestone type="pb" n="251"/>
       Joshua, <verse eID="Josh.8.23"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.8.29" osisID="Josh.8.29"/> who hung him on a tree till evening; at sunset Joshua ordered his body to be
       taken down from the tree and thrown down at the entrance to the town-gate. They raised a cairn of stones over it, which
       is there to this day. <verse eID="Josh.8.29"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eID="Josh.8"/>
    <chapter osisID="Josh.9" sID="Josh.9"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Josh.9.1" osisID="Josh.9.1"/>When this was heard by all the kings west of the Jordan, in the highlands and the
       low­lands and all along the coast of the Mediterranean as far as Leb­anon, then Hittites, Amorites, Canaanites, Perizzites,
       Hivites, and Jebusites, <verse eID="Josh.9.1"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.9.2" osisID="Josh.9.2"/> gathered like one man to attack Joshua and Israel. <verse eID="Josh.9.2"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Josh.9.3" osisID="Josh.9.3"/> But the citizens of Gibeon, hearing what Joshua had done to Jericho and Ai,
      <verse eID="Josh.9.3"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.9.4" osisID="Josh.9.4"/> went to work craftily. They took provisions in old sacks on their asses, and old
       mended wineskins, <verse eID="Josh.9.4"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.9.5" osisID="Josh.9.5"/> with old patched shoes on their feet and old clothes on their bodies; the bread
       they took was all dry and crumbling. <verse eID="Josh.9.5"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.9.6" osisID="Josh.9.6"/> They went to Joshua at the camp in Gilgal and said to him and to the Israel­ites,
       <q>We have come from a far country; pray make a treaty with us.</q> <verse eID="Josh.9.6"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.9.7" osisID="Josh.9.7"/> The Israelites said to these Hivites, <q>Perhaps you live in our country, and
       why should we make a treaty with you?</q> <verse eID="Josh.9.7"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.9.8" osisID="Josh.9.8"/> <q>We are at your service,</q> they said to Joshua. <q>But who are you,</q>
       Joshua asked, <q>and where do you come from?</q> <verse eID="Josh.9.8"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.9.9" osisID="Josh.9.9"/> <q>From a country very far away,</q> they said, <q>and we have come on account
       of the Eternal, your God, for we have heard of his fame, of all he did in Egypt, <verse eID="Josh.9.9"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.9.10" osisID="Josh.9.10"/> and of all he did to the two Amorite kings east of the Jordan, Sihon king of
       Heshbon and Og king of Bashan who reigned at Ashtaroth. <verse eID="Josh.9.10"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.9.11" osisID="Josh.9.11"/> Our sheikhs and all our people told us to take provisions with us for the
       journey and to go and meet you and say, <q>We are at your service; pray make a treaty with us.</q> <verse eID="Josh.9.11"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.9.12" osisID="Josh.9.12"/> This bread we took hot out of our houses on the day we started, and there,
       you see, it is dry and crumbling by this time! <verse eID="Josh.9.12"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.9.13" osisID="Josh.9.13"/> These wineskins were new when we filled them, and you see they are torn.
       These clothes and shoes of ours are worn out, owing to the long journey.</q> <verse eID="Josh.9.13"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Josh.9.14" osisID="Josh.9.14"/> So the Israelites partook of their provisions, never asking the Eternal for
       advice; <verse eID="Josh.9.14"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.9.15" osisID="Josh.9.15"/> Joshua made peace with them and made a treaty with them to spare their lives,
       and the leaders of the com­munity swore an oath to them. <verse eID="Josh.9.15"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.9.16" osisID="Josh.9.16"/> Three days after they had made the treaty, they heard that the men were
       neighbours, living in the same country! <verse eID="Josh.9.16"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.9.17" osisID="Josh.9.17"/> [[On the third day, as the Israelites marched forward, they came to their
       towns, Gibeon, Kefirah, Beeroth, and Kiriath-jearim. <verse eID="Josh.9.17"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.9.18" osisID="Josh.9.18"/> The Israelites did not kill them, because the leaders of the community had
       sworn an oath to them by the Eternal, the God of Israel. The community all grumbled against the leaders, <verse eID="Josh.9.18"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.9.19" osisID="Josh.9.19"/> but the leaders all replied, <q>We swore an oath to them by the Eternal the
       God of Israel: so now we cannot touch them. <verse eID="Josh.9.19"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.9.20" osisID="Josh.9.20"/> We must grant them the favour of their lives, lest wrath come upon us over the
       oath we took to them. <verse eID="Josh.9.20"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.9.21" osisID="Josh.9.21"/> Let them live,</q> said the leaders. So they became wood-cutters and
       water-carriers to all the community, as the leaders directed.]] <verse eID="Josh.9.21"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Josh.9.22" osisID="Josh.9.22"/> Then Joshua called for them and asked them, <q>Why have you deceived us by
       saying you came from far, far away, when you live in the same country as our­selves?
      <verse eID="Josh.9.22"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.9.23" osisID="Josh.9.23"/>
       A curse on you! You shall ever provide us with slaves
       <milestone type="pb" n="252"/>
       for the temple of my God, wood­cutters and water-carriers.</q> <verse eID="Josh.9.23"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.9.24" osisID="Josh.9.24"/> They answered Joshua, <q>It was because your servants were as­sured that the
       Eternal your God had ordered his servant Moses to assign you all the land and to destroy all the natives before you. That
       put us in terror of our lives before you, and so we did this. <verse eID="Josh.9.24"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.9.25" osisID="Josh.9.25"/> Well, we are in your power. Whatever you think right and fair to do to us, do
       it.</q> <verse eID="Josh.9.25"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.9.26" osisID="Josh.9.26"/> This, then, was how Joshua treated them; he saved them from the Israelites
       and kept them from being murdered, <verse eID="Josh.9.26"/>
      <verse sID="Josh.9.27" osisID="Josh.9.27"/> but he made them that day wood­cutters and water-carriers for the community
       and for the altar of the Eternal, wherever the Eternal chooses. As they still are. <verse eID="Josh.9.27"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eID="Josh.9"/>
   </div>