   <div type="book" osisID="Judg">
    <milestone type="pb" n="271"/>
    <chapter osisID="Judg.1" sID="Judg.1"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.1.1" osisID="Judg.1.1"/>After Joshua died, the Israel­ites asked the Eternal which of them was to march up
       first and attack the Canaanites. <verse eID="Judg.1.1"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.1.2" osisID="Judg.1.2"/> The Eternal answered, <q>Judah is to march up; I hand over the country to him.</q>
      <verse eID="Judg.1.2"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.1.3" osisID="Judg.1.3"/> So Judah said to his brother Simeon, <q>March with me into my allotted terri­tory,
       to attack the Canaanites, and then I will march with you into your allotted territory.</q> Simeon accompanied him <verse eID="Judg.1.3"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.1.4" osisID="Judg.1.4"/> [[and, when Judah marched up, the Eternal handed over to them the Canaanites and
       the Perizzites; they defeated ten thousand of them at Bezek]]. <verse eID="Judg.1.4"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.1.5" osisID="Judg.1.5"/> At Bezek they came upon Adoni-bezek and attacked him, defeat­ing the Canaanites and
       the Perizzites. <verse eID="Judg.1.5"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.1.6" osisID="Judg.1.6"/> Adonibezek fled, but they pursued him, cap­tured him, and lopped off his thumbs and
       his great toes. <verse eID="Judg.1.6"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.1.7" osisID="Judg.1.7"/><q>Seventy chiefs, with their thumbs and great toes lopped off, used to pick up their
       food under my table,</q> said Adoni­bezek; <q>as I did, so has God done to me in turn.</q> He was carried off to Jerusalem,
       and there he died. <verse eID="Judg.1.7"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.1.19" osisID="Judg.1.19"/> The Eternal was with the Judahites; they gained posses­sion of the highlands,
       although they were unable to evict the dwellers in the plain, who had iron chariots. <verse eID="Judg.1.19"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.1.21" osisID="Judg.1.21"/> Neither did the men of Judah evict the Jebusites who inhabited Jerusalem; the
       Jebusites lived among the men of Judah as they do to this day in Jerusalem. <verse eID="Judg.1.21"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.1.8" osisID="Judg.1.8"/> [[The men of Judah attacked and captured Jerusalem, giving no quarter and burning
       up the town. <verse eID="Judg.1.8"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.1.9" osisID="Judg.1.9"/> After that, the men of Judah marched off to attack the Canaanites who lived in the
       highlands, the Negeb, and the lowlands. <verse eID="Judg.1.9"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.1.10" osisID="Judg.1.10"/> Judah marched against the Canaanites who lived in Hebron (formerly called
       Kiriath-arba); they vanquished Sheshai, Ahiman, and TalmaiJ] <verse eID="Judg.1.10"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.1.11" osisID="Judg.1.11"/> Then they marched against the natives of Debir (formerly called Kiriath-sepher).
      <verse eID="Judg.1.11"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.1.12" osisID="Judg.1.12"/> Caleb declared, <q>Whoever attacks Kiriath-sepher and captures it, I will give
       him my daughter Achsah in marriage.</q> <verse eID="Judg.1.12"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.1.13" osisID="Judg.1.13"/> Othniel, the son of Caleb’s younger brother Kenaz, captured it. So Caleb gave
       him his daughter Achsah in marriage. <verse eID="Judg.1.13"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.1.14" osisID="Judg.1.14"/> When she arrived, Othniel induced her to ask her father for a tract of land as
       her dowry; so she alighted from her ass, and, when Caleb asked her what she wanted, <verse eID="Judg.1.14"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.1.15" osisID="Judg.1.15"/> she said to him, <q>Give me a parting present; as you have settled me in the dry
       south country, let me have some springs of water.</q> Then Caleb gave her the up­per springs and the lower springs. <verse eID="Judg.1.15"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.1.16" osisID="Judg.1.16"/> When Hobab the Kenite, the father-in-law of Moses, left Palmtown to accompany
       the men of Judah into the desert of Judah near Arad, he went on to settle among the Amalekites. <verse eID="Judg.1.16"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.1.17" osisID="Judg.1.17"/> But Judah accompanied his brother Simeon; they defeated the Canaanites who
       inhabited Zephath, and massacred them. So the place came to be called Sacredtown (Hormah). <verse eID="Judg.1.17"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.1.18" osisID="Judg.1.18"/> Judah also captured Gaza and its terri­tory, Ashkelon and its terri­tory and Ekron
       and its terri­tory; <verse eID="Judg.1.18"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.1.20" osisID="Judg.1.20"/> Hebron they assigned to Caleb, as Moses had ordered,
       <milestone type="pb" n="272"/>
       and Caleb ejected from it the three giants. <verse eID="Judg.1.20"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.1.22" osisID="Judg.1.22"/> The clansmen of Joseph marched also against Bethel. The Eternal was with them.
      <verse eID="Judg.1.22"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.1.23" osisID="Judg.1.23"/> When the clansmen of Joseph sent men to reconnoitre at Bethel (formerly called
       Luz), <verse eID="Judg.1.23"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.1.24" osisID="Judg.1.24"/> the scouts saw a man leaving the town and caught him; <q>Come, tell us,</q> they
       said, <q>how to get into the town, and we will treat you well.</q> <verse eID="Judg.1.24"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.1.25" osisID="Judg.1.25"/> So he showed them how to get into the town, and they stormed it, giving no
       quarter; they let the man and his family go free, <verse eID="Judg.1.25"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.1.26" osisID="Judg.1.26"/> and he went to the land of the Hittites, where he built a town, calling it Luz.
       That is its name to this day. <verse eID="Judg.1.26"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.1.27" osisID="Judg.1.27"/> Manasseh did not gain pos­session of Beth-shean and its townships, nor of Taanak
       and its townships; they did not evict the inhabitants of Dor and its townships, nor of Ibleam and its townships, nor of
       Megiddo and its townships. The Canaanites clung to this country. <verse eID="Judg.1.27"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.1.28" osisID="Judg.1.28"/> When Israel became a power, they forced the Canaanites to slave for them, but
       they never evicted them entirely. <verse eID="Judg.1.28"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.1.29" osisID="Judg.1.29"/> Eph­raim did not evict the Canaan­ites who lived at Gezer; the Canaanites lived
       among them in Gezer. <verse eID="Judg.1.29"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.1.30" osisID="Judg.1.30"/> Zebulun did not evict the inhabitants of Kitron or of Nahalal; the Canaanites
       lived among them and were turned into labour-gangs. <verse eID="Judg.1.30"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.1.31" osisID="Judg.1.31"/> Asher did not evict the inhabitants of Acco or of Sidon or of Ahlab or of Achzib
       or of Helbah or of Aphek or of Rehob; <verse eID="Judg.1.31"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.1.32" osisID="Judg.1.32"/> the Asherites lived among the native Canaanites, who could not be evicted. <verse eID="Judg.1.32"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.1.33" osisID="Judg.1.33"/> Naphtali did not evict the inhabitants of Beth-shemesh or of Beth-anath, but
       lived among the native Canaanites. The inhabitants of Beth-shemesh and Beth-anath, however, were turned into labour-gangs.
      <verse eID="Judg.1.33"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.1.34" osisID="Judg.1.34"/> As for the Danites, they were forced into the highlands by the Amorites, who
       would not allow them down into the plain. <verse eID="Judg.1.34"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.1.35" osisID="Judg.1.35"/> The Amorites clung to Harheres, Aijalon, and Shaalbim; but, as the clans­men of
       Joseph prevailed in pow­er, they were turned into labour-gangs. <verse eID="Judg.1.35"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.1.36" osisID="Judg.1.36"/> [[The frontier of the Edomites ran from the Scorpion Pass to Sela and beyond
       it.]] <verse eID="Judg.1.36"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eID="Judg.1"/>
    <chapter osisID="Judg.2" sID="Judg.2"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.2.1" osisID="Judg.2.1"/>Then the angel of the Eternal went from Gilgal up to Bethel, and said: <q>...I
       brought you out of Egypt into the land I swore to your fathers that I would give to you. I said that I would never break
       my compact with you, <verse eID="Judg.2.1"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.2.2" osisID="Judg.2.2"/> and that you must never make terms with the natives--you must pull down their
       altars. But you have not obeyed my orders. What is this you have done? <verse eID="Judg.2.2"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.2.3" osisID="Judg.2.3"/> So I add this word: <q>I will not dispossess them to make room for you: they shall
       be a scourge on your flanks, and their gods shall prove a danger to you.</q> <verse eID="Judg.2.3"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.2.4" osisID="Judg.2.4"/> When the angel of the Eternal said this to all the Israelites, the people burst
       into loud weeping. <verse eID="Judg.2.4"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.2.5" osisID="Judg.2.5"/> They called the place Bochim (or Weepers), and there they sacrificed to the
       Eternal.</q><verse eID="Judg.2.5"/>
     </p>
     <p> * * * * </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.2.6" osisID="Judg.2.6"/> When Joshua dismissed the people, the Israelites went back, each to his own
       property, to take possession of the country. <verse eID="Judg.2.6"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.2.7" osisID="Judg.2.7"/> During all the lifetime of Joshua and of the sheikhs who survived Joshua, who had
       seen all the great work done by the Eternal for Israel, the people continued to serve the Eternal. <verse eID="Judg.2.7"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.2.8" osisID="Judg.2.8"/> At the 8 age of a hundred and ten Joshua
       <milestone type="pb" n="273"/>
       the son of Nun, the servant of the Eternal, died. <verse eID="Judg.2.8"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.2.9" osisID="Judg.2.9"/> They buried him on his estate at Timnath-heres in the highlands of Eph­raim, north
       of mount Gaash. <verse eID="Judg.2.9"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.2.10" osisID="Judg.2.10"/> Then all that generation was gathered to their fathers, and another generation
       arose who knew nothing about the Eternal or the work he had done for Israel. <verse eID="Judg.2.10"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.2.11" osisID="Judg.2.11"/> These Israelites did what was evil in the sight of the Eternal, serving the
       Baals <verse eID="Judg.2.11"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.2.12" osisID="Judg.2.12"/> and forsaking the Eternal, the God of their fathers, who had brought them from
       the land of Egypt, running after other gods belonging to the gods of the nations around, and bowing down to them; <verse eID="Judg.2.12"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.2.13" osisID="Judg.2.13"/> they vexed the Eternal by forsaking the Eternal and sacrificing to Baal and
       Astarte. <verse eID="Judg.2.13"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.2.14" osisID="Judg.2.14"/> So the anger of the Eternal blazed against Israel; he handed them over to
       plun­derers who plundered them, he sold them into the power of their enemies around, till they could no longer hold their
       own against their enemies; <verse eID="Judg.2.14"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.2.15" osisID="Judg.2.15"/> wherever they marched, the Eternal’s hand was against them for evil, as the
       Eternal had threatened and sworn. They were in a sore plight. <verse eID="Judg.2.15"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.2.16" osisID="Judg.2.16"/> The Eternal raised up heroes, who rescued them from their plunderers; <verse eID="Judg.2.16"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.2.17" osisID="Judg.2.17"/> but they would not listen even to their heroes. Faithlessly they went after
       other gods, bowing down to them; they soon swerved from the line of their fathers who obeyed the com­mands of the
       Eternal--which was not what they did. <verse eID="Judg.2.17"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.2.18" osisID="Judg.2.18"/> When the Eternal raised up heroes for them, the Eternal would be with the
       heroes and rescue them from the power of their enemies dur­ing all the days of the hero; for the Eternal was moved to pity
       by their groans under the grip of their tyrants and oppressors. <verse eID="Judg.2.18"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.2.19" osisID="Judg.2.19"/> But whenever the hero died, they would relapse and behave worse than ever,
       running after other gods, sacrificing to them and bowing before them; they would not drop any of their practices or
       stubborn ways. <verse eID="Judg.2.19"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.2.20" osisID="Judg.2.20"/> So the anger of the Eternal blazed against Israel; he said, <q>As this nation
       has violated the compact which I enjoined upon their fathers and has not listened to my orders, <verse eID="Judg.2.20"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.2.21" osisID="Judg.2.21"/> I will no longer evict for them any of the nations that Joshua left when he
       died</q><verse eID="Judg.2.21"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.2.22" osisID="Judg.2.22"/>--His aim being to test Israel by means of them, to see whether or not they would
       live by the rules of the Eternal as their fathers did. <verse eID="Judg.2.22"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.2.23" osisID="Judg.2.23"/> So the Eternal left these nations, in­stead of evicting them all at once[[; he
       did not hand them over to Joshua]]. <verse eID="Judg.2.23"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eID="Judg.2"/>
    <chapter osisID="Judg.3" sID="Judg.3"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.3.1" osisID="Judg.3.1"/>The following are the nations left by the Eternal as a test for all the Israelites
       who had had no experience of the war of invasion in Canaan--<verse eID="Judg.3.1"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.3.2" osisID="Judg.3.2"/>simply for giving lessons in war­fare to these generations of Israelites who
       hitherto knew nothing about fighting; <verse eID="Judg.3.2"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.3.3" osisID="Judg.3.3"/> there were the five tyrants of the Philistines, all the Canaanites, the
       Phoenicians, and the Hittites of mount Lebanon, stretch­ing from mount Baal-hermon to the pass of Hamath. <verse eID="Judg.3.3"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.3.4" osisID="Judg.3.4"/> They served as a test, to show whether Israel would obey what the Eternal had
       commanded their fathers through Moses. <verse eID="Judg.3.4"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.3.5" osisID="Judg.3.5"/> As the Israelites lived among the Canaanites, the Hittites, the Amorites, the
       Perizzites, the Hivites, and the Jebusites,
      <verse eID="Judg.3.5"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.3.6" osisID="Judg.3.6"/> they married their daughters,
       <milestone type="pb" n="274"/>
       married their own daughters to their sons, and sacrificed to their gods. <verse eID="Judg.3.6"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.3.7" osisID="Judg.3.7"/> The Israelites did what was evil in the sight of the Eternal, forgetting the
       Eternal their own God and worshipping the Baals and sacred poles. <verse eID="Judg.3.7"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.3.8" osisID="Judg.3.8"/> So the anger of the Eternal flamed hot against Israel; he sold them into the
       power of Kushan-rishathaim the king of Mesopo­tamia, and for eight years the Israelites were subject to Kushan-rishathaim.
      <verse eID="Judg.3.8"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.3.9" osisID="Judg.3.9"/> Then the Israelites cried to the Eternal, and the Eternal raised up a champion for
       the Israelites, who rescued them; it was Othniel, the son of Caleb’s younger brother, Kenaz. <verse eID="Judg.3.9"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.3.10" osisID="Judg.3.10"/> The spirit of the Eternal in­spired him; he avenged Israel. When he marched out
       to battle, the Eternal handed over to him Kushan-rishathaim the king of Mesopotamia, till he got the upper hand of
       Kushan-rishathaim. <verse eID="Judg.3.10"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.3.11" osisID="Judg.3.11"/> For forty years the land lay safe. Then Othniel the son of Kenaz died, <verse eID="Judg.3.11"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.3.12" osisID="Judg.3.12"/> and again the Israelites did what was evil in the sight of the Eternal. So the
       Eternal made Eglon the king of Moab gain the upper hand over Israel, since they had done what was evil in the sight of the
       Eternal. <verse eID="Judg.3.12"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.3.13" osisID="Judg.3.13"/> Eglon, collecting the Ammonites and the Amalekites, went and defeated Israel,
       seizing Palmtown; <verse eID="Judg.3.13"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.3.14" osisID="Judg.3.14"/> and for eighteen years the Israelites were subject to Eglon the king of Moab.
      <verse eID="Judg.3.14"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.3.15" osisID="Judg.3.15"/> Then Israel cried to the Eternal, and the Eternal raised up a champion for them;
       it was Ehud the son of Gera, a Benjamite who was left-handed. He carried tribute from the Israel­ites to Eglon the king of
       Moab. <verse eID="Judg.3.15"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.3.16" osisID="Judg.3.16"/> On his right thigh under his clothes, Ehud hung a dirk which he had made, a
       two-edged weapon eighteen inches long. <verse eID="Judg.3.16"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.3.17" osisID="Judg.3.17"/> He presented the tribute to Eglon the king of Moab (Eglon was a very fat man),
      <verse eID="Judg.3.17"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.3.18" osisID="Judg.3.18"/> and when he had finished presenting the tribute, he dismissed the car­riers.
      <verse eID="Judg.3.18"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.3.19" osisID="Judg.3.19"/> He himself halted at the sculptured stones near Gilgal, and went back, saying,
       <q>I have a private message for you, O king.</q> <q>Silence!</q> said Eglon to his attendants, and they all left him. <verse eID="Judg.3.19"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.3.20" osisID="Judg.3.20"/> Then Ehud went in to see him, as he sat alone in his cool upper room. <q>I have
       a message from God for you,</q> said Ehud. As Eglon rose from his chair, <verse eID="Judg.3.20"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.3.21" osisID="Judg.3.21"/> Ehud put out his left hand, drew the dirk from his right thigh, and drove it
       into his belly; <verse eID="Judg.3.21"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.3.22" osisID="Judg.3.22"/> the hilt went in after the blade, and the fat closed over the blade, for he did
       not draw the dirk out of his belly. <verse eID="Judg.3.22"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.3.23" osisID="Judg.3.23"/> Ehud then went out into the vestibule, shutting the doors of the room and
       locking Eglon in. <verse eID="Judg.3.23"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.3.24" osisID="Judg.3.24"/> After he had gone, the king’s servants came; they saw that the doors of the
       upper room were locked, but they thought that he must be relieving him­self in the closet of the upper chamber. <verse eID="Judg.3.24"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.3.25" osisID="Judg.3.25"/> They waited, till they were at their wits' end. As he did not open the doors of
       the upper room, they opened them with a key--and there lay their lord dead on the floor! <verse eID="Judg.3.25"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.3.26" osisID="Judg.3.26"/> Meantime, as they were waiting, Ehud had escaped, past the sculptured stones,
       safe to Seirah. <verse eID="Judg.3.26"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.3.27" osisID="Judg.3.27"/> When he got there, he sounded the alarm through the high­lands of Ephraim, and
       the Is­raelites accompanied him from the highlands as their leader. <verse eID="Judg.3.27"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.3.28" osisID="Judg.3.28"/> <q>Follow me down,</q> he cried, <q>the Eternal has handed you over your enemies
       in Moab!</q> So they marched after him and
       <milestone type="pb" n="275"/>
       seized the fords of the Jordan, preventing any Moabite from crossing. <verse eID="Judg.3.28"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.3.29" osisID="Judg.3.29"/> They slew that day about ten thousand Moabites, stout warriors, all of them;
       not a man escaped. <verse eID="Judg.3.29"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.3.30" osisID="Judg.3.30"/> Moab was subdued that day by Israel, and for eighty years the land lay safe. <verse eID="Judg.3.30"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.3.31" osisID="Judg.3.31"/> After him came Shamgar the son of Anath, who killed six hundred Philistines with
       an ox-goad; he also rescued Israel. <verse eID="Judg.3.31"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eID="Judg.3"/>
    <chapter osisID="Judg.4" sID="Judg.4"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.4.1" osisID="Judg.4.1"/>When Ehud died, the Israel­ites again did evil in the sight of the Eternal. <verse eID="Judg.4.1"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.4.2" osisID="Judg.4.2"/> So the Eternal sold them into the power of Jabin the king of Canaan, who reigned
       in Hazor; his general was Sisera, who lived at Harosheth-of-the-nations. <verse eID="Judg.4.2"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.4.3" osisID="Judg.4.3"/> And the Israelites cried to the Eternal, for Jabin had nine hundred iron chariots,
       and for twenty years he oppressed Israel cruelly. <verse eID="Judg.4.3"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.4.4" osisID="Judg.4.4"/> At that time Israel was being managed by Deborah a prophetess, the wife of
       Lapidoth, <verse eID="Judg.4.4"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.4.5" osisID="Judg.4.5"/> who used to sit under the Deborah palm-tree between Ramah and Bethel in the
       highlands of Eph­raim, deciding cases brought to her by the Israelites. <verse eID="Judg.4.5"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.4.6" osisID="Judg.4.6"/> She sent to summon Barak the son of Abinoam from Kedesh in Naphtali, and told him,
       <q>Does not the Eternal, the God of Israel, order you to march on mount Tabor with ten thousand men from Naphtali and
        Zebulun, <verse eID="Judg.4.6"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.4.7" osisID="Judg.4.7"/> saying, <q>I will draw Sisera, Jabin's general, to meet you at the Kishon wady with
       his char­iots and his troops, and put him in your power</q>?</q> <verse eID="Judg.4.7"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.4.8" osisID="Judg.4.8"/> Barak said to her, <q>If you will come with me, I will go; but if you will not
       come with me, I will not.</q> <verse eID="Judg.4.8"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.4.9" osisID="Judg.4.9"/> She answered, <q>I will certainly come with you. Only, the glory of the expedition
       will not be yours; for the Eternal will sell Sisera into a woman’s hand.</q> Then Deborah went with Barak to Kedesh. <verse eID="Judg.4.9"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.4.10" osisID="Judg.4.10"/> Barak summoned Zebulun and Naph­tali to Kedesh; ten thousand men were at his
       back, and Deborah marched with him. <verse eID="Judg.4.10"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.4.11" osisID="Judg.4.11"/> (Now Heber the Kenite had withdrawn from the Kenites, the sept of Hobab the
       father-in-law of Moses, pitching his tent as far north as the oak of Basaanim near Kedesh.) <verse eID="Judg.4.11"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.4.12" osisID="Judg.4.12"/> Learning that Barak the son of Abinoam had marched to mount Tabor, <verse eID="Judg.4.12"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.4.13" osisID="Judg.4.13"/> Sisera summoned all his chariots, nine hundred iron chariots, and all his
       forces, from Harosheth-of-the-nations to the Kishon wady. <verse eID="Judg.4.13"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.4.14" osisID="Judg.4.14"/> Then said Deborah to Barak, <q>Up! this is the day when the Eternal puts Sisera
       in your power! Is not the Eternal marching in front of you?</q> So Barak, with ten thousand men at his back, charged down
       from mount Tabor, <verse eID="Judg.4.14"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.4.15" osisID="Judg.4.15"/> and the Eternal routed Sisera and all his char­iots and all his army before
       Barak. Sisera alighted from his chariot and fled on foot; <verse eID="Judg.4.15"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.4.16" osisID="Judg.4.16"/> but Barak pursued the chariots and the army as far as Harosheth-of-the-nations,
       killing the entire army of Sisera and giving no quarter; not a single man was left. <verse eID="Judg.4.16"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.4.17" osisID="Judg.4.17"/> Sisera, however, fled on foot to the tent of Jael the wife of Heber the Kenite;
       for Jabin the king of Hazor and the family of Heber the Kenite were on friendly terms. <verse eID="Judg.4.17"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.4.18" osisID="Judg.4.18"/> Jael came out to meet Sisera, saying, <q>Turn in, my lord, turn into my tent;
       have no fear!</q> So he turned into her tent, and she covered him up with a rug. <verse eID="Judg.4.18"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.4.19" osisID="Judg.4.19"/> He said to her, <q>Pray give me a little water, for I am thirsty.</q> So she
       opened her skin of milk,
       <milestone type="pb" n="276"/>
       gave him a drink, and covered him up again. <verse eID="Judg.4.19"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.4.20" osisID="Judg.4.20"/> He said to her, <q>Stand at the door of the tent, and then, if anyone comes and
       asks you if there is a man here, say no.</q> <verse eID="Judg.4.20"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.4.21" osisID="Judg.4.21"/> But Jael the wife of Heber the Kenite took a tent-peg and a mallet in her hand,
       and, slipping quietly up to him, she drove the peg into his temple right through to the ground--for he was fast asleep and
       exhausted; so he died. <verse eID="Judg.4.21"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.4.22" osisID="Judg.4.22"/> Up came Barak in pursuit of Sisera; and Jael went out to meet him, saying,
       <q>Here, I will show you the man you are looking for!</q> So Barak went inside her tent, and there lay Sisera dead, with
        the tent-peg in his temple! <verse eID="Judg.4.22"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.4.23" osisID="Judg.4.23"/> Thus did God that day subdue Jabin the king of Canaan before the Israelites;
      <verse eID="Judg.4.23"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.4.24" osisID="Judg.4.24"/> the Israelites bore harder and harder upon Jabin the king of Canaan, till they
       finally destroyed Jabin the king of Canaan. <verse eID="Judg.4.24"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eID="Judg.4"/>
    <chapter osisID="Judg.5" sID="Judg.5"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.5.1" osisID="Judg.5.1"/>On that day Deborah sang with Barak the son of Abinoam:
      <verse eID="Judg.5.1"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.5.2" osisID="Judg.5.2"/> That Israel’s leaders took the lead, that the folk came forward freely, bless
       the Eternal! <verse eID="Judg.5.2"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.5.3" osisID="Judg.5.3"/>
       <lg>
        <l> Listen, O kings, </l>
        <l> rulers, hear! </l>
        <l> I will sing to the Eternal, </l>
        <l> to Israel’s God I chant, to the Eternal. </l>
       </lg>
      <verse eID="Judg.5.3"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.5.4" osisID="Judg.5.4"/>
       <lg>
        <l> At thine advance from Seir, O Eternal, </l>
        <l> upon thy march from Edom’s land, </l>
        <l> earth was shaking, </l>
        <l> the skies quaking, </l>
        <l> clouds dripped water, </l>
      <verse eID="Judg.5.4"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.5.5" osisID="Judg.5.5"/>
        <l> mountains streamed, </l>
        <l> in front of the Eternal, Israel’s God. </l>
       </lg>
      <verse eID="Judg.5.5"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.5.6" osisID="Judg.5.6"/>
       <lg>
        <l> In Shamgar’s day, the son of Anath,
        </l>
        <l> in the years gone by, </l>
        <l> the caravans had ceased, </l>
        <l> wayfarers kept to the by-roads, </l>
      <verse eID="Judg.5.6"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.5.7" osisID="Judg.5.7"/>
        <l> and Israel’s hamlets were deserted--
        </l>
        <l> till I arose, Deborah, </l>
        <l> a matron within Israel. </l>
      <verse eID="Judg.5.7"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.5.8" osisID="Judg.5.8"/>
        <l> Not one shield for five towns then! </l>
        <l> not a lance for Israel’s forty thou­sand men!</l>
      <verse eID="Judg.5.8"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.5.9" osisID="Judg.5.9"/>
        <l> But Israel had leaders--my heart goes out to them-- </l>
        <l> folk who came forward! Bless the Eternal! </l>
       </lg>
      <verse eID="Judg.5.9"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.5.10" osisID="Judg.5.10"/>
       <lg>
        <l> Tell of them, you on your tawny asses, </l>
        <l> riding on your rugs, </l>
        <l> and you that tramp the roads! </l>
      <verse eID="Judg.5.10"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.5.11" osisID="Judg.5.11"/>
        <l>Far from the whizzing of arrows, </l>
        <l> where cattle are watered, </l>
        <l> men tell how the Eternal upholds the right, </l>
        <l> upholds it for Israel’s hamlets.</l>
       </lg>
      <verse eID="Judg.5.11"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.5.12" osisID="Judg.5.12"/>
       <lg>
        <l> Up, O Deborah, </l>
        <l> up, up, with your war-cry! </l>
        <l> To your feet, O Barak son of Abinoam, </l>
        <l> and capture your captors! </l>
       </lg>
      <verse eID="Judg.5.12"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.5.13" osisID="Judg.5.13"/>
       <lg>
        <l> Out the folk of the Eternal marched, </l>
        <l> out came all the nobles left, </l>
        <l> out for the Eternal marched his folk like heroes, </l>
      <verse eID="Judg.5.13"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.5.14" osisID="Judg.5.14"/>
        <l> wheeling from Ephraim into the glen--
        </l>
        <l> <q>We follow you, Benjamin, your clan’s men!</q> </l>
        <l> Out from Machir came com­manders, </l>
        <l> adjutants from Zebulun; </l>
      <verse eID="Judg.5.14"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.5.15" osisID="Judg.5.15"/>
        <l> Issachar’s chieftains rallied to Deborah, </l>
        <l> as Naphtali backed up Barak, </l>
        <l> tearing down at his heels to the glen. </l>
        <l> But in the shires of Reuben </l>
        <l> were divisions and debates. </l>
      <verse eID="Judg.5.15"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.5.16" osisID="Judg.5.16"/>
        <l> Why did you lounge by shepherds' cotes, </l>
        <l> with only an ear for pastoral notes? </l>
      <verse eID="Judg.5.16"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.5.17" osisID="Judg.5.17"/>
        <l> East of the Jordan the Gileadites stayed; </l>
        <l> Dan held to his ships; </l>
        <l> Asher sat still by the seaboard, </l>
        <l> clinging to his creeks. </l>
      <verse eID="Judg.5.17"/>
      <milestone type="pb" n="277"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.5.18" osisID="Judg.5.18"/>
        <l> But Zebulun--the clan risked life and death </l>
        <l> with Naphtali out in the open field! </l>
       </lg>
      <verse eID="Judg.5.18"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.5.19" osisID="Judg.5.19"/>
       <lg>
        <l> On came the kings, came at them, </l>
        <l> Canaan’s kings came at them, </l>
        <l> by Taanak, on Megiddo’s streams; </l>
        <l> and much they made of it! </l>
      <verse eID="Judg.5.19"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.5.20" osisID="Judg.5.20"/>
        <l> The very stars in heaven were fighting, </l>
        <l> fighting Sisera from their spheres; </l>
      <verse eID="Judg.5.20"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.5.21" osisID="Judg.5.21"/>
        <l> Kishon’s torrent swept the foe off, </l>
        <l> Kishon’s torrent in their faces! </l>
        <l> (Bless the Eternal’s power, my soul!) </l>
      <verse eID="Judg.5.21"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.5.22" osisID="Judg.5.22"/>
        <l> Then thudded hoofs of horses, </l>
        <l> as the chargers thundered away. </l>
       </lg>
      <verse eID="Judg.5.22"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.5.23" osisID="Judg.5.23"/>
       <lg>
        <l> Curse Meroz, the Eternal’s angel cries, </l>
        <l> blast her burghers with a curse! </l>
        <l> They never came to the Eternal’s aid, </l>
        <l> to the Eternal’s aid, to join the heroes! </l>
      <verse eID="Judg.5.23"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.5.24" osisID="Judg.5.24"/>
        <l> But blest above women be Jael, </l>
        <l> blest above Bedawin women! </l>
      <verse eID="Judg.5.24"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.5.25" osisID="Judg.5.25"/>
        <l> Water he asked, and milk she gave him, </l>
        <l> brought him curds in a lordly bowl, </l>
      <verse eID="Judg.5.25"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.5.26" osisID="Judg.5.26"/>
        <l> laid her hand upon a tent-pin, </l>
        <l> laid her right hand on a mallet, </l>
        <l> and pounded Sisera, shattered his head, </l>
        <l> smashed him, crashed his tem­ple in; </l>
      <verse eID="Judg.5.26"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.5.27" osisID="Judg.5.27"/>
        <l> he sank at her feet, he fell down dead, </l>
        <l> and where he sank he fell--her victim! </l>
       </lg>
      <verse eID="Judg.5.27"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.5.28" osisID="Judg.5.28"/>
       <lg>
        <l> Out of the window she leans and peers, </l>
        <l> Sisera’s mother, out of the lattice:</l>
        <q><l>Why are his chariots lingering? Why?</l>
        <l>Why is the sound of his wheels so long?</l></q>
      <verse eID="Judg.5.28"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.5.29" osisID="Judg.5.29"/>
        <l> And her ladies (so knowing) reply--</l>
        <l> nay, she answers herself as they answer--</l>
      <verse eID="Judg.5.29"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.5.30" osisID="Judg.5.30"/>
        <q><l> They must be dividing the spoil </l>
        <l> they have taken, a wench or two wenches apiece, </l>
        <l> dyed robes for Sisera’s share, and brocade and brocades, for my neck!</l></q>
       </lg>
      <verse eID="Judg.5.30"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.5.31" osisID="Judg.5.31"/>
       <lg>
        <l> So be thy foes, Eternal, all undone! </l>
        <l> But may thy friends fare like the rising sun! </l>
       </lg>
     </p>
     <p>
       For forty years the land lay safe. <verse eID="Judg.5.31"/>
    <chapter eID="Judg.5"/>
    <chapter osisID="Judg.6" sID="Judg.6"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.6.1" osisID="Judg.6.1"/>
       But the Israelites did what was evil in the sight of the Eternal, and the Eternal handed them over to Midian for seven
       years. <verse eID="Judg.6.1"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.6.2" osisID="Judg.6.2"/> Midian gained the upper hand over Israel; it was to escape Midian that the
       Israel­ites made hiding-places among the mountains, caves, and strongholds. <verse eID="Judg.6.2"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.6.3" osisID="Judg.6.3"/> Whenever Israel had sown their crops, Midian and Amalek and the Bedawin would
       come up raiding, and, entrenching themselves, would destroy the produce of the country as far south as Gaza; <verse eID="Judg.6.3"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.6.4" osisID="Judg.6.4"/> they left Israel nothing to live on, neither sheep nor ox nor ass. <verse eID="Judg.6.4"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.6.5" osisID="Judg.6.5"/> For they would come up with their cattle, tents and all, swarming like locusts;
       they and their camels were past num­bering, and their coming was the ruin of the country. <verse eID="Judg.6.5"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.6.6" osisID="Judg.6.6"/> So Israel was greatly reduced, owing to Midian. The Israelites cried to the
       Eternal, <verse eID="Judg.6.6"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.6.7" osisID="Judg.6.7"/> and, when the Israelites cried to the Eternal on account of Midian, <verse eID="Judg.6.7"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.6.8" osisID="Judg.6.8"/> the Eternal sent the Israelites a prophet, who gave them this message from the
       Eternal, God of Israel: <q>I brought you out of Egypt, I brought you from that slave-pen, <verse eID="Judg.6.8"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.6.9" osisID="Judg.6.9"/> I rescued you from the power of Egypt and from the grip of all your oppressors, I
       dis­possessed your foes in front of you and gave you their land, and I said to you, <verse eID="Judg.6.9"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.6.10" osisID="Judg.6.10"/> I am the Eternal, your God; you must not revere the gods of the Amorites in
       whose
       <milestone type="pb" n="278"/>
       land you are living. But you have not heeded what I said.</q> <verse eID="Judg.6.10"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.6.11" osisID="Judg.6.11"/> Now the angel of the Eternal came and sat down under the sacred tree at Ophrah,
       which belonged to Joash the Abiezrite. His son Gideon was beat­ing out some wheat inside the winepress, to save it from
       Midian; <verse eID="Judg.6.11"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.6.12" osisID="Judg.6.12"/> and to him the angel of the Eternal appeared, saying, <q>You stalwart hero, the
       Eternal is with you!</q> <verse eID="Judg.6.12"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.6.13" osisID="Judg.6.13"/> <q>The Eternal with us, my lord?</q> said Gideon. <q>Then why has all this
       hap­pened to us? Where are all his deeds of wonder that our fathers recounted to us? They said, <q>Did not the Eternal
       bring us out of Egypt?</q> But now the Eternal has thrown us aside, he has abandoned us to Midian!</q> <verse eID="Judg.6.13"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.6.14" osisID="Judg.6.14"/> The Eternal turned to him and said, <q>Go with this strength of your own, and
       rescue Israel from Midian. Am I not sending you?</q> <verse eID="Judg.6.14"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.6.15" osisID="Judg.6.15"/><q>But, my lord,</q> said Gideon, <q>how am I to rescue Israel? My sept is the
       weakest in Manasseh, and I have least weight in my family.</q> <verse eID="Judg.6.15"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.6.16" osisID="Judg.6.16"/> The Eternal said to him, <q>I will be with you, and you shall de­feat Midian,
       every man of them.</q> <verse eID="Judg.6.16"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.6.17" osisID="Judg.6.17"/> Gideon said to him, <q>If I find favour with you, pray let me have a proof that
       you are speaking to me; <verse eID="Judg.6.17"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.6.18" osisID="Judg.6.18"/> pray do not leave until I come back and offer you my present.</q> <q>I will
       wait till you return, </q> he answered. <verse eID="Judg.6.18"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.6.19" osisID="Judg.6.19"/> So Gideon went indoors, prepared a kid, and made a bushel of flour into
       unleavened cakes; the meat he put in a basket, the broth in a pot, and then he brought out the food and presented it to
       him under the sacred tree. <verse eID="Judg.6.19"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.6.20" osisID="Judg.6.20"/> But the angel of God said to him, <q>Take the meat and the unleavened cakes,
       and put them on the rock yonder; pour the broth over them.</q> <verse eID="Judg.6.20"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.6.21" osisID="Judg.6.21"/> He did so; and the angel of the Eternal, reaching out the tip of the stick in
       his hand, touched the meat and the un­leavened cakes. Then fire spurted out of the rock and burned up the meat and the
       un­leavened cakes. <verse eID="Judg.6.21"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.6.22" osisID="Judg.6.22"/> So Gideon realized it was the angel of the Eter­nal. <q>Alas! my lord the
       Eter­nal!</q> he cried, <q>I have seen the angel of the Eternal face to face!</q> <verse eID="Judg.6.22"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.6.23" osisID="Judg.6.23"/> But the Eternal said to him, <q>All is well, have no fear; you are not to die!
       </q> <verse eID="Judg.6.23"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.6.24" osisID="Judg.6.24"/> Then the angel of the Eternal vanished from his sight, and Gideon erected an altar
       to the Eternal on the spot, calling it <q>Allswell-Eternal.</q> It stands to this day at Ophrah, which belongs to the
       Abiezrites. <verse eID="Judg.6.24"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.6.25" osisID="Judg.6.25"/> That very night the Eternal said to him, <q>Take ten of your servants, and take
       a seven-year-old bull; pull down the altar of Baal that belongs to your father, cutting down the sacred pole beside it, <verse eID="Judg.6.25"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.6.26" osisID="Judg.6.26"/> and then erect an altar in due form to the Eternal your God on the summit of
       this stronghold, burning the bull in sacrifice with the wood of the sacred pole that you are to cut down.</q> <verse eID="Judg.6.26"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.6.27" osisID="Judg.6.27"/> So Gideon took ten of his servants and did as the Eternal told him; but he did
       it by night; so terrified was he of his father's family and of the towns­folk, that he dared not do it by day. <verse eID="Judg.6.27"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.6.28" osisID="Judg.6.28"/> When the townsfolk rose in the morning, there was Baal's altar broken down, the
       sacred pole cut down, and the bull sacrificed on the altar that had been erected! <verse eID="Judg.6.28"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.6.29" osisID="Judg.6.29"/> They said to each other, <q>Who has
       <milestone type="pb" n="279"/>
       done this?</q> And after making strict inquiry they found that Gideon the son of Joash had done it. <verse eID="Judg.6.29"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.6.30" osisID="Judg.6.30"/> The townsfolk said to Joash, <q>Bring out your son; he must die. He has broken
       down Baal’s altar and cut down the sacred pole beside it.</q> <verse eID="Judg.6.30"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.6.31" osisID="Judg.6.31"/> But Joash said to all his opponents, <q>And are you going to fight Baal’s
       battles? Are you to be his champions? Whoever fights for him shall be put to death next morning! If he is a god, let him
       fight for himself!</q> <verse eID="Judg.6.31"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.6.32" osisID="Judg.6.32"/> So Gideon was called that day <q>Jerubbaal</q> (or Baalfight), meaning, <q>Let
       Baal fight with him, since he broke down his altar!</q> <verse eID="Judg.6.32"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.6.33" osisID="Judg.6.33"/> Then all the Midianites and the Amalekites and the Bedawin mustered, crossed
       the Jordan, and encamped on the plain of Jezreel. <verse eID="Judg.6.33"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.6.34" osisID="Judg.6.34"/> But the spirit of the Eternal took hold of Gideon; he sounded the alarm,
       calling the Abiezrites to arms, <verse eID="Judg.6.34"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.6.35" osisID="Judg.6.35"/> and sent messengers all through Manasseh, calling them to arms, and also
       through Asher, Zebulun, and Naphtali, who marched out to battle. <verse eID="Judg.6.35"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.6.36" osisID="Judg.6.36"/> Then Gideon said to God, <q>If thou art going to rescue Israel by me, as thou
       hast said-- <verse eID="Judg.6.36"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.6.37" osisID="Judg.6.37"/> here I lay a fleece of wool upon the threshing-floor; if dew falls only on the
       fleece, and all the ground is dry, then I shall be sure that thou art going to res­cue Israel by me, as thou hast said.</q>
      <verse eID="Judg.6.37"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.6.38" osisID="Judg.6.38"/> This did happen. When he rose next morning, he wrung the fleece and squeezed
       out dew enough to fill a bowl. <verse eID="Judg.6.38"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.6.39" osisID="Judg.6.39"/> And Gideon said to God, <q>Let not thine anger blaze hotly against me; I will
       ask only one thing more. Pray let me try one more test with the fleece: pray let the fleece alone be dry, with dew on all
       the ground.</q> <verse eID="Judg.6.39"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.6.40" osisID="Judg.6.40"/> That night, God did it; the fleece alone was dry, and dew lay on all the
       ground. <verse eID="Judg.6.40"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eID="Judg.6"/>
   </div>