   <div type="book" osisID="Judg">
    <milestone type="pb" n="271"/>
    <chapter osisID="Judg.1" sID="Judg.1"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.1.1" osisID="Judg.1.1"/>After Joshua died, the Israel­ites asked the Eternal which of them was to march up
       first and attack the Canaanites. <verse eID="Judg.1.1"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.1.2" osisID="Judg.1.2"/> The Eternal answered, <q>Judah is to march up; I hand over the country to him.</q>
      <verse eID="Judg.1.2"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.1.3" osisID="Judg.1.3"/> So Judah said to his brother Simeon, <q>March with me into my allotted terri­tory,
       to attack the Canaanites, and then I will march with you into your allotted territory.</q> Simeon accompanied him <verse eID="Judg.1.3"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.1.4" osisID="Judg.1.4"/> [[and, when Judah marched up, the Eternal handed over to them the Canaanites and
       the Perizzites; they defeated ten thousand of them at Bezek]]. <verse eID="Judg.1.4"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.1.5" osisID="Judg.1.5"/> At Bezek they came upon Adoni-bezek and attacked him, defeat­ing the Canaanites and
       the Perizzites. <verse eID="Judg.1.5"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.1.6" osisID="Judg.1.6"/> Adonibezek fled, but they pursued him, cap­tured him, and lopped off his thumbs and
       his great toes. <verse eID="Judg.1.6"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.1.7" osisID="Judg.1.7"/><q>Seventy chiefs, with their thumbs and great toes lopped off, used to pick up their
       food under my table,</q> said Adoni­bezek; <q>as I did, so has God done to me in turn.</q> He was carried off to Jerusalem,
       and there he died. <verse eID="Judg.1.7"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.1.19" osisID="Judg.1.19"/> The Eternal was with the Judahites; they gained posses­sion of the highlands,
       although they were unable to evict the dwellers in the plain, who had iron chariots. <verse eID="Judg.1.19"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.1.21" osisID="Judg.1.21"/> Neither did the men of Judah evict the Jebusites who inhabited Jerusalem; the
       Jebusites lived among the men of Judah as they do to this day in Jerusalem. <verse eID="Judg.1.21"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.1.8" osisID="Judg.1.8"/> [[The men of Judah attacked and captured Jerusalem, giving no quarter and burning
       up the town. <verse eID="Judg.1.8"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.1.9" osisID="Judg.1.9"/> After that, the men of Judah marched off to attack the Canaanites who lived in the
       highlands, the Negeb, and the lowlands. <verse eID="Judg.1.9"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.1.10" osisID="Judg.1.10"/> Judah marched against the Canaanites who lived in Hebron (formerly called
       Kiriath-arba); they vanquished Sheshai, Ahiman, and TalmaiJ] <verse eID="Judg.1.10"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.1.11" osisID="Judg.1.11"/> Then they marched against the natives of Debir (formerly called Kiriath-sepher).
      <verse eID="Judg.1.11"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.1.12" osisID="Judg.1.12"/> Caleb declared, <q>Whoever attacks Kiriath-sepher and captures it, I will give
       him my daughter Achsah in marriage.</q> <verse eID="Judg.1.12"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.1.13" osisID="Judg.1.13"/> Othniel, the son of Caleb’s younger brother Kenaz, captured it. So Caleb gave
       him his daughter Achsah in marriage. <verse eID="Judg.1.13"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.1.14" osisID="Judg.1.14"/> When she arrived, Othniel induced her to ask her father for a tract of land as
       her dowry; so she alighted from her ass, and, when Caleb asked her what she wanted, <verse eID="Judg.1.14"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.1.15" osisID="Judg.1.15"/> she said to him, <q>Give me a parting present; as you have settled me in the dry
       south country, let me have some springs of water.</q> Then Caleb gave her the up­per springs and the lower springs. <verse eID="Judg.1.15"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.1.16" osisID="Judg.1.16"/> When Hobab the Kenite, the father-in-law of Moses, left Palmtown to accompany
       the men of Judah into the desert of Judah near Arad, he went on to settle among the Amalekites. <verse eID="Judg.1.16"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.1.17" osisID="Judg.1.17"/> But Judah accompanied his brother Simeon; they defeated the Canaanites who
       inhabited Zephath, and massacred them. So the place came to be called Sacredtown (Hormah). <verse eID="Judg.1.17"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.1.18" osisID="Judg.1.18"/> Judah also captured Gaza and its terri­tory, Ashkelon and its terri­tory and Ekron
       and its terri­tory; <verse eID="Judg.1.18"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.1.20" osisID="Judg.1.20"/> Hebron they assigned to Caleb, as Moses had ordered,
       <milestone type="pb" n="272"/>
       and Caleb ejected from it the three giants. <verse eID="Judg.1.20"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.1.22" osisID="Judg.1.22"/> The clansmen of Joseph marched also against Bethel. The Eternal was with them.
      <verse eID="Judg.1.22"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.1.23" osisID="Judg.1.23"/> When the clansmen of Joseph sent men to reconnoitre at Bethel (formerly called
       Luz), <verse eID="Judg.1.23"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.1.24" osisID="Judg.1.24"/> the scouts saw a man leaving the town and caught him; <q>Come, tell us,</q> they
       said, <q>how to get into the town, and we will treat you well.</q> <verse eID="Judg.1.24"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.1.25" osisID="Judg.1.25"/> So he showed them how to get into the town, and they stormed it, giving no
       quarter; they let the man and his family go free, <verse eID="Judg.1.25"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.1.26" osisID="Judg.1.26"/> and he went to the land of the Hittites, where he built a town, calling it Luz.
       That is its name to this day. <verse eID="Judg.1.26"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.1.27" osisID="Judg.1.27"/> Manasseh did not gain pos­session of Beth-shean and its townships, nor of Taanak
       and its townships; they did not evict the inhabitants of Dor and its townships, nor of Ibleam and its townships, nor of
       Megiddo and its townships. The Canaanites clung to this country. <verse eID="Judg.1.27"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.1.28" osisID="Judg.1.28"/> When Israel became a power, they forced the Canaanites to slave for them, but
       they never evicted them entirely. <verse eID="Judg.1.28"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.1.29" osisID="Judg.1.29"/> Eph­raim did not evict the Canaan­ites who lived at Gezer; the Canaanites lived
       among them in Gezer. <verse eID="Judg.1.29"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.1.30" osisID="Judg.1.30"/> Zebulun did not evict the inhabitants of Kitron or of Nahalal; the Canaanites
       lived among them and were turned into labour-gangs. <verse eID="Judg.1.30"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.1.31" osisID="Judg.1.31"/> Asher did not evict the inhabitants of Acco or of Sidon or of Ahlab or of Achzib
       or of Helbah or of Aphek or of Rehob; <verse eID="Judg.1.31"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.1.32" osisID="Judg.1.32"/> the Asherites lived among the native Canaanites, who could not be evicted. <verse eID="Judg.1.32"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.1.33" osisID="Judg.1.33"/> Naphtali did not evict the inhabitants of Beth-shemesh or of Beth-anath, but
       lived among the native Canaanites. The inhabitants of Beth-shemesh and Beth-anath, however, were turned into labour-gangs.
      <verse eID="Judg.1.33"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.1.34" osisID="Judg.1.34"/> As for the Danites, they were forced into the highlands by the Amorites, who
       would not allow them down into the plain. <verse eID="Judg.1.34"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.1.35" osisID="Judg.1.35"/> The Amorites clung to Harheres, Aijalon, and Shaalbim; but, as the clans­men of
       Joseph prevailed in pow­er, they were turned into labour-gangs. <verse eID="Judg.1.35"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.1.36" osisID="Judg.1.36"/> [[The frontier of the Edomites ran from the Scorpion Pass to Sela and beyond
       it.]] <verse eID="Judg.1.36"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eID="Judg.1"/>
    <chapter osisID="Judg.2" sID="Judg.2"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.2.1" osisID="Judg.2.1"/>Then the angel of the Eternal went from Gilgal up to Bethel, and said: <q>...I
       brought you out of Egypt into the land I swore to your fathers that I would give to you. I said that I would never break
       my compact with you, <verse eID="Judg.2.1"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.2.2" osisID="Judg.2.2"/> and that you must never make terms with the natives--you must pull down their
       altars. But you have not obeyed my orders. What is this you have done? <verse eID="Judg.2.2"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.2.3" osisID="Judg.2.3"/> So I add this word: <q>I will not dispossess them to make room for you: they shall
       be a scourge on your flanks, and their gods shall prove a danger to you.</q> <verse eID="Judg.2.3"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.2.4" osisID="Judg.2.4"/> When the angel of the Eternal said this to all the Israelites, the people burst
       into loud weeping. <verse eID="Judg.2.4"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.2.5" osisID="Judg.2.5"/> They called the place Bochim (or Weepers), and there they sacrificed to the
       Eternal.</q><verse eID="Judg.2.5"/>
     </p>
     <p> * * * * </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.2.6" osisID="Judg.2.6"/> When Joshua dismissed the people, the Israelites went back, each to his own
       property, to take possession of the country. <verse eID="Judg.2.6"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.2.7" osisID="Judg.2.7"/> During all the lifetime of Joshua and of the sheikhs who survived Joshua, who had
       seen all the great work done by the Eternal for Israel, the people continued to serve the Eternal. <verse eID="Judg.2.7"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.2.8" osisID="Judg.2.8"/> At the 8 age of a hundred and ten Joshua
       <milestone type="pb" n="273"/>
       the son of Nun, the servant of the Eternal, died. <verse eID="Judg.2.8"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.2.9" osisID="Judg.2.9"/> They buried him on his estate at Timnath-heres in the highlands of Eph­raim, north
       of mount Gaash. <verse eID="Judg.2.9"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.2.10" osisID="Judg.2.10"/> Then all that generation was gathered to their fathers, and another generation
       arose who knew nothing about the Eternal or the work he had done for Israel. <verse eID="Judg.2.10"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.2.11" osisID="Judg.2.11"/> These Israelites did what was evil in the sight of the Eternal, serving the
       Baals <verse eID="Judg.2.11"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.2.12" osisID="Judg.2.12"/> and forsaking the Eternal, the God of their fathers, who had brought them from
       the land of Egypt, running after other gods belonging to the gods of the nations around, and bowing down to them; <verse eID="Judg.2.12"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.2.13" osisID="Judg.2.13"/> they vexed the Eternal by forsaking the Eternal and sacrificing to Baal and
       Astarte. <verse eID="Judg.2.13"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.2.14" osisID="Judg.2.14"/> So the anger of the Eternal blazed against Israel; he handed them over to
       plun­derers who plundered them, he sold them into the power of their enemies around, till they could no longer hold their
       own against their enemies; <verse eID="Judg.2.14"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.2.15" osisID="Judg.2.15"/> wherever they marched, the Eternal’s hand was against them for evil, as the
       Eternal had threatened and sworn. They were in a sore plight. <verse eID="Judg.2.15"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.2.16" osisID="Judg.2.16"/> The Eternal raised up heroes, who rescued them from their plunderers; <verse eID="Judg.2.16"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.2.17" osisID="Judg.2.17"/> but they would not listen even to their heroes. Faithlessly they went after
       other gods, bowing down to them; they soon swerved from the line of their fathers who obeyed the com­mands of the
       Eternal--which was not what they did. <verse eID="Judg.2.17"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.2.18" osisID="Judg.2.18"/> When the Eternal raised up heroes for them, the Eternal would be with the
       heroes and rescue them from the power of their enemies dur­ing all the days of the hero; for the Eternal was moved to pity
       by their groans under the grip of their tyrants and oppressors. <verse eID="Judg.2.18"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.2.19" osisID="Judg.2.19"/> But whenever the hero died, they would relapse and behave worse than ever,
       running after other gods, sacrificing to them and bowing before them; they would not drop any of their practices or
       stubborn ways. <verse eID="Judg.2.19"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.2.20" osisID="Judg.2.20"/> So the anger of the Eternal blazed against Israel; he said, <q>As this nation
       has violated the compact which I enjoined upon their fathers and has not listened to my orders, <verse eID="Judg.2.20"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.2.21" osisID="Judg.2.21"/> I will no longer evict for them any of the nations that Joshua left when he
       died</q><verse eID="Judg.2.21"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.2.22" osisID="Judg.2.22"/>--His aim being to test Israel by means of them, to see whether or not they would
       live by the rules of the Eternal as their fathers did. <verse eID="Judg.2.22"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.2.23" osisID="Judg.2.23"/> So the Eternal left these nations, in­stead of evicting them all at once[[; he
       did not hand them over to Joshua]]. <verse eID="Judg.2.23"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eID="Judg.2"/>
    <chapter osisID="Judg.3" sID="Judg.3"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.3.1" osisID="Judg.3.1"/>The following are the nations left by the Eternal as a test for all the Israelites
       who had had no experience of the war of invasion in Canaan--<verse eID="Judg.3.1"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.3.2" osisID="Judg.3.2"/>simply for giving lessons in war­fare to these generations of Israelites who
       hitherto knew nothing about fighting; <verse eID="Judg.3.2"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.3.3" osisID="Judg.3.3"/> there were the five tyrants of the Philistines, all the Canaanites, the
       Phoenicians, and the Hittites of mount Lebanon, stretch­ing from mount Baal-hermon to the pass of Hamath. <verse eID="Judg.3.3"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.3.4" osisID="Judg.3.4"/> They served as a test, to show whether Israel would obey what the Eternal had
       commanded their fathers through Moses. <verse eID="Judg.3.4"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.3.5" osisID="Judg.3.5"/> As the Israelites lived among the Canaanites, the Hittites, the Amorites, the
       Perizzites, the Hivites, and the Jebusites,
      <verse eID="Judg.3.5"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.3.6" osisID="Judg.3.6"/> they married their daughters,
       <milestone type="pb" n="274"/>
       married their own daughters to their sons, and sacrificed to their gods. <verse eID="Judg.3.6"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.3.7" osisID="Judg.3.7"/> The Israelites did what was evil in the sight of the Eternal, forgetting the
       Eternal their own God and worshipping the Baals and sacred poles. <verse eID="Judg.3.7"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.3.8" osisID="Judg.3.8"/> So the anger of the Eternal flamed hot against Israel; he sold them into the
       power of Kushan-rishathaim the king of Mesopo­tamia, and for eight years the Israelites were subject to Kushan-rishathaim.
      <verse eID="Judg.3.8"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.3.9" osisID="Judg.3.9"/> Then the Israelites cried to the Eternal, and the Eternal raised up a champion for
       the Israelites, who rescued them; it was Othniel, the son of Caleb’s younger brother, Kenaz. <verse eID="Judg.3.9"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.3.10" osisID="Judg.3.10"/> The spirit of the Eternal in­spired him; he avenged Israel. When he marched out
       to battle, the Eternal handed over to him Kushan-rishathaim the king of Mesopotamia, till he got the upper hand of
       Kushan-rishathaim. <verse eID="Judg.3.10"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.3.11" osisID="Judg.3.11"/> For forty years the land lay safe. Then Othniel the son of Kenaz died, <verse eID="Judg.3.11"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.3.12" osisID="Judg.3.12"/> and again the Israelites did what was evil in the sight of the Eternal. So the
       Eternal made Eglon the king of Moab gain the upper hand over Israel, since they had done what was evil in the sight of the
       Eternal. <verse eID="Judg.3.12"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.3.13" osisID="Judg.3.13"/> Eglon, collecting the Ammonites and the Amalekites, went and defeated Israel,
       seizing Palmtown; <verse eID="Judg.3.13"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.3.14" osisID="Judg.3.14"/> and for eighteen years the Israelites were subject to Eglon the king of Moab.
      <verse eID="Judg.3.14"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.3.15" osisID="Judg.3.15"/> Then Israel cried to the Eternal, and the Eternal raised up a champion for them;
       it was Ehud the son of Gera, a Benjamite who was left-handed. He carried tribute from the Israel­ites to Eglon the king of
       Moab. <verse eID="Judg.3.15"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.3.16" osisID="Judg.3.16"/> On his right thigh under his clothes, Ehud hung a dirk which he had made, a
       two-edged weapon eighteen inches long. <verse eID="Judg.3.16"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.3.17" osisID="Judg.3.17"/> He presented the tribute to Eglon the king of Moab (Eglon was a very fat man),
      <verse eID="Judg.3.17"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.3.18" osisID="Judg.3.18"/> and when he had finished presenting the tribute, he dismissed the car­riers.
      <verse eID="Judg.3.18"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.3.19" osisID="Judg.3.19"/> He himself halted at the sculptured stones near Gilgal, and went back, saying,
       <q>I have a private message for you, O king.</q> <q>Silence!</q> said Eglon to his attendants, and they all left him. <verse eID="Judg.3.19"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.3.20" osisID="Judg.3.20"/> Then Ehud went in to see him, as he sat alone in his cool upper room. <q>I have
       a message from God for you,</q> said Ehud. As Eglon rose from his chair, <verse eID="Judg.3.20"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.3.21" osisID="Judg.3.21"/> Ehud put out his left hand, drew the dirk from his right thigh, and drove it
       into his belly; <verse eID="Judg.3.21"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.3.22" osisID="Judg.3.22"/> the hilt went in after the blade, and the fat closed over the blade, for he did
       not draw the dirk out of his belly. <verse eID="Judg.3.22"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.3.23" osisID="Judg.3.23"/> Ehud then went out into the vestibule, shutting the doors of the room and
       locking Eglon in. <verse eID="Judg.3.23"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.3.24" osisID="Judg.3.24"/> After he had gone, the king’s servants came; they saw that the doors of the
       upper room were locked, but they thought that he must be relieving him­self in the closet of the upper chamber. <verse eID="Judg.3.24"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.3.25" osisID="Judg.3.25"/> They waited, till they were at their wits' end. As he did not open the doors of
       the upper room, they opened them with a key--and there lay their lord dead on the floor! <verse eID="Judg.3.25"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.3.26" osisID="Judg.3.26"/> Meantime, as they were waiting, Ehud had escaped, past the sculptured stones,
       safe to Seirah. <verse eID="Judg.3.26"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.3.27" osisID="Judg.3.27"/> When he got there, he sounded the alarm through the high­lands of Ephraim, and
       the Is­raelites accompanied him from the highlands as their leader. <verse eID="Judg.3.27"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.3.28" osisID="Judg.3.28"/> <q>Follow me down,</q> he cried, <q>the Eternal has handed you over your enemies
       in Moab!</q> So they marched after him and
       <milestone type="pb" n="275"/>
       seized the fords of the Jordan, preventing any Moabite from crossing. <verse eID="Judg.3.28"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.3.29" osisID="Judg.3.29"/> They slew that day about ten thousand Moabites, stout warriors, all of them;
       not a man escaped. <verse eID="Judg.3.29"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.3.30" osisID="Judg.3.30"/> Moab was subdued that day by Israel, and for eighty years the land lay safe. <verse eID="Judg.3.30"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.3.31" osisID="Judg.3.31"/> After him came Shamgar the son of Anath, who killed six hundred Philistines with
       an ox-goad; he also rescued Israel. <verse eID="Judg.3.31"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eID="Judg.3"/>
    <chapter osisID="Judg.4" sID="Judg.4"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.4.1" osisID="Judg.4.1"/>When Ehud died, the Israel­ites again did evil in the sight of the Eternal. <verse eID="Judg.4.1"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.4.2" osisID="Judg.4.2"/> So the Eternal sold them into the power of Jabin the king of Canaan, who reigned
       in Hazor; his general was Sisera, who lived at Harosheth-of-the-nations. <verse eID="Judg.4.2"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.4.3" osisID="Judg.4.3"/> And the Israelites cried to the Eternal, for Jabin had nine hundred iron chariots,
       and for twenty years he oppressed Israel cruelly. <verse eID="Judg.4.3"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.4.4" osisID="Judg.4.4"/> At that time Israel was being managed by Deborah a prophetess, the wife of
       Lapidoth, <verse eID="Judg.4.4"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.4.5" osisID="Judg.4.5"/> who used to sit under the Deborah palm-tree between Ramah and Bethel in the
       highlands of Eph­raim, deciding cases brought to her by the Israelites. <verse eID="Judg.4.5"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.4.6" osisID="Judg.4.6"/> She sent to summon Barak the son of Abinoam from Kedesh in Naphtali, and told him,
       <q>Does not the Eternal, the God of Israel, order you to march on mount Tabor with ten thousand men from Naphtali and
        Zebulun, <verse eID="Judg.4.6"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.4.7" osisID="Judg.4.7"/> saying, <q>I will draw Sisera, Jabin's general, to meet you at the Kishon wady with
       his char­iots and his troops, and put him in your power</q>?</q> <verse eID="Judg.4.7"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.4.8" osisID="Judg.4.8"/> Barak said to her, <q>If you will come with me, I will go; but if you will not
       come with me, I will not.</q> <verse eID="Judg.4.8"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.4.9" osisID="Judg.4.9"/> She answered, <q>I will certainly come with you. Only, the glory of the expedition
       will not be yours; for the Eternal will sell Sisera into a woman’s hand.</q> Then Deborah went with Barak to Kedesh. <verse eID="Judg.4.9"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.4.10" osisID="Judg.4.10"/> Barak summoned Zebulun and Naph­tali to Kedesh; ten thousand men were at his
       back, and Deborah marched with him. <verse eID="Judg.4.10"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.4.11" osisID="Judg.4.11"/> (Now Heber the Kenite had withdrawn from the Kenites, the sept of Hobab the
       father-in-law of Moses, pitching his tent as far north as the oak of Basaanim near Kedesh.) <verse eID="Judg.4.11"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.4.12" osisID="Judg.4.12"/> Learning that Barak the son of Abinoam had marched to mount Tabor, <verse eID="Judg.4.12"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.4.13" osisID="Judg.4.13"/> Sisera summoned all his chariots, nine hundred iron chariots, and all his
       forces, from Harosheth-of-the-nations to the Kishon wady. <verse eID="Judg.4.13"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.4.14" osisID="Judg.4.14"/> Then said Deborah to Barak, <q>Up! this is the day when the Eternal puts Sisera
       in your power! Is not the Eternal marching in front of you?</q> So Barak, with ten thousand men at his back, charged down
       from mount Tabor, <verse eID="Judg.4.14"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.4.15" osisID="Judg.4.15"/> and the Eternal routed Sisera and all his char­iots and all his army before
       Barak. Sisera alighted from his chariot and fled on foot; <verse eID="Judg.4.15"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.4.16" osisID="Judg.4.16"/> but Barak pursued the chariots and the army as far as Harosheth-of-the-nations,
       killing the entire army of Sisera and giving no quarter; not a single man was left. <verse eID="Judg.4.16"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.4.17" osisID="Judg.4.17"/> Sisera, however, fled on foot to the tent of Jael the wife of Heber the Kenite;
       for Jabin the king of Hazor and the family of Heber the Kenite were on friendly terms. <verse eID="Judg.4.17"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.4.18" osisID="Judg.4.18"/> Jael came out to meet Sisera, saying, <q>Turn in, my lord, turn into my tent;
       have no fear!</q> So he turned into her tent, and she covered him up with a rug. <verse eID="Judg.4.18"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.4.19" osisID="Judg.4.19"/> He said to her, <q>Pray give me a little water, for I am thirsty.</q> So she
       opened her skin of milk,
       <milestone type="pb" n="276"/>
       gave him a drink, and covered him up again. <verse eID="Judg.4.19"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.4.20" osisID="Judg.4.20"/> He said to her, <q>Stand at the door of the tent, and then, if anyone comes and
       asks you if there is a man here, say no.</q> <verse eID="Judg.4.20"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.4.21" osisID="Judg.4.21"/> But Jael the wife of Heber the Kenite took a tent-peg and a mallet in her hand,
       and, slipping quietly up to him, she drove the peg into his temple right through to the ground--for he was fast asleep and
       exhausted; so he died. <verse eID="Judg.4.21"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.4.22" osisID="Judg.4.22"/> Up came Barak in pursuit of Sisera; and Jael went out to meet him, saying,
       <q>Here, I will show you the man you are looking for!</q> So Barak went inside her tent, and there lay Sisera dead, with
        the tent-peg in his temple! <verse eID="Judg.4.22"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.4.23" osisID="Judg.4.23"/> Thus did God that day subdue Jabin the king of Canaan before the Israelites;
      <verse eID="Judg.4.23"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.4.24" osisID="Judg.4.24"/> the Israelites bore harder and harder upon Jabin the king of Canaan, till they
       finally destroyed Jabin the king of Canaan. <verse eID="Judg.4.24"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eID="Judg.4"/>
    <chapter osisID="Judg.5" sID="Judg.5"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.5.1" osisID="Judg.5.1"/>On that day Deborah sang with Barak the son of Abinoam:
      <verse eID="Judg.5.1"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.5.2" osisID="Judg.5.2"/> That Israel’s leaders took the lead, that the folk came forward freely, bless
       the Eternal! <verse eID="Judg.5.2"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.5.3" osisID="Judg.5.3"/>
       <lg>
        <l> Listen, O kings, </l>
        <l> rulers, hear! </l>
        <l> I will sing to the Eternal, </l>
        <l> to Israel’s God I chant, to the Eternal. </l>
       </lg>
      <verse eID="Judg.5.3"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.5.4" osisID="Judg.5.4"/>
       <lg>
        <l> At thine advance from Seir, O Eternal, </l>
        <l> upon thy march from Edom’s land, </l>
        <l> earth was shaking, </l>
        <l> the skies quaking, </l>
        <l> clouds dripped water, </l>
      <verse eID="Judg.5.4"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.5.5" osisID="Judg.5.5"/>
        <l> mountains streamed, </l>
        <l> in front of the Eternal, Israel’s God. </l>
       </lg>
      <verse eID="Judg.5.5"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.5.6" osisID="Judg.5.6"/>
       <lg>
        <l> In Shamgar’s day, the son of Anath,
        </l>
        <l> in the years gone by, </l>
        <l> the caravans had ceased, </l>
        <l> wayfarers kept to the by-roads, </l>
      <verse eID="Judg.5.6"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.5.7" osisID="Judg.5.7"/>
        <l> and Israel’s hamlets were deserted--
        </l>
        <l> till I arose, Deborah, </l>
        <l> a matron within Israel. </l>
      <verse eID="Judg.5.7"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.5.8" osisID="Judg.5.8"/>
        <l> Not one shield for five towns then! </l>
        <l> not a lance for Israel’s forty thou­sand men!</l>
      <verse eID="Judg.5.8"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.5.9" osisID="Judg.5.9"/>
        <l> But Israel had leaders--my heart goes out to them-- </l>
        <l> folk who came forward! Bless the Eternal! </l>
       </lg>
      <verse eID="Judg.5.9"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.5.10" osisID="Judg.5.10"/>
       <lg>
        <l> Tell of them, you on your tawny asses, </l>
        <l> riding on your rugs, </l>
        <l> and you that tramp the roads! </l>
      <verse eID="Judg.5.10"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.5.11" osisID="Judg.5.11"/>
        <l>Far from the whizzing of arrows, </l>
        <l> where cattle are watered, </l>
        <l> men tell how the Eternal upholds the right, </l>
        <l> upholds it for Israel’s hamlets.</l>
       </lg>
      <verse eID="Judg.5.11"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.5.12" osisID="Judg.5.12"/>
       <lg>
        <l> Up, O Deborah, </l>
        <l> up, up, with your war-cry! </l>
        <l> To your feet, O Barak son of Abinoam, </l>
        <l> and capture your captors! </l>
       </lg>
      <verse eID="Judg.5.12"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.5.13" osisID="Judg.5.13"/>
       <lg>
        <l> Out the folk of the Eternal marched, </l>
        <l> out came all the nobles left, </l>
        <l> out for the Eternal marched his folk like heroes, </l>
      <verse eID="Judg.5.13"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.5.14" osisID="Judg.5.14"/>
        <l> wheeling from Ephraim into the glen--
        </l>
        <l> <q>We follow you, Benjamin, your clan’s men!</q> </l>
        <l> Out from Machir came com­manders, </l>
        <l> adjutants from Zebulun; </l>
      <verse eID="Judg.5.14"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.5.15" osisID="Judg.5.15"/>
        <l> Issachar’s chieftains rallied to Deborah, </l>
        <l> as Naphtali backed up Barak, </l>
        <l> tearing down at his heels to the glen. </l>
        <l> But in the shires of Reuben </l>
        <l> were divisions and debates. </l>
      <verse eID="Judg.5.15"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.5.16" osisID="Judg.5.16"/>
        <l> Why did you lounge by shepherds' cotes, </l>
        <l> with only an ear for pastoral notes? </l>
      <verse eID="Judg.5.16"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.5.17" osisID="Judg.5.17"/>
        <l> East of the Jordan the Gileadites stayed; </l>
        <l> Dan held to his ships; </l>
        <l> Asher sat still by the seaboard, </l>
        <l> clinging to his creeks. </l>
      <verse eID="Judg.5.17"/>
      <milestone type="pb" n="277"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.5.18" osisID="Judg.5.18"/>
        <l> But Zebulun--the clan risked life and death </l>
        <l> with Naphtali out in the open field! </l>
       </lg>
      <verse eID="Judg.5.18"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.5.19" osisID="Judg.5.19"/>
       <lg>
        <l> On came the kings, came at them, </l>
        <l> Canaan’s kings came at them, </l>
        <l> by Taanak, on Megiddo’s streams; </l>
        <l> and much they made of it! </l>
      <verse eID="Judg.5.19"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.5.20" osisID="Judg.5.20"/>
        <l> The very stars in heaven were fighting, </l>
        <l> fighting Sisera from their spheres; </l>
      <verse eID="Judg.5.20"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.5.21" osisID="Judg.5.21"/>
        <l> Kishon’s torrent swept the foe off, </l>
        <l> Kishon’s torrent in their faces! </l>
        <l> (Bless the Eternal’s power, my soul!) </l>
      <verse eID="Judg.5.21"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.5.22" osisID="Judg.5.22"/>
        <l> Then thudded hoofs of horses, </l>
        <l> as the chargers thundered away. </l>
       </lg>
      <verse eID="Judg.5.22"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.5.23" osisID="Judg.5.23"/>
       <lg>
        <l> Curse Meroz, the Eternal’s angel cries, </l>
        <l> blast her burghers with a curse! </l>
        <l> They never came to the Eternal’s aid, </l>
        <l> to the Eternal’s aid, to join the heroes! </l>
      <verse eID="Judg.5.23"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.5.24" osisID="Judg.5.24"/>
        <l> But blest above women be Jael, </l>
        <l> blest above Bedawin women! </l>
      <verse eID="Judg.5.24"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.5.25" osisID="Judg.5.25"/>
        <l> Water he asked, and milk she gave him, </l>
        <l> brought him curds in a lordly bowl, </l>
      <verse eID="Judg.5.25"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.5.26" osisID="Judg.5.26"/>
        <l> laid her hand upon a tent-pin, </l>
        <l> laid her right hand on a mallet, </l>
        <l> and pounded Sisera, shattered his head, </l>
        <l> smashed him, crashed his tem­ple in; </l>
      <verse eID="Judg.5.26"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.5.27" osisID="Judg.5.27"/>
        <l> he sank at her feet, he fell down dead, </l>
        <l> and where he sank he fell--her victim! </l>
       </lg>
      <verse eID="Judg.5.27"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.5.28" osisID="Judg.5.28"/>
       <lg>
        <l> Out of the window she leans and peers, </l>
        <l> Sisera’s mother, out of the lattice:</l>
        <q><l>Why are his chariots lingering? Why?</l>
        <l>Why is the sound of his wheels so long?</l></q>
      <verse eID="Judg.5.28"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.5.29" osisID="Judg.5.29"/>
        <l> And her ladies (so knowing) reply--</l>
        <l> nay, she answers herself as they answer--</l>
      <verse eID="Judg.5.29"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.5.30" osisID="Judg.5.30"/>
        <q><l> They must be dividing the spoil </l>
        <l> they have taken, a wench or two wenches apiece, </l>
        <l> dyed robes for Sisera’s share, and brocade and brocades, for my neck!</l></q>
       </lg>
      <verse eID="Judg.5.30"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.5.31" osisID="Judg.5.31"/>
       <lg>
        <l> So be thy foes, Eternal, all undone! </l>
        <l> But may thy friends fare like the rising sun! </l>
       </lg>
     </p>
     <p>
       For forty years the land lay safe. <verse eID="Judg.5.31"/>
    <chapter eID="Judg.5"/>
    <chapter osisID="Judg.6" sID="Judg.6"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.6.1" osisID="Judg.6.1"/>
       But the Israelites did what was evil in the sight of the Eternal, and the Eternal handed them over to Midian for seven
       years. <verse eID="Judg.6.1"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.6.2" osisID="Judg.6.2"/> Midian gained the upper hand over Israel; it was to escape Midian that the
       Israel­ites made hiding-places among the mountains, caves, and strongholds. <verse eID="Judg.6.2"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.6.3" osisID="Judg.6.3"/> Whenever Israel had sown their crops, Midian and Amalek and the Bedawin would
       come up raiding, and, entrenching themselves, would destroy the produce of the country as far south as Gaza; <verse eID="Judg.6.3"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.6.4" osisID="Judg.6.4"/> they left Israel nothing to live on, neither sheep nor ox nor ass. <verse eID="Judg.6.4"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.6.5" osisID="Judg.6.5"/> For they would come up with their cattle, tents and all, swarming like locusts;
       they and their camels were past num­bering, and their coming was the ruin of the country. <verse eID="Judg.6.5"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.6.6" osisID="Judg.6.6"/> So Israel was greatly reduced, owing to Midian. The Israelites cried to the
       Eternal, <verse eID="Judg.6.6"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.6.7" osisID="Judg.6.7"/> and, when the Israelites cried to the Eternal on account of Midian, <verse eID="Judg.6.7"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.6.8" osisID="Judg.6.8"/> the Eternal sent the Israelites a prophet, who gave them this message from the
       Eternal, God of Israel: <q>I brought you out of Egypt, I brought you from that slave-pen, <verse eID="Judg.6.8"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.6.9" osisID="Judg.6.9"/> I rescued you from the power of Egypt and from the grip of all your oppressors, I
       dis­possessed your foes in front of you and gave you their land, and I said to you, <verse eID="Judg.6.9"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.6.10" osisID="Judg.6.10"/> I am the Eternal, your God; you must not revere the gods of the Amorites in
       whose
       <milestone type="pb" n="278"/>
       land you are living. But you have not heeded what I said.</q> <verse eID="Judg.6.10"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.6.11" osisID="Judg.6.11"/> Now the angel of the Eternal came and sat down under the sacred tree at Ophrah,
       which belonged to Joash the Abiezrite. His son Gideon was beat­ing out some wheat inside the winepress, to save it from
       Midian; <verse eID="Judg.6.11"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.6.12" osisID="Judg.6.12"/> and to him the angel of the Eternal appeared, saying, <q>You stalwart hero, the
       Eternal is with you!</q> <verse eID="Judg.6.12"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.6.13" osisID="Judg.6.13"/> <q>The Eternal with us, my lord?</q> said Gideon. <q>Then why has all this
       hap­pened to us? Where are all his deeds of wonder that our fathers recounted to us? They said, <q>Did not the Eternal
       bring us out of Egypt?</q> But now the Eternal has thrown us aside, he has abandoned us to Midian!</q> <verse eID="Judg.6.13"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.6.14" osisID="Judg.6.14"/> The Eternal turned to him and said, <q>Go with this strength of your own, and
       rescue Israel from Midian. Am I not sending you?</q> <verse eID="Judg.6.14"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.6.15" osisID="Judg.6.15"/><q>But, my lord,</q> said Gideon, <q>how am I to rescue Israel? My sept is the
       weakest in Manasseh, and I have least weight in my family.</q> <verse eID="Judg.6.15"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.6.16" osisID="Judg.6.16"/> The Eternal said to him, <q>I will be with you, and you shall de­feat Midian,
       every man of them.</q> <verse eID="Judg.6.16"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.6.17" osisID="Judg.6.17"/> Gideon said to him, <q>If I find favour with you, pray let me have a proof that
       you are speaking to me; <verse eID="Judg.6.17"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.6.18" osisID="Judg.6.18"/> pray do not leave until I come back and offer you my present.</q> <q>I will
       wait till you return, </q> he answered. <verse eID="Judg.6.18"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.6.19" osisID="Judg.6.19"/> So Gideon went indoors, prepared a kid, and made a bushel of flour into
       unleavened cakes; the meat he put in a basket, the broth in a pot, and then he brought out the food and presented it to
       him under the sacred tree. <verse eID="Judg.6.19"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.6.20" osisID="Judg.6.20"/> But the angel of God said to him, <q>Take the meat and the unleavened cakes,
       and put them on the rock yonder; pour the broth over them.</q> <verse eID="Judg.6.20"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.6.21" osisID="Judg.6.21"/> He did so; and the angel of the Eternal, reaching out the tip of the stick in
       his hand, touched the meat and the un­leavened cakes. Then fire spurted out of the rock and burned up the meat and the
       un­leavened cakes. <verse eID="Judg.6.21"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.6.22" osisID="Judg.6.22"/> So Gideon realized it was the angel of the Eter­nal. <q>Alas! my lord the
       Eter­nal!</q> he cried, <q>I have seen the angel of the Eternal face to face!</q> <verse eID="Judg.6.22"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.6.23" osisID="Judg.6.23"/> But the Eternal said to him, <q>All is well, have no fear; you are not to die!
       </q> <verse eID="Judg.6.23"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.6.24" osisID="Judg.6.24"/> Then the angel of the Eternal vanished from his sight, and Gideon erected an altar
       to the Eternal on the spot, calling it <q>Allswell-Eternal.</q> It stands to this day at Ophrah, which belongs to the
       Abiezrites. <verse eID="Judg.6.24"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.6.25" osisID="Judg.6.25"/> That very night the Eternal said to him, <q>Take ten of your servants, and take
       a seven-year-old bull; pull down the altar of Baal that belongs to your father, cutting down the sacred pole beside it, <verse eID="Judg.6.25"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.6.26" osisID="Judg.6.26"/> and then erect an altar in due form to the Eternal your God on the summit of
       this stronghold, burning the bull in sacrifice with the wood of the sacred pole that you are to cut down.</q> <verse eID="Judg.6.26"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.6.27" osisID="Judg.6.27"/> So Gideon took ten of his servants and did as the Eternal told him; but he did
       it by night; so terrified was he of his father's family and of the towns­folk, that he dared not do it by day. <verse eID="Judg.6.27"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.6.28" osisID="Judg.6.28"/> When the townsfolk rose in the morning, there was Baal's altar broken down, the
       sacred pole cut down, and the bull sacrificed on the altar that had been erected! <verse eID="Judg.6.28"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.6.29" osisID="Judg.6.29"/> They said to each other, <q>Who has
       <milestone type="pb" n="279"/>
       done this?</q> And after making strict inquiry they found that Gideon the son of Joash had done it. <verse eID="Judg.6.29"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.6.30" osisID="Judg.6.30"/> The townsfolk said to Joash, <q>Bring out your son; he must die. He has broken
       down Baal’s altar and cut down the sacred pole beside it.</q> <verse eID="Judg.6.30"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.6.31" osisID="Judg.6.31"/> But Joash said to all his opponents, <q>And are you going to fight Baal’s
       battles? Are you to be his champions? Whoever fights for him shall be put to death next morning! If he is a god, let him
       fight for himself!</q> <verse eID="Judg.6.31"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.6.32" osisID="Judg.6.32"/> So Gideon was called that day <q>Jerubbaal</q> (or Baalfight), meaning, <q>Let
       Baal fight with him, since he broke down his altar!</q> <verse eID="Judg.6.32"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.6.33" osisID="Judg.6.33"/> Then all the Midianites and the Amalekites and the Bedawin mustered, crossed
       the Jordan, and encamped on the plain of Jezreel. <verse eID="Judg.6.33"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.6.34" osisID="Judg.6.34"/> But the spirit of the Eternal took hold of Gideon; he sounded the alarm,
       calling the Abiezrites to arms, <verse eID="Judg.6.34"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.6.35" osisID="Judg.6.35"/> and sent messengers all through Manasseh, calling them to arms, and also
       through Asher, Zebulun, and Naphtali, who marched out to battle. <verse eID="Judg.6.35"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.6.36" osisID="Judg.6.36"/> Then Gideon said to God, <q>If thou art going to rescue Israel by me, as thou
       hast said-- <verse eID="Judg.6.36"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.6.37" osisID="Judg.6.37"/> here I lay a fleece of wool upon the threshing-floor; if dew falls only on the
       fleece, and all the ground is dry, then I shall be sure that thou art going to res­cue Israel by me, as thou hast said.</q>
      <verse eID="Judg.6.37"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.6.38" osisID="Judg.6.38"/> This did happen. When he rose next morning, he wrung the fleece and squeezed
       out dew enough to fill a bowl. <verse eID="Judg.6.38"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.6.39" osisID="Judg.6.39"/> And Gideon said to God, <q>Let not thine anger blaze hotly against me; I will
       ask only one thing more. Pray let me try one more test with the fleece: pray let the fleece alone be dry, with dew on all
       the ground.</q> <verse eID="Judg.6.39"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.6.40" osisID="Judg.6.40"/> That night, God did it; the fleece alone was dry, and dew lay on all the
       ground. <verse eID="Judg.6.40"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eID="Judg.6"/>
    <chapter osisID="Judg.7" sID="Judg.7"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.7.1" osisID="Judg.7.1"/>So Jerubbaal (that is, Gideon) and all his men rose early and encamped beside
       the spring of Harod, the Midianite camp lying north of Gibeath-Hammoreh on the plain. <verse eID="Judg.7.1"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.7.2" osisID="Judg.7.2"/> But the Eternal said to Gideon, <q>There are too many men with you, for me to
       hand over the Midianites; Israel might glory over me by claiming, <q>My own hand has ■won the victory.</q> <verse eID="Judg.7.2"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.7.3" osisID="Judg.7.3"/> Come now, issue this proclamation to the people, that <q>anyone who is
       terrified and trembling must go home.</q></q> Gideon applied this test, and twenty-two thousand went home, leaving ten
       thousand. <verse eID="Judg.7.3"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.7.4" osisID="Judg.7.4"/><q>There are still too many,</q> said the Eternal to Gideon; <q>take them down
       to the water, and let me sift them there; whenever I tell you, <q>this man shall go with you,</q> he is to go with you,
       and whenever I tell you, <q>this man shall not go with you,</q> he is not to go.</q> <verse eID="Judg.7.4"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.7.5" osisID="Judg.7.5"/> So Gideon took them down to the water. And the Eternal said, <q>Place on one
       side everyone who laps up the water with his tongue like a dog, and place on the other side everyone who kneels down to
       drink.</q> <verse eID="Judg.7.5"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.7.6" osisID="Judg.7.6"/> The men who lapped numbered three hundred; all the others knelt down to drink
       the water, putting their hands to their lips. <verse eID="Judg.7.6"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.7.7" osisID="Judg.7.7"/> Then the Eternal said to Gideon. <q>By the three hundred men who lapped I will
       rescue you and put Midian into your hands; let all the rest go home.</q> <verse eID="Judg.7.7"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.7.8" osisID="Judg.7.8"/> So he sent all the
       <milestone type="pb" n="280"/>
       Israelites home, every man of them, keeping only the three hundred, who took the pitchers belonging to the others and
       their trumpets. <verse eID="Judg.7.8"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.7.9" osisID="Judg.7.9"/> The Midianite camp lay below him in the valley. And that very night the Eternal
       said to him, <q>Get away down and attack the camp; I put it in your hands. <verse eID="Judg.7.9"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.7.10" osisID="Judg.7.10"/> If you are afraid to make an attack, steal down to the camp with your page
       Purah, <verse eID="Judg.7.10"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.7.11" osisID="Judg.7.11"/> and listen to their talk; that will encourage you to attack the camp.</q>
      So down he stole with his page Purah to the out­posts of armed sentries round the camp. <verse eID="Judg.7.11"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.7.12" osisID="Judg.7.12"/> The Midianites and the Amalekites and all the Bedawin were lying along the
       valley in swarms, like locusts, and their camels were past counting, as numerous as the sand on the sea-shore. <verse eID="Judg.7.12"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.7.13" osisID="Judg.7.13"/> When Gideon arrived, one man was telling his comrade a dream. <q>I had a
       dream,</q> he was saying; <q>there was a barley-cake rolling into the camp of Midian! It reached one tent and knocked
       it right over!</q> <verse eID="Judg.7.13"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.7.14" osisID="Judg.7.14"/> His comrade replied, <q>That is the men of Israel! God puts Midian and all
       the camp into their hands!</q> <verse eID="Judg.7.14"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.7.15" osisID="Judg.7.15"/> When Gideon heard the dream told and explained, he knelt down. Getting back
       to the camp of Israel, he said, <q>Up to your feet! The Eternal puts the camp of Midian into your hands!</q> <verse eID="Judg.7.15"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.7.16" osisID="Judg.7.16"/> Then he divided the three hundred men into three companies, furnishing them
       all with trumpets and empty pitchers and torches inside the pitchers. <verse eID="Judg.7.16"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.7.17" osisID="Judg.7.17"/> <q>Watch me,</q> he said, <q>and do as I do; when­ever I reach the outskirts
       of the camp, then you must do as I do; <verse eID="Judg.7.17"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.7.18" osisID="Judg.7.18"/> whenever I blow the trumpet, I and all my men, blow you the trumpet also all
       round the camp, crying, <q>For the Eter­nal and for Gideon!</q></q> <verse eID="Judg.7.18"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.7.19" osisID="Judg.7.19"/> So, when Gideon and his hundred men reached the outskirts of the camp at the
       beginning of the middle watch, just when the guard had been posted, they blew their trumpets and smashed the pitchers in
       their hands. <verse eID="Judg.7.19"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.7.20" osisID="Judg.7.20"/> All three companies blew their trumpets and shat­tered their pitchers, holding
       the torches in their left hands and the trumpets in their right, and shouting, <q>A sword for the Eternal and for
       Gideon!</q> <verse eID="Judg.7.20"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.7.21" osisID="Judg.7.21"/> They stood where they were, all round the camp, and the whole army, wakening
       up, fled with a wild cry; <verse eID="Judg.7.21"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.7.22" osisID="Judg.7.22"/> when the three hundred blew their trumpets, the Eter­nal set every man’s sword
       against his fellow throughout all the army, and they fled as far as Beth-shittah, in the di­rection of Sererah, as far as
       the edge of Abel-meholah near Tabbath. <verse eID="Judg.7.22"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.7.23" osisID="Judg.7.23"/> From Naphtali and Asher and all Manasseh the Israel­ites were summoned to
       pur­sue Midian, <verse eID="Judg.7.23"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.7.24" osisID="Judg.7.24"/> and Gideon sent messengers all over the high­lands of Ephraim, saying, <q>Come
       down against Midian and seize the streams as far as Beth-barah, seize the Jordan against them.</q> So all the men of
       Ephraim mustered, seized the streams as far as Beth-barah, seized the Jordan also, <verse eID="Judg.7.24"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.7.25" osisID="Judg.7.25"/> and captured the two chiefs of Midian, Oreb and Zeeb; Oreb they killed at
       Oreb’s Rock, Zeeb at Zeeb’s winepress, in their pursuit of Midian, and they brought the heads of Oreb and Zeeb to Gideon
       on the east side of the Jordan. <verse eID="Judg.7.25"/>
     </p>
     <milestone type="pb" n="281"/>
    <chapter eID="Judg.7"/>
    <chapter osisID="Judg.8" sID="Judg.8"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.8.1" osisID="Judg.8.1"/>The men of Ephraim then asked him, <q>What do you mean by treating us like
       this?--you never summoned us when you started the attack on Midian!</q> Bitterly did they upbraid him. <verse eID="Judg.8.1"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.8.2" osisID="Judg.8.2"/> But he replied, <q>What have I done, after all, compared to what you have?
       Surely what Ephraim has gleaned is richer than the full vintage of Abiezer. <verse eID="Judg.8.2"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.8.3" osisID="Judg.8.3"/> God has put the chiefs of Midian into your hand, Oreb and Zeeb. What have I
       been able to achieve, compared with you?</q> As he said that, their anger at him melted. <verse eID="Judg.8.3"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.8.4" osisID="Judg.8.4"/> When Gideon reached the Jordan and crossed it, he and his three hundred men,
       they were worn out and famishing. <verse eID="Judg.8.4"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.8.5" osisID="Judg.8.5"/> So he asked the men of Sukkoth, <q>Pray give my followers some loaves of
       bread, for they are worn out; we are in pursuit of Zebah and Zalmunna, the Midianite kings.</q><verse eID="Judg.8.5"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.8.6" osisID="Judg.8.6"/> <q>Give bread to your forces?</q> said the headmen of Sukkoth. <q>Are
       Zebah and Zalmunna already in your hands?</q> <verse eID="Judg.8.6"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.8.7" osisID="Judg.8.7"/> Gideon answered, <q>Very well, as soon as the Eternal has put Zebah and
       Zalmunna into my hands I will trample you naked among thorns of the desert and thistles!</q> <verse eID="Judg.8.7"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.8.8" osisID="Judg.8.8"/> He then marched up to Penuel and asked the men of Penuel for the same food;
       but they answered like the men of Sukkoth. <verse eID="Judg.8.8"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.8.9" osisID="Judg.8.9"/> So he told the men of Penuel, <q>When I come back in triumph, I will demolish
       this hold of yours!</q> <verse eID="Judg.8.9"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.8.10" osisID="Judg.8.10"/> Zebah and Zalmunna were at Karkor with their troops, about fifteen thousand
       of them--all that was left of the nomad host; for a hundred and twenty thousand warriors had fallen. <verse eID="Judg.8.10"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.8.11" osisID="Judg.8.11"/> Gideon marched up by the caravan route east of Nobah and Jogbehah, and
       attacked the army, which lay off its guard. <verse eID="Judg.8.11"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.8.12" osisID="Judg.8.12"/> Zebah and Zalmunna took to flight, but he pursued them and captured
       Midian’s two kings, Zebah and Zalmunna, while their whole army was panic-stricken. <verse eID="Judg.8.12"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.8.13" osisID="Judg.8.13"/> Then Gideon the son of Joash returned from the battle, from the pass of
       Heres. <verse eID="Judg.8.13"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.8.14" osisID="Judg.8.14"/> He caught a lad belonging to Sukkoth, who, on being ques­tioned, wrote down
       for him a list of the headmen of Sukkoth and its sheikhs, seventy-seven of them; <verse eID="Judg.8.14"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.8.15" osisID="Judg.8.15"/> and on reaching the men of Sukkoth he said, <q>Here are Zebah and Zalmunna!
       You taunted me about them, saying, <q>Give bread to your forces? Are Zebah and Zalmunna already in your hands?</q></q>
      <verse eID="Judg.8.15"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.8.16" osisID="Judg.8.16"/> Whereupon he laid the sheikhs of the town upon thorns of the desert and
       thistles, and trampled down these men of Sukkoth. <verse eID="Judg.8.16"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.8.17" osisID="Judg.8.17"/> He also demolished the hold of Penuel and killed the men of the town. <verse eID="Judg.8.17"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.8.18" osisID="Judg.8.18"/> Then he asked Zebah and Zalmunna, <q>Who were the men you killed at
       Tabor?</q> <q>Men like yourself,</q> they re­torted, <q>each like a monarch!</q> <verse eID="Judg.8.18"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.8.19" osisID="Judg.8.19"/> <q>They were my own brothers,</q> he said, <q>the sons of my mother. By the
       Eternal, if you had spared them, I would not be slaying you.</q> <verse eID="Judg.8.19"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.8.20" osisID="Judg.8.20"/> Then he told his eldest son Jether to go and slay them. But the lad did not
       draw his sword; he was afraid, for he was still a lad. <verse eID="Judg.8.20"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.8.21" osisID="Judg.8.21"/><q>Come 21 and slay us yourself,</q> said Zebah and Zalmunna; <q>a man
       strikes a man’s blow!</q> So Gid­eon went and killed Zebah and Zalmunna; he also took the collars from their camels.<verse eID="Judg.8.21"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.8.22" osisID="Judg.8.22"/> The Israelites then said to
       <milestone type="pb" n="282"/>
       Gideon, <q>Rule over us, you and your son, and your son’s son, for you have rescued us from Midian.</q> <verse eID="Judg.8.22"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.8.23" osisID="Judg.8.23"/> But Gideon said to them, <q>I will not rule over you, nor shall my son rule
       over you; the Eternal shall rule over you.</q> <verse eID="Judg.8.23"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.8.24" osisID="Judg.8.24"/> Gideon said to them, <q>But let me ask a favour; let every man of you give
       me the ear-rings from his booty</q> (they were golden ear-rings, for the men had been Ishmaelites). <verse eID="Judg.8.24"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.8.25" osisID="Judg.8.25"/> <q>Gladly,</q> they answered. So they spread out a mantle, and every man
       threw his ear-rings into it. <verse eID="Judg.8.25"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.8.26" osisID="Judg.8.26"/> The weight of the golden ear-rings which he had asked amounted to seventy
       pounds, in addi­tion to the collars and pendants and the purple robes worn by the kings of Midian and the collars from
       their camels. <verse eID="Judg.8.26"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.8.27" osisID="Judg.8.27"/> Gid­eon made out of this an orna­mental idol, which he set up in his native
       town of Ophrah; all Israel faithlessly resorted to it, until it proved a danger to Gideon and his house. <verse eID="Judg.8.27"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.8.28" osisID="Judg.8.28"/> Thus were the Midianites sub­dued by Israel; they never raised their heads
       again. During the lifetime of Gideon the land lay safe. <verse eID="Judg.8.28"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.8.29" osisID="Judg.8.29"/> Jerubbaal (or, Gideon) the son of Joash went to reside in his own house at
       Ophrah; <verse eID="Judg.8.29"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.8.30" osisID="Judg.8.30"/> he had seventy sons of his body, for he had many wives, <verse eID="Judg.8.30"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.8.31" osisID="Judg.8.31"/> and his concubine, who lived at Shechem, also bore him a son, whom he
       called Abimelek. <verse eID="Judg.8.31"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.8.32" osisID="Judg.8.32"/> At a good old age Gideon the son of Joash died, and was buried in the tomb
       of his father Joash at Ophrah, which belongs to the Abiezrites. <verse eID="Judg.8.32"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.8.33" osisID="Judg.8.33"/> [[No sooner had Gideon died than the Israelites again went faith­lessly
       astray after the Baals, and made Baal-berith their god. <verse eID="Judg.8.33"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.8.34" osisID="Judg.8.34"/> The Israelites forgot the Eter34 nal their God, who had rescued them from
       all their foes on every side, <verse eID="Judg.8.34"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.8.35" osisID="Judg.8.35"/> and they ill-treated the family of Jerubbaal (or Gid­eon), after all the
       good service he had rendered to Israel.]] <verse eID="Judg.8.35"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eID="Judg.8"/>
    <chapter osisID="Judg.9" sID="Judg.9"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.9.1" osisID="Judg.9.1"/>Abimelek the son of Jerubbaal went to his kinsmen at Shechem and talked to
       them and to the whole sept of his mother’s family; <verse eID="Judg.9.1"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.9.2" osisID="Judg.9.2"/> he said, <q>Pray ask all the citizens of Shechem whether it is better for
       them to have seventy men ruling over them, all the sons of Jerub­baal, or to have one man; also remind them that I am
       their own flesh and blood.</q> <verse eID="Judg.9.2"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.9.3" osisID="Judg.9.3"/> When his kinsmen repeated all this on his behalf to all the citizens of
       Shechem, their hearts in­clined to Abimelek. <q>He is our brother,</q> they said, <verse eID="Judg.9.3"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.9.4" osisID="Judg.9.4"/> and they gave him ten pounds in silver from the temple of Baal-berith.<verse eID="Judg.9.4"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.9.5" osisID="Judg.9.5"/> With this money Abimelek hired some worthless and reck­less followers;
     </p>
     <p>
       he went to his father’s house at Ophrah and there, on a single stone, he mur­dered seventy men, his brothers, the sons
       of Jerubbaal. Jotham, the youngest son of Jerubbaal, alone survived, for he hid him­self. <verse eID="Judg.9.5"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.9.6" osisID="Judg.9.6"/> Then all the citizens of Shechem and Beth-millo gath­ered and made Abimelek
       king beside the sacred tree at the standing-stone in Shechem. <verse eID="Judg.9.6"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.9.7" osisID="Judg.9.7"/> Jotham was told of this; he went and stood on the top of mount Gerizim,
       shouting aloud to them: <q>Citizens of Shechem, listen to me, that God may listen to you! <verse eID="Judg.9.7"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.9.8" osisID="Judg.9.8"/> Once upon a time the trees set out to elect themselves a king. They said to
       the olive, <q>Reign over us;</q> <verse eID="Judg.9.8"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.9.9" osisID="Judg.9.9"/> but the olive answered, <q>What!
       <milestone type="pb" n="283"/>
       am I to give up my rich oil, with which men honour God, and sway trees?</q> <verse eID="Judg.9.9"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.9.10" osisID="Judg.9.10"/> Then the trees said to the fig-tree, <q>Come you and reign over us.</q>
      <verse eID="Judg.9.10"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.9.11" osisID="Judg.9.11"/> But the fig-tree answered, <q>What! am I to give up my sweetness and rare
       produce, and sway trees?</q> <verse eID="Judg.9.11"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.9.12" osisID="Judg.9.12"/> Then the trees said to the vine, <q>Come you and reign over us.</q> <verse eID="Judg.9.12"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.9.13" osisID="Judg.9.13"/> But the vine answered, <q>What! am I to give up my juice that gladdens God
       and men, and sway trees?</q> <verse eID="Judg.9.13"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.9.14" osisID="Judg.9.14"/> So all the trees said to the thorn, <q>Come you and reign over us.</q> <verse eID="Judg.9.14"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.9.15" osisID="Judg.9.15"/> The thorn said to the trees, <q>If you are electing me king in good faith,
       come and shelter under my shadow; if not, then fire shall blaze from the thorn to burn up the very cedars of Lebanon!</q>
      <verse eID="Judg.9.15"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.9.16" osisID="Judg.9.16"/> Now then, if you have acted in good faith and honour by making Abimelek
       your king, if you have acted fairly to Jerubbaal and his family and treated him as he deserved--<verse eID="Judg.9.16"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.9.17" osisID="Judg.9.17"/>ay, my father fought for you and risked his life to rescue you from Midian,
      <verse eID="Judg.9.17"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.9.18" osisID="Judg.9.18"/> and you have risen against my father's family this very day and killed his
       sons, seventy of them, on a single stone, and elected Abimelek, the son of his slave-girl, king over the citizens of
       Shechem, because he is your kinsman-- <verse eID="Judg.9.18"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.9.19" osisID="Judg.9.19"/> if, I say, you have acted in good faith and honour towards Jerubbaal and
       his family to-day, then I wish you joy of Abimelek, and I wish him joy of you! <verse eID="Judg.9.19"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.9.20" osisID="Judg.9.20"/> But if not, fire shall blaze from Abimelek and burn up the citizens of
       Shechem and Beth-millo; fire shall blaze from the citizens of Shechem and Beth-millo and burn up Abimelek.</q> <verse eID="Judg.9.20"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.9.21" osisID="Judg.9.21"/> Then Jotham ran off and made his way to Beer, and there he stayed for fear
       of his brother Abimelek. <verse eID="Judg.9.21"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.9.22" osisID="Judg.9.22"/> For three years Abimelek held sway over Israel. <verse eID="Judg.9.22"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.9.23" osisID="Judg.9.23"/> Then God sent an evil spirit to make mischief between Abimelek and the
       citizens of Shechem--the citizens of Shechem playing false to Abimelek--<verse eID="Judg.9.23"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.9.24" osisID="Judg.9.24"/>that the bloody murder of the seventy sons of Jerubbaal might be avenged
       upon their brother Abimelek who had murdered them, and upon the citizens of Shechem who had aided him in the murder of
       his brothers. <verse eID="Judg.9.24"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.9.25" osisID="Judg.9.25"/> The citizens of Shechem damaged him by setting men in am­bush on the
       hill-tops, who robbed all passers-by along the road. And Abimelek was told about it. <verse eID="Judg.9.25"/>
      <hi type="italic">
       <verse sID="Judg.9.26" osisID="Judg.9.26"/> Now Gaal the son of Obed moved into Shechem with his kinsmen. The citizens
        of Shechem put their confidence in him, <verse eID="Judg.9.26"/>
       <verse sID="Judg.9.27" osisID="Judg.9.27"/> and, after going out into the fields and cutting the grapes and treading
        them in the winepress, they held a festival, entering the house of their god, eating and drinking, and reviling
        Abimelek. <verse eID="Judg.9.27"/>
       <verse sID="Judg.9.28" osisID="Judg.9.28"/> Said Gaal the son of Obed, <q>Who is Abimelek, that we of Shechem should be
        subject to him? Were not Jerubbaal’s son and his lieutenant Zebul once subject to the family of Hamor the founder of
        Shechem? Why, then, should we be subject to him? <verse eID="Judg.9.28"/>
       <verse sID="Judg.9.29" osisID="Judg.9.29"/> Would that I had command of this people! I would get rid of Abimelek! I
        would challenge Abimelek to come out and fight, with all his troops!</q> <verse eID="Judg.9.29"/>
       </hi>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.9.30" osisID="Judg.9.30"/> When Zebul the governor of the town heard what Gaal the son of Obed was
       saying, his anger blazed; <verse eID="Judg.9.30"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.9.31" osisID="Judg.9.31"/> he sent messengers to tell Abimelek at Arumah, <q>Here are Gaal the son of
       Obed and his kinsmen at Shechem,
       <milestone type="pb" n="284"/>
       and they are stirring up the town against you! <verse eID="Judg.9.31"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.9.32" osisID="Judg.9.32"/> Now march by night, you and your men, and lie hid in the open country;
      <verse eID="Judg.9.32"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.9.33" osisID="Judg.9.33"/> then, in the morning, at sun­rise, rise and rush on the town; when he and
       his men come out to face you, you can handle him as occasion demands.</q> <verse eID="Judg.9.33"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.9.34" osisID="Judg.9.34"/> So Abimelek and all his men made a night-march and lay round Shechem in
       ambush, four divisions of them. <verse eID="Judg.9.34"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.9.35" osisID="Judg.9.35"/> Gaal the son of Obed was standing at the gate of entry into the town, and
       when Abimelek and his men left their ambuscade, <verse eID="Judg.9.35"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.9.36" osisID="Judg.9.36"/> Gaal saw them and said to Zebul, <q>Look, there are men coming down from
       the hill-tops!</q> <q>It is the mountain-shadows,</q> said Zebul, <q>they look to you like men!</q> <verse eID="Judg.9.36"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.9.37" osisID="Judg.9.37"/> But Gaal said again, <q>Look, there are men coming down from the Height!
       One division is marching by the road from Augur’s Oak!</q> <verse eID="Judg.9.37"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.9.38" osisID="Judg.9.38"/> Then said Zebul, <q>What about your boasting now? You said, <q>Who is
       Abimelek, that we should be subject to him?</q> Are not these the very men you scoffed at? March out now and fight
       them!</q> <verse eID="Judg.9.38"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.9.39" osisID="Judg.9.39"/> So Gaal marched out, in front of the citizens of Shechem; he fought
       Abimelek, <verse eID="Judg.9.39"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.9.40" osisID="Judg.9.40"/> but Abimelek pursued him, and he ran away, while many of his men fell down
       slain right up to the gate of the town. <verse eID="Judg.9.40"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.9.41" osisID="Judg.9.41"/> Abimelek remained at Arumah; meantime Zebul drove out Gaal and his kinsmen
       from Shechem. <verse eID="Judg.9.41"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.9.42" osisID="Judg.9.42"/> Next day, the citizens moved into the open. Abimelek was told of it; <verse eID="Judg.9.42"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.9.43" osisID="Judg.9.43"/> so he took his men, divided them into three compa­nies and lay in ambush in
       the open country. He looked out, and there were the citizens leav­ing the town! So he started up and attacked them,
      <verse eID="Judg.9.43"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.9.44" osisID="Judg.9.44"/> Abimelek and his company dashing for­ward to occupy the entrances to the
       town, while the two other companies rushed to engage those who were in the open. <verse eID="Judg.9.44"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.9.45" osisID="Judg.9.45"/> All that day Abimelek fought against the town; he captured the town and
       killed the people in it, demolishing the town and sowing the site with salt. <verse eID="Judg.9.45"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.9.46" osisID="Judg.9.46"/> When the citizens of Tower-Shechem heard this, they all got into the crypt
       of the temple of El-berith. <verse eID="Judg.9.46"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.9.47" osisID="Judg.9.47"/> Abimelek was told that all the citizens of Tower-Shechem had gathered
       there; <verse eID="Judg.9.47"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.9.48" osisID="Judg.9.48"/> so Abimelek and all his men marched up to mount Zalmon, where Abimelek,
       taking an axe, cut a bundle of brushwood and shouldered it, telling his men, <q>Quick, do just what you have seen me
       do!</q>
      <verse eID="Judg.9.48"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.9.49" osisID="Judg.9.49"/> Each man then cut his bundle; they followed Abimelek, piled their bundles
       at the crypt, and set the crypt on fire. Thus died all the citi­zens of Tower-Shechem, inside the crypt, about a
       thousand men and women. <verse eID="Judg.9.49"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.9.50" osisID="Judg.9.50"/> Marching on Tabez, Abimelek invested Tabez and captured it.<verse eID="Judg.9.50"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.9.51" osisID="Judg.9.51"/> Inside the town there was a castle, where all the citizens, both men and
       women, fled for refuge; they shut themselves in, and went up on the roof. <verse eID="Judg.9.51"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.9.52" osisID="Judg.9.52"/> When Abimelek reached the castle, he attacked it, and went up to the door
       in order to set it on fire. <verse eID="Judg.9.52"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.9.53" osisID="Judg.9.53"/> But a woman flung an upper millstone on Abimelek's head, and broke his
       skull. <verse eID="Judg.9.53"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.9.54" osisID="Judg.9.54"/> Hastily he called to the page who bore his armour, <q>Draw your sword and
       despatch me, lest men say of me, <q>A woman killed him!</q></q>So the page ran him through, and he died. <verse eID="Judg.9.54"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.9.55" osisID="Judg.9.55"/> When the Israelites
       <milestone type="pb" n="285"/>
       saw that Abimelek was dead, they each went home. <verse eID="Judg.9.55"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.9.56" osisID="Judg.9.56"/> Thus did God punish the crime of Abimelek against his father, in murdering
       his seventy brothers; <verse eID="Judg.9.56"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.9.57" osisID="Judg.9.57"/> God also punished the citizens of Shechem for their crime, and the curse of
       Jotham the son of Jerubbaal came true for them. <verse eID="Judg.9.57"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eID="Judg.9"/>
    <chapter osisID="Judg.10" sID="Judg.10"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.10.1" osisID="Judg.10.1"/>After Abimelek, Tola the son of Puah and grandson of Dodo, a man of
       Issachar, rose to rescue Israel; he resided at Shamir in the highlands of Ephraim. <verse eID="Judg.10.1"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.10.2" osisID="Judg.10.2"/> For twenty-three years he governed Israel, and, when he died, he was buried
       at Shamir. <verse eID="Judg.10.2"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.10.3" osisID="Judg.10.3"/> After him Jair the Gileadite rose; he governed Israel for twenty-two years.
      <verse eID="Judg.10.3"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.10.4" osisID="Judg.10.4"/> He had thirty sons, who rode on thirty saddle-asses and who possessed
       thirty towns in the land of Gilead (which are called to this day Havvothjair). <verse eID="Judg.10.4"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.10.5" osisID="Judg.10.5"/> Jair died and was buried at Kamon. <verse eID="Judg.10.5"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.10.6" osisID="Judg.10.6"/> The Israelites again did what was evil in the eyes of the Eter­nal,
       worshipping the Baals and Astartes, the gods of Aram, the gods of Sidon, the gods of Moab, the gods of the Ammonites,
       and the gods of the Philistines; they forsook the Eternal and would not worship him. <verse eID="Judg.10.6"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.10.7" osisID="Judg.10.7"/> So the anger of the Eternal blazed against Israel; he sold them into the
       hands of the Philistines and into the hands of the Am­monites for eighteen years. <verse eID="Judg.10.7"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.10.8" osisID="Judg.10.8"/> They broke and crushed the Israelites, that is, all the Israel­ites east of
       the Jordan in the land of the Amorites, which is Gilead. <verse eID="Judg.10.8"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.10.9" osisID="Judg.10.9"/> The Ammonites even crossed the Jordan to fight Judah and Benjamin and the
       house of Ephraim. So Israel was hard put to it. <verse eID="Judg.10.9"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.10.10" osisID="Judg.10.10"/> Then the Israelites cried to the Eternal, <q>We have sinned against thee;
       we have forsaken the Eternal our God and worshipped Baals!</q> <verse eID="Judg.10.10"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.10.11" osisID="Judg.10.11"/> The Eternal answered the Israelites, <q>When the Egyptians and the
       Amorites and the Am­monites and the Philistines <verse eID="Judg.10.11"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.10.12" osisID="Judg.10.12"/> and the Phoenicians and the Amalekites and the Maonites op­pressed you,
       and you cried to me, did I not rescue you from their power? <verse eID="Judg.10.12"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.10.13" osisID="Judg.10.13"/> Yet you have forsaken me and worshipped other gods; therefore I will
       de­liver you no more. <verse eID="Judg.10.13"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.10.14" osisID="Judg.10.14"/> Go and cry to the gods you have chosen! Let them deliver you in your hour
       of woe!</q> <verse eID="Judg.10.14"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.10.15" osisID="Judg.10.15"/> Then said the Israelites to the Eternal, <q>We have sinned; do to us what
       thou wilt, only do rescue us this day!</q> <verse eID="Judg.10.15"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.10.16" osisID="Judg.10.16"/> And they put the foreign gods away from them, they worshipped the
       Eternal, till he could no longer bear the misery of Israel. <verse eID="Judg.10.16"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.10.17" osisID="Judg.10.17"/> Now the Ammonites had gathered for war and encamped in Gilead, while the
       Israelites had mustered and encamped at Mizpah. <verse eID="Judg.10.17"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.10.18" osisID="Judg.10.18"/> Every man in the force of Israel said to his fellow, <q>Who will begin
       the war against the Ammonites? That man shall be head over all the inhabitants of Gilead.</q> <verse eID="Judg.10.18"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eID="Judg.10"/>
    <chapter osisID="Judg.11" sID="Judg.11"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.11.1" osisID="Judg.11.1"/>Now Jephthah the Gileadite was a stalwart hero; he was the son of a harlot,
       and Gilead was his father. <verse eID="Judg.11.1"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.11.2" osisID="Judg.11.2"/> Gilead’s wife had borne him sons, and when his wife’s sons grew up, they
       had expelled Jephthah, tell­ing him, <q>You shall not inherit anything in our father’s house, for you are the son of
       another woman.</q> <verse eID="Judg.11.2"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.11.3" osisID="Judg.11.3"/> So Jephthah fled from his brothers and stayed in the land of Tob, where
       he gathered round him a number of
       <milestone type="pb" n="286"/>
       worth­less fellows, who used to go raiding with him. <verse eID="Judg.11.3"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.11.4" osisID="Judg.11.4"/> After a while, when the Ammonites were fighting Israel, <verse eID="Judg.11.4"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.11.5" osisID="Judg.11.5"/> the sheikhs of Gilead went to fetch Jephthah from the land of Tob. <verse eID="Judg.11.5"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.11.6" osisID="Judg.11.6"/> <q>Come,</q> they said to Jephthah, <q>be our commander, that we may
       fight the Ammonites.</q> <verse eID="Judg.11.6"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.11.7" osisID="Judg.11.7"/> But Jeph­thah said to the sheikhs of Gilead, <q>Are not you the men who
       hated me and expelled me from my father’s house? Why come to me now, when you are in straits?</q> <verse eID="Judg.11.7"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.11.8" osisID="Judg.11.8"/> The sheikhs of Gilead said to him, <q>That is why we have come back to
       you; come and fight the Ammonites, and you shall be our head, the head of all the inhabitants of Gilead.</q> <verse eID="Judg.11.8"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.11.9" osisID="Judg.11.9"/> Said Jephthah to the sheikhs of Gilead, <q>If you take me back to fight
       the Ammonites, and if the Eternal hands them over to me, shall I be your head?</q> <verse eID="Judg.11.9"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.11.10" osisID="Judg.11.10"/> <q>The Eternal shall be our witness,</q> said the sheikhs of Gilead to
       Jephthah; <q>we swear to do as you say.</q> <verse eID="Judg.11.10"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.11.11" osisID="Judg.11.11"/> So Jephthah went along with the sheikhs of Gilead; the people appointed
       him as their head and commander, and Jephthah made all his claims in presence of the Eternal at Mizpah. <verse eID="Judg.11.11"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.11.12" osisID="Judg.11.12"/> Jephthah then sent messengers to the king of the Ammonites, saying,
       <q>What business have you here, coming to me to attack my country?</q> <verse eID="Judg.11.12"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.11.13" osisID="Judg.11.13"/> The king of the Ammonites told the messengers of Jephthah, <q>When
       Israel came up from Egypt, they took away my land, from the Arnon as far as to the Jabbok and the Jordan. Now, then,
       restore it peaceably.</q> <verse eID="Judg.11.13"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.11.14" osisID="Judg.11.14"/> Then Jephthah sent messengers again to the king of the Ammonites, <verse eID="Judg.11.14"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.11.15" osisID="Judg.11.15"/> saying, <q>This is what Jephthah says: Israel did not take away the
       land of the Am­monites. <verse eID="Judg.11.15"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.11.16" osisID="Judg.11.16"/> When Israel came up from Egypt, they marched through the desert to the
       Reed Sea and reached Kadesh. <verse eID="Judg.11.16"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.11.17" osisID="Judg.11.17"/> They sent messengers to the king of Edom, saying, <q>Pray let us pass
       through your country</q>; but the king of Edom would not listen to them. They also sent to the king of Moab, but he
       would not consent. So Israel halted at Kadesh, <verse eID="Judg.11.17"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.11.18" osisID="Judg.11.18"/> and then passed through the desert, round the land of Edom and the land
       of Moab, keeping east of the land of Moab, till they camped north of the Arnon; they did not enter the territory of
       Moab, for the Arnon is the boundary of Moab. <verse eID="Judg.11.18"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.11.19" osisID="Judg.11.19"/> Israel then sent messengers to Sihon king of the Amorites, the king of
       Heshbon, saying, <q>Pray let us pass through your country to our own land.</q> <verse eID="Judg.11.19"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.11.20" osisID="Judg.11.20"/> But Sihon refused to let Israel pass through his territory; Sihon
       gathered all his forces and encamped at Jahaz, where he fought Israel. <verse eID="Judg.11.20"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.11.21" osisID="Judg.11.21"/> But the Eternal the God of Israel put Sihon and all his forces into the
       hand of Israel, who defeated them. <verse eID="Judg.11.21"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.11.22" osisID="Judg.11.22"/> Then Israel occupied all the land of the Amorites, the inhabitants of
       that country; Israel gained possession of all the territory of the Amorites, from the Arnon to the Jabbok, and from
       the desert to the Jor­dan. <verse eID="Judg.11.22"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.11.23" osisID="Judg.11.23"/> Well, then, the Eternal, the God of Israel, dispossessed the Amorites
       in favour of his people Israel; and are you to claim possession? <verse eID="Judg.11.23"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.11.24" osisID="Judg.11.24"/> Is it not for you to claim possession of those dispossessed by your own
       god Kemosh, and for us to claim possession of all whom the Eternal our God has evicted in our favour? <verse eID="Judg.11.24"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.11.25" osisID="Judg.11.25"/> What! are you any
       <milestone type="pb" n="287"/>
       stronger than Balak, son of Zippor, king of Moab? Did he ever quarrel with Israel? Did he ever fight them? <verse eID="Judg.11.25"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.11.26" osisID="Judg.11.26"/> Israel has occupied Heshbon and its dependencies, Aroer and its
       dependencies, and all the towns adjoining the Anion, for three hundred years. Pray, why have you never recaptured
       them during all that time? <verse eID="Judg.11.26"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.11.27" osisID="Judg.11.27"/> No, I have done no wrong to you; it is you who are injuring me by
       fighting me! Let the Eter­nal as Judge decide to-day the issue between Israelites and Ammonites!</q> <verse eID="Judg.11.27"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.11.28" osisID="Judg.11.28"/> However, the king of the Am­monites would not listen to the message
       which Jephthah sent him. <verse eID="Judg.11.28"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.11.29" osisID="Judg.11.29"/> Then the spirit of the Eter­nal inspired Jephthah; he went across to
       Gilead and Manasseh, went over to Mizpah in Gilead, and from Mizpah in Gilead crossed over to meet the Ammonites. <verse eID="Judg.11.29"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.11.30" osisID="Judg.11.30"/> Jephthah made a vow to the Eternal. <q>If thou wilt hand me over the
       Ammonites,</q> he vowed, <verse eID="Judg.11.30"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.11.31" osisID="Judg.11.31"/><q>then whoever comes out of my house to meet me when I come back
       victorious from the Ammonites, he shall be the Eternal's; I will offer him up as a burnt-offering!</q> <verse eID="Judg.11.31"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.11.32" osisID="Judg.11.32"/> So Jeph­thah crossed to fight against the Ammonites, and the Eternal put
       them into his hands; <verse eID="Judg.11.32"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.11.33" osisID="Judg.11.33"/> he routed them with terrible slaughter from Aroer as far as Minnith,
       capturing over twenty towns, even as far as Abel-keramim. Thus were the Ammonites sub­dued by the Israelites. <verse eID="Judg.11.33"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.11.34" osisID="Judg.11.34"/>Then Jephthah went home to Mizpah. And there was his daugh­ter coming out
       to meet him with girls dancing to the tambourine! She was the one and only child he had; besides her he had neither
       son nor daughter. <verse eID="Judg.11.34"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.11.35" osisID="Judg.11.35"/> When he saw her, he tore his clothes and cried, <q>Alas, my daughter,
       you have struck me down! Low, low have you laid me! For I made my promise to the Eter­nal, and I cannot go back upon
       my word!</q> <verse eID="Judg.11.35"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.11.36" osisID="Judg.11.36"/> <q>My father,</q> she said to him, <q>if you have made your promise to
       the Eternal, do to me whatever you have vowed, since the Eternal has given you full vengeance on your foes, upon the
       Ammon­ites.</q> <verse eID="Judg.11.36"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.11.37" osisID="Judg.11.37"/> She said to her father, <q>But grant me this: spare me for two months,
       that I may go and wander free among the hills, bewailing my maidenhood--I and my companions.</q> <verse eID="Judg.11.37"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.11.38" osisID="Judg.11.38"/> <q>Go,</q> he said, and he sent her away for two months. So she went,
       she and her companions, to be­wail her maidenhood among the hills. <verse eID="Judg.11.38"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.11.39" osisID="Judg.11.39"/> At the end of the two months she returned to her father, and he did to
       her what he had vowed to do--to her a virgin! It became a custom in Israel <verse eID="Judg.11.39"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.11.40" osisID="Judg.11.40"/> for the women to la­ment the daughter of Jephthah the Gileadite four
       days every year. <verse eID="Judg.11.40"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eID="Judg.11"/>
    <chapter osisID="Judg.12" sID="Judg.12"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.12.1" osisID="Judg.12.1"/>The men of Ephraim gathered and crossed to Zaphon, to ask Jephthah, <q>Why
       did you cross to fight the Am­monites without summoning us to go with you? We will burn down your house over your
       head.</q> <verse eID="Judg.12.1"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.12.2" osisID="Judg.12.2"/> But Jephthah said to them, <q>I and my men were en­gaged in a sharp
       struggle, the Ammonites were pressing us hard; we summoned you, but you never rescued us from their power. <verse eID="Judg.12.2"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.12.3" osisID="Judg.12.3"/> So when I saw that there was no one to rescue us, I risked my life, I
       crossed to meet the Ammonites, and the Eter­nal gave them over to me. Why, then,have you come forward
       <milestone type="pb" n="288"/>
       to-day to fight me?</q> <verse eID="Judg.12.3"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.12.4" osisID="Judg.12.4"/> Then Jephthah mustered all the men of Gilead, and fought Ephraim; the men
       of Gilead routed Ephraim, <verse eID="Judg.12.4"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.12.5" osisID="Judg.12.5"/> and Gilead seized the fords of the Jordan to check Ephraim; whenever a
       fugitive from Eph­raim said, <q>Let me cross,</q> the men of Gilead would ask him, <q>Are you an Ephraimite?</q> If
       he said, <q>No,</q> <verse eID="Judg.12.5"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.12.6" osisID="Judg.12.6"/> they said to him, <q>Then say, <q>Shibboleth</q></q>; if he said,
       <q>Sibboleth,</q> if he could not pronounce the word cor­rectly, they seized him and slew him at the fords of Jordan.
       So perished forty-two thousand men of Ephraim. <verse eID="Judg.12.6"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.12.7" osisID="Judg.12.7"/> Jephthah governed Israel for six years. Then Jephthah the Gileadite died
       and was buried in his town, at Mizpah belonging to Gilead. <verse eID="Judg.12.7"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.12.8" osisID="Judg.12.8"/> After him Ibzan of Bethlehem governed Israel. <verse eID="Judg.12.8"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.12.9" osisID="Judg.12.9"/> He had thirty sons, he married thirty daugh­ters into other families, and
       brought in thirty daughters of other families for his sons. For seven years he governed Israel. <verse eID="Judg.12.9"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.12.10" osisID="Judg.12.10"/> Then Ibzan died and was buried at Bethlehem. <verse eID="Judg.12.10"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.12.11" osisID="Judg.12.11"/> After him Elon the Zebulunite governed Israel; he governed for ten
       years. <verse eID="Judg.12.11"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.12.12" osisID="Judg.12.12"/> Then Elon the Zebulunite died and was buried at Aijalon in the land of
       Zebulun. <verse eID="Judg.12.12"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.12.13" osisID="Judg.12.13"/> After him Abdon the son of Hillel from Pirathon governed Israel. <verse eID="Judg.12.13"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.12.14" osisID="Judg.12.14"/> He had forty sons and thirty grandsons, who rode on seventy
       saddle-asses. He gov­erned Israel for eight years. <verse eID="Judg.12.14"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.12.15" osisID="Judg.12.15"/> Then Abdon the son of Hillel from Pirathon died, and was buried at
       Pirathon in the land of Ephraim, in the Amalekite highlands. <verse eID="Judg.12.15"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eID="Judg.12"/>
    <chapter osisID="Judg.13" sID="Judg.13"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.13.1" osisID="Judg.13.1"/>Again the Israelites did what was evil in the sight of the Eternal, and
       the Eternal handed them over to the Phil­istines for forty years. <verse eID="Judg.13.1"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.13.2" osisID="Judg.13.2"/> There was a man of Zorah, belonging to the Danite clan, whose name was
       Manoah. His wife was barren, she had borne no children; <verse eID="Judg.13.2"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.13.3" osisID="Judg.13.3"/> but the angel of the Eternal appeared to the woman and said, <q>You are
       0bar­ren, you have borne no children. <verse eID="Judg.13.3"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.13.4" osisID="Judg.13.4"/>Now, then, pray be careful to drink no wine or any liquor and to eat no
       unclean food,<verse eID="Judg.13.4"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.13.5" osisID="Judg.13.5"/> for you are with child and you will bear a son, whose head will never know a razor; the lad shall be
       consecrated to God from his birth, and he will begin the de­liverance of Israel from the Phil­istines.</q> <verse eID="Judg.13.5"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.13.6" osisID="Judg.13.6"/> So the woman went and told her husband. <q>A man of God came to me,</q>
       she said; <q>his look was like the look of the Eternal’s angel, awe-in­spiring. I did not ask him where he came from,
       nor did he tell me his name, <verse eID="Judg.13.6"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.13.7" osisID="Judg.13.7"/> but he said to me, <q>You are with child, and you will bear a son; now,
       then, drink neither wine nor liquor, and eat no unclean food, for the lad shall be consecrated to God from birth to
       death.</q></q> <verse eID="Judg.13.7"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.13.8" osisID="Judg.13.8"/> Then Manoah besought the Eternal. <q>O Lord,</q> he said, <q>pray let the
       man of God whom thou didst send come back to tell us how we are to train the boy that is to be born.</q> <verse eID="Judg.13.8"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.13.9" osisID="Judg.13.9"/> God listened to what Manoah said, and the angel of God again came to the
       woman. She was sitting out-of-doors; her husband Manoah was not with her. <verse eID="Judg.13.9"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.13.10" osisID="Judg.13.10"/> So she ran in a hurry to tell her husband that the man of God who
       ap­peared to her the other day had just appeared again. <verse eID="Judg.13.10"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.13.11" osisID="Judg.13.11"/> Manoah started to follow his wife, and when he reached the man he
       <milestone type="pb" n="289"/>
       said, <q>Are you the man who spoke to this woman?</q> He answered, <q>Yes.</q> <verse eID="Judg.13.11"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.13.12" osisID="Judg.13.12"/> Then Manoah asked, <q>When your words come true, how is the lad to he
       trained? What is he to be?</q> <verse eID="Judg.13.12"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.13.13" osisID="Judg.13.13"/> The angel of the Eternal said to Manoah, <q>Let the woman pay careful
       heed to all that I said. <verse eID="Judg.13.13"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.13.14" osisID="Judg.13.14"/> She must never taste any prod­uce of the vine, no wine, no liquor; she
       must never eat any unclean food. All that I com­manded her, she must observe.</q> <verse eID="Judg.13.14"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.13.15" osisID="Judg.13.15"/> Then said Manoah to the angel of the Eternal, <q>Let us press you to
       stay till we prepare a kid for you</q> <verse eID="Judg.13.15"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.13.16" osisID="Judg.13.16"/> (for Manoah did not realize that he was the angel of the Eternal). But
       the angel of the Eternal said to Manoah, <q>You may press me, but I will not eat your food; if you make a
       burnt-offering, offer it to the Eternal.</q> <verse eID="Judg.13.16"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.13.17" osisID="Judg.13.17"/> Manoah said to the angel of the Eternal, <q>What is your name?--so that
       we may honour you when your words come true.</q> <verse eID="Judg.13.17"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.13.18" osisID="Judg.13.18"/> <q>Why ask my name?</q> said the angel of the Eternal; <q>it is not to
       be uttered.</q> <verse eID="Judg.13.18"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.13.19" osisID="Judg.13.19"/> Then Manoah took the kid [[with the offering of cereals]] and
       sacrificed it on the rock to the Eternal, who works wonders, <verse eID="Judg.13.19"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.13.20" osisID="Judg.13.20"/> and as the flame rose to heaven from the altar, the angel of the
       Eternal went up to heaven in the flame of the altar. Manoah and his wife, who were looking on, dropped on their
       faces to the ground. <verse eID="Judg.13.20"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.13.21" osisID="Judg.13.21"/> (But the angel of the Eternal never ap­peared again to Manoah and his
       wife.) Then Manoah realized that it had been the angel of the Eternal. <verse eID="Judg.13.21"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.13.22" osisID="Judg.13.22"/> And Manoah said to his wife, <q>We are certain to die, for it is a god
       we have seen!</q> <verse eID="Judg.13.22"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.13.23" osisID="Judg.13.23"/> But his wife said to him, <q>If the Eternal had meant to kill us, he
       would not have accepted a burnt-offering from us [[and an offering of cereals]], nor would he have let us see all
       this, nor would he have told us all this.</q> <verse eID="Judg.13.23"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.13.24" osisID="Judg.13.24"/>The woman did bear a son; she called him Samson, and the child grew up
       and the Eternal blessed him. <verse eID="Judg.13.24"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.13.25" osisID="Judg.13.25"/> The spirit of the Eternal first began to stir him at Mahaneh-Dan,
       between Zorah and Eshtaol. <verse eID="Judg.13.25"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eID="Judg.13"/>
    <chapter osisID="Judg.14" sID="Judg.14"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.14.1" osisID="Judg.14.1"/>Samson went down to Timnath, and at Timnath he saw a woman belonging to
       the Philistines. <verse eID="Judg.14.1"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.14.2" osisID="Judg.14.2"/> When he came back, he said to his father and mother, <q>I saw a woman at
       Timnath who belongs to the Philistines; get her for me as a wife.</q> <verse eID="Judg.14.2"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.14.3" osisID="Judg.14.3"/> His father [[and mother]] said to him, <q>Is there no woman among your
       own clansfolk or among my people, that you must go and take a wife from the uncircumcised Philistines?</q> <q>Get
       her,</q> said Samson to his father, <q>get her for me; I like her!</q> <verse eID="Judg.14.3"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.14.4" osisID="Judg.14.4"/> (Little did his father and mother know that this was due to the Eternal;
       for the Eternal was seeking some occasion against the Philistines, who then were in power over Israel.) <verse eID="Judg.14.4"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.14.5" osisID="Judg.14.5"/> Then Samson went down to Timnath [[with his father and mother]], and
       there, at the vineyards of Timnath, a young lion came growling at him. <verse eID="Judg.14.5"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.14.6" osisID="Judg.14.6"/> The spirit of the Eternal came over him, and he tore the creature in
       pieces as easily as one might tear a kid, though he had no weapon in his hands. [[But he did not tell his father or
       his mother what he had done.]] <verse eID="Judg.14.6"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.14.7" osisID="Judg.14.7"/> When he went down, he talked to the woman, and liked her. <verse eID="Judg.14.7"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.14.8" osisID="Judg.14.8"/> On his way back, after a while, he stepped aside to look at the carcase
       of the lion; and there was a swarm of bees
       <milestone type="pb" n="290"/>
       inside the lion’s body, and some honey! <verse eID="Judg.14.8"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.14.9" osisID="Judg.14.9"/> So he scraped it out into his hands and ate it as he went along. When he
       reached his father and mother he gave them some of it to eat, but he did not tell them that he had taken it from the
       lion’s body. <verse eID="Judg.14.9"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.14.10" osisID="Judg.14.10"/> Samson went down to the woman and held a feast there (for so
       bridegrooms used to do). <verse eID="Judg.14.10"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.14.11" osisID="Judg.14.11"/> Samson took thirty companions, who kept beside him. <verse eID="Judg.14.11"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.14.12" osisID="Judg.14.12"/> To them Samson said, <q>Let me give you a riddle; if you can tell me
       the answer during the seven days of the feast, I will give you thirty fine linen shawls and thirty gala robes; <verse eID="Judg.14.12"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.14.13" osisID="Judg.14.13"/> but if you cannot tell me the answer, then you must give me thirty fine
       linen shawls and thirty gala robes.</q> <q>Propound your riddle,</q> they said, <q>let us hear it.</q> <verse eID="Judg.14.13"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.14.14" osisID="Judg.14.14"/> So he said to them,
       <lg>
        <l> From the eater came something to eat, </l>
        <l> from the strong came something sweet. </l>
       </lg>
      <verse eID="Judg.14.14"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.14.15" osisID="Judg.14.15"/> As they could not guess the riddle, they said to Samson’s wife, <q>Coax
       your husband to give away the answer, or we will burn you and your father’s house. Did you invite us here to beggar
       us?</q> <verse eID="Judg.14.15"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.14.16" osisID="Judg.14.16"/> So Samson's wife irritated him by weeping and crying, <q>You simply
       hate me, you do not love me; you have propounded a riddle to my countrymen, and you have never told me the answer!</q>
       <q>Why,</q> he said, <q>I have not told my father or my mother! and am I to tell you?</q> <verse eID="Judg.14.16"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.14.17" osisID="Judg.14.17"/> All the seven days that the feast lasted, she irritated him by weeping.
       At last, on the seventh day, he did tell her--she pressed him so hard. She told the riddle to her countrymen, <verse eID="Judg.14.17"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.14.18" osisID="Judg.14.18"/> and just as he was entering the bridal chamber on the seventh day the
       men of the town said to him,
       <lg>
        <l> What is sweeter than honey? </l>
        <l> What is stronger than a lion? </l>
       </lg>
       He retorted,
       <lg>
        <l> Had you not used my heifer for your plough, </l>
        <l> you never would have guessed my riddle now! </l>
       </lg>
      <verse eID="Judg.14.18"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.14.19" osisID="Judg.14.19"/> The spirit of the Eternal inspired him mightily; he went down to
       Ashkelon, where he killed thirty of the citizens, plundered them, and handed the gala robes to those who had guessed
       his riddle. Then in blazing fury he went away to his father’s house. <verse eID="Judg.14.19"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.14.20" osisID="Judg.14.20"/> And Samson's wife was given to one of his companions, who had been his
       best man. <verse eID="Judg.14.20"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eID="Judg.14"/>
    <chapter osisID="Judg.15" sID="Judg.15"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.15.1" osisID="Judg.15.1"/>Later on, during wheat harvest, Samson went to visit his wife with the
       present of a kid. He said, <q>I am going into the bridal chamber to my wife.</q> But her father would not allow him
       to enter; <verse eID="Judg.15.1"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.15.2" osisID="Judg.15.2"/> her father said, <q>I thought you must hate her, so I gave her to your
       companion. But her younger sister is more beautiful, is she not? Take her instead.</q> <verse eID="Judg.15.2"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.15.3" osisID="Judg.15.3"/> Samson said to him, <q>I shall be quits with the Phil­istines this time; I
       shall do them a mischief.</q> <verse eID="Judg.15.3"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.15.4" osisID="Judg.15.4"/> Then Samson went and caught three hundred foxes; turning them tail to tail
       and putting a torch between each pair of tails, <verse eID="Judg.15.4"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.15.5" osisID="Judg.15.5"/> he lit the torches and set the foxes loose in the fields of the
       Philistines, till both the shocks and the stand­ing corn were burned, and even the vineyards and the olive-orchards.
      <verse eID="Judg.15.5"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.15.6" osisID="Judg.15.6"/><q>Who has done this?</q> said the Philistines. When they were told it was
       Samson, the Timnite’s son-in-law, who had done it, be­cause his wife had been taken
       <milestone type="pb" n="291"/>
       from him and given to his com­rade, the Philistines went up and burned her and her father’s house. <verse eID="Judg.15.6"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.15.7" osisID="Judg.15.7"/> Samson said to them, <q>If this is what you do, I will have my revenge on
       you before I am done!</q> <verse eID="Judg.15.7"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.15.8" osisID="Judg.15.8"/> He routed them headlong with heavy slaughter; then he went down and
       stayed at the cliff of Etam, in the fissure there. <verse eID="Judg.15.8"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.15.9" osisID="Judg.15.9"/> The Philistines came up and camped in Judah, making a raid on Lehi. <verse eID="Judg.15.9"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.15.10" osisID="Judg.15.10"/> The men of Judah said, <q>Why have you come up against us?</q><q>To
       seize Samson,</q> they said; <q>to do to him what he has done to us.</q> <verse eID="Judg.15.10"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.15.11" osisID="Judg.15.11"/> So three thousand men of Judah went to the fissure in the cliff of Etam
       and said to Samson, <q>Don’t you know the Philistines are our over-lords? What is this that you have brought upon
       us?</q> <q>As they did to me,</q> said Samson, <q>so I did to them.</q> <verse eID="Judg.15.11"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.15.12" osisID="Judg.15.12"/> They said to him, <q>We have come here to seize you and hand you over
       to the Philistines.</q> <q>Well,</q> said Samson, <q>swear to me that you will not murder me yourselves.</q> <verse eID="Judg.15.12"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.15.13" osisID="Judg.15.13"/> <q>No,</q> they answered, <q>we will not kill you; we will simply bind
       you and hand you over to them.</q> So they tied him fast with two new ropes and brought him away from the cliff. <verse eID="Judg.15.13"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.15.14" osisID="Judg.15.14"/> When he reached Lehi, the Philistines met him with loud shouts; but the
       spirit of the Eternal in­spired him mightily, the ropes round his arms became like flax that has caught fire, the
       bonds melted off his hands, <verse eID="Judg.15.14"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.15.15" osisID="Judg.15.15"/> and catch­ing up the fresh jaw-bone of an ass he felled a thousand men.
      <verse eID="Judg.15.15"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.15.16" osisID="Judg.15.16"/>Said Samson,
       <lg>
        <l> With the jaw-bone of an ass I have piled them in a mass! </l>
        <l> With the jaw-bone of an ass I have assailed assailants! </l>
       </lg>
      <verse eID="Judg.15.16"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.15.17" osisID="Judg.15.17"/> When he had said this, he threw aside the jaw-bone, and so the spot was
       called Jawbonethrow (Ramath-Iehi). <verse eID="Judg.15.17"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.15.18" osisID="Judg.15.18"/> He was terribly thirsty; so he called to the Eternal, <q>Thou hast
       granted thy servant this great victory, and am I now to die of thirst and fall into the hands of the
       uncircumcised?</q> <verse eID="Judg.15.18"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.15.19" osisID="Judg.15.19"/> Then God split the hollow at Lehi, and water poured from it; when he
       drank, his spirits rose, and he revived. Hence the spot was named Caller-spring (Enhak- kore); it is at Lehi to this
       day. <verse eID="Judg.15.19"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.15.20" osisID="Judg.15.20"/> He governed Israel for twenty years during the period of the
       Philistines. <verse eID="Judg.15.20"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eID="Judg.15"/>
    <chapter osisID="Judg.16" sID="Judg.16"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.16.1" osisID="Judg.16.1"/>Samson once went to Gaza, where he saw a harlot and had intercourse with
       her. <verse eID="Judg.16.1"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.16.2" osisID="Judg.16.2"/> When the folk of Gaza learned that Samson had come, they [[surrounded the
       house and lay in wait for him all day at the gate of the town; they]] kept quiet all the night, saying, <q>Wait till
       morning, then we can kill him!</q> <verse eID="Judg.16.2"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.16.3" osisID="Judg.16.3"/> Samson lay till midnight. At midnight he got up, seized the doors of the
       town-gate and the two door-posts, pulled them up, bar and all, and, after shoul­dering them, carried them to the
       hill-top in front of Hebron. <verse eID="Judg.16.3"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.16.4" osisID="Judg.16.4"/> After that he fell in love with a woman in the wady of Sorek, who was
       called Delilah. <verse eID="Judg.16.4"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.16.5" osisID="Judg.16.5"/> The Philistine tyrants went and said to her, <q>Coax him and find out why
       he is so strong; find out how we can master him and tie him up to be tortured, and we will each give you a hundred
       and fifty pounds in silver.</q> <verse eID="Judg.16.5"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.16.6" osisID="Judg.16.6"/> So Delilah asked Samson, <q>Do tell me why you are so strong. How could
       one tie you up to be tortured?</q> <verse eID="Judg.16.6"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.16.7" osisID="Judg.16.7"/> Samson said to her, <q>If I am tied with seven
       <milestone type="pb" n="292"/>
       fresh bowstrings that have never been dried, my strength will fail, and I shall be like any other man.</q> <verse eID="Judg.16.7"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.16.8" osisID="Judg.16.8"/> Then the Phil­istine tyrants brought her seven fresh bowstrings which had
       never been dried, and with these she tied up Samson. <verse eID="Judg.16.8"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.16.9" osisID="Judg.16.9"/> (She had men concealed in the inner room.) She said to him, <q>The
       Philistines are on you, Samson!</q> But he snapped the bowstrings like a strand of tow at the touch of fire. So the
       secret of his strength was not disclosed. <verse eID="Judg.16.9"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.16.10" osisID="Judg.16.10"/> Then said Delilah to Samson, <q>There, you have cheated me! You have
       told me a lie! Do tell me how you could be tied up.</q> <verse eID="Judg.16.10"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.16.11" osisID="Judg.16.11"/> He said to her, <q>If I am tied tight with new ropes that have never
       been used, my strength will fail, and I shall be like any other man.</q> <verse eID="Judg.16.11"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.16.12" osisID="Judg.16.12"/> So De­lilah took new ropes and tied him; she said, <q>The Philistines
       are on you, Samson!</q> (Men were lying concealed in the inner room.) But he snapped them off his arms as if they
       had been threads. <verse eID="Judg.16.12"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.16.13" osisID="Judg.16.13"/> Then Delilah said to Samson, <q>You have been cheating me all the time,
       telling me lies! Tell me how you could be tied up.</q> He said to her, <q>If you weave the seven plaits of my head
       into the web of the loom and twist them in with the pin, my strength will fail, and I shall be like any other man.</q>
      <verse eID="Judg.16.13"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.16.14" osisID="Judg.16.14"/> So, as he slept, Delilah took the seven plaits of his head, wove them
       into the web of the loom, and twisted them in with the pin. Then she said, <q>The Philistines are on you, Samson!</q>
       He woke up, and pulled out both loom and web. <verse eID="Judg.16.14"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.16.15" osisID="Judg.16.15"/> She said to him, <q>How can you say, <q>I love you</q> when you do not
       trust me? Three times al­ready you have cheated me; you have never told me why you are so strong.</q> <verse eID="Judg.16.15"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.16.16" osisID="Judg.16.16"/> At last, as she pressed him every day and urged him, he got tired to
       death <verse eID="Judg.16.16"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.16.17" osisID="Judg.16.17"/> and told her all the secret; he said to her, <q>No razor has ever been
       used on my head, for I have been consecrated to God from birth. If I am shaved, then my strength will leave me, and
       I shall be like any other man.</q> <verse eID="Judg.16.17"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.16.18" osisID="Judg.16.18"/> When Delilah saw that he had trusted her with all the secret, she
       summoned the Phil­istine tyrants, saying, <q>Come up, this once; he has told me everything.</q> So the Philistine
       tyrants came, with the money in their hands. <verse eID="Judg.16.18"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.16.19" osisID="Judg.16.19"/> She made Samson sleep on her lap, and then called for a man, who shaved
       off the seven plaits of his head; his strength began to weaken, and then left him. <verse eID="Judg.16.19"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.16.20" osisID="Judg.16.20"/> She cried, <q>The Philistines are on you Samson!</q> He woke up,
       think­ing, <q>I shall get off as I have done over and over again, and shake myself free</q>--not knowing that the
       Eternal had left him. <verse eID="Judg.16.20"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.16.21" osisID="Judg.16.21"/> The Philistines seized him; they bored out his eyes, and took him down
       to Gaza, where he was shackled in bronze chains and employed to grind corn in the prison. <verse eID="Judg.16.21"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.16.22" osisID="Judg.16.22"/> But no sooner had his head been shaved than the hair began to grow
       again. <verse eID="Judg.16.22"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.16.23" osisID="Judg.16.23"/> The Philistine tyrants had gathered for a great sacrifice to their god
       Dagon and for merry­making. <q>Our god,</q> they said, <q>has put Samson our enemy into our hands!</q> <verse eID="Judg.16.23"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.16.25" osisID="Judg.16.25"/> They were in 25 high spirits, and shouted, <q>Call for Samson, that he
       may make sport for us!</q> So Samson was called from prison and he made
       <milestone type="pb" n="293"/>
       sport before them. Then they put him between the pillars. <verse eID="Judg.16.25"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.16.24" osisID="Judg.16.24"/> When the people saw him, they shouted in honour of their god, Our god
       has now put the foe in our hands, who wasted our lands and slew us in bands! <verse eID="Judg.16.24"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.16.26" osisID="Judg.16.26"/>Samson said to the lad who held his hand, <q>Let me touch the pillars
       that support the house, let me lean against them.</q> <verse eID="Judg.16.26"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.16.27" osisID="Judg.16.27"/> Now the building was filled with men and women; all the Philistine
       tyrants were there, and there were about three thousand men and women on the roof, watching Samson at his sport. <verse eID="Judg.16.27"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.16.28" osisID="Judg.16.28"/> Then Samson called upon the Eternal: <q>Lord Eternal, O remember me;
       pray strengthen me, O God, only for this once, to avenge myself upon the Philistines for one of my two eyes!</q> <verse eID="Judg.16.28"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.16.29" osisID="Judg.16.29"/> And Samson grasped the two middle pillars that supported the house; he
       braced himself against them, holding one with his right hand and the other with his left. <verse eID="Judg.16.29"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.16.30" osisID="Judg.16.30"/><q>Let us die together, myself and the Philistines!</q> said Sam­son, and
       he pulled with all his might; down fell the temple on the tyrants and on all the people who were inside! So those he
       killed in death were more than he had killed in life. <verse eID="Judg.16.30"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.16.31" osisID="Judg.16.31"/> His kinsmen and all his family came down and took him away to be buried,
       between Zorah and Eshtaol, in the grave of his father Manoah. He had gov­erned Israel for twenty years. <verse eID="Judg.16.31"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eID="Judg.16"/>
    <chapter osisID="Judg.17" sID="Judg.17"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.17.1" osisID="Judg.17.1"/>In the highlands of Eph­raim there lived a man called Micah. <verse eID="Judg.17.1"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.17.2" osisID="Judg.17.2"/> He said to his mother. <q>The hundred and fifty pounds in silver which
       were stolen from you, and which with an oath in my hearing you solemnly devoted to the Eternal as your own gift, to
       make a carved metal idol--I have that money, it was I who took it; I will return it to you now.</q> His mother said,
       <q>May the Eternal bless my son!</q> <verse eID="Judg.17.2"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.17.3-Judg.17.4" osisID="Judg.17.3 Judg.17.4"/> So he returned the hun­dred and fifty pounds in silver to his mother. His
       mother took twenty-eight pounds of it, and gave it to a silversmith who made a carved metal idol, which stood in
       Micah’s house. <verse eID="Judg.17.3-Judg.17.4"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.17.5" osisID="Judg.17.5"/> This man Micah had a shrine; he made an ephod and house­hold gods, and
       installed one of his sons as priest. <verse eID="Judg.17.5"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.17.6" osisID="Judg.17.6"/> (In those days there was no king in Israel, and everyone did exactly as
       he pleased.) <verse eID="Judg.17.6"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.17.7" osisID="Judg.17.7"/> Now there was a young man from Bethlehem in Judah, a Levite who belonged
       to the clan of Judah, residing in the neighbourhood; <verse eID="Judg.17.7"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.17.8" osisID="Judg.17.8"/> he had left the town of Bethlehem in Judah to stay wherever he could find
       a place, and in the course of his wanderings he had reached Micah’s house, in the highlands of Ephraim. <verse eID="Judg.17.8"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.17.9" osisID="Judg.17.9"/> Micah asked him, <q>Where do you come from?</q> He said, <q>I am a
       Levite from Bethlehem in Judah, and I am travelling to find some place to stay in.</q> <verse eID="Judg.17.9"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.17.10" osisID="Judg.17.10"/> <q>Stay with me,</q> said Micah, <q>be my father and priest; I will give
       you a pound in silver every year, a suit of clothes, and your food.</q> So the Levite agreed to live with the man;
      <verse eID="Judg.17.10"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.17.11" osisID="Judg.17.11"/> he became like one of his own sons. <verse eID="Judg.17.11"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.17.12" osisID="Judg.17.12"/> Micah installed the Levite, and the young man became his priest and
       lived in his house. <verse eID="Judg.17.12"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.17.13" osisID="Judg.17.13"/><q>Now,</q> said Micah, <q>I know the Eternal will prosper me, since I
       have got a Levite as my priest.</q> (In those days there was no king in Israel.) <verse eID="Judg.17.13"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eID="Judg.17"/>
    <milestone type="pb" n="294"/>
    <chapter osisID="Judg.18" sID="Judg.18"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.18.1" osisID="Judg.18.1"/>In those days the Danite clan was in search of terri­tory, for up till then
       no territory had fallen to them among the clans of Israel. <verse eID="Judg.18.1"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.18.2" osisID="Judg.18.2"/> So the Danites sent five men out of their whole clan, men of prowess from
       Zorah and Eshtaol, to explore and ex­amine the country; their orders were to go and examine the country. They reached
       Micah’s house in the highlands of Ephraim, and halted there for the night. <verse eID="Judg.18.2"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.18.3" osisID="Judg.18.3"/> When they were near the house, they recognized the voice of the young
       Levite; they stepped aside and said to him, <q>Who brought you here? What are you doing in a place like this? What
       is your business here?</q> <verse eID="Judg.18.3"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.18.4" osisID="Judg.18.4"/> He told them what Micah had done for him; <q>He hired me and I became his
       priest.</q> <verse eID="Judg.18.4"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.18.5" osisID="Judg.18.5"/> So they said, <q>Pray consult God, that we may know whether or not our
       errand will be a success.</q> <verse eID="Judg.18.5"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.18.6" osisID="Judg.18.6"/> The priest said to them, <q>Go and prosper, your errand is under the
       Eternal’s favour.</q> <verse eID="Judg.18.6"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.18.7" osisID="Judg.18.7"/> So the five men passed on to Laish, where they found the folk living in
       perfect security, like the Sidonians, quiet and unsuspicious; there was no lack of anything in the land, and they
       were far from the Phoeni­cians and had no intercourse with Aram. <verse eID="Judg.18.7"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.18.8" osisID="Judg.18.8"/> When the scouts came back to their kinsmen at Zorah and Eshtaol, their
       kinsmen asked them for their report. <verse eID="Judg.18.8"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.18.9" osisID="Judg.18.9"/> They said, <q>Let us be up and off to Laish! We have seen the country;
       it is a fine country. And you sit idle here! Lose no time in entering and occupying the country, <verse eID="Judg.18.9"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.18.10" osisID="Judg.18.10"/> for God has put it into your hands. When you go, you will find an
       unsuspicious people; besides, the land is large, and there is no lack of anything in that region.</q> <verse eID="Judg.18.10"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.18.11" osisID="Judg.18.11"/> So six hundred armed men of the Danite clan set out from Zorah and
       Eshtaol. <verse eID="Judg.18.11"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.18.12" osisID="Judg.18.12"/> They marched up and encamped at Kiriath-jearim in Judah. Hence the
       name of the spot to this day is Dans-camp (Mahaneh-Dan); it lies west of Kiriath-jearim. <verse eID="Judg.18.12"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.18.13" osisID="Judg.18.13"/> From this they moved on to the high­lands of Ephraim and reached the
       house of Micah. <verse eID="Judg.18.13"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.18.14" osisID="Judg.18.14"/> The five men who had explored the country of Laish then said to their
       kinsmen, <q>Do you know there is an ephod in these build­ings, and household gods and a carved metal idol?  What are
       you going to do? Make up your minds.</q> <verse eID="Judg.18.14"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.18.15" osisID="Judg.18.15"/> They stepped aside to the house of the young Levite, by Micah’s house,
       and greeted him. <verse eID="Judg.18.15"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.18.16" osisID="Judg.18.16"/> But while the six hundred armed warriors of the Danite clan were
       standing at the gate of the yard, <verse eID="Judg.18.16"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.18.17" osisID="Judg.18.17"/> the five scouts made their way inside and took the ephod, the
       house­hold gods, and the metal idol; the priest was standing at the gate of the yard with the six hundred armed
       warriors, <verse eID="Judg.18.17"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.18.18" osisID="Judg.18.18"/> while these others entered Micah’s house and took the carved metal
       idol, the ephod, and the house­hold gods. The priest said to them, <q>What are you doing?</q> <verse eID="Judg.18.18"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.18.19" osisID="Judg.18.19"/> <q>Hold your tongue,</q> they answered, <q>clap your hand on your lips,
       and come along with us; be father and priest to us. Is it better for you to be priest for one man’s household or
       priest for a whole division and clan in Israel?</q> <verse eID="Judg.18.19"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.18.20" osisID="Judg.18.20"/> The priest was glad at heart; he took the ephod and the household gods
       and the carved idol, and accompanied the force, <verse eID="Judg.18.20"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.18.21" osisID="Judg.18.21"/> which moved away, putting the children and the
       <milestone type="pb" n="295"/>
       cattle and the goods in front of them. <verse eID="Judg.18.21"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.18.22" osisID="Judg.18.22"/> When they had gone some distance from Micah’s house, the men in the
       houses near Micah’s residence mus­tered and pursued the Danites. <verse eID="Judg.18.22"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.18.23" osisID="Judg.18.23"/> They called out to the Danites, who turned their heads and said to
       Micah, <q>What ails you, that you are up in arms?</q> <verse eID="Judg.18.23"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.18.24" osisID="Judg.18.24"/> He answered, <q>You steal the gods I made, and my own priest, and off
       you go! What have I left? And then you ask what ails me!</q> <verse eID="Judg.18.24"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.18.25" osisID="Judg.18.25"/> The Danites said to him, <q>Don’t shout at us! Some hot spirit in our
       company might turn on you, and you might lose your own life and the lives of your household!</q> <verse eID="Judg.18.25"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Judg.18.26" osisID="Judg.18.26"/> Then the Danites went their way, and, as Micah saw they were too strong
       for him, he turned home. <verse eID="Judg.18.26"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.18.27" osisID="Judg.18.27"/> Taking with them the articles that Micah had made and Micah’s private
       priest, they went to Laish, a people living quiet and unsuspicious; the inhabitants they killed with­out giving
       quarter, and the town they burned; <verse eID="Judg.18.27"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.18.28" osisID="Judg.18.28"/> there was no one to succour the people, for Laish was far from Sidon
       (it lies in the val­ley of Beth-rehob), and the peo­ple had no intercourse with Aram. The Danites rebuilt the town and
       settled there, <verse eID="Judg.18.28"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.18.29" osisID="Judg.18.29"/> calling it Dan, after their ancestor Dan; but Laish was the original
       name of the town. <verse eID="Judg.18.29"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.18.30" osisID="Judg.18.30"/> The Danites set up the carved idol for them­selves, and the Danite
       priests, down to the day when the land was depopulated, were Jona­than the son of Gershom, a grandson of Moses, and
       his descendants. <verse eID="Judg.18.30"/>
      <verse sID="Judg.18.31" osisID="Judg.18.31"/> They maintained the carved idol made by Micah, all the time that the
       temple of God stood at Shilo. <verse eID="Judg.18.31"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eID="Judg.18"/>
   </div>