   <div type="book" osisID="Lev">
    <milestone type="pb" n="110"/>
    <chapter osisId="Lev.1" sId="Lev.1"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Lev.1.1" osisID="Lev.1.1"/>Then the Eternal called Moses, and from the Trysting tent gave him these orders for
       the Israelites. <verse eID="Lev.1.1"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Lev.1.2" osisID="Lev.1.2"/> <q>When any man of you brings an offering to the Eternal, you must make your
       offering from your live-stock, from your herds and flocks. <verse eID="Lev.1.2"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.1.3" osisID="Lev.1.3"/>
       If the man’s offer­ing from his herd be a burnt-offering, it must be an unblem­ished male, and he must offer it of his own
       freewill at the en­trance to the Trysting tent before the Eternal. <verse eID="Lev.1.3"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.1.4" osisID="Lev.1.4"/> He must lay his hand upon the head of the victim, and it shall be accepted as
       expiation for him. <verse eID="Lev.1.4"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.1.5" osisID="Lev.1.5"/> He must then kill the bullock before the Eternal; but Aaron’s sons, the priests,
       shall present the blood, splashing it all round the sides of the altar at the entrance to the Trysting tent. <verse eID="Lev.1.5"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.1.6" osisID="Lev.1.6"/>
       He must skin the victim and cut it up; <verse eID="Lev.1.6"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.1.7" osisID="Lev.1.7"/> then the sons of Aaron, the priests, shall put fire on the altar, arranging wood on
       the fire, <verse eID="Lev.1.7"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.1.8" osisID="Lev.1.8"/> and arranging the pieces of the victim, with its head and suet, on the wood upon
       the top of the fire on the altar. <verse eID="Lev.1.8"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.1.9" osisID="Lev.1.9"/> (The entrails and the legs the man must wash in water.) The priests shall burn the
       whole of it on the altar as a burnt-offering, an offering made by fire, with a soothing odour for the Eternal,</q><verse eID="Lev.1.9"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Lev.1.10" osisID="Lev.1.10"/><q>If his offering be from the flock, a sheep or a goat, what he offers must be an
       unblemished male. <verse eID="Lev.1.10"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.1.11" osisID="Lev.1.11"/> He must kill it on the north side of the altar before the Eternal; but Aaron’s
       sons, the priests, shall splash its blood all round the sides of the altar. <verse eID="Lev.1.11"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.1.12" osisID="Lev.1.12"/> He must cut it up, and then the priest shall arrange the pieces, with the head and
       suet, on the wood upon the top of the fire on the altar. <verse eID="Lev.1.12"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.1.13" osisID="Lev.1.13"/> (The entrails and the legs the man must wash in water.) The priests shall offer
       the whole of it, burning it on the altar, as a burnt-offering, an offering made by fire, with a soothing odour for the
       Eternal.</q>
      <verse eID="Lev.1.13"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Lev.1.14" osisID="Lev.1.14"/><q> If his offering to the Eternal be an offering of birds, what he offers must be
       a turtle-dove or a young pigeon. <verse eID="Lev.1.14"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.1.15" osisID="Lev.1.15"/> The priest shall take it to the altar, and first nip off its head, which he must
       burn on the altar; then the blood of the bird shall be squeezed out on the side of the altar, <verse eID="Lev.1.15"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.1.16" osisID="Lev.1.16"/> and the priest must remove the crop and feathers, flinging them to the east of the
       altar upon the ash-heap; <verse eID="Lev.1.16"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.1.17" osisID="Lev.1.17"/> after tearing it by the wings, though without dividing it in two, the priest shall
       burn it on the wood upon the fire on the altar, as a burnt-offering, an offering made by fire, with a soothing odour for the
       Eternal.</q> <verse eID="Lev.1.17"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eId="Lev.1"/>
    <chapter osisId="Lev.3" sId="Lev.3"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Lev.3.1" osisID="Lev.3.1"/><q>When the man’s offering is a recompense-offering, if his offering be from the herd,
       then what he offers, male or female, must be unblemished before the Eternal. <verse eID="Lev.3.1"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.3.2" osisID="Lev.3.2"/> He must lay his hand upon the head of the victim and kill it at the entrance to the
       Trysting tent; but Aaron’s sons, the priests, shall splash the blood all round the sides of the altar. <verse eID="Lev.3.2"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.3.3" osisID="Lev.3.3"/> He must offer part of the recompense-offering as an offering by fire to the
       Eternal, namely, the fat covering the entrails, all the fat on the intestines, <verse eID="Lev.3.3"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.3.4" osisID="Lev.3.4"/> the two kidneys and the fat upon them at the loins, also the lobe of the liver,
       which is to be cut off at the kidneys. <verse eID="Lev.3.4"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.3.5" osisID="Lev.3.5"/> Aaron’s sons shall
       <milestone type="pb" n="111"/> burn this above the burnt-offering on the wood upon the fire on the altar, as an offering
        made by fire, with a soothing odour for the Eternal.</q> <verse eID="Lev.3.5"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Lev.3.6" osisID="Lev.3.6"/><q>If what he offers as a recom­pense-offering be from the flock, then, male or female,
       it must be unblemished. <verse eID="Lev.3.6"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.3.7" osisID="Lev.3.7"/> If he is offering a lamb, then he shall offer it before the Eternal, <verse eID="Lev.3.7"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.3.8" osisID="Lev.3.8"/> laying his hand upon the head of the victim and then killing it in front of the
       Trysting tent; but Aaron’s sons are to splash the blood all round the sides of the altar. <verse eID="Lev.3.8"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.3.9" osisID="Lev.3.9"/> He must offer part of the recompense-­offering as an offering by fire to the
       Eternal, namely, the fat, the entire fat tail, which is to be cut off close to the backbone, the fat covering the
       entrails, all the fat on the intestines, <verse eID="Lev.3.9"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.3.10" osisID="Lev.3.10"/> the two kid­neys and the fat upon them at the loins, also the lobe of the liver,
       which is to be cut off at the kidneys. <verse eID="Lev.3.10"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.3.11" osisID="Lev.3.11"/> The priest shall burn this on the altar, as the food of the offering made by fire
       to the Eternal. <verse eID="Lev.3.11"/></q>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Lev.3.12" osisID="Lev.3.12"/><q> If what he offers is a goat, then he shall offer it before the Eternal, <verse eID="Lev.3.12"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.3.13" osisID="Lev.3.13"/> laying his hand upon the head of the victim and then killing it in front of the
       Trysting tent; but Aaron’s sons shall splash the blood all round the sides of the altar. <verse eID="Lev.3.13"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.3.14" osisID="Lev.3.14"/> He must offer part of the recompense-­offering as an offering by fire to the
       Eternal, namely, the fat covering the entrails, all the fat upon the intestines, <verse eID="Lev.3.14"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.3.15" osisID="Lev.3.15"/> the two kid­neys and the fat upon them at the loins, and the lobe of the liver,
       which is to be cut off at the kidneys. <verse eID="Lev.3.15"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.3.16" osisID="Lev.3.16"/> The priest shall burn this on the altar, as the food of the offering made by fire,
       to be a soothing odour; the fat all belongs to the Eternal. <verse eID="Lev.3.16"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.3.17" osisID="Lev.3.17"/> This regulation is to last for all time and all over the country: <q>Never eat fat
       or blood.</q> <verse eID="Lev.3.17"/></q>
     </p>
    <chapter eId="Lev.3"/>
    <chapter osisId="Lev.2" sId="Lev.2"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Lev.2.1" osisID="Lev.2.1"/><q>When a man’s offering is an offering of cereals to the Eternal, what he offers must
       be fine flour; he must pour oil upon it, adding incense, <verse eID="Lev.2.1"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.2.2" osisID="Lev.2.2"/>
       and take it to Aaron’s sons, the priests, who shall remove a handful of the flour, oil, and incense, burning it as a
       reminder to the Eternal on the altar, as an offering by fire, with a soothing odour for the Eternal; <verse eID="Lev.2.2"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.2.3" osisID="Lev.2.3"/> what is left over of the cereal-offering belongs to Aaron and his sons as being a
       most sacred part of the fire-offerings to the Eternal. <verse eID="Lev.2.3"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.2.4" osisID="Lev.2.4"/> When you offer a cereal-offering baked in the oven, it must be unleavened cakes of
       fine flour mixed with oil, <verse eID="Lev.2.4"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.2.5" osisID="Lev.2.5"/> or unleavened pancakes smeared with oil. <verse eID="Lev.2.5"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.2.6" osisID="Lev.2.6"/> If your offering is a cereal-offering of griddle-cakes, they must be made of
       un­leavened fine flour mixed with oil; break them in pieces and pour oil over them, as a cereal­-offering. <verse eID="Lev.2.6"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.2.7" osisID="Lev.2.7"/> And if your offering is a cereal-offering from the fry­ing-pan, it must be made of
       fine flour mixed with oil. <verse eID="Lev.2.7"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.2.8" osisID="Lev.2.8"/> All these cereal-offerings you must bring to the Eternal, presenting them to the
       priest, who shall take them to the altar; <verse eID="Lev.2.8"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.2.9" osisID="Lev.2.9"/> the priest shall remove from the cereal-offering the reminder-to-the-Eternal part,
       burning it on the altar, as an offering made by fire, with a soothing odour for the Eternal. <verse eID="Lev.2.9"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.2.10" osisID="Lev.2.10"/> What is left over of the cereal-offering belongs to Aaron and his sons, as being
       a most sacred part of the fire-offerings to the Eternal. <verse eID="Lev.2.10"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.2.11" osisID="Lev.2.11"/> No cereal-offering to the Eternal is to be made with dough; you must never burn
       dough or honey in any fire-offering to the
       <milestone type="pb" n="112"/>
       Eternal. <verse eID="Lev.2.11"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.2.12" osisID="Lev.2.12"/> You may offer these to the Eternal as first-fruits, but they must never appear on
       the altar as a soothing odour. <verse eID="Lev.2.12"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.2.13" osisID="Lev.2.13"/> Also, you must season every cereal-offer­ing with salt; never leave the salt of
       the Compact of your God out of your cereal-offering; offer salt with every offering. <verse eID="Lev.2.13"/></q>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Lev.2.14" osisID="Lev.2.14"/><q> If you offer a cereal-offering of firstfruits to the Eternal, you must offer
       roasted ears of corn, bruised grain from fresh corn. <verse eID="Lev.2.14"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.2.15" osisID="Lev.2.15"/> Add oil to it and sprinkle incense on it, as a cereal-offering. <verse eID="Lev.2.15"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.2.16" osisID="Lev.2.16"/> The priest shall burn the reminder-to-the-Eternal part of the bruised grain, the
       oil, and the incenses, as an offering made by fire to the Eternal.</q> <verse eID="Lev.2.16"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eId="Lev.2"/>
    <chapter osisId="Lev.4" sId="Lev.4"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Lev.4.1" osisID="Lev.4.1"/>Then the Eternal gave Moses these orders <verse eID="Lev.4.1"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.4.2" osisID="Lev.4.2"/> for the Israelites in the case of anyone sinning unawares, doing
       something which the Eternal has forbidden to be done. <verse eID="Lev.4.2"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Lev.4.3" osisID="Lev.4.3"/><q>If an anointed priest by sinning makes the people incur guilt, then he
       must offer to the Eternal for the sin he has committed a young unblemished bullock as a sin-offering. <verse eID="Lev.4.3"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.4.4" osisID="Lev.4.4"/> He must bring the bullock to the entrance of the Trysting tent before the
       Eternal, lay his hand upon the head of the bullock, and then kill the bullock before the Eternal. <verse eID="Lev.4.4"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.4.5" osisID="Lev.4.5"/> The anointed priest must then take some of the bullock’s blood into the
       Trysting tent, <verse eID="Lev.4.5"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.4.6" osisID="Lev.4.6"/> dip his finger in the blood, and sprinkle some of the blood seven times
       before the Eternal, before the curtain of the inner sanctuary. <verse eID="Lev.4.6"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.4.7" osisID="Lev.4.7"/> The priest must also smear some of the blood on the knobs of the altar
       for fragrant incense before the Eternal which stands inside the Trysting tent; all the rest of the bullock’s
       blood he must pour out at the base of the altar of burnt-offering which stands at the entrance to the Trysting
       tent. <verse eID="Lev.4.7"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.4.8" osisID="Lev.4.8"/> He must remove all the fat from the bullock of the sin-offering, the fat
       covering the entrails, all the fat on the intestines, <verse eID="Lev.4.8"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.4.9" osisID="Lev.4.9"/> the two kidneys with the fat upon them at the loins, also the lobe of the
       liver, which is to be cut off at the kidneys, <verse eID="Lev.4.9"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.4.10" osisID="Lev.4.10"/> just as in the case of the bullock sacrificed in the
       recompense-offering; this is all to be burned by the priest on the altar of burnt-offering. <verse eID="Lev.4.10"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.4.11" osisID="Lev.4.11"/> The skin of the bullock, all its flesh, its head, legs, entrails, and
      dung-- <verse eID="Lev.4.11"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.4.12" osisID="Lev.4.12"/>all the rest of the bullock must be carried away by the priest to some
       clean spot where ashes are poured out, and burned up there on a wood-fire; it must be burned where the ashes are
       poured out.</q><verse eID="Lev.4.12"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Lev.4.13" osisID="Lev.4.13"/><q> If the whole community of Israel does some wrong which escapes the
       notice of the people, if they have done something which the Eternal has forbidden to be done, and so incur guilt, <verse eID="Lev.4.13"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.4.14" osisID="Lev.4.14"/> then, as soon as their sin is discovered, the people must offer a
       bullock as a sin-offering, bringing it in front of the Trysting tent; <verse eID="Lev.4.14"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.4.15" osisID="Lev.4.15"/> the sheikhs of the community must lay their hands upon the head of the
       bullock before the Eternal, and then the bullock shall be killed before the Eternal. <verse eID="Lev.4.15"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.4.16" osisID="Lev.4.16"/> The anointed priest 16 shall take some of the bullock’s blood into the
       Trysting tent, <verse eID="Lev.4.16"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.4.17" osisID="Lev.4.17"/> dip his finger in the blood, and sprinkle some of it seven times before
       the Eternal, before the curtain; <verse eID="Lev.4.17"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.4.18" osisID="Lev.4.18"/> he shall smear some of the blood on the knobs of the altar which stands
       before the Eternal inside the Trysting tent, and pour all the rest of the blood out at the base of the altar of
       <milestone type="pb" n="113"/>
       burnt-offering at the entrance to the Trysting tent. <verse eID="Lev.4.18"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.4.19" osisID="Lev.4.19"/> He must remove all the fat of the victim and burn it on the altar. <verse eID="Lev.4.19"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.4.20" osisID="Lev.4.20"/> This is what he must do to the bullock, treating it as he treated the
       bullock of the sin-offering; <verse eID="Lev.4.20"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.4.21" osisID="Lev.4.21"/> he must also carry the bullock outside the camp and burn it as he
       burned the first bullock. <verse eID="Lev.4.21"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.4.20" osisID="Lev.4.20"/> Such is the sin-offering for the people. The priest shall thus make
       expiation for them, and they shall be forgiven.</q><verse eID="Lev.4.20"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Lev.4.22" osisID="Lev.4.22"/><q>When a chief sins unawares, doing something which the Eternal his God
       has forbidden him to do, and so incurring guilt, <verse eID="Lev.4.22"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.4.23" osisID="Lev.4.23"/>if he becomes conscious of the sin he has committed, he must bring an
       unblemished hairy goat as his offering, <verse eID="Lev.4.23"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.4.24" osisID="Lev.4.24"/> lay his hand upon the head of the goat, and then kill it where the
       victims of the burnt-offering are killed before the Eternal: it is a sin-offering. <verse eID="Lev.4.24"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.4.25" osisID="Lev.4.25"/> The priest shall then take some of the blood of the victim with his
       finger and smear it on the knobs of the altar of burnt-offering, pouring the rest of the blood out at the base
       of the altar of burnt-offering. <verse eID="Lev.4.25"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.4.26" osisID="Lev.4.26"/> All the fat he must burn on the altar, like the fat of the victims
       sacrificed in recompense-offerings; so shall the priest make expiation for him in the matter of his sin, and he
       shall be forgiven.</q><verse eID="Lev.4.26"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Lev.4.27" osisID="Lev.4.27"/><q>When any ordinary person sins unawares, doing something which the
       Eternal has forbidden to be done, and so incurring guilt, <verse eID="Lev.4.27"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.4.28" osisID="Lev.4.28"/> if he becomes conscious of the sin he has committed, then he must bring
       an unblemished female goat as his offering for the sin he has committed; <verse eID="Lev.4.28"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.4.29" osisID="Lev.4.29"/> he must lay his hand upon the head of this sin-offering and kill the
       victim at the spot for burnt-offerings. <verse eID="Lev.4.29"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.4.30" osisID="Lev.4.30"/> The priest must then take some of the blood with his finger and smear
       the knobs of the altar of burnt-offering, pouring all the rest of the blood out at the base of the altar. <verse eID="Lev.4.30"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.4.31" osisID="Lev.4.31"/> All its fat he must remove, as he removes the fat from the victims
       sacrificed in the recompense-offerings; he must burn it on the altar as a soothing odour for the Eternal. So
       shall the priest make expiation for the man, and he shall be forgiven. <verse eID="Lev.4.31"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.4.32" osisID="Lev.4.32"/> If he brings a sheep as his offering for sin, he must bring an
       unblemished ewe, <verse eID="Lev.4.32"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.4.33" osisID="Lev.4.33"/> laying his hand upon the head of this sin-offering and killing it where
       the victims of the burnt-offering are killed. <verse eID="Lev.4.33"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.4.34" osisID="Lev.4.34"/> The priest shall then take some of the blood with his finger and smear
       the knobs of the altar of burnt-offering, pouring out all the rest of the blood at the base of the altar; <verse eID="Lev.4.34"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.4.35" osisID="Lev.4.35"/> all the fat he must remove, as he removes the fat from the lamb
       sacrificed in the recompense-offering, burning it on the altar like the fire-offerings to the Eternal. So shall
       the priest make expiation for the man in connexion with the sin he has committed, and he shall be forgiven.</q>
      <verse eID="Lev.4.35"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eId="Lev.4"/>
   </div>
       