   <div type="book" osisID="Lev">
    <milestone type="pb" n="110"/>
    <chapter osisId="Lev.1" sId="Lev.1"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Lev.1.1" osisID="Lev.1.1"/>Then the Eternal called Moses, and from the Trysting tent gave him these orders for
       the Israelites. <verse eID="Lev.1.1"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Lev.1.2" osisID="Lev.1.2"/> <q>When any man of you brings an offering to the Eternal, you must make your
       offering from your live-stock, from your herds and flocks. <verse eID="Lev.1.2"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.1.3" osisID="Lev.1.3"/>
       If the man’s offer­ing from his herd be a burnt-offering, it must be an unblem­ished male, and he must offer it of his own
       freewill at the en­trance to the Trysting tent before the Eternal. <verse eID="Lev.1.3"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.1.4" osisID="Lev.1.4"/> He must lay his hand upon the head of the victim, and it shall be accepted as
       expiation for him. <verse eID="Lev.1.4"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.1.5" osisID="Lev.1.5"/> He must then kill the bullock before the Eternal; but Aaron’s sons, the priests,
       shall present the blood, splashing it all round the sides of the altar at the entrance to the Trysting tent. <verse eID="Lev.1.5"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.1.6" osisID="Lev.1.6"/>
       He must skin the victim and cut it up; <verse eID="Lev.1.6"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.1.7" osisID="Lev.1.7"/> then the sons of Aaron, the priests, shall put fire on the altar, arranging wood on
       the fire, <verse eID="Lev.1.7"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.1.8" osisID="Lev.1.8"/> and arranging the pieces of the victim, with its head and suet, on the wood upon
       the top of the fire on the altar. <verse eID="Lev.1.8"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.1.9" osisID="Lev.1.9"/> (The entrails and the legs the man must wash in water.) The priests shall burn the
       whole of it on the altar as a burnt-offering, an offering made by fire, with a soothing odour for the Eternal,</q><verse eID="Lev.1.9"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Lev.1.10" osisID="Lev.1.10"/><q>If his offering be from the flock, a sheep or a goat, what he offers must be an
       unblemished male. <verse eID="Lev.1.10"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.1.11" osisID="Lev.1.11"/> He must kill it on the north side of the altar before the Eternal; but Aaron’s
       sons, the priests, shall splash its blood all round the sides of the altar. <verse eID="Lev.1.11"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.1.12" osisID="Lev.1.12"/> He must cut it up, and then the priest shall arrange the pieces, with the head and
       suet, on the wood upon the top of the fire on the altar. <verse eID="Lev.1.12"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.1.13" osisID="Lev.1.13"/> (The entrails and the legs the man must wash in water.) The priests shall offer
       the whole of it, burning it on the altar, as a burnt-offering, an offering made by fire, with a soothing odour for the
       Eternal.</q>
      <verse eID="Lev.1.13"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Lev.1.14" osisID="Lev.1.14"/><q> If his offering to the Eternal be an offering of birds, what he offers must be
       a turtle-dove or a young pigeon. <verse eID="Lev.1.14"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.1.15" osisID="Lev.1.15"/> The priest shall take it to the altar, and first nip off its head, which he must
       burn on the altar; then the blood of the bird shall be squeezed out on the side of the altar, <verse eID="Lev.1.15"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.1.16" osisID="Lev.1.16"/> and the priest must remove the crop and feathers, flinging them to the east of the
       altar upon the ash-heap; <verse eID="Lev.1.16"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.1.17" osisID="Lev.1.17"/> after tearing it by the wings, though without dividing it in two, the priest shall
       burn it on the wood upon the fire on the altar, as a burnt-offering, an offering made by fire, with a soothing odour for the
       Eternal.</q> <verse eID="Lev.1.17"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eId="Lev.1"/>
    <chapter osisId="Lev.3" sId="Lev.3"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Lev.3.1" osisID="Lev.3.1"/><q>When the man’s offering is a recompense-offering, if his offering be from the herd,
       then what he offers, male or female, must be unblemished before the Eternal. <verse eID="Lev.3.1"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.3.2" osisID="Lev.3.2"/> He must lay his hand upon the head of the victim and kill it at the entrance to the
       Trysting tent; but Aaron’s sons, the priests, shall splash the blood all round the sides of the altar. <verse eID="Lev.3.2"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.3.3" osisID="Lev.3.3"/> He must offer part of the recompense-offering as an offering by fire to the
       Eternal, namely, the fat covering the entrails, all the fat on the intestines, <verse eID="Lev.3.3"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.3.4" osisID="Lev.3.4"/> the two kidneys and the fat upon them at the loins, also the lobe of the liver,
       which is to be cut off at the kidneys. <verse eID="Lev.3.4"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.3.5" osisID="Lev.3.5"/> Aaron’s sons shall
       <milestone type="pb" n="111"/> burn this above the burnt-offering on the wood upon the fire on the altar, as an offering
        made by fire, with a soothing odour for the Eternal.</q> <verse eID="Lev.3.5"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Lev.3.6" osisID="Lev.3.6"/><q>If what he offers as a recom­pense-offering be from the flock, then, male or female,
       it must be unblemished. <verse eID="Lev.3.6"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.3.7" osisID="Lev.3.7"/> If he is offering a lamb, then he shall offer it before the Eternal, <verse eID="Lev.3.7"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.3.8" osisID="Lev.3.8"/> laying his hand upon the head of the victim and then killing it in front of the
       Trysting tent; but Aaron’s sons are to splash the blood all round the sides of the altar. <verse eID="Lev.3.8"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.3.9" osisID="Lev.3.9"/> He must offer part of the recompense-­offering as an offering by fire to the
       Eternal, namely, the fat, the entire fat tail, which is to be cut off close to the backbone, the fat covering the
       entrails, all the fat on the intestines, <verse eID="Lev.3.9"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.3.10" osisID="Lev.3.10"/> the two kid­neys and the fat upon them at the loins, also the lobe of the liver,
       which is to be cut off at the kidneys. <verse eID="Lev.3.10"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.3.11" osisID="Lev.3.11"/> The priest shall burn this on the altar, as the food of the offering made by fire
       to the Eternal. <verse eID="Lev.3.11"/></q>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Lev.3.12" osisID="Lev.3.12"/><q> If what he offers is a goat, then he shall offer it before the Eternal, <verse eID="Lev.3.12"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.3.13" osisID="Lev.3.13"/> laying his hand upon the head of the victim and then killing it in front of the
       Trysting tent; but Aaron’s sons shall splash the blood all round the sides of the altar. <verse eID="Lev.3.13"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.3.14" osisID="Lev.3.14"/> He must offer part of the recompense-­offering as an offering by fire to the
       Eternal, namely, the fat covering the entrails, all the fat upon the intestines, <verse eID="Lev.3.14"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.3.15" osisID="Lev.3.15"/> the two kid­neys and the fat upon them at the loins, and the lobe of the liver,
       which is to be cut off at the kidneys. <verse eID="Lev.3.15"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.3.16" osisID="Lev.3.16"/> The priest shall burn this on the altar, as the food of the offering made by fire,
       to be a soothing odour; the fat all belongs to the Eternal. <verse eID="Lev.3.16"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.3.17" osisID="Lev.3.17"/> This regulation is to last for all time and all over the country: <q>Never eat fat
       or blood.</q> <verse eID="Lev.3.17"/></q>
     </p>
    <chapter eId="Lev.3"/>
    <chapter osisId="Lev.2" sId="Lev.2"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Lev.2.1" osisID="Lev.2.1"/><q>When a man’s offering is an offering of cereals to the Eternal, what he offers must
       be fine flour; he must pour oil upon it, adding incense, <verse eID="Lev.2.1"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.2.2" osisID="Lev.2.2"/>
       and take it to Aaron’s sons, the priests, who shall remove a handful of the flour, oil, and incense, burning it as a
       reminder to the Eternal on the altar, as an offering by fire, with a soothing odour for the Eternal; <verse eID="Lev.2.2"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.2.3" osisID="Lev.2.3"/> what is left over of the cereal-offering belongs to Aaron and his sons as being a
       most sacred part of the fire-offerings to the Eternal. <verse eID="Lev.2.3"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.2.4" osisID="Lev.2.4"/> When you offer a cereal-offering baked in the oven, it must be unleavened cakes of
       fine flour mixed with oil, <verse eID="Lev.2.4"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.2.5" osisID="Lev.2.5"/> or unleavened pancakes smeared with oil. <verse eID="Lev.2.5"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.2.6" osisID="Lev.2.6"/> If your offering is a cereal-offering of griddle-cakes, they must be made of
       un­leavened fine flour mixed with oil; break them in pieces and pour oil over them, as a cereal­-offering. <verse eID="Lev.2.6"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.2.7" osisID="Lev.2.7"/> And if your offering is a cereal-offering from the fry­ing-pan, it must be made of
       fine flour mixed with oil. <verse eID="Lev.2.7"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.2.8" osisID="Lev.2.8"/> All these cereal-offerings you must bring to the Eternal, presenting them to the
       priest, who shall take them to the altar; <verse eID="Lev.2.8"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.2.9" osisID="Lev.2.9"/> the priest shall remove from the cereal-offering the reminder-to-the-Eternal part,
       burning it on the altar, as an offering made by fire, with a soothing odour for the Eternal. <verse eID="Lev.2.9"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.2.10" osisID="Lev.2.10"/> What is left over of the cereal-offering belongs to Aaron and his sons, as being
       a most sacred part of the fire-offerings to the Eternal. <verse eID="Lev.2.10"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.2.11" osisID="Lev.2.11"/> No cereal-offering to the Eternal is to be made with dough; you must never burn
       dough or honey in any fire-offering to the
       <milestone type="pb" n="112"/>
       Eternal. <verse eID="Lev.2.11"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.2.12" osisID="Lev.2.12"/> You may offer these to the Eternal as first-fruits, but they must never appear on
       the altar as a soothing odour. <verse eID="Lev.2.12"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.2.13" osisID="Lev.2.13"/> Also, you must season every cereal-offer­ing with salt; never leave the salt of
       the Compact of your God out of your cereal-offering; offer salt with every offering. <verse eID="Lev.2.13"/></q>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Lev.2.14" osisID="Lev.2.14"/><q> If you offer a cereal-offering of firstfruits to the Eternal, you must offer
       roasted ears of corn, bruised grain from fresh corn. <verse eID="Lev.2.14"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.2.15" osisID="Lev.2.15"/> Add oil to it and sprinkle incense on it, as a cereal-offering. <verse eID="Lev.2.15"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.2.16" osisID="Lev.2.16"/> The priest shall burn the reminder-to-the-Eternal part of the bruised grain, the
       oil, and the incenses, as an offering made by fire to the Eternal.</q> <verse eID="Lev.2.16"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eId="Lev.2"/>
    <chapter osisId="Lev.4" sId="Lev.4"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Lev.4.1" osisID="Lev.4.1"/>Then the Eternal gave Moses these orders <verse eID="Lev.4.1"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.4.2" osisID="Lev.4.2"/> for the Israelites in the case of anyone sinning unawares, doing
       something which the Eternal has forbidden to be done. <verse eID="Lev.4.2"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Lev.4.3" osisID="Lev.4.3"/><q>If an anointed priest by sinning makes the people incur guilt, then he
       must offer to the Eternal for the sin he has committed a young unblemished bullock as a sin-offering. <verse eID="Lev.4.3"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.4.4" osisID="Lev.4.4"/> He must bring the bullock to the entrance of the Trysting tent before the
       Eternal, lay his hand upon the head of the bullock, and then kill the bullock before the Eternal. <verse eID="Lev.4.4"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.4.5" osisID="Lev.4.5"/> The anointed priest must then take some of the bullock’s blood into the
       Trysting tent, <verse eID="Lev.4.5"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.4.6" osisID="Lev.4.6"/> dip his finger in the blood, and sprinkle some of the blood seven times
       before the Eternal, before the curtain of the inner sanctuary. <verse eID="Lev.4.6"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.4.7" osisID="Lev.4.7"/> The priest must also smear some of the blood on the knobs of the altar
       for fragrant incense before the Eternal which stands inside the Trysting tent; all the rest of the bullock’s
       blood he must pour out at the base of the altar of burnt-offering which stands at the entrance to the Trysting
       tent. <verse eID="Lev.4.7"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.4.8" osisID="Lev.4.8"/> He must remove all the fat from the bullock of the sin-offering, the fat
       covering the entrails, all the fat on the intestines, <verse eID="Lev.4.8"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.4.9" osisID="Lev.4.9"/> the two kidneys with the fat upon them at the loins, also the lobe of the
       liver, which is to be cut off at the kidneys, <verse eID="Lev.4.9"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.4.10" osisID="Lev.4.10"/> just as in the case of the bullock sacrificed in the
       recompense-offering; this is all to be burned by the priest on the altar of burnt-offering. <verse eID="Lev.4.10"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.4.11" osisID="Lev.4.11"/> The skin of the bullock, all its flesh, its head, legs, entrails, and
      dung-- <verse eID="Lev.4.11"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.4.12" osisID="Lev.4.12"/>all the rest of the bullock must be carried away by the priest to some
       clean spot where ashes are poured out, and burned up there on a wood-fire; it must be burned where the ashes are
       poured out.</q><verse eID="Lev.4.12"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Lev.4.13" osisID="Lev.4.13"/><q> If the whole community of Israel does some wrong which escapes the
       notice of the people, if they have done something which the Eternal has forbidden to be done, and so incur guilt, <verse eID="Lev.4.13"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.4.14" osisID="Lev.4.14"/> then, as soon as their sin is discovered, the people must offer a
       bullock as a sin-offering, bringing it in front of the Trysting tent; <verse eID="Lev.4.14"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.4.15" osisID="Lev.4.15"/> the sheikhs of the community must lay their hands upon the head of the
       bullock before the Eternal, and then the bullock shall be killed before the Eternal. <verse eID="Lev.4.15"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.4.16" osisID="Lev.4.16"/> The anointed priest 16 shall take some of the bullock’s blood into the
       Trysting tent, <verse eID="Lev.4.16"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.4.17" osisID="Lev.4.17"/> dip his finger in the blood, and sprinkle some of it seven times before
       the Eternal, before the curtain; <verse eID="Lev.4.17"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.4.18" osisID="Lev.4.18"/> he shall smear some of the blood on the knobs of the altar which stands
       before the Eternal inside the Trysting tent, and pour all the rest of the blood out at the base of the altar of
       <milestone type="pb" n="113"/>
       burnt-offering at the entrance to the Trysting tent. <verse eID="Lev.4.18"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.4.19" osisID="Lev.4.19"/> He must remove all the fat of the victim and burn it on the altar. <verse eID="Lev.4.19"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.4.20" osisID="Lev.4.20"/> This is what he must do to the bullock, treating it as he treated the
       bullock of the sin-offering; <verse eID="Lev.4.20"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.4.21" osisID="Lev.4.21"/> he must also carry the bullock outside the camp and burn it as he
       burned the first bullock. <verse eID="Lev.4.21"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.4.20" osisID="Lev.4.20"/> Such is the sin-offering for the people. The priest shall thus make
       expiation for them, and they shall be forgiven.</q><verse eID="Lev.4.20"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Lev.4.22" osisID="Lev.4.22"/><q>When a chief sins unawares, doing something which the Eternal his God
       has forbidden him to do, and so incurring guilt, <verse eID="Lev.4.22"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.4.23" osisID="Lev.4.23"/>if he becomes conscious of the sin he has committed, he must bring an
       unblemished hairy goat as his offering, <verse eID="Lev.4.23"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.4.24" osisID="Lev.4.24"/> lay his hand upon the head of the goat, and then kill it where the
       victims of the burnt-offering are killed before the Eternal: it is a sin-offering. <verse eID="Lev.4.24"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.4.25" osisID="Lev.4.25"/> The priest shall then take some of the blood of the victim with his
       finger and smear it on the knobs of the altar of burnt-offering, pouring the rest of the blood out at the base
       of the altar of burnt-offering. <verse eID="Lev.4.25"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.4.26" osisID="Lev.4.26"/> All the fat he must burn on the altar, like the fat of the victims
       sacrificed in recompense-offerings; so shall the priest make expiation for him in the matter of his sin, and he
       shall be forgiven.</q><verse eID="Lev.4.26"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Lev.4.27" osisID="Lev.4.27"/><q>When any ordinary person sins unawares, doing something which the
       Eternal has forbidden to be done, and so incurring guilt, <verse eID="Lev.4.27"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.4.28" osisID="Lev.4.28"/> if he becomes conscious of the sin he has committed, then he must bring
       an unblemished female goat as his offering for the sin he has committed; <verse eID="Lev.4.28"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.4.29" osisID="Lev.4.29"/> he must lay his hand upon the head of this sin-offering and kill the
       victim at the spot for burnt-offerings. <verse eID="Lev.4.29"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.4.30" osisID="Lev.4.30"/> The priest must then take some of the blood with his finger and smear
       the knobs of the altar of burnt-offering, pouring all the rest of the blood out at the base of the altar. <verse eID="Lev.4.30"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.4.31" osisID="Lev.4.31"/> All its fat he must remove, as he removes the fat from the victims
       sacrificed in the recompense-offerings; he must burn it on the altar as a soothing odour for the Eternal. So
       shall the priest make expiation for the man, and he shall be forgiven. <verse eID="Lev.4.31"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.4.32" osisID="Lev.4.32"/> If he brings a sheep as his offering for sin, he must bring an
       unblemished ewe, <verse eID="Lev.4.32"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.4.33" osisID="Lev.4.33"/> laying his hand upon the head of this sin-offering and killing it where
       the victims of the burnt-offering are killed. <verse eID="Lev.4.33"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.4.34" osisID="Lev.4.34"/> The priest shall then take some of the blood with his finger and smear
       the knobs of the altar of burnt-offering, pouring out all the rest of the blood at the base of the altar; <verse eID="Lev.4.34"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.4.35" osisID="Lev.4.35"/> all the fat he must remove, as he removes the fat from the lamb
       sacrificed in the recompense-offering, burning it on the altar like the fire-offerings to the Eternal. So shall
       the priest make expiation for the man in connexion with the sin he has committed, and he shall be forgiven.</q>
      <verse eID="Lev.4.35"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eId="Lev.4"/>
    <chapter osisId="Lev.5" sId="Lev.5"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Lev.5.1" osisID="Lev.5.1"/><q>(If anyone sins by remaining silent when he is adjured to give evidence as
       a witness of something he has seen or known, and so incurs punishment; <verse eID="Lev.5.1"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.5.2" osisID="Lev.5.2"/> or if anyone touches something un­clean, the carcase of an unclean wild
       animal or of an unclean farm-beast or of an unclean reptile, without being aware of it at the time, and so incurs
       guilt for becoming himself unclean; <verse eID="Lev.5.2"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.5.3" osisID="Lev.5.3"/> or if he touches any sort of human uncleanness, without knowing it at the
       moment, and so incurs guilt;
      <verse eID="Lev.5.3"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.5.4" osisID="Lev.5.4"/>
       or if anyone utters a rash
       <milestone type="pb" n="114"/>
       vow to do something either evil or good, taking any sort of rash oath as men will do, unthinkingly, and then
       becomes conscious of what he has done, incurring guilt; <verse eID="Lev.5.4"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.5.5" osisID="Lev.5.5"/> then, after incurring guilt in any of these ways, he must confess the sin
       he has committed, <verse eID="Lev.5.5"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.5.6" osisID="Lev.5.6"/> and bring to the Eternal, as amends for the sin he has committed, a
       female animal from his flock, either sheep or goat, as a sin-offering; the priest shall then make expiation for
       him in the matter of his sin.)</q><verse eID="Lev.5.6"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Lev.5.7" osisID="Lev.5.7"/><q>If he cannot afford a lamb, then he must bring to the Eternal as his
       offering for sin two turtle-doves or two young pigeons, one as a sin-offering and the other as a burnt-offering;
      <verse eID="Lev.5.7"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.5.8" osisID="Lev.5.8"/> he must take them to the priest, who shall offer the sin-offering first,
       nipping the bird’s head from its neck, without tearing the bird in two, <verse eID="Lev.5.8"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.5.9" osisID="Lev.5.9"/> sprinkling some of the blood on the side of the altar, and draining off
       the rest of the blood at the base of the altar, as a sin-offering. <verse eID="Lev.5.9"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.5.10" osisID="Lev.5.10"/> The second bird he shall sacrifice as a burnt-offering in the regular
       way. So shall the priest make expiation for him in the matter of the sin he has committed, he shall be forgiven. <verse eID="Lev.5.10"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.5.11" osisID="Lev.5.11"/> If he cannot afford even two turtle­doves or two young pigeons, he must bring as
       his sacrifice for his sin a tenth of a bushel of fine flour as a sin-offering; he must not add any oil or incense, for
       it is a sin-offering. <verse eID="Lev.5.11"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.5.12" osisID="Lev.5.12"/> He must take it to the priest, who shall remove the handful that serves as a
       re­minder to the Eternal, burning it on the altar, like the offerings made by fire to the Eternal; it is a sin-offering. <verse eID="Lev.5.12"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.5.13" osisID="Lev.5.13"/> So shall the priest make expiation for him in connexion with any of these sins
       of his, and he shall be forgiven. (The rest belongs to the priest, as in the case of the cereal-­offering.)</q>
      <verse eID="Lev.5.13"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Lev.5.14" osisID="Lev.5.14"/> The Eternal said to Moses, <verse eID="Lev.5.14"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.5.15" osisID="Lev.5.15"/> <q>If anyone commits fraud, incurring guilt unawares by appro­priating something
       sacred to the Eternal, then he must bring as amends for it to the Eternal an unblemished ram from his flock, valued in
       silver coin at least two half-crowns (by the half-crown of the sanctuary); <verse eID="Lev.5.15"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.5.16" osisID="Lev.5.16"/> he must also restore the sacred thing he has appropriated, adding a fifth to
       it, and handing it over to the priest, who shall make expiation for him by sacrificing the ram as amends for his sin; so
       shall he be forgiven. <verse eID="Lev.5.16"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.5.17" osisID="Lev.5.17"/> [[If anyone sins by doing something which the Eternal has forbidden to be done,
       though he is unaware of it, and incurs guilt and punishment for it, <verse eID="Lev.5.17"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.5.18" osisID="Lev.5.18"/> then he must bring to the priest an unblemished ram of some value from his
       flock, as amends for his sin; the priest shall make expiation for him over the wrong he did all un­awares, and he shall
       be forgiven. <verse eID="Lev.5.18"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.5.19" osisID="Lev.5.19"/> This is an offering for guilt, for the man is certainly guilty in the sight of
       the Eternal.]]</q> <verse eID="Lev.5.19"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eId="Lev.5"/>
    <chapter osisId="Lev.6" sId="Lev.6"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Lev.6.1" osisID="Lev.6.1"/> The Eternal said to Moses, <verse eID="Lev.6.1"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.6.2" osisID="Lev.6.2"/><q>If anyone sins by committing fraud against the Eternal, by cheating a neighbour
       over some deposit or pledge, or by theft, or by taking advantage of his neighbour, <verse eID="Lev.6.2"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.6.3" osisID="Lev.6.3"/> or by denying it when he has found some lost property, taking a false oath to
       that effect; then, in the case of any of these sins, <verse eID="Lev.6.3"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.6.4" osisID="Lev.6.4"/> if he be guilty of any of them, he must restore what he robbed or what he
       ex­torted or what was deposited with him for safe keeping, or the lost property he found,
      <verse eID="Lev.6.4"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.6.5" osisID="Lev.6.5"/>
       or anything 
       <milestone type="pb" n="115"/>
       about which he swore a false oath; he must restore it in full, adding a fifth to it, and handing it back to the owner on
       the day when he offers his guilt-offering. <verse eID="Lev.6.5"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.6.6" osisID="Lev.6.6"/> The guilt-offer­ing he must bring to the Eternal is an unblemished ram of some
       value from the flock, which he must hand to the priest, <verse eID="Lev.6.6"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.6.7" osisID="Lev.6.7"/> who shall make expiation for him be­fore the Eternal, and then he shall be
       forgiven for any mis­deed of which he has been guilty.</q>
      <verse eID="Lev.6.7"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Lev.6.8" osisID="Lev.6.8"/>Thie Eternal said to Moses, <verse eID="Lev.6.8"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.6.9" osisID="Lev.6.9"/><q>Enjoin upon Aaron and his sons this law for the burnt-offering. The
       burnt-offering must, remain on its firewood on the altar all night till the morn­ing, and the fire must be kept burning
       with firewood on the altar. <verse eID="Lev.6.9"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.6.10" osisID="Lev.6.10"/> Then the priest must put on his linen vestment, with linen drawers on his
       middle; he must remove the ashes to which the fire has reduced the burnt-offer­ing on the altar and lay them beside the
       altar; <verse eID="Lev.6.10"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.6.11" osisID="Lev.6.11"/> then, stripping off his vestments and putting on other vestments, he must carry
       the ashes outside the camp to a clean spot. <verse eID="Lev.6.11"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.6.12" osisID="Lev.6.12"/> The fire must be kept burning on the altar, never allowed to go out; the priest
       must put firewood on it every morning. He shall arrange the burnt-offering on it, and burn on it the fat slices of the
       recompense-offerings. <verse eID="Lev.6.12"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.6.13" osisID="Lev.6.13"/> Fire must be kept burning always on the altar; it must never be allowed to go
       out. <verse eID="Lev.6.13"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.6.14" osisID="Lev.6.14"/> Here is the law for the cereal-offering. The sons of Aaron shall offer it
       before the Eternal, in front of the altar. <verse eID="Lev.6.14"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.6.15" osisID="Lev.6.15"/> The priest shall take out his handful of the fine flour and oil and all the
       incense of the cereal-­offering, burning it as a soothing odour for the Eternal, as a reminder to the Eternal. <verse eID="Lev.6.15"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.6.16" osisID="Lev.6.16"/> The rest of it shall be eaten by Aaron and his sons as unleavened cakes in a
       sacred spot; they shall eat it in the courtyard of the Trysting tent. <verse eID="Lev.6.16"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.6.17" osisID="Lev.6.17"/> It must not be baked 17 with dough; I have assigned it to them as their share
       of the fire-offerings made to me; it is most sacred, like the sin-offering and the guilt-offering. <verse eID="Lev.6.17"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.6.18" osisID="Lev.6.18"/> Any male descendant of Aaron may eat it; it is your due for all time, from
       generation to generation, out of the fire-offerings made to the Eternal. Anyone who touches these most sacred offerings
       shall be taboo.</q> <verse eID="Lev.6.18"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Lev.6.19" osisID="Lev.6.19"/> The Eternal said to Moses, <verse eID="Lev.6.19"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.6.20" osisID="Lev.6.20"/> <q>This is the offering to be made by Aaron and his sons to the Eternal:
       one-tenth of a bushel of fine flour they must offer daily as a cereal-offering, one-half of it in the morning and the
       other half in the evening. <verse eID="Lev.6.20"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.6.21" osisID="Lev.6.21"/> It must be cooked with oil on a griddle; bring it soaked with oil, and after
       breaking the cake in pieces offer this cereal-offering as a soothing odour to the Eter­nal. <verse eID="Lev.6.21"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.6.22" osisID="Lev.6.22"/> The anointed priest of the Aaronic succession shall offer it by a lasting rule,
       burning it all to the Eternal. <verse eID="Lev.6.22"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.6.23" osisID="Lev.6.23"/> Every cereal-offering of a priest shall be burned up; it must not be eaten.</q> <verse eID="Lev.6.23"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Lev.6.24" osisID="Lev.6.24"/> The Eternal said to Moses, <verse eID="Lev.6.24"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.6.25" osisID="Lev.6.25"/><q>Tell Aaron and his sons that this is the law of the sin-offering: the victim of
       the sin-offering is to be killed before the Eternal where the victim of the burnt-offering is killed: it is most sacred. <verse eID="Lev.6.25"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.6.26" osisID="Lev.6.26"/> The priest who offers it for sin must eat it, and it must be eaten in a sacred
       spot, in the courtyard of the Trysting tent. <verse eID="Lev.6.26"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.6.27" osisID="Lev.6.27"/> Whoever touches the meat of
       <milestone type="pb" n="116"/>
       this offering shall be taboo; and if any of its
       blood is sprinkled on any garment, you must wash that garment in a sacred spot. <verse eID="Lev.6.27"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.6.28" osisID="Lev.6.28"/> Any earthen pot in which it has been cooked must be destroyed; but if it has
       been cooked in a bronze pot, that pot need only be scoured and rinsed in water. <verse eID="Lev.6.28"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.6.29" osisID="Lev.6.29"/> Any male among the priests may eat it: it is most sacred. <verse eID="Lev.6.29"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.6.30" osisID="Lev.6.30"/> [[But no sin-offering whose blood is ever brought inside the Trysting tent for
       expiation within the sacred interior, is to be eaten; it shall be burned with fire.]]</q><verse eID="Lev.6.30"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eId="Lev.6"/>
    <chapter osisId="Lev.7" sId="Lev.7"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Lev.7.1" osisID="Lev.7.1"/><q>This is the law of the guilt-offering: it is most sacred. <verse eID="Lev.7.1"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.7.2" osisID="Lev.7.2"/> The victim in the guilt-offering must be killed where the burnt-offering is
       killed, and its blood is to be sprinkled all round the sides of the altar. <verse eID="Lev.7.2"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.7.3" osisID="Lev.7.3"/> The priest must then offer all its fat, the fat tail, the fat covering the
       en­trails, <verse eID="Lev.7.3"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.7.4" osisID="Lev.7.4"/> the two kidneys and the fat on them by the loins, and the lobe of the liver,
       which is to be cut off at the kidneys; <verse eID="Lev.7.4"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.7.5" osisID="Lev.7.5"/> this the priest shall burn on the altar as a fire-offering to the Eternal: it is
       a guilt-offering. <verse eID="Lev.7.5"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.7.6" osisID="Lev.7.6"/> Any male among the priests may eat the rest of the flesh, but it must be eaten in
       a sacred spot: it is most sacred. <verse eID="Lev.7.6"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.7.7" osisID="Lev.7.7"/> The guilt-offering is like the sin-offering; the same law holds for both: the
       meat belongs to the priest who makes the expiation. <verse eID="Lev.7.7"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.7.8" osisID="Lev.7.8"/> Any priest who offers a man’s burnt-offering for him, that priest is entitled to
       the skin of the victim, <verse eID="Lev.7.8"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.7.9" osisID="Lev.7.9"/> and any cereal-­offering baked in an oven, any­thing cooked in the frying-pan or on
       the griddle, belongs to the sacrificing priest; <verse eID="Lev.7.9"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.7.10" osisID="Lev.7.10"/> but every other cereal-offering, either mixed with oil or dry, belongs to all
       the sons of Aaron as their common property.</q><verse eID="Lev.7.10"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Lev.7.11" osisID="Lev.7.11"/><q>This is the law of sacrifice for it recompense-offerings which may be offered
       to the Eternal. <verse eID="Lev.7.11"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.7.12" osisID="Lev.7.12"/> If man offers it as a thank-offer­ing, he must offer, along with this
       thank-offering, unleavened cakes mixed with oil, and un­leavened pancakes smeared with oil, and fine flour mixed with
       oil. <verse eID="Lev.7.12"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.7.13" osisID="Lev.7.13"/> In addition to the sacrifice of his thank-offering, he must bring leavened
       cakes as part of his offering. <verse eID="Lev.7.13"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.7.14" osisID="Lev.7.14"/> From this he must offer one cake of each sort as a select portion set aside for
       the Eternal; it belongs to the priest who splashes the blood of the recompense-offering. <verse eID="Lev.7.14"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.7.15" osisID="Lev.7.15"/> The flesh of the victim of the recompense-offering which is offered as a
       thank-offering must be eaten on the day it is sacrificed; nothing must be left over till next morn­ing. <verse eID="Lev.7.15"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.7.16" osisID="Lev.7.16"/> But if he is offering a votive offering or a freewill offering, while the
       flesh must be eaten on the day it is sacrificed, anything left over may be eaten next day; <verse eID="Lev.7.16"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.7.17" osisID="Lev.7.17"/> whatever remains on the third day must be burned up. <verse eID="Lev.7.17"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.7.18" osisID="Lev.7.18"/> If any meat from the recompense-offerings is eaten on the third day, the
       offering shall not win you favour, it shall not count for the man who has offered it; it shall be reckoned mere refuse,
       and anyone who eats it must pay the pen­alty. <verse eID="Lev.7.18"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.7.19" osisID="Lev.7.19"/> Also, no flour that has touched anything unclean is to be eaten; it must be
       burned up. As for sacrificial flesh, anyone who is clean may eat it; <verse eID="Lev.7.19"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.7.20" osisID="Lev.7.20"/> but if anyone in a state of uncleanness eats the flesh of any
       recompense-­offering belonging to the Eternal, that soul shall be outlawed from his kinsfolk.
      <verse eID="Lev.7.20"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.7.21" osisID="Lev.7.21"/> And if anyone eats the flesh of any recompense-
       <milestone type="pb" n="117"/>
       offering belonging to the Eter­nal, after he has touched some­thing unclean, human or animal or reptile, that soul shall
       be out­lawed from his kinsfolk.</q>
      <verse eID="Lev.7.21"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Lev.7.22" osisID="Lev.7.22"/> [[The Eternal gave Moses <verse eID="Lev.7.22"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.7.23" osisID="Lev.7.23"/> these orders for the Israelites: <verse eID="Lev.7.23"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.7.24" osisID="Lev.7.24"/><q>You must never eat the fat of ox or sheep or goat. The fat of animals that
       have died a natural death or that have been torn to pieces, you may use for any other purpose, but on no account must
       you eat it; <verse eID="Lev.7.24"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.7.25" osisID="Lev.7.25"/> for who­ever eats the fat of any animal used in sacrifice and burned for the
       Eternal, that soul shall be outlawed from his kinsfolk. <verse eID="Lev.7.25"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.7.26" osisID="Lev.7.26"/> And you must never partake of blood in any of your houses, blood either of
       birds or of beasts; <verse eID="Lev.7.26"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.7.27" osisID="Lev.7.27"/> who­ever partakes of blood, that soul shall be outlawed from his kinsfolk.</q>]] <verse eID="Lev.7.27"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Lev.7.28" osisID="Lev.7.28"/> The Eternal gave Moses <verse eID="Lev.7.28"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.7.29" osisID="Lev.7.29"/> these orders for the Israelites that <q>anyone offering a recompense-offering
       in sacrifice to the Eter­nal must bring in his own hands to the Eternal the part of his recompense-offering which is to
       be burned; <verse eID="Lev.7.29"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.7.30" osisID="Lev.7.30"/> what he brings shall be the fat along with the breast of the victim, the breast
       to be waved to and fro, in presence of the Eternal, as a waved offering. <verse eID="Lev.7.30"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.7.31" osisID="Lev.7.31"/> The priest shall burn the fat on the altar, but the breast belongs to Aaron and
       his sons. <verse eID="Lev.7.31"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.7.32" osisID="Lev.7.32"/> The right thigh is also to be presented to the priest as his share of what you
       are sacrificing by way of recompense-offering; <verse eID="Lev.7.32"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.7.33" osisID="Lev.7.33"/> the particular priest who offers the blood and the fat of the
       recompense-offerings is to have the right thigh as his share. <verse eID="Lev.7.33"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.7.34" osisID="Lev.7.34"/> For I have set aside the breast that is waved and the right thigh from the
       sacrifices of the Israelites in these recompense-offerings, and assigned these to Aaron the priest and to his sons as
       their perpetual due from the Israelites.</q> <verse eID="Lev.7.34"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.7.35" osisID="Lev.7.35"/> Such is the share that fell to Aaron and his sons from the fire-offerings made
       to the Eternal, when Moses pre­sented them for the ministry of the Eternal as priests, <verse eID="Lev.7.35"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.7.36" osisID="Lev.7.36"/> the share that the Eternal ordered the Israelites to give them as their lasting
       due, generation after generation. <verse eID="Lev.7.36"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Lev.7.37" osisID="Lev.7.37"/> Such is the law of the burnt-offering, the cereal-offering, the sin-offering,
       the guilt-offering, and the recompense-offering in sacrifice, <verse eID="Lev.7.37"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.7.38" osisID="Lev.7.38"/> which the Eternal laid down for Moses on mount Sinai, when Moses was
       commanding the Israelites to present their offerings to the Eternal in the desert of Sinai. <verse eID="Lev.7.38"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eId="Lev.7"/>
    <chapter osisId="Lev.8" sId="Lev.8"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Lev.8.1" osisID="Lev.8.1"/>The Eternal then said to Moses, <verse eID="Lev.8.1"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.8.2" osisID="Lev.8.2"/> <q>Take Aaron and his sons, take the vestments and the anointing oil, the
       bullock for the sin-offering and the two rams, also the basket of unleavened cakes, <verse eID="Lev.8.2"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.8.3" osisID="Lev.8.3"/> and convene all the community at the entrance to the Trysting tent.</q> <verse eID="Lev.8.3"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.8.4" osisID="Lev.8.4"/> Moses did as the Eternal ordered him. And when the community had gath­ered at the
       entrance to the Trysting tent, <verse eID="Lev.8.4"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.8.5" osisID="Lev.8.5"/> Moses said to the community, <q>This is what the Eternal has ordered to be done.</q> <verse eID="Lev.8.5"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.8.6" osisID="Lev.8.6"/> Whereupon he brought forward Aaron and his sons and washed them with water. <verse eID="Lev.8.6"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.8.7" osisID="Lev.8.7"/> He then put the tunic on Aaron, girdled him with the sash, invested him with the
       robe, put on him the sacred apron, tying its artistic ribbon round his waist and so fastening on the apron, <verse eID="Lev.8.7"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.8.8" osisID="Lev.8.8"/> and then hung over his shoulders the sacred pouch, inside which he placed the
       sacred lots. <verse eID="Lev.8.8"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.8.9" osisID="Lev.8.9"/> He placed the turban on his head, and on his
       <milestone type="pb" n="118"/>
       forehead the golden diadem or sacred crown. All this as the Eternal had commanded Moses.
      <verse sID="Lev.8.12" osisID="Lev.8.12"/> Then Moses took some of the anointing oil and poured it over the head of Aaron,
       anointing him to consecrate him. <verse eID="Lev.8.12"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.8.13" osisID="Lev.8.13"/> Moses next brought Aaron’s sons, put tunics on them, girdled them with sashes,
       and tied caps on their heads, as the Eternal had commanded him. <verse eID="Lev.8.13"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.8.14" osisID="Lev.8.14"/> He brought forward the bullock of the sin-offering, and after Aaron and his
       sons had laid their hands on the head of the bullock, <verse eID="Lev.8.14"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.8.15" osisID="Lev.8.15"/> Moses slaughtered it. Taking some of the blood, he smeared it with his finger
       all round the knobs of the altar, pouring the rest of the blood out at the base of the altar and thereby consecrating
       it, purging it of guilt. <verse eID="Lev.8.15"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.8.16" osisID="Lev.8.16"/> Taking all the fat upon the entrails, the lobe of the liver, the two kid­neys
       and their fat, Moses burned it on the altar; <verse eID="Lev.8.16"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.8.17" osisID="Lev.8.17"/> but the skin, flesh, and dung of the bullock he burned up outside the camp, as
       the Eternal had commanded him. <verse eID="Lev.8.17"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Lev.8.18" osisID="Lev.8.18"/> He then brought the ram of the burnt-offering, and, after Aaron and his sons
       had laid their hands upon the head of the ram, <verse eID="Lev.8.18"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.8.19" osisID="Lev.8.19"/> Moses slaughtered it, splashing the blood all round the sides of the altar. <verse eID="Lev.8.19"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.8.20" osisID="Lev.8.20"/> He cut up the ram, burning the pieces, with the head and the suet, <verse eID="Lev.8.20"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.8.21" osisID="Lev.8.21"/> and washing the entrails and legs with water; the whole of this he burned on
       the altar as a burnt-offering with a soothing odour, a fire-offering of the Eternal, as the Eternal had commanded him. <verse eID="Lev.8.21"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Lev.8.22" osisID="Lev.8.22"/>He then brought the other ram, the ram for the rite of installation; after
       Aaron and his sons had laid their hands upon the head of the ram, <verse eID="Lev.8.22"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.8.23" osisID="Lev.8.23"/> Moses slaughtered it. Taking some of the blood, he smeared it on the tip of
       Aaron’s right ear, on the thumb of his right hand, and on the great toe of his right foot; <verse eID="Lev.8.23"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.8.24" osisID="Lev.8.24"/> then Moses brought Aaron’s sons and smeared some of the blood on the tips of
       their right ears, on the thumbs of their right hands, and on the great toes of their right feet; the rest of the
       blood Moses splashed all round the sides of the altar. <verse eID="Lev.8.24"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.8.25" osisID="Lev.8.25"/> Taking the fat of the ram, the fat tail, all the fat on the entrails, the
       lobe of the liver, the two kidneys and their fat, with the right thigh; <verse eID="Lev.8.25"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.8.26" osisID="Lev.8.26"/> taking also one unleavened cake, one cake of bread baked with oil, and one
       pancake, from the basket of unleavened cakes before the Eternal, and placing these on the top of the fat and the
       right thigh, <verse eID="Lev.8.26"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.8.27" osisID="Lev.8.27"/> he put the whole mass into the hands of Aaron and his sons, and had them
       waved to and fro as an offering before the Eternal. <verse eID="Lev.8.27"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.8.28" osisID="Lev.8.28"/> Then Moses took it all out of their hands and burned it on the top of the
       burnt-offering upon the altar, as an installation-­offering with a soothing odour, a fire-offering to the Eternal. <verse eID="Lev.8.28"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.8.29" osisID="Lev.8.29"/> The breast of the ram Moses waved to and fro as an offering before the
       Eternal; he had that as his own share of the ram in the rite of installation, as the Eternal had commanded him. <verse eID="Lev.8.29"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.8.30" osisID="Lev.8.30"/> Then Moses took some of the anointing oil and the blood on the altar,
       sprinkling it over Aaron and his vestments as well as over his sons and their vest­ments, to consecrate Aaron and his
       vestments, and his sons and their vestments. <verse eID="Lev.8.30"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Lev.8.31" osisID="Lev.8.31"/> Moses further said to Aaron and his sons, <q>Boil the meat at
       <milestone type="pb" n="119"/>
       the entrance to the Trysting tent and eat it there, with the cakes in the basket of the in­stallation-rite--for so I
       have been commanded to bid Aaron and his sons eat. <verse eID="Lev.8.31"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.8.32" osisID="Lev.8.32"/> The rest of the meat and cakes you must burn up. <verse eID="Lev.8.32"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.8.33" osisID="Lev.8.33"/> For seven days you must never leave the entrance to the Trysting tent, till
       the days of your installation are over; the installation is to last for seven days. <verse eID="Lev.8.33"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.8.34" osisID="Lev.8.34"/> What has been now done, has been done by order of the Eternal, as expiation
       on your account. <verse eID="Lev.8.34"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.8.35" osisID="Lev.8.35"/> Remain at the en­trance of the Trysting tent for seven days, day and night,
       and do your duty to the Eternal, lest you die--so I am commanded.</q> <verse eID="Lev.8.35"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Lev.8.36" osisID="Lev.8.36"/> Aaron and his sons did every­thing that the Eternal ordered them by Moses. <verse eID="Lev.8.36"/>
    <chapter eId="Lev.8"/>
    <chapter osisId="Lev.9" sId="Lev.9"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.9.1" osisID="Lev.9.1"/> And on the eighth day Moses called Aaron and his sons and the sheikhs of
       Israel, <verse eID="Lev.9.1"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.9.2" osisID="Lev.9.2"/> saying to Aaron, <q>Take a bull calf for a sin-offer­ing and a ram for a
       burnt-offer­ing, both unblemished, and offer them before the Eternal. <verse eID="Lev.9.2"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.9.3" osisID="Lev.9.3"/> Also, tell the Israelites to take a he-goat for a sin-offering, as well as a
       yearling calf and a yearling lamb, both unblemished, for a burnt-offering, <verse eID="Lev.9.3"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.9.4" osisID="Lev.9.4"/> and an ox and a ram for recompense-offerings, to sacrifice before the Eternal;
       furthermore, they are to bring a cereal-offering mixed with oil. For the Eternal will appear to you this day.</q>
      <verse eID="Lev.9.4"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Lev.9.5" osisID="Lev.9.5"/>They brought all these, as Moses ordered, before the Trysting tent; and as all
       the community came forward to stand before the Eternal, <verse eID="Lev.9.5"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.9.6" osisID="Lev.9.6"/> Moses told them what they must do, in obedience to the Eternal, that the
       splendour of the Eter­nal might appear to them. <verse eID="Lev.9.6"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.9.7" osisID="Lev.9.7"/> <q>Come up to the altar</q>, he said to Aaron, <q>offer your sin-offer­ing and
       burnt-offering, as ex­piation for yourself and for your household; then offer sacrifice for the people and make
       expi­ation for them, as the Eternal has ordered.</q> <verse eID="Lev.9.7"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Lev.9.8" osisID="Lev.9.8"/> So Aaron went up to the altar and slaughtered the calf of the sin-offering
       made for himself; <verse eID="Lev.9.8"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.9.9" osisID="Lev.9.9"/> his sons brought the blood to him, and dipping his fingers in it he smeared it
       on the knobs of the altar, pouring the rest of the blood out at the base of the altar; <verse eID="Lev.9.9"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.9.10" osisID="Lev.9.10"/> the fat, the kidneys, and the lobe of the liver of the vic­tim, he burned on
       the altar, as the Eternal had commanded Moses. <verse eID="Lev.9.10"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.9.11" osisID="Lev.9.11"/> The flesh and the skin he burned outside the camp. <verse eID="Lev.9.11"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.9.12" osisID="Lev.9.12"/> He then slaughtered the victim of the burnt-offering; his sons handed him
       the blood, and he splashed it all round the sides of the altar. <verse eID="Lev.9.12"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.9.13" osisID="Lev.9.13"/> They handed him the various pieces of the burnt-offering, including the head,
       and he burned them on the altar. <verse eID="Lev.9.13"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.9.14" osisID="Lev.9.14"/> The entrails and legs he washed with water, and then burned them on the top
       of the burnt-offering on the altar. <verse eID="Lev.9.14"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.9.15" osisID="Lev.9.15"/> He then brought the people’s offering, taking the goat of the sin-offering
       for the people and slaughtering it as an offering for sin in the same way. <verse eID="Lev.9.15"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.9.16" osisID="Lev.9.16"/> The burnt-offering he presented in the regular way. <verse eID="Lev.9.16"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.9.17" osisID="Lev.9.17"/> The cereal-offering he presented, taking out the usual handful, and burn­ing
       it on the altar in addition to the burnt-offering of the morn­ing sacrifice. <verse eID="Lev.9.17"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.9.18" osisID="Lev.9.18"/> He also slaughtered the ox and the ram, the recompense-offering sacrificed
       for the people; his sons handed him the blood, which he splashed on the altar all round, <verse eID="Lev.9.18"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.9.19" osisID="Lev.9.19"/> while the fat parts of the ox, the
       <milestone type="pb" n="120"/>
       fat tail of the ram, the fat cover­ing the entrails, the kidneys, and the lobe of the liver, <verse eID="Lev.9.19"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.9.20" osisID="Lev.9.20"/> were placed upon the breasts of the animals; the fat he burned on the altar, <verse eID="Lev.9.20"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.9.21" osisID="Lev.9.21"/> but the breast Aaron waved to and fro as an offering before the Eternal, as
       Moses had commanded. <verse eID="Lev.9.21"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.9.22" osisID="Lev.9.22"/> Raising his hands to­wards the people, Aaron blessed them, and stepped down
       from the altar when he had sacrificed the sin-offering, the burnt-offer­ing, and the recompense-offer­ings. <verse eID="Lev.9.22"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Lev.9.23" osisID="Lev.9.23"/> Moses and Aaron then en­tered the Trysting tent; when they came out, they
       blessed the people, and the splendour of the Eternal appeared to all the people. <verse eID="Lev.9.23"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.9.24" osisID="Lev.9.24"/> [[Fire issued from the presence of the Eternal, con­suming the burnt-offering
       and fat upon the altar.]] When all the people saw this, they shouted and fell on their faces. <verse eID="Lev.9.24"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eId="Lev.9"/>
    <chapter osisId="Lev.10" sId="Lev.10"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Lev.10.1" osisID="Lev.10.1"/> Now Nadab and Abihu, two sons of Aaron, each took his pan, lighted it and
       laid incense on it, offering irregular fire before the Eternal, which the Eternal had not ordered them to offer. <verse eID="Lev.10.1"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.10.2" osisID="Lev.10.2"/> Fire issued from the presence of the Eternal and devoured them, so that they
       died before the Eternal. <verse eID="Lev.10.2"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.10.3" osisID="Lev.10.3"/> Where­upon Moses said to Aaron, <q>This must be what the Eternal meant by
       saying,
       <lg>
        <l> I will display my sacred dread among those near to me, </l>
        <l> I will show my splendour before all the people. </l>
       </lg></q>
     </p>
     <p>
      Aaron said nothing. <verse eID="Lev.10.3"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.10.4" osisID="Lev.10.4"/> Then Moses called Mishael and Elzaphan, the sons of Uzziel, Aaron’s uncle,
      and told them to come and carry their kinsmen away from the sanctuary, outside the camp. <verse eID="Lev.10.4"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.10.5" osisID="Lev.10.5"/> They came up and car­ried away the men in their robes outside the camp, as
       Moses had told them. <verse eID="Lev.10.5"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.10.12" osisID="Lev.10.12"/> Then said Moses to Aaron and his remaining sons, Eleazar and Ithamar,
       <q>Take the cereal-offering left over from the fire-offerings made to the Eter­nal, and eat it unleavened beside the
       altar, for it is most sacred, <verse eID="Lev.10.12"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.10.13" osisID="Lev.10.13"/> and you must eat it in a sacred spot; it is your due, and your sons' due,
       from the fire-offerings made to the Eternal; such are my instructions. <verse eID="Lev.10.13"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.10.14" osisID="Lev.10.14"/> The waved breast and the selected thigh of the victim you must eat in a
       clean spot, you and your sons and your daughters; they are assigned you and your sons as your due, from the
       sacrifices of the recompense-offerings of the Israelites. <verse eID="Lev.10.14"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.10.15" osisID="Lev.10.15"/> The waved breast is to be brought along with the fat of the fire-offerings,
       to be waved to and fro before the Eternal; it belongs to you and to your sons as your due for all time, as the Eternal
        has commanded.</q> <verse eID="Lev.10.15"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.10.16" osisID="Lev.10.16"/> [[When Moses made careful search for the goat of the sin-offering, he
       found that it had been burned! He was angry with Eleazar and Ithamar, the re­maining sons of Aaron. <verse eID="Lev.10.16"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.10.17" osisID="Lev.10.17"/> <q>Why have you not eaten the sin-offering at the sanctuary? It is most
       sacred, and you were given it as food in order that you might remove the guilt of the community, by making expi­ation
       for them before the Eter­nal. <verse eID="Lev.10.17"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.10.18" osisID="Lev.10.18"/> And you never brought the blood inside the sanctuary! You ought certainly
       to have eaten the flesh inside the sanc­tuary, as I gave orders.</q> <verse eID="Lev.10.18"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.10.19" osisID="Lev.10.19"/>
       Aaron answered, <q>My sons have this day sacrificed their sin-offering and their burnt-offering before the Eternal;
       and yet such a mis­fortune has befallen me! If I had eaten the sin-offering today,
       <milestone type="pb" n="121"/>
       would it have been acceptable to the Eternal?</q> <verse eID="Lev.10.19"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.10.20" osisID="Lev.10.20"/> When Moses heard that, he was satisfied.]] <verse eID="Lev.10.20"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Lev.10.6" osisID="Lev.10.6"/> [[Moses said to Aaron and to his sons Eleazar and Ithamar: <q>Never let your
       hair hang loose or tear your clothes in grief, lest you die, lest the Eternal be wroth with all the community; leave
       it to your fellows, the whole family of Israel, to bewail any outburst of the Eternal. <verse eID="Lev.10.6"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.10.7" osisID="Lev.10.7"/>And never leave the entrance of the Trysting tent, lest you die; for the
       Eternal’s anointing oil is on you.</q> So they followed the directions of Moses.]] <verse eID="Lev.10.7"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Lev.10.8" osisID="Lev.10.8"/> [[The Eternal said to Aaron, <verse eID="Lev.10.8"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.10.9" osisID="Lev.10.9"/> <q>When you or your sons are en­tering the Trysting tent, never drink wine or
       liquor, lest you die; this is to be a standing rule from generation to generation, <verse eID="Lev.10.9"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.10.10" osisID="Lev.10.10"/> that you may distinguish what is sacred and what is profane, what is
       unclean and what is clean, <verse eID="Lev.10.10"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.10.11" osisID="Lev.10.11"/> and that you may teach the Israelites all the rules that the Eternal has
       given them by Moses.</q>]] <verse eID="Lev.10.11"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eId="Lev.10"/>
    <chapter osisId="Lev.11" sId="Lev.11"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Lev.11.1" osisID="Lev.11.1"/>The Eternal gave Moses and Aaron these orders for the Israelites. <verse eID="Lev.11.1"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.11.2" osisID="Lev.11.2"/> <q>Here are the crea­tures you are allowed to eat, of all animals on earth. <verse eID="Lev.11.2"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.11.3" osisID="Lev.11.3"/> You may eat any animal with a parted hoof, that has its hoof divided through,
       and that chews the cud. <verse eID="Lev.11.3"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.11.4" osisID="Lev.11.4"/> But of those that either chew the cud or have a parted hoof, you must not
       eat the fol­lowing: the camel, because, al­though it chews the cud, it has not a parted hoof and therefore is unclean
       for you; <verse eID="Lev.11.4"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.11.5" osisID="Lev.11.5"/> the hyrax, because, although it chews the cud, it has not a parted hoof and
       therefore is unclean for you; <verse eID="Lev.11.5"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.11.6" osisID="Lev.11.6"/> the hare, because, although she chews the cud, she has not a parted hoof and
       therefore is un­clean for you; <verse eID="Lev.11.6"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.11.7" osisID="Lev.11.7"/> the pig, because, although it has a parted hoof, divided through, it does
       not chew the cud and therefore is unclean for you. <verse eID="Lev.11.7"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.11.8" osisID="Lev.11.8"/> Of their meat 8 you must not eat, their carcases you must not touch; they
       are unclean for you.</q><verse eID="Lev.11.8"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Lev.11.9" osisID="Lev.11.9"/><q> As for fish, you may eat anything with fins and scales that lives in the
       water, in sea or stream. <verse eID="Lev.11.9"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.11.10" osisID="Lev.11.10"/> But things in sea or stream that have no fins and scales, either things
       that swarm in the waters or animals in the waters, they are all detestable for you <verse eID="Lev.11.10"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.11.11" osisID="Lev.11.11"/> and shall be detested by you; you must never eat their flesh, and you must
       detest their very carcases: <verse eID="Lev.11.11"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.11.12" osisID="Lev.11.12"/> any creature in the waters without fins or scales is detestable for you.</q><verse eID="Lev.11.12"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Lev.11.13" osisID="Lev.11.13"/><q>Of birds, these are what you must detest, birds never to be eaten,
       detestable birds: the griffin, the vulture, <verse eID="Lev.11.13"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.11.14" osisID="Lev.11.14"/> the eagle, the kite, the buzzard of any species, <verse eID="Lev.11.14"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.11.15" osisID="Lev.11.15"/> the raven of every species, <verse eID="Lev.11.15"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.11.16" osisID="Lev.11.16"/> the ostrich, the night-jar, the sea-mew, the hawk of any species, <verse eID="Lev.11.16"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.11.17" osisID="Lev.11.17"/> the cormorant, the various kinds of owl, <verse eID="Lev.11.17"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.11.18" osisID="Lev.11.18"/> the water-hen, the pelican, the carrion-vulture, <verse eID="Lev.11.18"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.11.19" osisID="Lev.11.19"/> the stork, the heron of every species, the bittern, and the bat. <verse eID="Lev.11.19"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.11.20" osisID="Lev.11.20"/> Also, all winged insects that go on four legs are de­testable for you; <verse eID="Lev.11.20"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.11.21" osisID="Lev.11.21"/> however, of winged insects that go on four legs, you may eat those with
       jointed legs above their feet for leaping over the ground, <verse eID="Lev.11.21"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.11.22" osisID="Lev.11.22"/> the migratory locust of any species, the bald locust of any species, the
       dropping locust of any species, and the grasshopper of any species. <verse eID="Lev.11.22"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.11.23" osisID="Lev.11.23"/> All other winged insects with four legs are detest­able for you.</q><verse eID="Lev.11.23"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Lev.11.24" osisID="Lev.11.24"/><q>[[You shall become unclean by
       <milestone type="pb" n="122"/>
       contact with the following: who­ever touches any carcase of them shall remain unclean till evening, <verse eID="Lev.11.24"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.11.25" osisID="Lev.11.25"/> and whoever carries any carcase of them shall wash his clothes and remain
       unclean till evening. <verse eID="Lev.11.25"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.11.26" osisID="Lev.11.26"/> Any animal with hoof parted but not divided through and not chewing its
       cud is unclean for you; anyone who touches such an animal shall be unclean. <verse eID="Lev.11.26"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.11.27" osisID="Lev.11.27"/> Any quadruped that goes on its paws is unclean for you; whoever touches
       its carcase shall remain unclean till evening. <verse eID="Lev.11.27"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.11.28" osisID="Lev.11.28"/> Anyone who carries any carcase of such animal shall wash his clothes and
       remain un­clean till evening: they are unclean for you. <verse eID="Lev.11.28"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.11.29" osisID="Lev.11.29"/> Of swarming creatures upon earth, these are unclean for you: the weasel,
       the mouse, the lizard of every species, <verse eID="Lev.11.29"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.11.30" osisID="Lev.11.30"/> the gecko, the land-crocodile, the beetle, the snail, and the chameleon. <verse eID="Lev.11.30"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.11.31" osisID="Lev.11.31"/> These are unclean for you, among the swarming creatures; anyone who
       touches their dead bodies shall remain unclean till evening, <verse eID="Lev.11.31"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.11.32" osisID="Lev.11.32"/> and anything on which their dead bodies fall shall be unclean, any article
       of wood or dress, any skin or sack, any vessel in use--it must be put into water, it remains unclean till evening,
       and then is clean again. <verse eID="Lev.11.32"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.11.33" osisID="Lev.11.33"/> Any earthen jar into which one of their dead bodies falls must be broken, <verse eID="Lev.11.33"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.11.34" osisID="Lev.11.34"/> and the contents shall be unclean; any food that ab­sorbs water shall be
       unclean, and any liquid drink in any such jar shall be unclean. <verse eID="Lev.11.34"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.11.35" osisID="Lev.11.35"/>  Any uten­sil on which any of their dead bodies falls shall be unclean; an
       oven or a chafing pot must be broken in pieces, it is unclean and must be counted unclean. <verse eID="Lev.11.35"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.11.36" osisID="Lev.11.36"/> But a fountain or a cistern for holding water shall be clean, though
       anything used to lift out the dead body shall be unclean. <verse eID="Lev.11.36"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.11.37" osisID="Lev.11.37"/> If any of their dead bodies falls on seed ready to be sown, the seed
       remains clean; <verse eID="Lev.11.37"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.11.38" osisID="Lev.11.38"/> but if it falls on seed soaked by water, the seed is unclean for you.</q> <verse eID="Lev.11.38"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Lev.11.39" osisID="Lev.11.39"/><q>Also, if an animal used for food dies, he who touches the carcase shall
       remain unclean till evening; <verse eID="Lev.11.39"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.11.40" osisID="Lev.11.40"/> he who eats the carcase shall wash his clothes and re­main unclean till
       evening; he who carries the carcase shall also wash his clothes and re­main unclean till evening.]]</q><verse eID="Lev.11.40"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Lev.11.41" osisID="Lev.11.41"/><q>Every swarming insect on earth is detestable for you; not one must be
       eaten. <verse eID="Lev.11.41"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.11.42" osisID="Lev.11.42"/> Whatever crawls on its belly, whatever goes on four legs, and what­ever has
       many legs, any swarm­ing insect whatever on earth, you must never eat; such are de­testable. <verse eID="Lev.11.42"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.11.43" osisID="Lev.11.43"/> You must not render yourselves detestable by eating any swarming insect,
       you must not render yourselves unclean over them, thus defiling your­selves. <verse eID="Lev.11.43"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.11.44" osisID="Lev.11.44"/> For as I am the Eternal your God, so you must hallow yourselves and keep
       yourselves sacred, for I am sacred; never defile yourselves with any sort of swarming insect. <verse eID="Lev.11.44"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.11.45" osisID="Lev.11.45"/> For as I am the Eternal who brought you out of the land of Egypt to be
       your God, you must be sacred, for I am sacred.</q><verse eID="Lev.11.45"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Lev.11.46" osisID="Lev.11.46"/><q>Such is the law regarding beasts, birds, fish, and swarm­ing creatures upon
       earth, <verse eID="Lev.11.46"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.11.47" osisID="Lev.11.47"/> that you may distinguish between what is unclean and what is clean,
       between the living crea­tures that may be eaten and the living creatures that may not be eaten.</q> <verse eID="Lev.11.47"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eId="Lev.11"/>
    <chapter osisId="Lev.13" sId="Lev.13"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Lev.13.1" osisID="Lev.13.1"/>The Eternal said to Moses and Aaron: <verse eID="Lev.13.1"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.13.2" osisID="Lev.13.2"/><q>When a man has some swelling or
       <milestone type="pb" n="123"/>
       eruption or white spot on the skin of his body, which becomes the mark of leprosy on his skin, he must be taken to
       Aaron the priest or to one of his sons the priests; <verse eID="Lev.13.2"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.13.3" osisID="Lev.13.3"/> the priest shall look at the mark on the skin, and if the hair on the spot
       has turned white, while the marked patch seems to go under the skin, then it is the mark of leprosy, and the priest,
       after inspection, shall pronounce him unclean. <verse eID="Lev.13.3"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.13.4" osisID="Lev.13.4"/> Should the white spot shine and yet not appear to go under the skin, while
       the hair on it has not turned white, then the priest must isolate the marked man for seven days; on the seventh day, <verse eID="Lev.13.4"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.13.5" osisID="Lev.13.5"/> when the priest looks at him again, if the mark is unchanged in colour and
       has not spread, then the priest must isolate him for seven days more; <verse eID="Lev.13.5"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.13.6" osisID="Lev.13.6"/> on the seventh day the priest shall again look at him, and if the mark has
       faded and has not spread over the skin, then the priest shall pronounce him clean--it is merely some eruption, and
       the man shall wash his clothes and be clean. <verse eID="Lev.13.6"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.13.7" osisID="Lev.13.7"/> But if the eruption does spread over the skin, after he has shown himself to
       the priest in order to be pronounced clean, the priest must look at it, <verse eID="Lev.13.7"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.13.8" osisID="Lev.13.8"/> and if the eruption still spreads, the priest must pro­nounce him unclean;
       it is a case of leprosy.</q><verse eID="Lev.13.8"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Lev.13.9" osisID="Lev.13.9"/><q>When the mark of leprosy is on a man, he must be taken to the priest; <verse eID="Lev.13.9"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.13.10" osisID="Lev.13.10"/> the priest must look at him, and, if there is a white swelling on the
       skin, which has turned the hair white, if there is raw flesh inside the swelling, <verse eID="Lev.13.10"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.13.11" osisID="Lev.13.11"/> then it is chronic leprosy in the skin of his body; the priest shall
       pronounce him unclean, he need not isolate him--the man is un­clean. <verse eID="Lev.13.11"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.13.12" osisID="Lev.13.12"/> If the leprosy breaks out all over the skin, so that the whole skin of the
       marked man is covered with leprosy, from head to foot, as far as the priest can see, <verse eID="Lev.13.12"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.13.13" osisID="Lev.13.13"/> then the priest must look, and, if the leprosy has cov­ered all his body,
       he must pro­nounce the marked man clean; the skin has all turned white, he is clean. <verse eID="Lev.13.13"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.13.14" osisID="Lev.13.14"/> Should raw flesh ap­pear on him, however, he is un­clean; <verse eID="Lev.13.14"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.13.15" osisID="Lev.13.15"/> when the priest sees the raw flesh, he must pronounce the man unclean; the
       raw flesh is unclean, a sign of leprosy. <verse eID="Lev.13.15"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.13.16" osisID="Lev.13.16"/> Should the raw flesh turn white again, the man must go to the priest, <verse eID="Lev.13.16"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.13.17" osisID="Lev.13.17"/> and if the priest sees that the mark has changed into white, then he must
       pronounce the marked man clean: clean he is.</q><verse eID="Lev.13.17"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Lev.13.18" osisID="Lev.13.18"/><q>When a boil on the skin of the body has healed, <verse eID="Lev.13.18"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.13.19" osisID="Lev.13.19"/> leaving a white swelling or a reddish-white, bright spot, the man must
       show it to the priest, <verse eID="Lev.13.19"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.13.20" osisID="Lev.13.20"/> who shall look at it; if it appears to go under the skin, and if the hair
       on the swelling or spot has turned white, then the priest must pro­nounce him unclean--it is a mark of leprosy,
       which has broken out in the boil. <verse eID="Lev.13.20"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.13.21" osisID="Lev.13.21"/> But if the priest sees no white hair on the spot, and the spot does not go
       under the skin, but has faded, then the priest must isolate him for seven days; <verse eID="Lev.13.21"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.13.22" osisID="Lev.13.22"/> if it spreads in the skin, the priest must pro­nounce him unclean--it is a
       mark of leprosy; <verse eID="Lev.13.22"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.13.23" osisID="Lev.13.23"/> but if the bright spot stays where it is, without spreading, it is the
       scar of the boil, and the priest shall pronounce the man clean.</q><verse eID="Lev.13.23"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Lev.13.24" osisID="Lev.13.24"/><q> Or again, when the skin of the body has been burned, and the raw flesh
       of the burn has become a bright spot, reddish-white
       <milestone type="pb" n="124"/>
       or white, <verse eID="Lev.13.24"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.13.25" osisID="Lev.13.25"/>the priest must look at it; if the hair on the bright spot has turned
       white, and it appears to go under the skin, then it is leprosy which has broken out in the burn, and the priest must
       pronounce the man unclean--it is the mark of leprosy. <verse eID="Lev.13.25"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.13.26" osisID="Lev.13.26"/> But if the priest sees there is no white hair on the bright spot, and it
       does not ap­pear to go under the skin, but has faded, then the priest must isolate him for seven days; <verse eID="Lev.13.26"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.13.27" osisID="Lev.13.27"/> on the seventh day he must look again, and if it has spread on the skin,
       then the priest shall pro­nounce him unclean--it is a mark of leprosy. <verse eID="Lev.13.27"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.13.28" osisID="Lev.13.28"/> But if the bright spot stays where it is, without spreading, but has
       faded, then it is the swelling caused by the burn, and the priest shall pronounce him clean--it is only the scar of
       the burn.</q> <verse eID="Lev.13.28"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Lev.13.29" osisID="Lev.13.29"/><q>When a man or a woman has a sore on the head or on the beard, <verse eID="Lev.13.29"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.13.30" osisID="Lev.13.30"/> the priest must look at it; if it appears to go under the skin, and if it
       has thin, yellow hair, the priest shall pronounce him unclean--it is ringworm, a leprosy of the head or beard. <verse eID="Lev.13.30"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.13.31" osisID="Lev.13.31"/> If the priest sees that the ring­worm sore does not appear to go under the
       skin and has no black hair on it, the priest must isolate the patient for seven days. <verse eID="Lev.13.31"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.13.32" osisID="Lev.13.32"/> On the seventh day the priest shall look at the ringworm, and if the sore
       has not spread, if it has no yellow hair, and if the sore does not appear to go under the skin, <verse eID="Lev.13.32"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.13.33" osisID="Lev.13.33"/> then the man must be shaved, all except the sore; the priest must isolate
       him for seven days more. <verse eID="Lev.13.33"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.13.34" osisID="Lev.13.34"/> On the seventh day the priest shall look at it again, and if the ringworm
       has not spread on the skin, if it does not appear to go under the skin, then the priest shall pronounce him clean,
       and he shall wash his clothes and be clean. <verse eID="Lev.13.34"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.13.35" osisID="Lev.13.35"/> However, if the ringworm spreads after he has been pronounced clean, <verse eID="Lev.13.35"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.13.36" osisID="Lev.13.36"/> then the priest must look at it; and if the ringworm has spread, the
       priest need not look for yellow hair--the man is unclean. <verse eID="Lev.13.36"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.13.37" osisID="Lev.13.37"/> But if the ringworm remains as it appeared before, with black hair growing
       on the sore, the ringworm is healed, the man is clean, and the priest shall pro­nounce him clean.</q> <verse eID="Lev.13.37"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Lev.13.38" osisID="Lev.13.38"/><q>When a man or a woman has bright spots, bright white spots, on the skin of
       the body, <verse eID="Lev.13.38"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.13.39" osisID="Lev.13.39"/> the priest must look at them; if these bright spots are a dull white, it
       is only a tetter which has broken out on the skin; the person is clean.</q><verse eID="Lev.13.39"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Lev.13.40" osisID="Lev.13.40"/><q>When a man loses his hair, he is bald, but he is clean. <verse eID="Lev.13.40"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.13.41" osisID="Lev.13.41"/> If he loses his hair in front, he is fore­head-bald, but he is clean. <verse eID="Lev.13.41"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.13.42" osisID="Lev.13.42"/> However, if there is a reddish-white mark on the bald head or the bald
       forehead, it is leprosy breaking out on his bald head or his bald forehead. <verse eID="Lev.13.42"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.13.43" osisID="Lev.13.43"/> The priest must look at it; if the swelling on his bald head or bald
       fore­head is reddish-white, like lep­rosy in the skin, <verse eID="Lev.13.43"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.13.44" osisID="Lev.13.44"/> he is a leprous man, he is unclean; the priest shall pronounce him
       unclean--the mark of it is on his head. <verse eID="Lev.13.44"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.13.45" osisID="Lev.13.45"/> And when a man has the mark of leprosy, he must tear his clothes, let his
       hair hang loose, and cover his moustache, crying <q>Unclean! Unclean!</q> <verse eID="Lev.13.45"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.13.46" osisID="Lev.13.46"/> So long as the mark is on him, he shall be counted unclean; unclean he is,
       he must live apart, and stay outside the camp.</q> <verse eID="Lev.13.46"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Lev.13.47" osisID="Lev.13.47"/><q>[[When the mark of leprosy is on a garment, woollen or linen, <verse eID="Lev.13.47"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.13.48" osisID="Lev.13.48"/> either in the warp or in the 
       <milestone type="pb" n="125"/>
       woof, either in leather or in anything made of leather, if the mark on the garment or in the leather, in warp or
       woof, or in anything made of leather, <verse eID="Lev.13.48"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.13.49" osisID="Lev.13.49"/> is greenish or reddish, it is the mark of leprosy and must be shown to the
       priest. <verse eID="Lev.13.49"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.13.50" osisID="Lev.13.50"/> The priest shall look at the mark and shut the marked object away for
       seven days. <verse eID="Lev.13.50"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.13.51" osisID="Lev.13.51"/> On the seventh day he shall look at it again; and if the mark has spread
       in the gar­ment, in warp or woof, or in any­thing made of leather, then the mark means a malignant lep­rosy, and the
       object is unclean; <verse eID="Lev.13.51"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.13.52" osisID="Lev.13.52"/> he must burn the marked gar­ment, warp or woof, woollen or linen, or the
       leather article; for it is a malignant leprosy, it must be burned up. <verse eID="Lev.13.52"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.13.53" osisID="Lev.13.53"/> However, when the priest looks, if the mark has not spread in the garment,
       warp or woof, or in the leather article, <verse eID="Lev.13.53"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.13.54" osisID="Lev.13.54"/> the priest shall order the marked object to be washed, and then shut it
       away for seven days more; <verse eID="Lev.13.54"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.13.55" osisID="Lev.13.55"/> the priest shall then look at the washed mark, and if the mark has not
       changed colour, though it has not spread, it is unclean--you must burn the thing up, it has eaten into the stuff,
       whether the mischief is at the back or in front. <verse eID="Lev.13.55"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.13.56" osisID="Lev.13.56"/> Should the priest see that the mark is pale after being washed, he must
       tear it out of the garment or leather, warp or woof; <verse eID="Lev.13.56"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.13.57" osisID="Lev.13.57"/> if it still appears in the garment, in warp or woof, or in anything made
       of leather, then it is breaking out afresh, and you must burn up the marked object. <verse eID="Lev.13.57"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.13.58" osisID="Lev.13.58"/> You must wash the garment, warp or woof, or the leather from which the
       mark has disappeared, wash it a second time, and then it is clean. <verse eID="Lev.13.58"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.13.59" osisID="Lev.13.59"/> Such is the law regard­ing marks of leprosy in a woollen or a linen
       garment, warp or woof, or in leather, showing how to pronounce anything clean or unclean.]]</q> <verse eID="Lev.13.59"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eId="Lev.13"/>
    <chapter osisId="Lev.14" sId="Lev.14"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Lev.14.1" osisID="Lev.14.1"/> The Eternal said to Moses,
      <verse eID="Lev.14.1"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.14.2" osisID="Lev.14.2"/><q> This shall be the law for the leper at the time when he is pronounced
       clean. He must be taken to the priest, <verse eID="Lev.14.2"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.14.3" osisID="Lev.14.3"/> and the priest, who has come outside the camp, shall look to see if the
       mark of leprosy is healed in the leper; <verse eID="Lev.14.3"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.14.4" osisID="Lev.14.4"/> then shall the priest order two clean, living birds and some cedar-wood
       and marjoram tied with scarlet thread, to be brought for the man who is to be cleansed, <verse eID="Lev.14.4"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.14.5" osisID="Lev.14.5"/> and order one of the birds to be killed over fresh water in an earthen
       dish. <verse eID="Lev.14.5"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.14.6" osisID="Lev.14.6"/> Taking the other bird along with the cedar-wood and marjoram tied with
       scarlet thread, he shall dip them all in the blood of the bird killed over the fresh water; <verse eID="Lev.14.6"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.14.7" osisID="Lev.14.7"/> the blood he must sprinkle seven times over the man to be cleansed from
       leprosy, pro­nouncing him clean, but the bird he shall set free in the open country. <verse eID="Lev.14.7"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.14.8" osisID="Lev.14.8"/> The man to be cleansed must then wash his clothes, shave off all his hair,
       and bathe in water; so shall he be clean.</q>
     </p>
     <p>
       <q>[[After that, he may come in­side the camp. But for seven days he must remain outside his tent; <verse eID="Lev.14.8"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.14.9" osisID="Lev.14.9"/> on the seventh day he shall shave off all his hair, the hair on his head,
       his beard, and his eye­brows, and wash his clothes and bathe his body in water and so be clean. <verse eID="Lev.14.9"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.14.10" osisID="Lev.14.10"/> On the eighth day he must take two unblemished male lambs and one
       yearling ewe lamb also unblemished, with a cereal-offering of a peck and a half of fine flour mixed with oil and
       one pint of pure oil; <verse eID="Lev.14.10"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.14.11" osisID="Lev.14.11"/> these, together with the man
       <milestone type="pb" n="126"/>
       himself, the officiating priest must place before the Eternal at the entrance to the Trysting tent. <verse eID="Lev.14.11"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.14.12" osisID="Lev.14.12"/> The priest shall then offer one of the male lambs and the pint of oil as
       a guilt-offering, waving them to and fro as an offering before the Eternal; <verse eID="Lev.14.12"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.14.13" osisID="Lev.14.13"/> he must kill the male lamb where the sin-offering and the burnt-offering
       are killed, in the court­yard of the sanctuary (for as the sin-offering belongs to the priest, so does the
       guilt-offering--it is most sacred), <verse eID="Lev.14.13"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.14.14" osisID="Lev.14.14"/> and, taking some of the blood of the guilt-offering, the priest shall
       smear it on the tip of the man’s right ear, the thumb of his right hand, and the great toe of his right foot. <verse eID="Lev.14.14"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.14.15" osisID="Lev.14.15"/> Then, pouring some of the pint of oil into the palm of his left hand, <verse eID="Lev.14.15"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.14.16" osisID="Lev.14.16"/> the priest shall dip his right fore-finger in the oil on his left hand
       and sprinkle some of it with his finger seven times in front of the Eternal; <verse eID="Lev.14.16"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.14.17" osisID="Lev.14.17"/> the rest of the oil in his hand the priest shall use, partly to smear
       the tip of the man’s right ear, the thumb of his right hand, and the great toe of his right foot, where the blood
       of the guilt-offering had been applied, <verse eID="Lev.14.17"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.14.18" osisID="Lev.14.18"/> and partly to drop on the man’s head. So shall the priest make expiation
       for him before the Eternal.</q><verse eID="Lev.14.18"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Lev.14.19" osisID="Lev.14.19"/><q> Then the priest must offer the sin-offering and make expia­tion for
       the man to be cleansed, owing to his uncleanness; after which he must kill the burnt-offering victim, <verse eID="Lev.14.19"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.14.20" osisID="Lev.14.20"/> and offer on the altar the burnt-offering and the cereal-offering. So
       shall the priest make expiation for him, and he shall be clean. <verse eID="Lev.14.20"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.14.21" osisID="Lev.14.21"/> If the man is poor and cannot afford so much, he must take one male lamb
       as a guilt-offering, to be waved to and fro as expiation for him, with a cereal-offering of half a peck of fine
       flour mixed with oil, and one pint of pure oil, <verse eID="Lev.14.21"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.14.22" osisID="Lev.14.22"/> also two turtle-doves or two young pigeons, such as he can afford to
       buy, the one as a sin-offering, the other as a burnt-offering. <verse eID="Lev.14.22"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.14.23" osisID="Lev.14.23"/> These he must bring on the eighth day to the priest, for his cleansing,
       to the entrance of the Trysting tent, before the Eternal; <verse eID="Lev.14.23"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.14.24" osisID="Lev.14.24"/> and the priest, taking the lamb of the guilt-offering and the pint of
       oil, shall wave them to and fro as an offering before the Eternal. <verse eID="Lev.14.24"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.14.25" osisID="Lev.14.25"/> Then, killing the lamb of the guilt-offer­ing, the priest shall take some
       of the blood and smear it on the tip of the man’s right ear, on the thumb of his right hand, and on the great toe
       of his right foot. <verse eID="Lev.14.25"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.14.26" osisID="Lev.14.26"/> Then, pouring some of the pint of oil into the palm of his left hand, <verse eID="Lev.14.26"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.14.27" osisID="Lev.14.27"/> the priest with his right fore-finger shall sprinkle some of the oil in
       his left hand seven times in front of the Eternal; <verse eID="Lev.14.27"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.14.28" osisID="Lev.14.28"/> the rest of the oil in his hand the priest shall use, partly to smear
       the tip of the man’s right ear, the thumb of his right hand, and the great toe of his right foot, where the blood
       of the guilt-offering had been applied, <verse eID="Lev.14.28"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.14.29" osisID="Lev.14.29"/> partly to drop on the man’s head, by way of making expi­ation for him
       before the Eternal. <verse eID="Lev.14.29"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.14.30" osisID="Lev.14.30"/> He must offer one of the turtle-doves or young pigeons, <verse eID="Lev.14.30"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.14.31" osisID="Lev.14.31"/> which the man has been able to afford, one as a sin-offering and the
       other as a burnt-offering, along with the cereal-offering; so shall the priest make expiation before the Eternal
       for the man to be cleansed. <verse eID="Lev.14.31"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.14.32" osisID="Lev.14.32"/> Such is the law for the man marked by leprosy who cannot afford the
       regular sacri­fices at his cleansing.]]</q> <verse eID="Lev.14.32"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Lev.14.33" osisID="Lev.14.33"/> The Eternal said to Moses
       <milestone type="pb" n="127"/>
       and Aaron, <verse eID="Lev.14.33"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.14.34" osisID="Lev.14.34"/> <q>When you enter the land of Canaan, which I assign you as your
       possession, if I put the mark of leprosy on the inner wall of any house in the land you possess, <verse eID="Lev.14.34"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.14.35" osisID="Lev.14.35"/> then the owner of the house must go and tell the priest that there seems
       to he a kind of mark inside the house. <verse eID="Lev.14.35"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.14.36" osisID="Lev.14.36"/> Before the priest goes in to examine the mark, he must order the house
       to be cleared, so that everything inside the house may not be rendered unclean. Then shall the priest go in to
       examine the house; <verse eID="Lev.14.36"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.14.37" osisID="Lev.14.37"/> he shall look at the mark, and if the mark on the wall shows greenish or
       red­dish patches, and the discolour­ing has gone below the surface of the plaster, <verse eID="Lev.14.37"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.14.38" osisID="Lev.14.38"/> the priest shall step outside and shut up the house for seven days. <verse eID="Lev.14.38"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.14.39" osisID="Lev.14.39"/> On the seventh day he shall come back and examine it; if the mark has
       spread over the wall, <verse eID="Lev.14.39"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.14.40" osisID="Lev.14.40"/> the priest shall order the marked stones to be pulled out and thrown
       into some unclean place outside the town; <verse eID="Lev.14.40"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.14.41" osisID="Lev.14.41"/> he shall have the inside of the house scraped all round, and the mortar
       scraped off is to be put in some unclean place outside the town; <verse eID="Lev.14.41"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.14.42" osisID="Lev.14.42"/> fresh stones must be brought, to replace the old stones, and fresh
       mortar used to plaster the house. <verse eID="Lev.14.42"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.14.43" osisID="Lev.14.43"/> Should the mark break out again in the house, after he has had the
       stones pulled out and the house scraped and plastered, <verse eID="Lev.14.43"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.14.44" osisID="Lev.14.44"/> then the priest shall enter and examine it; if the mark has spread, it
       is a case of malignant leprosy in the house--it is unclean. <verse eID="Lev.14.44"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.14.45" osisID="Lev.14.45"/> He must have the house pulled down, stones, wood, mor­tar, and all, and
       have them car­ried outside the town to an unclean place. <verse eID="Lev.14.45"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.14.46" osisID="Lev.14.46"/> Also, anyone who enters the house, while it is shut up, shall be unclean
       till evening; <verse eID="Lev.14.46"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.14.47" osisID="Lev.14.47"/> anyone who sleeps in the house must wash his clothes, and anyone who
       eats in the house must wash his clothes. <verse eID="Lev.14.47"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.14.48" osisID="Lev.14.48"/> But if the priest enters, only to find that the mark has not spread,
       after the house has been plastered, then the priest shall pronounce the house clean, as the mark has disappeared. <verse eID="Lev.14.48"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.14.49" osisID="Lev.14.49"/> To cleanse the house, he must take two birds, along with some cedar-wood
       and marjoram tied with scarlet thread; <verse eID="Lev.14.49"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.14.50" osisID="Lev.14.50"/> one of the birds he must kill over fresh water in an earthen dish, <verse eID="Lev.14.50"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.14.51" osisID="Lev.14.51"/> and then take the cedar-wood and marjoram tied with scarlet thread, and
       the other bird, and dip them in the blood of the bird he killed and also in the fresh water, sprinkling the house
       seven times; <verse eID="Lev.14.51"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.14.52" osisID="Lev.14.52"/> with the blood of the one bird, with the fresh water, with the other
       bird, and with the cedar-wood and mar­joram tied with scarlet thread, he shall cleanse the house, <verse eID="Lev.14.52"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.14.53" osisID="Lev.14.53"/> letting the other bird fly free from the town into the open country.
       Thus shall he make expiation for the house, and it shall be clean. </q> <verse eID="Lev.14.53"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Lev.14.54" osisID="Lev.14.54"/> <q>Such is the law for all kinds of leprosy-marks, and for ring­worm, <verse eID="Lev.14.54"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.14.55" osisID="Lev.14.55"/> for leprosy in clothes or in a house, <verse eID="Lev.14.55"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.14.56" osisID="Lev.14.56"/> for a swelling, for an eruption, and for bright spots-- <verse eID="Lev.14.56"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.14.57" osisID="Lev.14.57"/> showing where each of these is unclean and where it is clean. Such is
       the law of leprosy.</q> <verse eID="Lev.14.57"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eId="Lev.14"/>
    <chapter osisId="Lev.15" sId="Lev.15"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Lev.15.1" osisID="Lev.15.1"/>The Eternal gave Moses and Aaron <verse eID="Lev.15.1"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.15.2" osisID="Lev.15.2"/> these orders for the Israelites: <q>When any man has a discharge from his
       private parts, the discharge is unclean. <verse eID="Lev.15.2"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.15.3" osisID="Lev.15.3"/> His uncleanness shall last as long as he has the discharge; whether the
       parts are discharg­ing or whether they are stopped
       <milestone type="pb" n="128"/>
       to prevent the discharge, the man is unclean. <verse eID="Lev.15.3"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.15.4" osisID="Lev.15.4"/> Every bed on which the man with the dis­charge lies, shall be unclean, and
       anything on which he sits shall be unclean; <verse eID="Lev.15.4"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.15.5" osisID="Lev.15.5"/> anyone who touches the man’s bed shall wash his clothes and bathe in water
       and remain unclean till evening, <verse eID="Lev.15.5"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.15.6" osisID="Lev.15.6"/> and anyone who sits on anything on which the man with the dis­charge has
       sat, shall wash his clothes and bathe in water and remain unclean till evening. <verse eID="Lev.15.6"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.15.7" osisID="Lev.15.7"/>Also, anyone who touches the body of the man with the dis­charge shall wash
       his clothes and bathe in water and remain unclean till evening. <verse eID="Lev.15.7"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.15.8" osisID="Lev.15.8"/> And if the man with the discharge spits on a clean man, the latter shall
       wash his clothes and bathe in water and remain unclean till evening. <verse eID="Lev.15.8"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.15.9" osisID="Lev.15.9"/> Any saddle on which the man with the discharge rides shall be unclean; <verse eID="Lev.15.9"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.15.10" osisID="Lev.15.10"/> and any­one who touches anything that has been under the man shall remain
       unclean till evening; <verse eID="Lev.15.10"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.15.11" osisID="Lev.15.11"/> anyone who carries any such thing shall wash his clothes and bathe in
       water and remain unclean till evening. Anyone whom the man with the dis­charge touches, without having rinsed his
       hand in water, must wash his clothes and bathe in water and remain unclean till evening. <verse eID="Lev.15.11"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.15.12" osisID="Lev.15.12"/> Any earthen pot touched by the man with the discharge must be broken,
       and any wooden article rinsed in water.</q> <verse eID="Lev.15.12"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Lev.15.13" osisID="Lev.15.13"/><q>When the man with the dis­charge is cleansed of his dis­charge, he must
       count seven days for his cleansing, washing his clothes, bathing his body in fresh water, and so becoming clean; <verse eID="Lev.15.13"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.15.14" osisID="Lev.15.14"/> on the eighth day he shall take two turtle-doves or two young pigeons
       and appear be­fore the Eternal at the entrance of the Trysting tent, handing the birds to the priest, <verse eID="Lev.15.14"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.15.15" osisID="Lev.15.15"/> who shall offer them, one for a sin-offering and the other for a
       burnt-offer­ing; so shall the priest make ex­piation for him and his discharge before the Eternal.</q><verse eID="Lev.15.15"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Lev.15.16" osisID="Lev.15.16"/><q>If a man has an emission of seed, he must bathe all his body in water
       and remain unclean till evening; <verse eID="Lev.15.16"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.15.17" osisID="Lev.15.17"/> every garment or piece of leather on which the seed has dropped must be
       washed in water and remain un­clean till evening. <verse eID="Lev.15.17"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.15.18" osisID="Lev.15.18"/> If a man lies with a woman and there is an emission of seed, they must
       both bathe themselves in water and remain unclean till evening.</q><verse eID="Lev.15.18"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Lev.15.19" osisID="Lev.15.19"/><q>If a woman has a discharge (the discharge in her case being blood from
       her body), she must be separated for seven days; anyone who touches her shall remain unclean till evening. <verse eID="Lev.15.19"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.15.20" osisID="Lev.15.20"/> Anything on which she lies, when in this condition, shall be unclean;
       also, anything on which she sits. <verse eID="Lev.15.20"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.15.21" osisID="Lev.15.21"/> Anyone who touches her bed shall wash his clothes and bathe in water and
       remain unclean till evening. <verse eID="Lev.15.21"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.15.22" osisID="Lev.15.22"/> Anyone who touches anything she sits on shall wash his clothes and bathe
       in water and remain unclean till evening. <verse eID="Lev.15.22"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.15.23" osisID="Lev.15.23"/> If he touches anything either in her bed or what she sits upon, he shall
       remain unclean till eve­ning. <verse eID="Lev.15.23"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.15.24" osisID="Lev.15.24"/> And if any man lies beside her, so that her impure dis­charge comes on
       him, he shall be unclean for seven days, and any bed on which he lies shall be unclean.</q><verse eID="Lev.15.24"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Lev.15.25" osisID="Lev.15.25"/><q>If a woman has a discharge of blood which goes on for a long time, when
       it is not her monthly period, or if she has a discharge
       <milestone type="pb" n="129"/>
       lasting beyond the time of her period, during this discharge she shall be unclean as she is during the time of her
       period. <verse eID="Lev.15.25"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.15.26" osisID="Lev.15.26"/> Any bed on which she lies during this dis­charge shall be to her as the
       bed of her monthly period, and any­thing on which she sits, shall be as unclean as if it were the period of her
       impurity. <verse eID="Lev.15.26"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.15.27" osisID="Lev.15.27"/> Anyone who touches any of these things shall be unclean; he must wash
       his clothes and bathe in water and remain unclean till evening. <verse eID="Lev.15.27"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.15.28" osisID="Lev.15.28"/> When she is cleansed of her dis­charge, she must count seven days for it;
       after that she shall become clean. <verse eID="Lev.15.28"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.15.29" osisID="Lev.15.29"/> On the eighth day she must take two turtle­doves or two young pigeons and
       bring them to the priest, at the entrance of the Trysting tent; <verse eID="Lev.15.29"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.15.30" osisID="Lev.15.30"/> one of them the priest shall offer as a sin-offering, the other as a
       burnt-offering. So shall the priest make expiation for her and her unclean discharge, be­fore the Eternal.</q> <verse eID="Lev.15.30"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eId="Lev.15"/>
    <chapter osisId="Lev.12" sId="Lev.12"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Lev.12.1" osisID="Lev.12.1"/>The Eternal also gave Moses <verse eID="Lev.12.1"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.12.2" osisID="Lev.12.2"/> these orders for the Israelites: <q>When a woman is delivered and bears
       a male child, she shall be unclean for seven days, for the same number of days as when she is separated for an
       unclean discharge. <verse eID="Lev.12.2"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.12.3" osisID="Lev.12.3"/> On the eighth day the flesh of the child’s foreskin shall be
       circumcised, <verse eID="Lev.12.3"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.12.4" osisID="Lev.12.4"/> and for thirty-three days further she must stay at home, while the
       blood flows, till she is purified; she must not touch anything sacred, nor must she enter the sanctuary, till
       the days of her purification are over. <verse eID="Lev.12.4"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.12.5" osisID="Lev.12.5"/> But if she bears a female child, she shall remain unclean for two weeks,
       as at her monthly period, and stay at home for sixty-six days, while the blood flows, till she is purified. <verse eID="Lev.12.5"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.12.6" osisID="Lev.12.6"/> When the days of her purification are over, either for a son or for a
       daughter, she shall bring a yearling lamb for a burnt-offering and a young pigeon or turtle-dove for a pur­gation
       offering, handing them to the priest at the entrance of the Trysting tent; <verse eID="Lev.12.6"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.12.7" osisID="Lev.12.7"/> the priest shall offer it before the Eternal and make expiation for her,
       that she may be cleansed from her un­clean flow of blood. Such is the law for a mother, whether the child be male
       or female. <verse eID="Lev.12.7"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.12.8" osisID="Lev.12.8"/> If she cannot afford a lamb, then she must bring two turtle-doves or
       two young pigeons, one for a burnt-offering and the other for a purgation offering; the priest shall make
       expiation for her, and she shall be clean.</q> <verse eID="Lev.12.8"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eId="Lev.12"/>
    <chapter osisId="Lev.15" sId="Lev.15"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Lev.15.31" osisID="Lev.15.31"/><q>So shall you warn the Israelites against their uncleanness, lest they
       die for their uncleanness, by polluting my Dwelling that is among them. <verse eID="Lev.15.31"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.15.32" osisID="Lev.15.32"/> Such is the law for a man with a discharge or for a man ren­dered
       unclean by an emission of seed, <verse eID="Lev.15.32"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.15.33" osisID="Lev.15.33"/> for a woman suffering from her monthly period of impurity, for
       people, men or women, who have discharges, and for a man who lies beside an unclean woman.</q> <verse eID="Lev.15.33"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eId="Lev.15"/>
    <chapter osisId="Lev.16" sId="Lev.16"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Lev.16.1" osisID="Lev.16.1"/>After the death of the two sons of Aaron, who had approached the
       presence of the Eternal and died, <verse eID="Lev.16.1"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.16.2" osisID="Lev.16.2"/> the Eternal said to Moses, <q>Tell your brother Aaron that he must not
       venture into the sacred place behind the curtain, in front of the cover of the ark, whenever he chooses--or he
       will die. For I manifest myself in the cloud upon the cover of the ark. <verse eID="Lev.16.2"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.16.3" osisID="Lev.16.3"/> Aaron must enter the sacred place only as he takes a young bullock for
       a sin-offering and a ram for a burnt-offering <verse eID="Lev.16.3"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.16.4" osisID="Lev.16.4"/> [[He
       <milestone type="pb" n="130"/> must wear the sacred linen tunic and the linen drawers on his middle, girdling
       himself with the linen sash, and putting on the linen turban; these are the sacred vestments, and before he puts
       them on he must bathe his body in water]], <verse eID="Lev.16.4"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.16.5" osisID="Lev.16.5"/> and two he-goats from the community of srael for a sin-offering and one
       for a burnt-offering. <verse eID="Lev.16.5"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.16.6" osisID="Lev.16.6"/> Then Aaron shall offer the bullock of the sin-offering, which is for
       himself, making expiation for himself and for his own household. <verse eID="Lev.16.6"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.16.7" osisID="Lev.16.7"/> The two goats he must place in front of the Eternal at the entrance to
       the Trysting tent; <verse eID="Lev.16.7"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.16.8" osisID="Lev.16.8"/> Aaron shall cast lots over the goats, one lot for the Eter­nal and the
       other for Azazel the demon; <verse eID="Lev.16.8"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.16.9" osisID="Lev.16.9"/> the goat that falls by lot to the Eternal shall be brought forward and
       offered as a sin-offering, <verse eID="Lev.16.9"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.16.10" osisID="Lev.16.10"/> but the goat that falls by lot to Azazel shall be set free in
       presence of the Eternal, that Aaron may perform ex­piatory rites over it and send it away for Azazel into the
       desert.</q> <verse eID="Lev.16.10"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Lev.16.11" osisID="Lev.16.11"/><q>Aaron must offer the bullock of the sin-offering, which is for
       himself, making expiation for himself and his own household. Aaron must offer the bullock of the sin-offering,
       which is for himself, making expiation for himself and his own household. He must slaughter the bullock of the
       sin-offering, which is for himself, <verse eID="Lev.16.11"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.16.12" osisID="Lev.16.12"/> and take a pan of red coals from the altar before the Eternal,
       filling his hands with fragrant incense, finely ground; this he must bring inside the curtain, <verse eID="Lev.16.12"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.16.13" osisID="Lev.16.13"/> placing the incense in the fire burning before the Eter­nal, so that
       the cloud of incense may be all over the cover of the ark of the law--or he will die. <verse eID="Lev.16.13"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.16.14" osisID="Lev.16.14"/> He must take some of the bullock’s blood and smear it with his finger
       on the east side of the ark, sprinkling some of the blood with his finger seven times in front of the cover of
       the ark. <verse eID="Lev.16.14"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.16.15" osisID="Lev.16.15"/> He must then slaughter the people’s goat of sin-offering, and inside
       the curtain do the same with its blood, smearing it on the cover of the ark and sprinkling it in front of the
       cover, <verse eID="Lev.16.15"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.16.16" osisID="Lev.16.16"/> so performing expiatory rites for the sacred place, on account of the
       unclean prac­tices of the Israelites and all their sinful transgressions; he must do the same for the Tryst­ing
       tent that is surrounded by them and their unclean prac­tices.</q>
      <verse eID="Lev.16.16"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Lev.16.17" osisID="Lev.16.17"/><q>When he enters to make expiation in the sacred place, no man shall be
       in the Trysting tent, till he comes out, after hav­ing made expiation for himself and for his own household and
       for all the community of Israel. <verse eID="Lev.16.17"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.16.18" osisID="Lev.16.18"/> Next, he must go outside to the altar before the Eternal and offer
       expiatory rites for it; he must take some of the bullock’s blood and some of the goat’s blood, smearing it on
       the knobs of the altar all round, <verse eID="Lev.16.18"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.16.19" osisID="Lev.16.19"/> smearing some of it on the altar with his finger seven times, to
       cleanse and hallow it from the unclean practices of the Israelites. <verse eID="Lev.16.19"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.16.25" osisID="Lev.16.25"/> (The fat part of the sin-offering he must burn on the altar.)</q><verse eID="Lev.16.25"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Lev.16.20" osisID="Lev.16.20"/><q>When he has finished the expiatory rites for the sacred place and the
       Trysting tent and the altar, Aaron shall bring forward the living goat; <verse eID="Lev.16.20"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.16.21" osisID="Lev.16.21"/> laying both hands upon its head, he shall confess over it all the
       iniquities of the Israelites and all their sin­ful transgressions, laying them on the head of the goat and
       sending it away to the desert, in charge of a man who is held in readiness; <verse eID="Lev.16.21"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.16.22" osisID="Lev.16.22"/> the goat shall bear away their iniquities into soli­tude, and shall
       be set free in the
       <milestone type="pb" n="131"/>
       desert. <verse eID="Lev.16.22"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.16.23" osisID="Lev.16.23"/> Then Aaron shall en­ter the Trysting tent, removing the linen
       vestments which he put on when he entered the sacred place and leaving them there; <verse eID="Lev.16.23"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.16.24" osisID="Lev.16.24"/> he shall bathe his body in water at some sacred place, put on his
       other clothes, and come out to offer his own burnt-offering and the people’s burnt-offering.</q> <verse eID="Lev.16.24"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Lev.16.26" osisID="Lev.16.26"/><q>The man who lets the goat loose for Azazel shall wash his clothes and
       bathe his body in water, before he re-enters the camp. <verse eID="Lev.16.26"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.16.27" osisID="Lev.16.27"/> And the bullock of the sin-offering, with the goat of the
       sin-offering, whose blood was carried in for the expiatory rite inside the sacred place, shall be carried
       outside the camp and burned up, skin, flesh, dung, and all; <verse eID="Lev.16.27"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.16.28" osisID="Lev.16.28"/> the man who burns them must also wash his clothes and bathe his body
       in water, before he re-enters the camp.</q><verse eID="Lev.16.28"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Lev.16.29" osisID="Lev.16.29"/><q>This shall be a standing rule for you: on the tenth day of the seventh
       month you shall abstain from food and all work, both the natives and the aliens settled among you, <verse eID="Lev.16.29"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.16.30" osisID="Lev.16.30"/> for on that day ex­piation is made for your cleans­ing, to cleanse you
       from all your sins before the Eternal; <verse eID="Lev.16.30"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.16.31" osisID="Lev.16.31"/> it shall be a sabbath of entire rest for you, a day of abstaining.
       This rule is for all time.</q><verse eID="Lev.16.31"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Lev.16.32" osisID="Lev.16.32"/><q>Expiation shall be made for you by the anointed priest who has duly
       succeeded his father; he shall put on the linen vestments, the sacred vestments, <verse eID="Lev.16.32"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.16.33" osisID="Lev.16.33"/> and make expiation for the sacred sanctuary, for the Trysting tent,
       for the altar, for the priests, and for all the laity.
      <verse eID="Lev.16.33"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.16.34" osisID="Lev.16.34"/>
       This shall be a perpetual rule for you, to make expiation for all the sins of Is­rael once a year.</q>
     </p>
     <p>
       As the Eternal commanded Moses, so he did. <verse eID="Lev.16.34"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eId="Lev.16"/>
    <chapter osisId="Lev.17" sId="Lev.17"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Lev.17.1" osisID="Lev.17.1"/>The Eternal gave Moses these orders <verse eID="Lev.17.1"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.17.2" osisID="Lev.17.2"/> for Aaron and his sons and all Israel. <verse eID="Lev.17.2"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.17.3" osisID="Lev.17.3"/> <q>The Eternal hereby commands that anyone belonging to Israel who
       slays an ox or a lamb or a goat [[in the camp or outside the camp]] <verse eID="Lev.17.3"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.17.4" osisID="Lev.17.4"/> and does not bring it [[to the entrance of the Trysting tent]] to make
       an offering to the Eternal in front of the Dwelling of the Eternal, that man shall be held guilty of
       bloodshed--he has shed blood--and he shall be out­lawed from his kinsfolk; <verse eID="Lev.17.4"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.17.5" osisID="Lev.17.5"/> this is to ensure that the Israelites bring to the Eternal the
       sacri­fices they are accustomed to sac­rifice in the open country, bring­ing them to the priest [[at the entrance
       of the Trysting tent]] and sacrificing them as recom­pense-offerings to the Eternal. <verse eID="Lev.17.5"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.17.6" osisID="Lev.17.6"/> [[The priest must splash the blood on the altar of the Eternal at the
       entrance of the Trysting tent, burning the fat as a sooth­ing odour for the Eternal.]] <verse eID="Lev.17.6"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.17.7" osisID="Lev.17.7"/> They shall no longer offer their sacrifices to the satyrs to whom they
       have deserted. This shall be a standing rule for them, generation after generation.</q>
      <verse eID="Lev.17.7"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Lev.17.8" osisID="Lev.17.8"/><q> Tell them this also: If anyone belonging to Israel or any alien who
       has settled in Israel offers a burnt-offering or sacrifice <verse eID="Lev.17.8"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.17.9" osisID="Lev.17.9"/> and does not bring it [[to the en­trance of the Trysting tent]] to offer
       it to the Eternal, that man shall be outlawed from his kins­folk.</q> <verse eID="Lev.17.9"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Lev.17.10" osisID="Lev.17.10"/><q>Again, if anyone belonging to Israel or any alien who has set­tled in
       Israel tastes any blood, I will set my face against him and outlaw him from his kinsfolk. <verse eID="Lev.17.10"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.17.11" osisID="Lev.17.11"/> For the soul of any creature lies in its blood, and I have ap­pointed
       blood as your means of expiation on the altar; blood
       <milestone type="pb" n="132"/>
       expiates by reason of the soul in it. <verse eID="Lev.17.11"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.17.12" osisID="Lev.17.12"/> Hence my order for Israel is, that no person among you, no alien
       settled among you, shall taste blood.</q><verse eID="Lev.17.12"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Lev.17.13" osisID="Lev.17.13"/><q>If anyone belonging to Israel or any alien who has settled among them
       captures by hunt­ing any beast or bird that may be eaten, he must pour its blood out, covering it with dust; <verse eID="Lev.17.13"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.17.14" osisID="Lev.17.14"/> for the soul of every creature is bound up with its blood. Hence my
       order for Israel is, that you must never taste the blood of any creature, for the soul of every creature lies in
       its blood; anyone who tastes it shall be outlawed. <verse eID="Lev.17.14"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.17.15" osisID="Lev.17.15"/> [[Also, anyone, na­tive or foreigner, who eats the flesh of a creature
       that has died a natural death or that has been torn by wild beasts, must wash his clothes and bathe in water and
       remain unclean till evening, when he shall be clean again. <verse eID="Lev.17.15"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.17.16" osisID="Lev.17.16"/> If he does not wash his clothes and bathe his body, he must take the
       consequences of his crime.]]
      <verse eID="Lev.17.16"/>
    <chapter eId="Lev.17"/>
    <chapter osisId="Lev.18" sId="Lev.18"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.18.2" osisID="Lev.18.2"/> I am the Eternal your God.</q> <verse eID="Lev.18.2"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Lev.18.1" osisID="Lev.18.1"/>The Eternal gave Moses these <verse eID="Lev.18.1"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.18.2" osisID="Lev.18.2"/> orders for the Israelites:<verse eID="Lev.18.2"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.18.3" osisID="Lev.18.3"/><q>You must not copy the prac­tices of Egypt, where you lived, nor the
       practices of Canaan, whither I am taking you; you must not rule your lives by theirs. <verse eID="Lev.18.3"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.18.4" osisID="Lev.18.4"/> Follow my regulations, keep my rules, and live by them; I am the
       Eternal your God. <verse eID="Lev.18.4"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.18.5" osisID="Lev.18.5"/> So keep my rules and regulations; if a man obeys them, it means life
       for him. I am the Eternal.</q><verse eID="Lev.18.5"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Lev.18.6" osisID="Lev.18.6"/><q>None of you shall approach any woman near of kin to you, to have
       intercourse with her. I am the Eternal. <verse eID="Lev.18.6"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.18.7" osisID="Lev.18.7"/> You shall not have intercourse with your mother, your father’s wife;
       she is your mother, and you shall not have intercourse with her. <verse eID="Lev.18.7"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.18.8" osisID="Lev.18.8"/> You shall not have intercourse with any wife of your father; she
       be­longs to your father. <verse eID="Lev.18.8"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.18.9" osisID="Lev.18.9"/> You shall not have intercourse with your sister, the daughter of your
       own mother, whether she is your full sister or a half-sister. <verse eID="Lev.18.9"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.18.10" osisID="Lev.18.10"/> You shall not have intercourse with your daughter or your son’s
       daughter or your daughter’s daughter, for they are part of yourself. <verse eID="Lev.18.10"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.18.11" osisID="Lev.18.11"/> You shall not have intercourse with the daughter of any wife of your
       father, for she is your own sister. <verse eID="Lev.18.11"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.18.12" osisID="Lev.18.12"/> You shall not have intercourse with your paternal aunt, for she is
       your father’s near kinswoman. <verse eID="Lev.18.12"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.18.13" osisID="Lev.18.13"/> You shall not have intercourse with your maternal aunt, for she is
       your mother’s near kins­woman. <verse eID="Lev.18.13"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.18.14" osisID="Lev.18.14"/> You shall not approach your uncle’s wife for in­tercourse; she is your
       aunt. <verse eID="Lev.18.14"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.18.15" osisID="Lev.18.15"/> You shall not have intercourse with your daughter-in-law; she is your
       son’s wife. <verse eID="Lev.18.15"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.18.16" osisID="Lev.18.16"/> You shall not have intercourse with your sister-in-law; she is your
       broth­er’s wife. <verse eID="Lev.18.16"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.18.17" osisID="Lev.18.17"/> You shall not have intercourse with a woman and with her daughter;
       you shall not have any intercourse with a woman and also with her son’s daughter or her daughter’s daughter;
       they are near kins­women of yours, and that would be a foul crime.
      <verse eID="Lev.18.17"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.18.18" osisID="Lev.18.18"/> You shall not have intercourse with a sister of your wife, as a
       fellow-wife, while your first wife is alive. <verse eID="Lev.18.18"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.18.19" osisID="Lev.18.19"/> You shall not approach any woman for intercourse while she is im­pure
       during her monthly period. <verse eID="Lev.18.19"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.18.20" osisID="Lev.18.20"/> You shall not lie with a neighhour’s wife, defiling yourself with her. <verse eID="Lev.18.20"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.18.21" osisID="Lev.18.21"/> (You shall not let any of your children be burned alive to Molek, nor
       shall you profane the name of your God: I am the Eternal.) <verse eID="Lev.18.21"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.18.22" osisID="Lev.18.22"/> You shall not lie with
       <milestone type="pb" n="133"/>
       a male as with a female: that would be loathsome. <verse eID="Lev.18.22"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.18.23" osisID="Lev.18.23"/> You shall not lie with a beast, defiling yourself with it; nor shall
       any woman go up to a beast, to lie down for it: that would be an unnatural crime. <verse eID="Lev.18.23"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.18.24" osisID="Lev.18.24"/> Never defile yourselves in any such way, for such crimes defile the
       nations I am expelling before you, <verse eID="Lev.18.24"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.18.25" osisID="Lev.18.25"/> defiling their land; hence I punished it for its crimes, and it
       vomited out its inhabitants.</q> <verse eID="Lev.18.25"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Lev.18.26" osisID="Lev.18.26"/><q> Keep my rules and regulations, then: never practise any of these
       loathsome crimes, neither the natives nor the aliens settled in your community <verse eID="Lev.18.26"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.18.27" osisID="Lev.18.27"/> (for the local inhabitants practised such loath­some crimes before you,
       and defiled the land), <verse eID="Lev.18.27"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.18.28" osisID="Lev.18.28"/> lest the land vomit you out, for your defile­ment, as it has vomited
       out the nations before you. <verse eID="Lev.18.28"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.18.29" osisID="Lev.18.29"/> For who­ever practises any of these loath­some vices, he shall be
       outlawed from his kinsfolk. <verse eID="Lev.18.29"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.18.30" osisID="Lev.18.30"/> Obey my in­junctions, then, and never prac­tise any of these loathsome
       cus­toms which existed before you, never defile yourselves with them. I am the Eternal your God: <verse eID="Lev.18.30"/>
    <chapter eId="Lev.18"/>
    <chapter osisId="Lev.19" sId="Lev.19"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.19.2" osisID="Lev.19.2"/> you must be sacred, for I, the Eternal your God. am sacred.</q><verse eID="Lev.19.2"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Lev.19.1" osisID="Lev.19.1"/>The Eternal gave Moses <verse eID="Lev.19.1"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.19.2" osisID="Lev.19.2"/> these orders for all the community of Israel. <verse eID="Lev.19.2"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.19.3" osisID="Lev.19.3"/> <q>You must revere your mother and your father, every one of you, and
       keep my sabbaths: I am the Eternal your God. <verse eID="Lev.19.3"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.19.4" osisID="Lev.19.4"/> Heed not unreal gods, never make yourselves metal gods: I am the Eternal
       your God. <verse eID="Lev.19.4"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.19.5" osisID="Lev.19.5"/> Also, when you sacri­fice any recompense-offering to the Eternal, offer
       it of your own freewill. <verse eID="Lev.19.5"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.19.6" osisID="Lev.19.6"/> It must be eaten on the day you sacrifice it, or on the next day;
       anything left over to the third day must be burned. <verse eID="Lev.19.6"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.19.7" osisID="Lev.19.7"/> If any part of it is eaten on the third day, the whole sacrifice shall
       be reckoned mere refuse and shall not win you favour; <verse eID="Lev.19.7"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.19.8" osisID="Lev.19.8"/> anyone who eats it must pay the penalty, for he has profaned the
       Eternal’s sacred possession; that soul shall be outlawed from his kinsfolk.</q> <verse eID="Lev.19.8"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Lev.19.9" osisID="Lev.19.9"/><q>When you reap your harvest, you must not reap the field to the very
       corners, nor gather the stray ears of the harvest; <verse eID="Lev.19.9"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.19.10" osisID="Lev.19.10"/> you must not glean your vineyard bare, nor pick up fallen grapes;
       leave them for poor folk and resident aliens: I am the Eternal your God.</q><verse eID="Lev.19.10"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Lev.19.11" osisID="Lev.19.11"/><q>You shall not steal; you shall not cheat, you shall not tell a lie. <verse eID="Lev.19.11"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.19.12" osisID="Lev.19.12"/> You shall not take a false oath in my name, profaning the name of
       your God: I am the Eternal your God.</q><verse eID="Lev.19.12"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Lev.19.13" osisID="Lev.19.13"/><q>You shall not defraud your fellow, nor rob him; you shall not keep a
       hired labourer out of his pay till next morning.</q><verse eID="Lev.19.13"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Lev.19.14" osisID="Lev.19.14"/><q>You shall not curse a deaf man, nor trip up a blind man; stand in awe
       of your God--I am the Eternal. <verse eID="Lev.19.14"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.19.15" osisID="Lev.19.15"/> You shall not be guilty of any injustice; you shall not be partial to
       a poor man, nor defer to a powerful man; you must judge the case of a fellow-Israelite fairly.</q><verse eID="Lev.19.15"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Lev.19.16" osisID="Lev.19.16"/><q>You shall not go up and down slandering people; you shall not forge a
       charge of murder against a neighbour: I am the Eternal.</q><verse eID="Lev.19.16"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Lev.19.17" osisID="Lev.19.17"/><q>You shall not cherish hate against your fellow-country­man; what you
       must do is to warn him of his fault, lest you incur guilt yourself. <verse eID="Lev.19.17"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.19.18" osisID="Lev.19.18"/> You shall not avenge yourself, you shall not bear a grudge, against
       your fellow-citizens, but love your neighbour as you love yourself: I am the Eternal.</q><verse eID="Lev.19.18"/>
     </p>
     <milestone type="pb" n="134"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Lev.19.19" osisID="Lev.19.19"/><q>Keep these rules of mine: Never let any of your cattle breed with a
       different kind; never sow two kinds of seed in your fields; never don a robe made of two different kinds of
       cloth.</q><verse eID="Lev.19.19"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Lev.19.23" osisID="Lev.19.23"/><q>When you enter the land and plant it with all kinds of trees for food,
       you must count their fruit as taboo for you, taboo for three years, not to be eaten; <verse eID="Lev.19.23"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.19.24" osisID="Lev.19.24"/> in the fourth year all their fruit shall be sacred, a praise-offering
       to the Eternal; <verse eID="Lev.19.24"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.19.25" osisID="Lev.19.25"/> and in the fifth year you may partake of the fruit, that the land may
       con­tinue to produce for you. I am the Eternal your God.</q><verse eID="Lev.19.25"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Lev.19.26" osisID="Lev.19.26"/><q>You shall not eat any meat with the blood in it; you shall not
       practise augury nor practise witchcraft.</q><verse eID="Lev.19.26"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Lev.19.27" osisID="Lev.19.27"/><q>You shall not shave your temples nor clip the edges of your beard <verse eID="Lev.19.27"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.19.28" osisID="Lev.19.28"/> nor gash your bodies for the dead, nor shall you tattoo your skin:
       I am the Eternal.</q><verse eID="Lev.19.28"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Lev.19.29" osisID="Lev.19.29"/><q>Degrade not your daughter to be a temple-prostitute, lest the country
       fall into harlotry and become full of foul vice.</q><verse eID="Lev.19.29"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Lev.19.30" osisID="Lev.19.30"/><q>You must keep my sabbaths and reverence my sanctuary: I am the
       Eternal. <verse eID="Lev.19.30"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.19.31" osisID="Lev.19.31"/> Never go to a medium or a wizard, never defile yourselves by
       consulting them: I am the Eternal your God.</q><verse eID="Lev.19.31"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Lev.19.32" osisID="Lev.19.32"/><q>You shall rise up before a man with white hair, and honour the person
       of an old man, standing in awe of your God: I am the Eternal.</q> <verse eID="Lev.19.32"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Lev.19.33" osisID="Lev.19.33"/><q>If an alien settles beside you in your land, you must not injure him; <verse eID="Lev.19.33"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.19.34" osisID="Lev.19.34"/> the alien who settles beside you shall be treated like a native, and
       you must love him as you love yourself; for you were aliens yourselves in the land of Egypt: I am the Eternal
       your God.</q><verse eID="Lev.19.34"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Lev.19.35" osisID="Lev.19.35"/><q>You must never act dishonestly, in court or in commerce, as you use
       measures of length, weight, or capacity; <verse eID="Lev.19.35"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.19.36" osisID="Lev.19.36"/> you must have accurate balances, accu­rate weights, and an honest
       measure for bushels and gallons: I am the Eternal your God who brought you out of the land of Egypt, <verse eID="Lev.19.36"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.19.37" osisID="Lev.19.37"/> and you must keep all my rules and regulations obedi­ently: I am the
       Eternal.</q> <verse eID="Lev.19.37"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eId="Lev.19"/>
    <chapter osisId="Lev.20" sId="Lev.20"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Lev.20.1" osisID="Lev.20.1"/>The Eternal gave Moses <verse eID="Lev.20.1"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.20.2" osisID="Lev.20.2"/> these orders for the Israelites. <q>Anyone belonging to Israel or any
       alien settled in Israel who dedicates any of his children to Molek, shall be put to death;
       the people of the land must stone him, <verse eID="Lev.20.2"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.20.3" osisID="Lev.20.3"/> for having dedicated some of his children to Molek, defiling my
       sanctuary and profaning my sacred name. <verse eID="Lev.20.3"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.20.4" osisID="Lev.20.4"/> If the people of the land ever disregard his sin of dedicating children
       to Molek and fail to put him to death, <verse eID="Lev.20.4"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.20.5" osisID="Lev.20.5"/> then I will set my face against that man and his family; I will outlaw
       from their kinsfolk both him and all who follow him in deserting me for Molek.</q> <verse eID="Lev.20.5"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Lev.20.6" osisID="Lev.20.6"/><q>Also, any person who consults a medium or a wizard, deserting me for
       them, I will set my face against that person and outlaw him from his kinsfolk. <verse eID="Lev.20.6"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.20.27" osisID="Lev.20.27"/> Any man or woman who is a medium or a wizard must be put to death,
       stoned to death: their blood shall be on their own heads.</q><verse eID="Lev.20.27"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Lev.20.7" osisID="Lev.20.7"/><q>Hallow yourselves, then, and keep yourselves sacred, for I am the
       Eternal your God; <verse eID="Lev.20.7"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.20.8" osisID="Lev.20.8"/> you shall keep my rules obediently: I am the Eternal who hallows you. <verse eID="Lev.20.8"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.20.9" osisID="Lev.20.9"/> For anyone who curses his father or his mother shall be put
       <milestone type="pb" n="135"/>
       to death; he has cursed his fa­ther or his mother--his blood be on his own head!</q><verse eID="Lev.20.9"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Lev.20.10" osisID="Lev.20.10"/><q>The man who commits adul­tery with a neighbour’s wife, he and she,
       adulterer and adulter­ess, shall both be put to death. <verse eID="Lev.20.10"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.20.11" osisID="Lev.20.11"/> The man who lies with his fa­ther’s wife has openly disgraced his
       father; both he and she shall be put to death--their blood be on their own heads! <verse eID="Lev.20.11"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.20.12" osisID="Lev.20.12"/> If a man lies with his daughter-in-law, both of them shall be put to
       death; they have committed an unnatural crime--their blood be on their own heads!</q> <verse eID="Lev.20.12"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eId="Lev.20"/>
    <chapter osisId="Lev.19" sId="Lev.19"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Lev.19.20" osisID="Lev.19.20"/><q>If any man lies with a slave girl who is betrothed but not yet
       released or freed, an inquiry shall be held, but they shall not be put to death, since she was not yet free; <verse eID="Lev.19.20"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.19.21" osisID="Lev.19.21"/> the man must bring his guilt-offering to the Eternal, at the
       entrance of the Trysting tent, and with this guilt-offering, a ram, <verse eID="Lev.19.21"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.19.22" osisID="Lev.19.22"/> the priest shall make expiation before the Eternal for his sin; so
       shall he be forgiven for the sin he has committed.</q><verse eID="Lev.19.22"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eId="Lev.19"/>
    <chapter osisId="Lev.20" sId="Lev.20"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Lev.20.13" osisID="Lev.20.13"/><q>If a man lies with a male as with a female, both men have done a
       loathsome thing and must be put to death--their blood be on their own heads! <verse eID="Lev.20.13"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.20.14" osisID="Lev.20.14"/> If a man marries both a wife and her mother, it is a foul vice; he
       and they shall be burned to death--to clear out vice from you. <verse eID="Lev.20.14"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.20.15" osisID="Lev.20.15"/> If a man lies with a beast, he shall be put to death, and the beast
       shall be killed. <verse eID="Lev.20.15"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.20.16" osisID="Lev.20.16"/> If a woman goes up to a beast and lies down for it, you shall kill
       both woman and beast; put them to death--their blood shall be on their own heads! <verse eID="Lev.20.16"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.20.17" osisID="Lev.20.17"/> If a man takes his sister, his father’s or his mother’s daughter, and
       he and she cohabit, it is disgrace­ful; they shall be outlawed from among this people; he has had intercourse
       with a sister--he must pay the penalty of his crime! <verse eID="Lev.20.17"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.20.18" osisID="Lev.20.18"/> If a man lies with a woman during her monthly pe­riod and has
       intercourse with her, he has bared her fountain and she has let the fountain of her blood be uncovered; both of
       them shall be outlawed from their people. <verse eID="Lev.20.18"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.20.19" osisID="Lev.20.19"/> (You shall not have intercourse with your mother’s sister or your
       father’s sister; that is to disgrace your near kin; both man and woman must pay the penalty of their crime.) <verse eID="Lev.20.19"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.20.20" osisID="Lev.20.20"/> If a man lies with his uncle’s wife, he has openly dis­graced his
       uncle; the pair must pay the penalty of their sin and die childless. <verse eID="Lev.20.20"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.20.21" osisID="Lev.20.21"/> If a man takes his brother’s wife, it is an impure act; he has openly
       disgraced his brother, and he and she shall be childless.</q><verse eID="Lev.20.21"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Lev.20.22" osisID="Lev.20.22"/><q>Well, then, keep all my rules and regulations obediently, lest the
       land where I have brought you to live vomit you out. <verse eID="Lev.20.22"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.20.23" osisID="Lev.20.23"/> You must not live by the customs of the nations I expelled before
       you; I abhorred them just be­cause they practised all these crimes. <verse eID="Lev.20.23"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.20.24" osisID="Lev.20.24"/> But to you I have said, <q>You shall inherit their land, I assign it
       to you as your own, a land abounding in milk and honey: I am the Eternal your God, who have separated you from
       other races, <verse eID="Lev.20.24"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.20.25" osisID="Lev.20.25"/> and therefore you must separate clean ani­mals from unclean, clean
       birds from unclean; you must not de­file your souls with beast or bird or swarming thing which I have separated
       as unclean for you. <verse eID="Lev.20.25"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.20.26" osisID="Lev.20.26"/> You must be sacred for me for I the Eternal am sacred and I have
       separated you from other races, to make you mine.</q></q>
      <verse eID="Lev.20.26"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eId="Lev.20"/>
    <milestone type="pb" n="136"/>
    <chapter osisId="Lev.21" sId="Lev.21"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Lev.21.1" osisID="Lev.21.1"/>The Eternal gave Moses these orders for the priests, the sons of Aaron.
       <q>No priest is to defile himself by mourning over any corpse of a kinsman, <verse eID="Lev.21.1"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.21.2" osisID="Lev.21.2"/> except for his next-of-kin, his mother, his father, his son, his
       daughter, or his brother, <verse eID="Lev.21.2"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.21.3" osisID="Lev.21.3"/> though he may also defile himself by mourning over his sister if she is
       a virgin and therefore still his kith and kin, as being unmarried. <verse eID="Lev.21.3"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.21.4" osisID="Lev.21.4"/> He must not defile him­self by mourning among his kinsfolk, so as to
       profane himself. <verse eID="Lev.21.4"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.21.5" osisID="Lev.21.5"/> Thus priests must never shave part of their heads bald, nor shave off
       the edges of their beards, nor gash their bodies. <verse eID="Lev.21.5"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.21.6" osisID="Lev.21.6"/> They shall be sacred to their God, never profaning the name of their
       God; sacred they must be, for they offer the fire-offer­ings of the Eternal, the food of their God. <verse eID="Lev.21.6"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.21.7" osisID="Lev.21.7"/> No priest shall marry a harlot or a woman who has been violated or a
       woman who has been divorced; for the priest is sacred for his God. <verse eID="Lev.21.7"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.21.8" osisID="Lev.21.8"/> (Hallow the priest, then, for he offers the bread of your God; he must
       be sacred for you, for I the Eternal, who hallow you, am sacred.) <verse eID="Lev.21.8"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.21.9" osisID="Lev.21.9"/> And if the daughter of a priest degrades herself by playing the harlot,
       she degrades her father and must be burned to death. <verse eID="Lev.21.9"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.21.10" osisID="Lev.21.10"/> The chief priest [[who has had the anointing oil poured over his head
       and who has been consecrated to wear the vestments]] must not let his hair hang loose nor tear his clothes in
       grief; <verse eID="Lev.21.10"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.21.11" osisID="Lev.21.11"/> he must not approach any corpse, defiling himself for his father or
       his mother; <verse eID="Lev.21.11"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.21.12" osisID="Lev.21.12"/> he must never leave the sanctuary, nor profane the sanctuary of his
       God [[for the consecration of the anointing oil of his God is upon him]]: I am the Eternal. <verse eID="Lev.21.12"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.21.13" osisID="Lev.21.13"/> His wife must be a virgin; <verse eID="Lev.21.13"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.21.14" osisID="Lev.21.14"/> he must not marry a widow or a woman who has been divorced or a woman
       who has been violated, he must marry a virgin of his own race, <verse eID="Lev.21.14"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.21.15" osisID="Lev.21.15"/> not to profane his children among the people: for I am the Eternal
       who hallows him.</q> <verse eID="Lev.21.15"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Lev.21.16" osisID="Lev.21.16"/> The Eternal also gave Moses these orders for Aaron. <verse eID="Lev.21.16"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.21.17" osisID="Lev.21.17"/> <q>Whoever of your sons [[throughout the generations]] is
       disfigured, he must not come forward to offer the food of his God. <verse eID="Lev.21.17"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.21.18" osisID="Lev.21.18"/> No disfigured person must come forward, no blind man, no lame man,
       no one writh a mutilated face, no one with a limb too long, <verse eID="Lev.21.18"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.21.19" osisID="Lev.21.19"/> no one with a broken foot or broken hand, <verse eID="Lev.21.19"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.21.20" osisID="Lev.21.20"/> no hunch-back, no dwarf, no one with defective eyesight, no one
       suffering from itch or skin-disease, no one with broken testicles--<verse eID="Lev.21.20"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.21.21" osisID="Lev.21.21"/> no member of Aaron the priest’s family who has any disfigurement
       shall approach to offer the fire-offerings of the Eternal; he is disfigured, he shall not approach to offer
       the food of his God. <verse eID="Lev.21.21"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.21.22" osisID="Lev.21.22"/> He may eat the food of his God [[either the sacred or the most
       sacred food]], <verse eID="Lev.21.22"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.21.23" osisID="Lev.21.23"/> but he must not approach [[the curtain or]] the altar, since he is
       dis­figured; otherwise he will pro­fane my sanctuaries--for I am the Eternal who hallows them.</q> <verse eID="Lev.21.23"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.21.24" osisID="Lev.21.24"/> So Moses directed Aaron and his sons and all the Israelites. <verse eID="Lev.21.24"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eId="Lev.21"/>
    <chapter osisId="Lev.22" sId="Lev.22"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Lev.22.1" osisID="Lev.22.1"/>The Eternal also bade Moses <verse eID="Lev.22.1"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.22.2" osisID="Lev.22.2"/> tell Aaron and his sons to <q>be careful about the sacred gifts of the
       Israelites [[which they consecrate to me]], and not to profane my sacred name: I am the Eternal.
      <verse eID="Lev.22.2"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.22.3" osisID="Lev.22.3"/> Tell them that if any of their number now or hereafter approaches the
       sacred gifts consecrated to the Eternal by the Israelites, when he is physically unclean, that
       <milestone type="pb" n="137"/>
       soul shall be outlawed from my presence: I am the Eternal.
      <verse eID="Lev.22.3"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.22.4" osisID="Lev.22.4"/> No descendant of Aaron whatsoever, who is a leper or who suffers from
       a discharge, shall partake of the sacred gifts till he is clean. If anyone touches any­thing rendered unclean by
       a dead body, if anyone has an emission of seed, <verse eID="Lev.22.4"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.22.5" osisID="Lev.22.5"/> if anyone touches a swarming creature that may cause uncleanness, or a
       man from whom he may catch any kind of uncleanness, <verse eID="Lev.22.5"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.22.6" osisID="Lev.22.6"/> the person who touches any of these shall remain unclean till eve­ning
       and shall not partake of the sacred gifts till he has bathed his body in water. <verse eID="Lev.22.6"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.22.7" osisID="Lev.22.7"/> When the sun goes down, he is clean; then he may partake of the sacred
       gifts, since these are his food. <verse eID="Lev.22.7"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.22.8" osisID="Lev.22.8"/> He must not defile himself by eat­ing anything that has died a nat­ural
       death or that has been tom by wild beasts: I am the Eternal. <verse eID="Lev.22.8"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.22.9" osisID="Lev.22.9"/> So shall they observe my order of service, lest they incur sin and die
       for having profaned it: I am the Eternal who hallows them.</q> <verse eID="Lev.22.9"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Lev.22.10" osisID="Lev.22.10"/><q>No layman shall partake of a sacred gift; no one lodging with a
       priest, no hired servant of a priest, shall partake of a sacred gift; <verse eID="Lev.22.10"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.22.11" osisID="Lev.22.11"/> but any slave whom a priest has bought with his own money may partake
       of it, and children born in his house may share his food. <verse eID="Lev.22.11"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.22.12" osisID="Lev.22.12"/> If a priest’s daughter has married a layman, she must not partake of
       the sa­cred gifts which have been set specially apart; <verse eID="Lev.22.12"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.22.13" osisID="Lev.22.13"/> but if a priest’s daughter has come back to her father’s house,
       living where she did in childhood, because she has been widowed or divorced (hav­ing no children), she may
       par­take of her father’s food; only, no layman ever must.</q><verse eID="Lev.22.13"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Lev.22.14" osisID="Lev.22.14"/><q>If a man partakes by mistake of any sacred gift, he must re­turn the
       gift to the priests, add­ing a fifth to it. <verse eID="Lev.22.14"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.22.15" osisID="Lev.22.15"/> Priests must never let the sacred gifts set apart by Israelites for
       the Eter­nal be profaned, <verse eID="Lev.22.15"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.22.16" osisID="Lev.22.16"/> thus rendering others responsible for sinful guilt by partaking of
       sacred gifts: for I am the Eternal who hallows them.</q>
      <verse eID="Lev.22.16"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Lev.22.17" osisID="Lev.22.17"/> The Eternal also gave Moses <verse eID="Lev.22.17"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.22.18" osisID="Lev.22.18"/> these orders for Aaron and his sons and all Israel. <q>Any one of you
       belonging to Israel or any alien settled in Israel who brings his offering, either a votive offer­ing or a
       freewill offering, to be burned in sacrifice to the Eter­nal, must offer it of his own freewill, <verse eID="Lev.22.18"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.22.19" osisID="Lev.22.19"/> and it must be an un­blemished male, an ox or sheep or goat. <verse eID="Lev.22.19"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.22.20" osisID="Lev.22.20"/> You must never offer any victim with a blemish; that would not win
       acceptance for you. <verse eID="Lev.22.20"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.22.21" osisID="Lev.22.21"/> Also, if anyone offers any recompense-offering to the Eter­nal, as a
       votive offering or as a freewill offering, from herd or flock, it must be quite unblem­ished to be accepted, free
       from blemish altogether. <verse eID="Lev.22.21"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.22.22" osisID="Lev.22.22"/> You must never offer to the Eternal a vic­tim blind or broken or
       mutilated or festering or suffering from itch or from skin-disease; you must never offer such by fire upon the
       altar to the Eternal. <verse eID="Lev.22.22"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.22.23" osisID="Lev.22.23"/> You may offer as a freewill-offering any animal from the flock or
       from the herd that has a limb too long or too short; but it cannot be accepted as a votive offering. <verse eID="Lev.22.23"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.22.24" osisID="Lev.22.24"/> No animal with its testicles bruised or crushed or broken or cut,
       must be offered to the Eternal; such animals you must never sacrifice within your country. <verse eID="Lev.22.24"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.22.25" osisID="Lev.22.25"/> Neither shall you get any of these from a foreigner and offer them as
       food to your
       <milestone type="pb" n="138"/>
       God. They are faulty, there is a blemish in them; they shall not be accepted for you.</q>
      <verse eID="Lev.22.25"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Lev.22.26" osisID="Lev.22.26"/> The Eternal said to Moses, <verse eID="Lev.22.26"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.22.27" osisID="Lev.22.27"/> <q>When an ox or a sheep or a goat is born, it shall remain with its
       dam for seven days; from the eighth day onwards it is accept­able as an offering by fire to the Eternal. <verse eID="Lev.22.27"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.22.28" osisID="Lev.22.28"/> And, cow, ewe, or she-goat, you must not sacrifice it and its young
       on the same day. <verse eID="Lev.22.28"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.22.29" osisID="Lev.22.29"/> Also, when you make a sacrifice of thanksgiving to the Eternal, see
       that is is done so as to win acceptance for you: <verse eID="Lev.22.29"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.22.30" osisID="Lev.22.30"/> it must be eaten on the day it is offered, and none of it must be
       left over till next morning. I am the Eternal.</q>
      <verse eID="Lev.22.30"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Lev.22.31" osisID="Lev.22.31"/><q>So keep my commands obediently: I am the Eternal. <verse eID="Lev.22.31"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.22.32" osisID="Lev.22.32"/> You shall not profane my sacred name; I will be hallowed among
       Israelites--I am the Eternal, who hallows you, <verse eID="Lev.22.32"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.22.33" osisID="Lev.22.33"/> who brought you from the land of Egypt in order to be your God:
       I am the Eternal.</q> <verse eID="Lev.22.33"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eId="Lev.22"/>
   </div>
   