   <div type="book" osisID="Lev">
    <milestone type="pb" n="110"/>
    <chapter osisId="Lev.1" sId="Lev.1"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Lev.1.1" osisID="Lev.1.1"/>Then the Eternal called Moses, and from the Trysting tent gave him these orders for
       the Israelites. <verse eID="Lev.1.1"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Lev.1.2" osisID="Lev.1.2"/> <q>When any man of you brings an offering to the Eternal, you must make your
       offering from your live-stock, from your herds and flocks. <verse eID="Lev.1.2"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.1.3" osisID="Lev.1.3"/>
       If the man’s offer­ing from his herd be a burnt-offering, it must be an unblem­ished male, and he must offer it of his own
       freewill at the en­trance to the Trysting tent before the Eternal. <verse eID="Lev.1.3"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.1.4" osisID="Lev.1.4"/> He must lay his hand upon the head of the victim, and it shall be accepted as
       expiation for him. <verse eID="Lev.1.4"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.1.5" osisID="Lev.1.5"/> He must then kill the bullock before the Eternal; but Aaron’s sons, the priests,
       shall present the blood, splashing it all round the sides of the altar at the entrance to the Trysting tent. <verse eID="Lev.1.5"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.1.6" osisID="Lev.1.6"/>
       He must skin the victim and cut it up; <verse eID="Lev.1.6"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.1.7" osisID="Lev.1.7"/> then the sons of Aaron, the priests, shall put fire on the altar, arranging wood on
       the fire, <verse eID="Lev.1.7"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.1.8" osisID="Lev.1.8"/> and arranging the pieces of the victim, with its head and suet, on the wood upon
       the top of the fire on the altar. <verse eID="Lev.1.8"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.1.9" osisID="Lev.1.9"/> (The entrails and the legs the man must wash in water.) The priests shall burn the
       whole of it on the altar as a burnt-offering, an offering made by fire, with a soothing odour for the Eternal,</q><verse eID="Lev.1.9"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Lev.1.10" osisID="Lev.1.10"/><q>If his offering be from the flock, a sheep or a goat, what he offers must be an
       unblemished male. <verse eID="Lev.1.10"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.1.11" osisID="Lev.1.11"/> He must kill it on the north side of the altar before the Eternal; but Aaron’s
       sons, the priests, shall splash its blood all round the sides of the altar. <verse eID="Lev.1.11"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.1.12" osisID="Lev.1.12"/> He must cut it up, and then the priest shall arrange the pieces, with the head and
       suet, on the wood upon the top of the fire on the altar. <verse eID="Lev.1.12"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.1.13" osisID="Lev.1.13"/> (The entrails and the legs the man must wash in water.) The priests shall offer
       the whole of it, burning it on the altar, as a burnt-offering, an offering made by fire, with a soothing odour for the
       Eternal.</q>
      <verse eID="Lev.1.13"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Lev.1.14" osisID="Lev.1.14"/><q> If his offering to the Eternal be an offering of birds, what he offers must be
       a turtle-dove or a young pigeon. <verse eID="Lev.1.14"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.1.15" osisID="Lev.1.15"/> The priest shall take it to the altar, and first nip off its head, which he must
       burn on the altar; then the blood of the bird shall be squeezed out on the side of the altar, <verse eID="Lev.1.15"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.1.16" osisID="Lev.1.16"/> and the priest must remove the crop and feathers, flinging them to the east of the
       altar upon the ash-heap; <verse eID="Lev.1.16"/>
      <verse sID="Lev.1.17" osisID="Lev.1.17"/> after tearing it by the wings, though without dividing it in two, the priest shall
       burn it on the wood upon the fire on the altar, as a burnt-offering, an offering made by fire, with a soothing odour for the
       Eternal.</q> <verse eID="Lev.1.17"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eId="Lev.1"/>
   </div>
       