   <div type="book" osisID="Num">
    <milestone type="pb" n="147"/>
    <chapter osisId="Num.1" sId="Num.1"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Num.1.1" osisID="Num.1.1"/>On the first day of the second month in the second year after they had
       left the land of Egypt, the Eternal spoke to Moses in the desert of Sinai, within the Trysting tent, bidding him
       and Aaron <verse eID="Num.1.1"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.2" osisID="Num.1.2"/> count up the total mem­bers of the community of Israel, clan by clan,
       family by family, and also number all the male individuals, head by head; <verse eID="Num.1.2"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.3" osisID="Num.1.3"/> all Israelites over twenty years who were able for active service were to
       be numbered, company by company. <verse eID="Num.1.3"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.4" osisID="Num.1.4"/> They were to take a representative of every clan, in each case the head
       of the family, <verse eID="Num.1.4"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.5" osisID="Num.1.5"/> the names of the representa­tives were to be as follows. From Reuben,
       Elizur the son of Shedeur; <verse eID="Num.1.5"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.6" osisID="Num.1.6"/> from Simeon, Shelumiel the son of Zurishaddai; <verse eID="Num.1.6"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.7" osisID="Num.1.7"/> from Judah, Nahshon the son of Amminadab; <verse eID="Num.1.7"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.8" osisID="Num.1.8"/> from Issachar, Nathaniel the son of Zuar; <verse eID="Num.1.8"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.9" osisID="Num.1.9"/> from Zebulun, Eliab the son of Helon; <verse eID="Num.1.9"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.10" osisID="Num.1.10"/> from the Josephites -- Ephraim, Elishama the son of Ammihud, and from
       Manasseh, Gamaliel the son of Pedahzur; <verse eID="Num.1.10"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.11" osisID="Num.1.11"/> from Benjamin, Abidan the son of Gideoni; <verse eID="Num.1.11"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.12" osisID="Num.1.12"/> from Dan, Ahiezer the son of Ammishaddai; <verse eID="Num.1.12"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.13" osisID="Num.1.13"/> from Asher, Pagiel the son of Ochran; <verse eID="Num.1.13"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.14" osisID="Num.1.14"/> from Gad, Eliasaph the son of Reuel; <verse eID="Num.1.14"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.15" osisID="Num.1.15"/> from Naphtali, Ahira the son of Enan. <verse eID="Num.1.15"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.16" osisID="Num.1.16"/> Such were the men selected from the com­munity, the leaders of their
       an­cestral clans, who were at the head of the septs in Israel. <verse eID="Num.1.16"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.17" osisID="Num.1.17"/> Moses and Aaron took these men who have been named, <verse eID="Num.1.17"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.18" osisID="Num.1.18"/> and mustered all the community on the first day of the second month,
       when they registered themselves, clan by clan, family by family, and had every indi­vidual over twenty numbered, <verse eID="Num.1.18"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.19" osisID="Num.1.19"/> head by head, as the Eternal had ordered.  Moses numbered them in the
       desert thus.<verse eID="Num.1.19"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Num.1.20" osisID="Num.1.20"/> The descendants of Reuben, Israel’s eldest son, reckoned clan by clan,
       family by family, with every male indi­vidual over twenty years, head by head, <verse eID="Num.1.20"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.21" osisID="Num.1.21"/> all the Reubenites who were able for active service amounted to
       forty-six thousand five hundred. <verse eID="Num.1.21"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.22" osisID="Num.1.22"/> The descendants of Simeon, reckoned clan by clan, family by family,
       with every male individual over twenty years, <verse eID="Num.1.22"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.23" osisID="Num.1.23"/> all the Simeonites who were able for active service amounted to
       fifty-nine thousand three hundred. <verse eID="Num.1.23"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.24" osisID="Num.1.24"/> The descendants of Gad, reckoned clan by clan, family by family, with
       every male individual over twenty years numbered, head by head, <verse eID="Num.1.24"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.25" osisID="Num.1.25"/> all the Gadites who were able for active service amounted to
       forty-five thousand six hundred and fifty. <verse eID="Num.1.25"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.26" osisID="Num.1.26"/> The descendants of Judah, reckoned clan by clan, family by family, with
       every male individual over twenty years, head by head, <verse eID="Num.1.26"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.27" osisID="Num.1.27"/> all the Judahites who were able for active service amounted to
       seventy-four thousand six hun­dred. <verse eID="Num.1.27"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.28" osisID="Num.1.28"/> The descendants of Issachar, reckoned clan by clan, family by family,
       with every male individual over twenty years, head by head, <verse eID="Num.1.28"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.29" osisID="Num.1.29"/> all the Issacharites who were able for active service amounted to
       fifty-four thousand four hun­dred. <verse eID="Num.1.29"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.30" osisID="Num.1.30"/> The descendants of Zebulun, reckoned clan by clan, family by family,
       with every male individual over twenty years, head by head,
      <verse eID="Num.1.30"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.31" osisID="Num.1.31"/> all the 
       <milestone type="pb" n="148"/>
       Zebulunites who were able for ac­tive service amounted to fifty-seven thousand four hundred. <verse eID="Num.1.31"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.32" osisID="Num.1.32"/> As for the Josephites--the de­scendants of Ephraim, reckoned clan by
       clan, family by family, with every male individual over twenty, head by head, <verse eID="Num.1.32"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.33" osisID="Num.1.33"/> all the Ephraimites who were able for active service amounted to forty
       thousand five hundred; <verse eID="Num.1.33"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.34" osisID="Num.1.34"/> the de­scendants of Manasseh, reck­oned clan by clan, family by family,
       with every male indi­vidual over twenty years, head by head, <verse eID="Num.1.34"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.35" osisID="Num.1.35"/> all the Manassites who were able for active service amounted to
       thirty-two thousand two hundred. <verse eID="Num.1.35"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.36" osisID="Num.1.36"/> The de­scendants of Benjamin, reck­oned clan by clan, family by family,
       with every male indi­vidual over twenty years, head by head, <verse eID="Num.1.36"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.37" osisID="Num.1.37"/> all the Benjamites who were able for active service amount to
       thirty-five thousand four hundred. <verse eID="Num.1.37"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.38" osisID="Num.1.38"/> The de­scendants of Dan, reckoned clan by clan, family by family, with
       every male descendant over twenty years, head by head, <verse eID="Num.1.38"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.39" osisID="Num.1.39"/> all the Danites who were able for active service amounted to sixty-two
       thousand seven hundred. <verse eID="Num.1.39"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.40" osisID="Num.1.40"/> The descendants of Asher, reckoned clan by clan, family by family, with
       every male individual over twenty years, head by head, <verse eID="Num.1.40"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.41" osisID="Num.1.41"/> all the Asherites who were able for active service amounted to
       forty-one thousand five hundred. <verse eID="Num.1.41"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.42" osisID="Num.1.42"/> The descendants of Naphtali, reck­oned clan by clan, family by family,
       with every male individual over twenty years, head by head, <verse eID="Num.1.42"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.43" osisID="Num.1.43"/> all the Naphtalites who were able for active service amounted to
       fifty-three thou­sand four hundred. <verse eID="Num.1.43"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Num.1.44" osisID="Num.1.44"/>Such were those whom Moses and Aaron counted up, along with the leaders
       of Israel, twelve men, each of whom represented his ancestral house. <verse eID="Num.1.44"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.45" osisID="Num.1.45"/> The number of the Israelites, family by family, over twenty years, who
       were able for active service, <verse eID="Num.1.45"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.46" osisID="Num.1.46"/> the total number was six hundred and three thousand five hun­dred and
       fifty. <verse eID="Num.1.46"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Num.1.47" osisID="Num.1.47"/> The ancestral clan of the Levites was not included, how­ever; <verse eID="Num.1.47"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.48" osisID="Num.1.48"/> the Eternal told Moses <verse eID="Num.1.48"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.49" osisID="Num.1.49"/> that he was to leave out the clan of Levi, and not to count its total
       among the Israelites, <verse eID="Num.1.49"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.50" osisID="Num.1.50"/> but to put the Levites in charge of the Dwelling of the Presence, with
       all its equipment and all its belongings; they were to carry the Dwelling and its equipment, to attend to it,
       and to encamp round it; <verse eID="Num.1.50"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.51" osisID="Num.1.51"/> whenever the Dwelling had to be moved, the Levites were to take it down,
       and when­ever it had to be pitched, the Levites were to erect it; any outsider who dared to interfere was to be
       put to death. <verse eID="Num.1.51"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.52" osisID="Num.1.52"/> The Israelites were to pitch their tents according to their respec­tive
       camps and companies, in military order, <verse eID="Num.1.52"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.53" osisID="Num.1.53"/> but the Levites were to pitch their tents round the Dwelling of the
       Presence, in order to avert any outburst of divine anger against the com­munity of Israel; they were to take
       charge of the Dwelling. <verse eID="Num.1.53"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.54" osisID="Num.1.54"/> The Israelites carried this out; they obeyed every order given by the
       Eternal to Moses. <verse eID="Num.1.54"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eId="Num.1"/>
    <chapter osisId="Num.2" sId="Num.2"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Num.2.1" osisID="Num.2.1"/>The Eternal told Moses and Aaron <verse eID="Num.2.1"/>
      <verse sID="Num.2.2" osisID="Num.2.2"/> that the Israelites were to pitch their tents according to their
       respective companies and the pennons of their clans, fac­ing the Trysting tent on every side.
      <verse eID="Num.2.2"/>
      <verse sID="Num.2.3" osisID="Num.2.3"/> Those who encamped on the eastern side, towards the dawn, were to be
       the companies
       <milestone type="pb" n="149"/>
       belonging to Judah, led by Nahshon the son of Amminadab;
      <verse eID="Num.2.3"/>
      <verse sID="Num.2.4" osisID="Num.2.4"/> his host numbered in all seventy-four thousand six hundred. <verse eID="Num.2.4"/>
      <verse sID="Num.2.5" osisID="Num.2.5"/>Next to him the clan of Issachar was to encamp, led by Nathaniel the son
       of Zuar; <verse eID="Num.2.5"/>
      <verse sID="Num.2.6" osisID="Num.2.6"/> his host numbered in all fifty-four thousand four hundred. <verse eID="Num.2.6"/>
      <verse sID="Num.2.7" osisID="Num.2.7"/> Then the clan of Zebulun, led by Eliab the son of Helon;
      <verse eID="Num.2.7"/>
      <verse sID="Num.2.8" osisID="Num.2.8"/>
       his host numbered in all fifty-seven thousand four hundred.
      <verse eID="Num.2.8"/>
      <verse sID="Num.2.9" osisID="Num.2.9"/> These battalions of Judah, numbering a hundred and eighty-six thou­sand
       four hundred, were to start on the march first. <verse eID="Num.2.9"/>
      <verse sID="Num.2.10" osisID="Num.2.10"/> On the south side the companies be­longing to Reuben were to en­camp,
       led by Elizur the son of Shedeur; <verse eID="Num.2.10"/>
      <verse sID="Num.2.11" osisID="Num.2.11"/> his host numbered in all forty-six thousand five hundred. <verse eID="Num.2.11"/>
      <verse sID="Num.2.12" osisID="Num.2.12"/> Next to him the clan of Simeon was to encamp, led by Shelumiel the son
       of Zurishaddai; <verse eID="Num.2.12"/>
      <verse sID="Num.2.13" osisID="Num.2.13"/> his host numbered in all fifty-nine thousand three hundred. <verse eID="Num.2.13"/>
      <verse sID="Num.2.14" osisID="Num.2.14"/> Then the clan of Gad, led by Eliasaph the son of Reuel; <verse eID="Num.2.14"/>
      <verse sID="Num.2.15" osisID="Num.2.15"/> his host numbered forty-five thousand six hundred and fifty. <verse eID="Num.2.15"/>
      <verse sID="Num.2.16" osisID="Num.2.16"/>These battalions of Reuben, numbering a hundred and fifty-one thousand
       four hundred and fifty, were to start second on the march. <verse eID="Num.2.16"/>
      <verse sID="Num.2.17" osisID="Num.2.17"/> Then the Trysting tent was to advance, along with the host of Levites,
       in the centre of the other hosts; they were to march, as they encamped, in their respective companies. <verse eID="Num.2.17"/>
      <verse sID="Num.2.18" osisID="Num.2.18"/> On the western side the com­panies belonging to Ephraim were to encamp,
       led by Elishama the son of Arnmihud; <verse eID="Num.2.18"/>
      <verse sID="Num.2.19" osisID="Num.2.19"/> his host numbered in all forty thousand five hundred. <verse eID="Num.2.19"/>
      <verse sID="Num.2.20" osisID="Num.2.20"/> Next to him the clan of Manasseh was to encamp, led by Gamaliel the
       son of Pedahzur; <verse eID="Num.2.20"/>
      <verse sID="Num.2.21" osisID="Num.2.21"/> his host numbered in all thirty-two thousand two hun­dred. <verse eID="Num.2.21"/>
      <verse sID="Num.2.22" osisID="Num.2.22"/> Then the clan of Benjamin, led by Abidan the son of Gideoni; <verse eID="Num.2.22"/>
      <verse sID="Num.2.23" osisID="Num.2.23"/> his host numbered in all thirty-five thousand four hun­dred. <verse eID="Num.2.23"/>
      <verse sID="Num.2.24" osisID="Num.2.24"/> These battalions of Ephraim, numbering a hundred and eight thousand
       one hundred, were to start third on the march. <verse eID="Num.2.24"/>
      <verse sID="Num.2.25" osisID="Num.2.25"/> On the northern side the companies belonging to Dan were to encamp,
       led by Ahiezer the son of Ammishaddai; <verse eID="Num.2.25"/>
      <verse sID="Num.2.26" osisID="Num.2.26"/> his host numbered in all sixty-two thousand seven hundred. <verse eID="Num.2.26"/>
      <verse sID="Num.2.27" osisID="Num.2.27"/> Next to him the clan of Asher was to encamp, led by Pagiel the son of
       Ochran; <verse eID="Num.2.27"/>
      <verse sID="Num.2.28" osisID="Num.2.28"/> his host numbered in all forty-one thousand five hundred. <verse eID="Num.2.28"/>
      <verse sID="Num.2.29" osisID="Num.2.29"/> Then the clan of Naphtali, led by Ahira the son of Enan; <verse eID="Num.2.29"/>
      <verse sID="Num.2.30" osisID="Num.2.30"/> his host numbered fifty-three thou­sand four hundred. <verse eID="Num.2.30"/>
      <verse sID="Num.2.31" osisID="Num.2.31"/> These battalions of Dan, numbering a hundred and fifty-seven thou­sand
       six hundred, were to march company by company in the rear. <verse eID="Num.2.31"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Num.2.32" osisID="Num.2.32"/> Such were the Israelites counted by their families; those who were
       numbered by com­panies in their respective camps amounted to six hundred and three thousand five hundred and
       fifty. <verse eID="Num.2.32"/>
      <verse sID="Num.2.33" osisID="Num.2.33"/> But, by order of the Eternal to Moses, the Levites were not included
       in the reckon­ing of the Israelites. <verse eID="Num.2.33"/>
      <verse sID="Num.2.34" osisID="Num.2.34"/> The Israelites carried this out; exactly as the Eternal had ordered
       Moses, so they encamped in their respective companies and marched, clan by clan, family by family. <verse eID="Num.2.34"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eId="Num.2"/>
    <chapter osisId="Num.3" sId="Num.3"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Num.3.1" osisID="Num.3.1"/>These were the descendants of Aaron and Moses, when the Eternal talked to
       Moses on mount Sinai. <verse eID="Num.3.1"/>
      <verse sID="Num.3.2" osisID="Num.3.2"/> The names of a Aaron’s sons were Nadab (the eldest), Abihu, Eleazar,
       and Ithamar; <verse eID="Num.3.2"/>
      <verse sID="Num.3.3" osisID="Num.3.3"/> these were the names 3 of Aaron’s sons, consecrated
       <milestone type="pb" n="150"/> priests, whom he installed in the priestly office. <verse eID="Num.3.3"/>
      <verse sID="Num.3.4" osisID="Num.3.4"/> Nadab and Abihu died before the Eternal, when they offered irregular
       fire before the Eternal in the desert of Sinai; they left no children. But Eleazar and Ithamar served as
       priests during the lifetime of their father. <verse eID="Num.3.4"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Num.3.5" osisID="Num.3.5"/>The Eternal said to Moses, <verse eID="Num.3.5"/>
      <verse sID="Num.3.6" osisID="Num.3.6"/><q>Bring the clan of Levi and present them before Aaron the priest, to be
       at his service. <verse eID="Num.3.6"/>
      <verse sID="Num.3.7" osisID="Num.3.7"/> They shall do duty for him and for the whole community at the Trysting
       tent, as attendants of the Dwelling, <verse eID="Num.3.7"/>
      <verse sID="Num.3.8" osisID="Num.3.8"/> taking charge of all the equipment of the Tryst­ing tent and the
       arrangements for the Israelites, as attendants of the Dwelling. <verse eID="Num.3.8"/>
      <verse sID="Num.3.9" osisID="Num.3.9"/> Assign the Levites to Aaron and his sons; they belong to him, out of the
       Israelites. <verse eID="Num.3.9"/>
      <verse sID="Num.3.10" osisID="Num.3.10"/> Appoint Aaron and his sons to hold their priest­hood; any layman who
       dares to interfere shall be put to death.</q> <verse eID="Num.3.10"/>
      <verse sID="Num.3.11" osisID="Num.3.11"/> The Eternal said to Moses, <verse eID="Num.3.11"/>
      <verse sID="Num.3.12" osisID="Num.3.12"/> <q>I myself have taken the Levites from Israel instead of the eldest
       children born in Israel; the Le­vites belong to me, <verse eID="Num.3.12"/>
      <verse sID="Num.3.13" osisID="Num.3.13"/> for all the eldest children belong to me. When I killed all the eldest
       born in the land of Egypt I claimed as my own all the eldest born in Israel, both man and beast; mine they shall
       be: I am the Eternal.</q> <verse eID="Num.3.13"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Num.3.14" osisID="Num.3.14"/> In the desert of Sinai the Eternal ordered Moses <verse eID="Num.3.14"/>
      <verse sID="Num.3.15" osisID="Num.3.15"/> to num­ber the Levites, clan by clan, family by family, counting every
       male over a month old. <verse eID="Num.3.15"/>
      <verse sID="Num.3.16" osisID="Num.3.16"/> Moses numbered them as the Eternal bade him. <verse eID="Num.3.16"/>
      <verse sID="Num.3.17" osisID="Num.3.17"/> The names of the sons of Levi were Gershon, Kohath, and Merari; <verse eID="Num.3.17"/>
      <verse sID="Num.3.18" osisID="Num.3.18"/> the names of the sons of Gershon, clan by clan, were Libni and Shimei; <verse eID="Num.3.18"/>
      <verse sID="Num.3.19" osisID="Num.3.19"/> the sons of Kohath, clan by clan, were Amram, Izhar, Hebron, and
       Uzziel; <verse eID="Num.3.19"/>
      <verse sID="Num.3.20" osisID="Num.3.20"/> the sons of Merari, clan by clan, were Mahli and Mushi. Such were the
       Levitical clans, family by family. <verse eID="Num.3.20"/>
      <verse sID="Num.3.21" osisID="Num.3.21"/> To Gershon belonged the Libnites and the Shimeites; <verse eID="Num.3.21"/>
      <verse sID="Num.3.22" osisID="Num.3.22"/> of these Gershonite clans there were counted seven thousand five hundred
       members, the total number of males over a month old. <verse eID="Num.3.22"/>
      <verse sID="Num.3.23" osisID="Num.3.23"/> The Gershonite clans were to encamp on the western side of the tent, <verse eID="Num.3.23"/>
      <verse sID="Num.3.24" osisID="Num.3.24"/> led by Eliasaph the son of Lael. <verse eID="Num.3.24"/>
      <verse sID="Num.3.25" osisID="Num.3.25"/> In the Trysting tent the Gershonites were to take charge of the
       Dwelling and the tent, of everything con­nected with the wrapper for the tent, the veil for the entrance into
       the Trysting tent, <verse eID="Num.3.25"/>
      <verse sID="Num.3.26" osisID="Num.3.26"/> the hangings, the curtains for the en­trance into the court round the
       tent and the altar, and the ropes. <verse eID="Num.3.26"/>
      <verse sID="Num.3.27" osisID="Num.3.27"/> To Kohath belonged the Amramites, the Izharites, the Hebronites, and
       the Uzzielites; <verse eID="Num.3.27"/>
      <verse sID="Num.3.28" osisID="Num.3.28"/> of these Kohathite clans there were counted eight thousand three
       hundred members, the total number of males over a month old. <verse eID="Num.3.28"/>
      <verse sID="Num.3.29" osisID="Num.3.29"/> The Kohathite clans were to encamp on the south side of the tent, <verse eID="Num.3.29"/>
      <verse sID="Num.3.30" osisID="Num.3.30"/> led by Elizaphan the son of Uzziel. <verse eID="Num.3.30"/>
      <verse sID="Num.3.31" osisID="Num.3.31"/> They were to take charge of everything connected with the ark, the
       table, the lampstand, the altars and articles of the sanctuary where the priests serve, and the curtain that
       screened it off. <verse eID="Num.3.31"/>
      <verse sID="Num.3.32" osisID="Num.3.32"/> Eleazar the son of Aaron was to have authority over the Levitical
       authorities and to supervise those who had charge of the sanctuary. <verse eID="Num.3.32"/>
      <verse sID="Num.3.33" osisID="Num.3.33"/> To Merari belonged the Mahlites and the Mushites; <verse eID="Num.3.33"/>
      <verse sID="Num.3.34" osisID="Num.3.34"/> of these Merari clans there were counted six thousand two hun­dred
       members, the total number
       <milestone type="pb" n="151"/>
       of males over a month old. <verse eID="Num.3.34"/>
      <verse sID="Num.3.35" osisID="Num.3.35"/> The Merarite clans were led by Zuriel the son of Abihail, and had to
       encamp on the north side of the tent. <verse eID="Num.3.35"/>
      <verse sID="Num.3.36" osisID="Num.3.36"/> The Merarites were to take full charge of the frames, bars, columns,
       and pedes­tals of the Dwelling, and every­thing connected with its frame-work, <verse eID="Num.3.36"/>
      <verse sID="Num.3.37" osisID="Num.3.37"/> as well as of the columns of the surrounding courtyard, their
       pedestals, pegs, and ropes. <verse eID="Num.3.37"/>
      <verse sID="Num.3.38" osisID="Num.3.38"/> Those who en­camp on the eastern side of the tent, on the front facing
       the dawn, were to be Moses and Aaron and his sons, attending to everything in the sanctuary, everything that is
       required for worship by the Israelites; any layman who dared to interfere must be put to death. <verse eID="Num.3.38"/>
      <verse sID="Num.3.39" osisID="Num.3.39"/> The total number of Levites counted by Moses at the bidding of the
       Eternal, clan by clan, all the males over a month old, amounted to twenty-two thou­sand. <verse eID="Num.3.39"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Num.3.40" osisID="Num.3.40"/> The Eternal said to Moses, <q>Number all the eldest males of Israel,
       from a month upwards; number them one by one. <verse eID="Num.3.40"/>
      <verse sID="Num.3.41" osisID="Num.3.41"/> And pick out for me (I am the Eter­nal) the Levites instead of all the
       eldest males in Israel, and the cattle of the Levites instead of all the first-born cattle belonging to the
       Israelites.</q> <verse eID="Num.3.41"/>
      <verse sID="Num.3.42" osisID="Num.3.42"/> Moses did as the Eternal ordered him, numbering all the eldest of the
       Israelites; <verse eID="Num.3.42"/>
      <verse sID="Num.3.43" osisID="Num.3.43"/> and all the eldest males, over a month old, counted one by one,
       amounted to twenty-two thousand two hundred and seventy-three. <verse eID="Num.3.43"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Num.3.44" osisID="Num.3.44"/><q>Now,</q> said the Eternal to Moses, <verse eID="Num.3.44"/>
      <verse sID="Num.3.45" osisID="Num.3.45"/> <q>pick out the Levites instead of all the eldest males in Israel, and
       the cattle of the Levites instead of their cattle, and the Levites shall be mine: I am the Eternal. <verse eID="Num.3.45"/>
      <verse sID="Num.3.46" osisID="Num.3.46"/> To redeem the two hundred and seventy-three among the eldest males of
       Israel, over and above the number of the Levites, <verse eID="Num.3.46"/>
      <verse sID="Num.3.47" osisID="Num.3.47"/> you must pay twelve shillings a head for them (reckoning by the sa­cred
       shekel, that is, twenty gerahs), <verse eID="Num.3.47"/>
      <verse sID="Num.3.48" osisID="Num.3.48"/> handing over the price of this extra number to Aaron and his sons.</q> <verse eID="Num.3.48"/>
      <verse sID="Num.3.49" osisID="Num.3.49"/> So Moses took the redemption-money from these extra men, over and
       above the number of the Levites; <verse eID="Num.3.49"/>
      <verse sID="Num.3.50" osisID="Num.3.50"/> he took from the eldest born of Israel a hundred and sixty-three
       pounds sixteen shillings (reckoning by the sacred shekel), <verse eID="Num.3.50"/>
      <verse sID="Num.3.51" osisID="Num.3.51"/> and this redemption-money Moses handed over to Aaron and his sons, as
       the Eternal had told him, as the Eternal had ordered Moses. <verse eID="Num.3.51"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eId="Num.3"/>
    <chapter osisId="Num.4" sId="Num.4"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Num.4.1" osisID="Num.4.1"/>The Eternal told Moses and Aaron <verse eID="Num.4.1"/>
      <verse sID="Num.4.2" osisID="Num.4.2"/> to count up the total number of the Kohathites, among the Levites, clan
       by clan, family by family, <verse eID="Num.4.2"/>
      <verse sID="Num.4.3" osisID="Num.4.3"/> all between thirty and fifty years of age, who entered the service for
       work in the Trysting tent. <verse eID="Num.4.3"/>
      <verse sID="Num.4.4" osisID="Num.4.4"/> The duties of the Kohathites with regard to the sacred fabric of the
       tent were to be as follows. <verse eID="Num.4.4"/>
      <verse sID="Num.4.5" osisID="Num.4.5"/> When the camp started on the march, Aaron and his sons were to enter the
       tent, take down the curtain that screened off the ark and put it over the ark of the Pres­ence, <verse eID="Num.4.5"/>
      <verse sID="Num.4.6" osisID="Num.4.6"/> wrapping a leather sheet over it, laying a violet pall on the top, and
       inserting the poles into the ark. <verse eID="Num.4.6"/>
      <verse sID="Num.4.7" osisID="Num.4.7"/> They were to spread a violet pall over the table of the Presence,
       placing on it the dishes, saucers, chal­ices, and flagons for pouring libations, along with the perennial bread, <verse eID="Num.4.7"/>
      <verse sID="Num.4.8" osisID="Num.4.8"/> laying a scarlet pall on the top, and wrapping a leather sheet over it,
       besides in­serting the poles in the table.
      <verse eID="Num.4.8"/>
      <milestone type="pb" n="152"/>
      <verse sID="Num.4.9" osisID="Num.4.9"/>They were to lay a violet pall over the lampstand, with its lamps,
       ash-trays, snuffers, and oil-cans, <verse eID="Num.4.9"/>
      <verse sID="Num.4.10" osisID="Num.4.10"/> wrapping all up in a leather sheet, and placing the things on a
       stretcher. <verse eID="Num.4.10"/>
      <verse sID="Num.4.11" osisID="Num.4.11"/> They were to lay a violet pall over the golden altar, covering it with
       a leather sheet, and inserting the poles in the altar; <verse eID="Num.4.11"/>
      <verse sID="Num.4.12" osisID="Num.4.12"/> also they were to wrap up all the sacerdotal utensils in a violet pall,
       covering the whole with a leather sheet, and placing them on the stretcher. <verse eID="Num.4.12"/>
      <verse sID="Num.4.13" osisID="Num.4.13"/> After removing the ashes, they were to lay a crimson pall over the
       other altar, <verse eID="Num.4.13"/>
      <verse sID="Num.4.14" osisID="Num.4.14"/> placing upon it all the utensils of the sacerdotal service, the
       fire-pans, the prongs, the shovels, and the bowls, wrapping all up in a leather sheet, and inserting the poles
       in the altar. <verse eID="Num.4.14"/>
      <verse sID="Num.4.15" osisID="Num.4.15"/> Once Aaron and his sons had finished cover­ing up the sanctuary and all
       its contents, then, as the camp marched forward, the Kohathites were to come forward and carry the load--but
       without touching the sacred objects themselves; that would be fatal to them. Such were the duties of the
       Kohathites in the Trysting tent. <verse eID="Num.4.15"/>
      <verse sID="Num.4.16" osisID="Num.4.16"/> Eleazar the son of Aaron the priest was to be re­sponsible for the oil
       required for the lighting, the fragrant in­cense, the perennial cereal-offer­ings, and the oil required for
       anointing; he was to take charge of all the Dwelling and its con­tents, the sanctuary and all its furnishing. <verse eID="Num.4.16"/>
      <verse sID="Num.4.17" osisID="Num.4.17"/> The Eternal told Moses and Aaron <verse eID="Num.4.17"/>
      <verse sID="Num.4.18" osisID="Num.4.18"/> to treat the Kohathites in this way, in order to prevent their clan
       and fam­ilies from being destroyed as Levites, <verse eID="Num.4.18"/>
      <verse sID="Num.4.19" osisID="Num.4.19"/> in order that they might live, and not die, in han­dling the sacred
       objects. Aaron and his sons were to enter the sacred precincts, <verse eID="Num.4.19"/>
      <verse sID="Num.4.20" osisID="Num.4.20"/> but the Kohathites, in discharging all their appointed tasks and
       duties, were not to set eyes for a second upon the sacred objects, since that would be fatal to them. <verse eID="Num.4.20"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Num.4.21" osisID="Num.4.21"/> The Eternal also told Moses <verse eID="Num.4.21"/>
      <verse sID="Num.4.22" osisID="Num.4.22"/> to count up the total number of the Gershonites, family by fam­ily,
       clan by clan, <verse eID="Num.4.22"/>
      <verse sID="Num.4.23" osisID="Num.4.23"/> all between thirty and fifty years of age, who entered the service for
       work in the Trysting tent. <verse eID="Num.4.23"/>
      <verse sID="Num.4.24" osisID="Num.4.24"/> The duties of the Gershonites as attendants and bearers were to be as
       follows. <verse eID="Num.4.24"/>
      <verse sID="Num.4.25" osisID="Num.4.25"/> They were to carry the curtains of the Dwell­ing, the hangings and the
       leather wrappers for the Trysting tent, the curtain for the entrance of the Trysting tent, <verse eID="Num.4.25"/>
      <verse sID="Num.4.26" osisID="Num.4.26"/> the hangings of the courtyard, the veil for the entrance of the
       courtyard that surrounds the Dwelling and the altar, with all the ropes and equipment, attending to every­thing
       connected with these. <verse eID="Num.4.26"/>
      <verse sID="Num.4.27" osisID="Num.4.27"/> Aaron and his sons were to have full authority over the Gershon­ites as
       attendants and bearers, specifying for them their duties in detail. <verse eID="Num.4.27"/>
      <verse sID="Num.4.28" osisID="Num.4.28"/> Such was to be the position of the Gershonites in serving the Trysting
       tent, and they were to be supervised by Ithamar the son of Aaron the priest. <verse eID="Num.4.28"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Num.4.29" osisID="Num.4.29"/> As for the Merarites, Moses was to number them clan by clan, family by
       family, <verse eID="Num.4.29"/>
      <verse sID="Num.4.30" osisID="Num.4.30"/> counting everyone between thirty and fifty years of age who entered
       the service for work in the Trysting tent. <verse eID="Num.4.30"/>
      <verse sID="Num.4.31" osisID="Num.4.31"/> The duties falling to them in the due course of this service were to
       be the transport of the frames, bars, columns, and pedestals of the Dwelling, <verse eID="Num.4.31"/>
      <verse sID="Num.4.32" osisID="Num.4.32"/> as well as of the columns of the surrounding
       <milestone type="pb" n="153"/>
       courtyard, their pedestals, pegs, and ropes, and all connected with the framework; they were to be told off one
       by one to the object each had to carry. <verse eID="Num.4.32"/>
      <verse sID="Num.4.33" osisID="Num.4.33"/> Such was to be the position of the Merarites in serving the Trysting
       tent, under the supervision of Ithamar, the son of Aaron the priest. <verse eID="Num.4.33"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Num.4.34" osisID="Num.4.34"/>Moses and Aaron and the leaders of the community then counted up the
       Kohathites, clan by clan, family by family, <verse eID="Num.4.34"/>
      <verse sID="Num.4.35" osisID="Num.4.35"/> reck­oning everyone between thirty and fifty years of age who en­tered
       the service for work in the Trysting tent; <verse eID="Num.4.35"/>
      <verse sID="Num.4.36" osisID="Num.4.36"/> and the total number was two thousand seven hundred and fifty. <verse eID="Num.4.36"/>
      <verse sID="Num.4.37" osisID="Num.4.37"/> These were all the Kohathites who served in the Trysting tent,
       numbered by Moses and Aaron as the Eternal had sent orders through Moses. <verse eID="Num.4.37"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Num.4.38" osisID="Num.4.38"/>As for the Gershonites, num­bered clan by clan, family by family, <verse eID="Num.4.38"/>
      <verse sID="Num.4.39" osisID="Num.4.39"/> the total number of those between thirty and fifty years of age who
       entered the service for work in the Trysting tent <verse eID="Num.4.39"/>
      <verse sID="Num.4.40" osisID="Num.4.40"/> amounted to two thousand six hundred and thirty. <verse eID="Num.4.40"/>
      <verse sID="Num.4.41" osisID="Num.4.41"/> These were all the Gershonites who served in the Trysting tent,
       numbered by Moses and Aaron, as the Eternal had ordered. <verse eID="Num.4.41"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Num.4.42" osisID="Num.4.42"/>As for the Merarites, num­bered clan by clan, family by family, <verse eID="Num.4.42"/>
      <verse sID="Num.4.43" osisID="Num.4.43"/> the total number of those between thirty and fifty years of age who
       entered the service for work in the Trysting tent <verse eID="Num.4.43"/>
      <verse sID="Num.4.44" osisID="Num.4.44"/> amounted to three thousand two hundred. <verse eID="Num.4.44"/>
      <verse sID="Num.4.45" osisID="Num.4.45"/> These were all the Merarites, numbered by Moses and Aaron as the
       Eternal had sent orders through Moses. <verse eID="Num.4.45"/>
      <verse sID="Num.4.46" osisID="Num.4.46"/>The total number of Levites, whom Moses and Aaron and the leaders of
       Israel counted clan by clan, family by family, <verse eID="Num.4.46"/>
      <verse sID="Num.4.47" osisID="Num.4.47"/> men be­tween thirty and fifty years of age, men who entered the
       service as attendants and bear­ers in connexion with the Tryst­ing tent--<verse eID="Num.4.47"/>
      <verse sID="Num.4.48" osisID="Num.4.48"/>their total amounted in all to eight thousand five hun­dred and eighty. <verse eID="Num.4.48"/>
      <verse sID="Num.4.49" osisID="Num.4.49"/> As the Eternal had given orders, they were assigned their respective
       tasks and duties by Moses, who num­bered them as the Eternal had ordered him. <verse eID="Num.4.49"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eId="Num.4"/>
    <chapter osisId="Num.5" sId="Num.5"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Num.5.1" osisID="Num.5.1"/>The Eternal said to Moses, <verse eID="Num.5.1"/>
      <verse sID="Num.5.2" osisID="Num.5.2"/> <q>Order the Israelites to shut out from their camp any leper, anyone
       suffering from a dis­charge, and anyone defiled by contact with a corpse; <verse eID="Num.5.2"/>
      <verse sID="Num.5.3" osisID="Num.5.3"/> male or female, out with them--put them outside the camp! They are not
       to pollute the camp within which I dwell.</q> <verse eID="Num.5.3"/>
      <verse sID="Num.5.4" osisID="Num.5.4"/> The Israelites obeyed, they put such persons outside the camp; the
       Israelites did as the Eternal gave orders to Moses. <verse eID="Num.5.4"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Num.5.5" osisID="Num.5.5"/> The Eternal gave Moses <verse eID="Num.5.5"/>
      <verse sID="Num.5.6" osisID="Num.5.6"/> this order for the Israelites. <q>If a man or woman commits any of the
       crimes into which men fall, breaking faith with the Eternal and incurring guilt, <verse eID="Num.5.6"/>
      <verse sID="Num.5.7" osisID="Num.5.7"/> they must confess their sinful act and re­store their ill-gotten gains in
       full, adding a fifth of the value as a present to the person they have wronged. <verse eID="Num.5.7"/>
      <verse sID="Num.5.8" osisID="Num.5.8"/> Should that person have died, leaving no next-of-kin to whom restitution
       can be made, the restored property falls to the priest for the Eter­nal, in addition to the ram required for the
       sacrifice of expi­ation. <verse eID="Num.5.8"/>
      <verse sID="Num.5.9" osisID="Num.5.9"/> Indeed, every contribution made by Israelites, every sacred gift
       presented to a priest, shall belong to that priest; <verse eID="Num.5.9"/>
      <verse sID="Num.5.10" osisID="Num.5.10"/> a man’s sacred offerings shall be­long to the priest; whatever anyone
       gives to a priest, his shall it be.</q> <verse eID="Num.5.10"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Num.5.11" osisID="Num.5.11"/>The Eternal gave Moses this
       <milestone type="pb" n="154"/>
      <verse eID="Num.5.11"/>
      <verse sID="Num.5.12" osisID="Num.5.12"/>
       order for the Israelites. <q>If a man’s wife goes wrong and proves unfaithful to him, <verse eID="Num.5.12"/>
      <verse sID="Num.5.13" osisID="Num.5.13"/> if an­other man lies with her, un­known to her husband, if she remains
       undetected although she has defiled herself, if there is no witness against her since she was not caught in the
       act, <verse eID="Num.5.13"/>
      <verse sID="Num.5.14" osisID="Num.5.14"/> then, if he has a fit of suspicion, suspect­ing his wife, even although
       she may not have defiled herself, <verse eID="Num.5.14"/>
      <verse sID="Num.5.15" osisID="Num.5.15"/> he must take his wife before the priest, bringing the requisite
       offering of seven pints of barley meal (but pouring no oil over it and adding no frankincense to it, since it
       is a cereal-offering of suspicion, a cereal-offering meant to recall sin). <verse eID="Num.5.15"/>
      <verse sID="Num.5.16" osisID="Num.5.16"/> The priest shall place her in front of the Eternal; <verse eID="Num.5.16"/>
      <verse sID="Num.5.17" osisID="Num.5.17"/> he shall put some holy water in an earthen jar and drop into the water
       some dust from the floor of the Dwelling; <verse eID="Num.5.17"/>
      <verse sID="Num.5.18" osisID="Num.5.18"/> then the priest shall loosen the woman’s hair and make her hold the
       cereal-offering that is a memento of sin, the cereal­offering of suspicion, he himself holding the water that
       causes pain, that brings a curse with it. <verse eID="Num.5.18"/>
      <verse sID="Num.5.19" osisID="Num.5.19"/> The priest shall then say to the woman, <q>If no man has lain with
       you, if you have not turned to unclean courses as a married woman, then may no harm come to you from this water
       that causes pain, that brings a curse with it! <verse eID="Num.5.19"/>
      <verse sID="Num.5.20" osisID="Num.5.20"/> But if, as a married woman, you have gone wrong, if you have defiled
       yourself and let another man besides your husband lie with you, then--</q> <verse eID="Num.5.20"/>
      <verse sID="Num.5.21" osisID="Num.5.21"/> adjuring the woman with a sol­emn curse, the priest shall add--<q>May
       the Eternal make an example of you, may he make you accursed among your peo­ple, by causing your thighs to
       shrivel and your belly to swell! <verse eID="Num.5.21"/>
      <verse sID="Num.5.22" osisID="Num.5.22"/> May this water that brings a curse with it enter your womb, causing
       your thighs to shrivel and your belly to swell!</q> <q>So be it,</q> shall the woman say, <q>so be it.</q></q>
      <verse eID="Num.5.22"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Num.5.23" osisID="Num.5.23"/><q>Then the priest shall write the curses down and wash the writ­ingk
       into the water that causes pain; <verse eID="Num.5.23"/>
      <verse sID="Num.5.24" osisID="Num.5.24"/> he shall make the woman drink the water that causes pain, that brings
       a curse with it, so that the water which brings a curse with it may pass into her and cause pain. <verse eID="Num.5.24"/>
      <verse sID="Num.5.25" osisID="Num.5.25"/> Then shall the priest take the cereal-offering of suspicion from the
       woman and wave the cereal-offering in front of the Eternal, bringing it up to the altar
      <verse eID="Num.5.25"/>
      <verse sID="Num.5.26" osisID="Num.5.26"/> and burning a handful of it on the altar as a memento. Once he has
       made the woman drink the water, <verse eID="Num.5.26"/>
      <verse sID="Num.5.27" osisID="Num.5.27"/> if she has de­filed herself and been unfaithful to her husband, then
       the water that brings a curse with it shall pass into her and cause pain, till her belly swells and her thighs
       shrivel and she becomes accursed among her people. <verse eID="Num.5.27"/>
      <verse sID="Num.5.28" osisID="Num.5.28"/> But if she has not defiled herself, if she is a pure woman, then she
       shall re­main unharmed, and she can still bear children.</q><verse eID="Num.5.28"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Num.5.29" osisID="Num.5.29"/><q>Such is the law in cases of suspicion, when a married wom­an goes wrong
       and defiles her­self, <verse eID="Num.5.29"/>
      <verse sID="Num.5.30" osisID="Num.5.30"/> or when a fit of suspicion comes over a man, till he is sus­picious of
       his wife; he shall make her stand in front of the Eter­nal, and the priest shall deal with her in terms of this
       law. <verse eID="Num.5.30"/>
      <verse sID="Num.5.31" osisID="Num.5.31"/> The husband shall incur no guilt, but the woman must be punished for
       her sin.</q>
      <verse eID="Num.5.31"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eId="Num.5"/>
   </div>