   <div type="book" osisID="Num">
    <milestone type="pb" n="147"/>
    <chapter osisId="Num.1" sId="Num.1"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Num.1.1" osisID="Num.1.1"/>On the first day of the second month in the second year after they had
       left the land of Egypt, the Eternal spoke to Moses in the desert of Sinai, within the Trysting tent, bidding him
       and Aaron <verse eID="Num.1.1"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.2" osisID="Num.1.2"/> count up the total mem­bers of the community of Israel, clan by clan,
       family by family, and also number all the male individuals, head by head; <verse eID="Num.1.2"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.3" osisID="Num.1.3"/> all Israelites over twenty years who were able for active service were to
       be numbered, company by company. <verse eID="Num.1.3"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.4" osisID="Num.1.4"/> They were to take a representative of every clan, in each case the head
       of the family, <verse eID="Num.1.4"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.5" osisID="Num.1.5"/> the names of the representa­tives were to be as follows. From Reuben,
       Elizur the son of Shedeur; <verse eID="Num.1.5"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.6" osisID="Num.1.6"/> from Simeon, Shelumiel the son of Zurishaddai; <verse eID="Num.1.6"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.7" osisID="Num.1.7"/> from Judah, Nahshon the son of Amminadab; <verse eID="Num.1.7"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.8" osisID="Num.1.8"/> from Issachar, Nathaniel the son of Zuar; <verse eID="Num.1.8"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.9" osisID="Num.1.9"/> from Zebulun, Eliab the son of Helon; <verse eID="Num.1.9"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.10" osisID="Num.1.10"/> from the Josephites -- Ephraim, Elishama the son of Ammihud, and from
       Manasseh, Gamaliel the son of Pedahzur; <verse eID="Num.1.10"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.11" osisID="Num.1.11"/> from Benjamin, Abidan the son of Gideoni; <verse eID="Num.1.11"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.12" osisID="Num.1.12"/> from Dan, Ahiezer the son of Ammishaddai; <verse eID="Num.1.12"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.13" osisID="Num.1.13"/> from Asher, Pagiel the son of Ochran; <verse eID="Num.1.13"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.14" osisID="Num.1.14"/> from Gad, Eliasaph the son of Reuel; <verse eID="Num.1.14"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.15" osisID="Num.1.15"/> from Naphtali, Ahira the son of Enan. <verse eID="Num.1.15"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.16" osisID="Num.1.16"/> Such were the men selected from the com­munity, the leaders of their
       an­cestral clans, who were at the head of the septs in Israel. <verse eID="Num.1.16"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.17" osisID="Num.1.17"/> Moses and Aaron took these men who have been named, <verse eID="Num.1.17"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.18" osisID="Num.1.18"/> and mustered all the community on the first day of the second month,
       when they registered themselves, clan by clan, family by family, and had every indi­vidual over twenty numbered, <verse eID="Num.1.18"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.19" osisID="Num.1.19"/> head by head, as the Eternal had ordered.  Moses numbered them in the
       desert thus.<verse eID="Num.1.19"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Num.1.20" osisID="Num.1.20"/> The descendants of Reuben, Israel’s eldest son, reckoned clan by clan,
       family by family, with every male indi­vidual over twenty years, head by head, <verse eID="Num.1.20"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.21" osisID="Num.1.21"/> all the Reubenites who were able for active service amounted to
       forty-six thousand five hundred. <verse eID="Num.1.21"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.22" osisID="Num.1.22"/> The descendants of Simeon, reckoned clan by clan, family by family,
       with every male individual over twenty years, <verse eID="Num.1.22"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.23" osisID="Num.1.23"/> all the Simeonites who were able for active service amounted to
       fifty-nine thousand three hundred. <verse eID="Num.1.23"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.24" osisID="Num.1.24"/> The descendants of Gad, reckoned clan by clan, family by family, with
       every male individual over twenty years numbered, head by head, <verse eID="Num.1.24"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.25" osisID="Num.1.25"/> all the Gadites who were able for active service amounted to
       forty-five thousand six hundred and fifty. <verse eID="Num.1.25"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.26" osisID="Num.1.26"/> The descendants of Judah, reckoned clan by clan, family by family, with
       every male individual over twenty years, head by head, <verse eID="Num.1.26"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.27" osisID="Num.1.27"/> all the Judahites who were able for active service amounted to
       seventy-four thousand six hun­dred. <verse eID="Num.1.27"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.28" osisID="Num.1.28"/> The descendants of Issachar, reckoned clan by clan, family by family,
       with every male individual over twenty years, head by head, <verse eID="Num.1.28"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.29" osisID="Num.1.29"/> all the Issacharites who were able for active service amounted to
       fifty-four thousand four hun­dred. <verse eID="Num.1.29"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.30" osisID="Num.1.30"/> The descendants of Zebulun, reckoned clan by clan, family by family,
       with every male individual over twenty years, head by head,
      <verse eID="Num.1.30"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.31" osisID="Num.1.31"/> all the 
       <milestone type="pb" n="148"/>
       Zebulunites who were able for ac­tive service amounted to fifty-seven thousand four hundred. <verse eID="Num.1.31"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.32" osisID="Num.1.32"/> As for the Josephites--the de­scendants of Ephraim, reckoned clan by
       clan, family by family, with every male individual over twenty, head by head, <verse eID="Num.1.32"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.33" osisID="Num.1.33"/> all the Ephraimites who were able for active service amounted to forty
       thousand five hundred; <verse eID="Num.1.33"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.34" osisID="Num.1.34"/> the de­scendants of Manasseh, reck­oned clan by clan, family by family,
       with every male indi­vidual over twenty years, head by head, <verse eID="Num.1.34"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.35" osisID="Num.1.35"/> all the Manassites who were able for active service amounted to
       thirty-two thousand two hundred. <verse eID="Num.1.35"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.36" osisID="Num.1.36"/> The de­scendants of Benjamin, reck­oned clan by clan, family by family,
       with every male indi­vidual over twenty years, head by head, <verse eID="Num.1.36"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.37" osisID="Num.1.37"/> all the Benjamites who were able for active service amount to
       thirty-five thousand four hundred. <verse eID="Num.1.37"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.38" osisID="Num.1.38"/> The de­scendants of Dan, reckoned clan by clan, family by family, with
       every male descendant over twenty years, head by head, <verse eID="Num.1.38"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.39" osisID="Num.1.39"/> all the Danites who were able for active service amounted to sixty-two
       thousand seven hundred. <verse eID="Num.1.39"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.40" osisID="Num.1.40"/> The descendants of Asher, reckoned clan by clan, family by family, with
       every male individual over twenty years, head by head, <verse eID="Num.1.40"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.41" osisID="Num.1.41"/> all the Asherites who were able for active service amounted to
       forty-one thousand five hundred. <verse eID="Num.1.41"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.42" osisID="Num.1.42"/> The descendants of Naphtali, reck­oned clan by clan, family by family,
       with every male individual over twenty years, head by head, <verse eID="Num.1.42"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.43" osisID="Num.1.43"/> all the Naphtalites who were able for active service amounted to
       fifty-three thou­sand four hundred. <verse eID="Num.1.43"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Num.1.44" osisID="Num.1.44"/>Such were those whom Moses and Aaron counted up, along with the leaders
       of Israel, twelve men, each of whom represented his ancestral house. <verse eID="Num.1.44"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.45" osisID="Num.1.45"/> The number of the Israelites, family by family, over twenty years, who
       were able for active service, <verse eID="Num.1.45"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.46" osisID="Num.1.46"/> the total number was six hundred and three thousand five hun­dred and
       fifty. <verse eID="Num.1.46"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Num.1.47" osisID="Num.1.47"/> The ancestral clan of the Levites was not included, how­ever; <verse eID="Num.1.47"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.48" osisID="Num.1.48"/> the Eternal told Moses <verse eID="Num.1.48"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.49" osisID="Num.1.49"/> that he was to leave out the clan of Levi, and not to count its total
       among the Israelites, <verse eID="Num.1.49"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.50" osisID="Num.1.50"/> but to put the Levites in charge of the Dwelling of the Presence, with
       all its equipment and all its belongings; they were to carry the Dwelling and its equipment, to attend to it,
       and to encamp round it; <verse eID="Num.1.50"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.51" osisID="Num.1.51"/> whenever the Dwelling had to be moved, the Levites were to take it down,
       and when­ever it had to be pitched, the Levites were to erect it; any outsider who dared to interfere was to be
       put to death. <verse eID="Num.1.51"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.52" osisID="Num.1.52"/> The Israelites were to pitch their tents according to their respec­tive
       camps and companies, in military order, <verse eID="Num.1.52"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.53" osisID="Num.1.53"/> but the Levites were to pitch their tents round the Dwelling of the
       Presence, in order to avert any outburst of divine anger against the com­munity of Israel; they were to take
       charge of the Dwelling. <verse eID="Num.1.53"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.54" osisID="Num.1.54"/> The Israelites carried this out; they obeyed every order given by the
       Eternal to Moses. <verse eID="Num.1.54"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eId="Num.1"/>
    <chapter osisId="Num.2" sId="Num.2"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Num.2.1" osisID="Num.2.1"/>The Eternal told Moses and Aaron <verse eID="Num.2.1"/>
      <verse sID="Num.2.2" osisID="Num.2.2"/> that the Israelites were to pitch their tents according to their
       respective companies and the pennons of their clans, fac­ing the Trysting tent on every side.
      <verse eID="Num.2.2"/>
      <verse sID="Num.2.3" osisID="Num.2.3"/> Those who encamped on the eastern side, towards the dawn, were to be
       the companies
       <milestone type="pb" n="149"/>
       belonging to Judah, led by Nahshon the son of Amminadab;
      <verse eID="Num.2.3"/>
      <verse sID="Num.2.4" osisID="Num.2.4"/> his host numbered in all seventy-four thousand six hundred. <verse eID="Num.2.4"/>
      <verse sID="Num.2.5" osisID="Num.2.5"/>Next to him the clan of Issachar was to encamp, led by Nathaniel the son
       of Zuar; <verse eID="Num.2.5"/>
      <verse sID="Num.2.6" osisID="Num.2.6"/> his host numbered in all fifty-four thousand four hundred. <verse eID="Num.2.6"/>
      <verse sID="Num.2.7" osisID="Num.2.7"/> Then the clan of Zebulun, led by Eliab the son of Helon;
      <verse eID="Num.2.7"/>
      <verse sID="Num.2.8" osisID="Num.2.8"/>
       his host numbered in all fifty-seven thousand four hundred.
      <verse eID="Num.2.8"/>
      <verse sID="Num.2.9" osisID="Num.2.9"/> These battalions of Judah, numbering a hundred and eighty-six thou­sand
       four hundred, were to start on the march first. <verse eID="Num.2.9"/>
      <verse sID="Num.2.10" osisID="Num.2.10"/> On the south side the companies be­longing to Reuben were to en­camp,
       led by Elizur the son of Shedeur; <verse eID="Num.2.10"/>
      <verse sID="Num.2.11" osisID="Num.2.11"/> his host numbered in all forty-six thousand five hundred. <verse eID="Num.2.11"/>
      <verse sID="Num.2.12" osisID="Num.2.12"/> Next to him the clan of Simeon was to encamp, led by Shelumiel the son
       of Zurishaddai; <verse eID="Num.2.12"/>
      <verse sID="Num.2.13" osisID="Num.2.13"/> his host numbered in all fifty-nine thousand three hundred. <verse eID="Num.2.13"/>
      <verse sID="Num.2.14" osisID="Num.2.14"/> Then the clan of Gad, led by Eliasaph the son of Reuel; <verse eID="Num.2.14"/>
      <verse sID="Num.2.15" osisID="Num.2.15"/> his host numbered forty-five thousand six hundred and fifty. <verse eID="Num.2.15"/>
      <verse sID="Num.2.16" osisID="Num.2.16"/>These battalions of Reuben, numbering a hundred and fifty-one thousand
       four hundred and fifty, were to start second on the march. <verse eID="Num.2.16"/>
      <verse sID="Num.2.17" osisID="Num.2.17"/> Then the Trysting tent was to advance, along with the host of Levites,
       in the centre of the other hosts; they were to march, as they encamped, in their respective companies. <verse eID="Num.2.17"/>
      <verse sID="Num.2.18" osisID="Num.2.18"/> On the western side the com­panies belonging to Ephraim were to encamp,
       led by Elishama the son of Arnmihud; <verse eID="Num.2.18"/>
      <verse sID="Num.2.19" osisID="Num.2.19"/> his host numbered in all forty thousand five hundred. <verse eID="Num.2.19"/>
      <verse sID="Num.2.20" osisID="Num.2.20"/> Next to him the clan of Manasseh was to encamp, led by Gamaliel the
       son of Pedahzur; <verse eID="Num.2.20"/>
      <verse sID="Num.2.21" osisID="Num.2.21"/> his host numbered in all thirty-two thousand two hun­dred. <verse eID="Num.2.21"/>
      <verse sID="Num.2.22" osisID="Num.2.22"/> Then the clan of Benjamin, led by Abidan the son of Gideoni; <verse eID="Num.2.22"/>
      <verse sID="Num.2.23" osisID="Num.2.23"/> his host numbered in all thirty-five thousand four hun­dred. <verse eID="Num.2.23"/>
      <verse sID="Num.2.24" osisID="Num.2.24"/> These battalions of Ephraim, numbering a hundred and eight thousand
       one hundred, were to start third on the march. <verse eID="Num.2.24"/>
      <verse sID="Num.2.25" osisID="Num.2.25"/> On the northern side the companies belonging to Dan were to encamp,
       led by Ahiezer the son of Ammishaddai; <verse eID="Num.2.25"/>
      <verse sID="Num.2.26" osisID="Num.2.26"/> his host numbered in all sixty-two thousand seven hundred. <verse eID="Num.2.26"/>
      <verse sID="Num.2.27" osisID="Num.2.27"/> Next to him the clan of Asher was to encamp, led by Pagiel the son of
       Ochran; <verse eID="Num.2.27"/>
      <verse sID="Num.2.28" osisID="Num.2.28"/> his host numbered in all forty-one thousand five hundred. <verse eID="Num.2.28"/>
      <verse sID="Num.2.29" osisID="Num.2.29"/> Then the clan of Naphtali, led by Ahira the son of Enan; <verse eID="Num.2.29"/>
      <verse sID="Num.2.30" osisID="Num.2.30"/> his host numbered fifty-three thou­sand four hundred. <verse eID="Num.2.30"/>
      <verse sID="Num.2.31" osisID="Num.2.31"/> These battalions of Dan, numbering a hundred and fifty-seven thou­sand
       six hundred, were to march company by company in the rear. <verse eID="Num.2.31"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Num.2.32" osisID="Num.2.32"/> Such were the Israelites counted by their families; those who were
       numbered by com­panies in their respective camps amounted to six hundred and three thousand five hundred and
       fifty. <verse eID="Num.2.32"/>
      <verse sID="Num.2.33" osisID="Num.2.33"/> But, by order of the Eternal to Moses, the Levites were not included
       in the reckon­ing of the Israelites. <verse eID="Num.2.33"/>
      <verse sID="Num.2.34" osisID="Num.2.34"/> The Israelites carried this out; exactly as the Eternal had ordered
       Moses, so they encamped in their respective companies and marched, clan by clan, family by family. <verse eID="Num.2.34"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eId="Num.2"/>
    <chapter osisId="Num.3" sId="Num.3"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Num.3.1" osisID="Num.3.1"/>These were the descendants of Aaron and Moses, when the Eternal talked to
       Moses on mount Sinai. <verse eID="Num.3.1"/>
      <verse sID="Num.3.2" osisID="Num.3.2"/> The names of a Aaron’s sons were Nadab (the eldest), Abihu, Eleazar,
       and Ithamar; <verse eID="Num.3.2"/>
      <verse sID="Num.3.3" osisID="Num.3.3"/> these were the names 3 of Aaron’s sons, consecrated
       <milestone type="pb" n="150"/> priests, whom he installed in the priestly office. <verse eID="Num.3.3"/>
      <verse sID="Num.3.4" osisID="Num.3.4"/> Nadab and Abihu died before the Eternal, when they offered irregular
       fire before the Eternal in the desert of Sinai; they left no children. But Eleazar and Ithamar served as
       priests during the lifetime of their father. <verse eID="Num.3.4"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Num.3.5" osisID="Num.3.5"/>The Eternal said to Moses, <verse eID="Num.3.5"/>
      <verse sID="Num.3.6" osisID="Num.3.6"/><q>Bring the clan of Levi and present them before Aaron the priest, to be
       at his service. <verse eID="Num.3.6"/>
      <verse sID="Num.3.7" osisID="Num.3.7"/> They shall do duty for him and for the whole community at the Trysting
       tent, as attendants of the Dwelling, <verse eID="Num.3.7"/>
      <verse sID="Num.3.8" osisID="Num.3.8"/> taking charge of all the equipment of the Tryst­ing tent and the
       arrangements for the Israelites, as attendants of the Dwelling. <verse eID="Num.3.8"/>
      <verse sID="Num.3.9" osisID="Num.3.9"/> Assign the Levites to Aaron and his sons; they belong to him, out of the
       Israelites. <verse eID="Num.3.9"/>
      <verse sID="Num.3.10" osisID="Num.3.10"/> Appoint Aaron and his sons to hold their priest­hood; any layman who
       dares to interfere shall be put to death.</q> <verse eID="Num.3.10"/>
      <verse sID="Num.3.11" osisID="Num.3.11"/> The Eternal said to Moses, <verse eID="Num.3.11"/>
      <verse sID="Num.3.12" osisID="Num.3.12"/> <q>I myself have taken the Levites from Israel instead of the eldest
       children born in Israel; the Le­vites belong to me, <verse eID="Num.3.12"/>
      <verse sID="Num.3.13" osisID="Num.3.13"/> for all the eldest children belong to me. When I killed all the eldest
       born in the land of Egypt I claimed as my own all the eldest born in Israel, both man and beast; mine they shall
       be: I am the Eternal.</q> <verse eID="Num.3.13"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Num.3.14" osisID="Num.3.14"/> In the desert of Sinai the Eternal ordered Moses <verse eID="Num.3.14"/>
      <verse sID="Num.3.15" osisID="Num.3.15"/> to num­ber the Levites, clan by clan, family by family, counting every
       male over a month old. <verse eID="Num.3.15"/>
      <verse sID="Num.3.16" osisID="Num.3.16"/> Moses numbered them as the Eternal bade him. <verse eID="Num.3.16"/>
      <verse sID="Num.3.17" osisID="Num.3.17"/> The names of the sons of Levi were Gershon, Kohath, and Merari; <verse eID="Num.3.17"/>
      <verse sID="Num.3.18" osisID="Num.3.18"/> the names of the sons of Gershon, clan by clan, were Libni and Shimei; <verse eID="Num.3.18"/>
      <verse sID="Num.3.19" osisID="Num.3.19"/> the sons of Kohath, clan by clan, were Amram, Izhar, Hebron, and
       Uzziel; <verse eID="Num.3.19"/>
      <verse sID="Num.3.20" osisID="Num.3.20"/> the sons of Merari, clan by clan, were Mahli and Mushi. Such were the
       Levitical clans, family by family. <verse eID="Num.3.20"/>
      <verse sID="Num.3.21" osisID="Num.3.21"/> To Gershon belonged the Libnites and the Shimeites; <verse eID="Num.3.21"/>
      <verse sID="Num.3.22" osisID="Num.3.22"/> of these Gershonite clans there were counted seven thousand five hundred
       members, the total number of males over a month old. <verse eID="Num.3.22"/>
      <verse sID="Num.3.23" osisID="Num.3.23"/> The Gershonite clans were to encamp on the western side of the tent, <verse eID="Num.3.23"/>
      <verse sID="Num.3.24" osisID="Num.3.24"/> led by Eliasaph the son of Lael. <verse eID="Num.3.24"/>
      <verse sID="Num.3.25" osisID="Num.3.25"/> In the Trysting tent the Gershonites were to take charge of the
       Dwelling and the tent, of everything con­nected with the wrapper for the tent, the veil for the entrance into
       the Trysting tent, <verse eID="Num.3.25"/>
      <verse sID="Num.3.26" osisID="Num.3.26"/> the hangings, the curtains for the en­trance into the court round the
       tent and the altar, and the ropes. <verse eID="Num.3.26"/>
      <verse sID="Num.3.27" osisID="Num.3.27"/> To Kohath belonged the Amramites, the Izharites, the Hebronites, and
       the Uzzielites; <verse eID="Num.3.27"/>
      <verse sID="Num.3.28" osisID="Num.3.28"/> of these Kohathite clans there were counted eight thousand three
       hundred members, the total number of males over a month old. <verse eID="Num.3.28"/>
      <verse sID="Num.3.29" osisID="Num.3.29"/> The Kohathite clans were to encamp on the south side of the tent, <verse eID="Num.3.29"/>
      <verse sID="Num.3.30" osisID="Num.3.30"/> led by Elizaphan the son of Uzziel. <verse eID="Num.3.30"/>
      <verse sID="Num.3.31" osisID="Num.3.31"/> They were to take charge of everything connected with the ark, the
       table, the lampstand, the altars and articles of the sanctuary where the priests serve, and the curtain that
       screened it off. <verse eID="Num.3.31"/>
      <verse sID="Num.3.32" osisID="Num.3.32"/> Eleazar the son of Aaron was to have authority over the Levitical
       authorities and to supervise those who had charge of the sanctuary. <verse eID="Num.3.32"/>
      <verse sID="Num.3.33" osisID="Num.3.33"/> To Merari belonged the Mahlites and the Mushites; <verse eID="Num.3.33"/>
      <verse sID="Num.3.34" osisID="Num.3.34"/> of these Merari clans there were counted six thousand two hun­dred
       members, the total number
       <milestone type="pb" n="151"/>
       of males over a month old. <verse eID="Num.3.34"/>
      <verse sID="Num.3.35" osisID="Num.3.35"/> The Merarite clans were led by Zuriel the son of Abihail, and had to
       encamp on the north side of the tent. <verse eID="Num.3.35"/>
      <verse sID="Num.3.36" osisID="Num.3.36"/> The Merarites were to take full charge of the frames, bars, columns,
       and pedes­tals of the Dwelling, and every­thing connected with its frame-work, <verse eID="Num.3.36"/>
      <verse sID="Num.3.37" osisID="Num.3.37"/> as well as of the columns of the surrounding courtyard, their
       pedestals, pegs, and ropes. <verse eID="Num.3.37"/>
      <verse sID="Num.3.38" osisID="Num.3.38"/> Those who en­camp on the eastern side of the tent, on the front facing
       the dawn, were to be Moses and Aaron and his sons, attending to everything in the sanctuary, everything that is
       required for worship by the Israelites; any layman who dared to interfere must be put to death. <verse eID="Num.3.38"/>
      <verse sID="Num.3.39" osisID="Num.3.39"/> The total number of Levites counted by Moses at the bidding of the
       Eternal, clan by clan, all the males over a month old, amounted to twenty-two thou­sand. <verse eID="Num.3.39"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Num.3.40" osisID="Num.3.40"/> The Eternal said to Moses, <q>Number all the eldest males of Israel,
       from a month upwards; number them one by one. <verse eID="Num.3.40"/>
      <verse sID="Num.3.41" osisID="Num.3.41"/> And pick out for me (I am the Eter­nal) the Levites instead of all the
       eldest males in Israel, and the cattle of the Levites instead of all the first-born cattle belonging to the
       Israelites.</q> <verse eID="Num.3.41"/>
      <verse sID="Num.3.42" osisID="Num.3.42"/> Moses did as the Eternal ordered him, numbering all the eldest of the
       Israelites; <verse eID="Num.3.42"/>
      <verse sID="Num.3.43" osisID="Num.3.43"/> and all the eldest males, over a month old, counted one by one,
       amounted to twenty-two thousand two hundred and seventy-three. <verse eID="Num.3.43"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Num.3.44" osisID="Num.3.44"/><q>Now,</q> said the Eternal to Moses, <verse eID="Num.3.44"/>
      <verse sID="Num.3.45" osisID="Num.3.45"/> <q>pick out the Levites instead of all the eldest males in Israel, and
       the cattle of the Levites instead of their cattle, and the Levites shall be mine: I am the Eternal. <verse eID="Num.3.45"/>
      <verse sID="Num.3.46" osisID="Num.3.46"/> To redeem the two hundred and seventy-three among the eldest males of
       Israel, over and above the number of the Levites, <verse eID="Num.3.46"/>
      <verse sID="Num.3.47" osisID="Num.3.47"/> you must pay twelve shillings a head for them (reckoning by the sa­cred
       shekel, that is, twenty gerahs), <verse eID="Num.3.47"/>
      <verse sID="Num.3.48" osisID="Num.3.48"/> handing over the price of this extra number to Aaron and his sons.</q> <verse eID="Num.3.48"/>
      <verse sID="Num.3.49" osisID="Num.3.49"/> So Moses took the redemption-money from these extra men, over and
       above the number of the Levites; <verse eID="Num.3.49"/>
      <verse sID="Num.3.50" osisID="Num.3.50"/> he took from the eldest born of Israel a hundred and sixty-three
       pounds sixteen shillings (reckoning by the sacred shekel), <verse eID="Num.3.50"/>
      <verse sID="Num.3.51" osisID="Num.3.51"/> and this redemption-money Moses handed over to Aaron and his sons, as
       the Eternal had told him, as the Eternal had ordered Moses. <verse eID="Num.3.51"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eId="Num.3"/>
    <chapter osisId="Num.4" sId="Num.4"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Num.4.1" osisID="Num.4.1"/>The Eternal told Moses and Aaron <verse eID="Num.4.1"/>
      <verse sID="Num.4.2" osisID="Num.4.2"/> to count up the total number of the Kohathites, among the Levites, clan
       by clan, family by family, <verse eID="Num.4.2"/>
      <verse sID="Num.4.3" osisID="Num.4.3"/> all between thirty and fifty years of age, who entered the service for
       work in the Trysting tent. <verse eID="Num.4.3"/>
      <verse sID="Num.4.4" osisID="Num.4.4"/> The duties of the Kohathites with regard to the sacred fabric of the
       tent were to be as follows. <verse eID="Num.4.4"/>
      <verse sID="Num.4.5" osisID="Num.4.5"/> When the camp started on the march, Aaron and his sons were to enter the
       tent, take down the curtain that screened off the ark and put it over the ark of the Pres­ence, <verse eID="Num.4.5"/>
      <verse sID="Num.4.6" osisID="Num.4.6"/> wrapping a leather sheet over it, laying a violet pall on the top, and
       inserting the poles into the ark. <verse eID="Num.4.6"/>
      <verse sID="Num.4.7" osisID="Num.4.7"/> They were to spread a violet pall over the table of the Presence,
       placing on it the dishes, saucers, chal­ices, and flagons for pouring libations, along with the perennial bread, <verse eID="Num.4.7"/>
      <verse sID="Num.4.8" osisID="Num.4.8"/> laying a scarlet pall on the top, and wrapping a leather sheet over it,
       besides in­serting the poles in the table.
      <verse eID="Num.4.8"/>
      <milestone type="pb" n="152"/>
      <verse sID="Num.4.9" osisID="Num.4.9"/>They were to lay a violet pall over the lampstand, with its lamps,
       ash-trays, snuffers, and oil-cans, <verse eID="Num.4.9"/>
      <verse sID="Num.4.10" osisID="Num.4.10"/> wrapping all up in a leather sheet, and placing the things on a
       stretcher. <verse eID="Num.4.10"/>
      <verse sID="Num.4.11" osisID="Num.4.11"/> They were to lay a violet pall over the golden altar, covering it with
       a leather sheet, and inserting the poles in the altar; <verse eID="Num.4.11"/>
      <verse sID="Num.4.12" osisID="Num.4.12"/> also they were to wrap up all the sacerdotal utensils in a violet pall,
       covering the whole with a leather sheet, and placing them on the stretcher. <verse eID="Num.4.12"/>
      <verse sID="Num.4.13" osisID="Num.4.13"/> After removing the ashes, they were to lay a crimson pall over the
       other altar, <verse eID="Num.4.13"/>
      <verse sID="Num.4.14" osisID="Num.4.14"/> placing upon it all the utensils of the sacerdotal service, the
       fire-pans, the prongs, the shovels, and the bowls, wrapping all up in a leather sheet, and inserting the poles
       in the altar. <verse eID="Num.4.14"/>
      <verse sID="Num.4.15" osisID="Num.4.15"/> Once Aaron and his sons had finished cover­ing up the sanctuary and all
       its contents, then, as the camp marched forward, the Kohathites were to come forward and carry the load--but
       without touching the sacred objects themselves; that would be fatal to them. Such were the duties of the
       Kohathites in the Trysting tent. <verse eID="Num.4.15"/>
      <verse sID="Num.4.16" osisID="Num.4.16"/> Eleazar the son of Aaron the priest was to be re­sponsible for the oil
       required for the lighting, the fragrant in­cense, the perennial cereal-offer­ings, and the oil required for
       anointing; he was to take charge of all the Dwelling and its con­tents, the sanctuary and all its furnishing. <verse eID="Num.4.16"/>
      <verse sID="Num.4.17" osisID="Num.4.17"/> The Eternal told Moses and Aaron <verse eID="Num.4.17"/>
      <verse sID="Num.4.18" osisID="Num.4.18"/> to treat the Kohathites in this way, in order to prevent their clan
       and fam­ilies from being destroyed as Levites, <verse eID="Num.4.18"/>
      <verse sID="Num.4.19" osisID="Num.4.19"/> in order that they might live, and not die, in han­dling the sacred
       objects. Aaron and his sons were to enter the sacred precincts, <verse eID="Num.4.19"/>
      <verse sID="Num.4.20" osisID="Num.4.20"/> but the Kohathites, in discharging all their appointed tasks and
       duties, were not to set eyes for a second upon the sacred objects, since that would be fatal to them. <verse eID="Num.4.20"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Num.4.21" osisID="Num.4.21"/> The Eternal also told Moses <verse eID="Num.4.21"/>
      <verse sID="Num.4.22" osisID="Num.4.22"/> to count up the total number of the Gershonites, family by fam­ily,
       clan by clan, <verse eID="Num.4.22"/>
      <verse sID="Num.4.23" osisID="Num.4.23"/> all between thirty and fifty years of age, who entered the service for
       work in the Trysting tent. <verse eID="Num.4.23"/>
      <verse sID="Num.4.24" osisID="Num.4.24"/> The duties of the Gershonites as attendants and bearers were to be as
       follows. <verse eID="Num.4.24"/>
      <verse sID="Num.4.25" osisID="Num.4.25"/> They were to carry the curtains of the Dwell­ing, the hangings and the
       leather wrappers for the Trysting tent, the curtain for the entrance of the Trysting tent, <verse eID="Num.4.25"/>
      <verse sID="Num.4.26" osisID="Num.4.26"/> the hangings of the courtyard, the veil for the entrance of the
       courtyard that surrounds the Dwelling and the altar, with all the ropes and equipment, attending to every­thing
       connected with these. <verse eID="Num.4.26"/>
      <verse sID="Num.4.27" osisID="Num.4.27"/> Aaron and his sons were to have full authority over the Gershon­ites as
       attendants and bearers, specifying for them their duties in detail. <verse eID="Num.4.27"/>
      <verse sID="Num.4.28" osisID="Num.4.28"/> Such was to be the position of the Gershonites in serving the Trysting
       tent, and they were to be supervised by Ithamar the son of Aaron the priest. <verse eID="Num.4.28"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Num.4.29" osisID="Num.4.29"/> As for the Merarites, Moses was to number them clan by clan, family by
       family, <verse eID="Num.4.29"/>
      <verse sID="Num.4.30" osisID="Num.4.30"/> counting everyone between thirty and fifty years of age who entered
       the service for work in the Trysting tent. <verse eID="Num.4.30"/>
      <verse sID="Num.4.31" osisID="Num.4.31"/> The duties falling to them in the due course of this service were to
       be the transport of the frames, bars, columns, and pedestals of the Dwelling, <verse eID="Num.4.31"/>
      <verse sID="Num.4.32" osisID="Num.4.32"/> as well as of the columns of the surrounding
       <milestone type="pb" n="153"/>
       courtyard, their pedestals, pegs, and ropes, and all connected with the framework; they were to be told off one
       by one to the object each had to carry. <verse eID="Num.4.32"/>
      <verse sID="Num.4.33" osisID="Num.4.33"/> Such was to be the position of the Merarites in serving the Trysting
       tent, under the supervision of Ithamar, the son of Aaron the priest. <verse eID="Num.4.33"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Num.4.34" osisID="Num.4.34"/>Moses and Aaron and the leaders of the community then counted up the
       Kohathites, clan by clan, family by family, <verse eID="Num.4.34"/>
      <verse sID="Num.4.35" osisID="Num.4.35"/> reck­oning everyone between thirty and fifty years of age who en­tered
       the service for work in the Trysting tent; <verse eID="Num.4.35"/>
      <verse sID="Num.4.36" osisID="Num.4.36"/> and the total number was two thousand seven hundred and fifty. <verse eID="Num.4.36"/>
      <verse sID="Num.4.37" osisID="Num.4.37"/> These were all the Kohathites who served in the Trysting tent,
       numbered by Moses and Aaron as the Eternal had sent orders through Moses. <verse eID="Num.4.37"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Num.4.38" osisID="Num.4.38"/>As for the Gershonites, num­bered clan by clan, family by family, <verse eID="Num.4.38"/>
      <verse sID="Num.4.39" osisID="Num.4.39"/> the total number of those between thirty and fifty years of age who
       entered the service for work in the Trysting tent <verse eID="Num.4.39"/>
      <verse sID="Num.4.40" osisID="Num.4.40"/> amounted to two thousand six hundred and thirty. <verse eID="Num.4.40"/>
      <verse sID="Num.4.41" osisID="Num.4.41"/> These were all the Gershonites who served in the Trysting tent,
       numbered by Moses and Aaron, as the Eternal had ordered. <verse eID="Num.4.41"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Num.4.42" osisID="Num.4.42"/>As for the Merarites, num­bered clan by clan, family by family, <verse eID="Num.4.42"/>
      <verse sID="Num.4.43" osisID="Num.4.43"/> the total number of those between thirty and fifty years of age who
       entered the service for work in the Trysting tent <verse eID="Num.4.43"/>
      <verse sID="Num.4.44" osisID="Num.4.44"/> amounted to three thousand two hundred. <verse eID="Num.4.44"/>
      <verse sID="Num.4.45" osisID="Num.4.45"/> These were all the Merarites, numbered by Moses and Aaron as the
       Eternal had sent orders through Moses. <verse eID="Num.4.45"/>
      <verse sID="Num.4.46" osisID="Num.4.46"/>The total number of Levites, whom Moses and Aaron and the leaders of
       Israel counted clan by clan, family by family, <verse eID="Num.4.46"/>
      <verse sID="Num.4.47" osisID="Num.4.47"/> men be­tween thirty and fifty years of age, men who entered the
       service as attendants and bear­ers in connexion with the Tryst­ing tent--<verse eID="Num.4.47"/>
      <verse sID="Num.4.48" osisID="Num.4.48"/>their total amounted in all to eight thousand five hun­dred and eighty. <verse eID="Num.4.48"/>
      <verse sID="Num.4.49" osisID="Num.4.49"/> As the Eternal had given orders, they were assigned their respective
       tasks and duties by Moses, who num­bered them as the Eternal had ordered him. <verse eID="Num.4.49"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eId="Num.4"/>
    <chapter osisId="Num.5" sId="Num.5"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Num.5.1" osisID="Num.5.1"/>The Eternal said to Moses, <verse eID="Num.5.1"/>
      <verse sID="Num.5.2" osisID="Num.5.2"/> <q>Order the Israelites to shut out from their camp any leper, anyone
       suffering from a dis­charge, and anyone defiled by contact with a corpse; <verse eID="Num.5.2"/>
      <verse sID="Num.5.3" osisID="Num.5.3"/> male or female, out with them--put them outside the camp! They are not
       to pollute the camp within which I dwell.</q> <verse eID="Num.5.3"/>
      <verse sID="Num.5.4" osisID="Num.5.4"/> The Israelites obeyed, they put such persons outside the camp; the
       Israelites did as the Eternal gave orders to Moses. <verse eID="Num.5.4"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Num.5.5" osisID="Num.5.5"/> The Eternal gave Moses <verse eID="Num.5.5"/>
      <verse sID="Num.5.6" osisID="Num.5.6"/> this order for the Israelites. <q>If a man or woman commits any of the
       crimes into which men fall, breaking faith with the Eternal and incurring guilt, <verse eID="Num.5.6"/>
      <verse sID="Num.5.7" osisID="Num.5.7"/> they must confess their sinful act and re­store their ill-gotten gains in
       full, adding a fifth of the value as a present to the person they have wronged. <verse eID="Num.5.7"/>
      <verse sID="Num.5.8" osisID="Num.5.8"/> Should that person have died, leaving no next-of-kin to whom restitution
       can be made, the restored property falls to the priest for the Eter­nal, in addition to the ram required for the
       sacrifice of expi­ation. <verse eID="Num.5.8"/>
      <verse sID="Num.5.9" osisID="Num.5.9"/> Indeed, every contribution made by Israelites, every sacred gift
       presented to a priest, shall belong to that priest; <verse eID="Num.5.9"/>
      <verse sID="Num.5.10" osisID="Num.5.10"/> a man’s sacred offerings shall be­long to the priest; whatever anyone
       gives to a priest, his shall it be.</q> <verse eID="Num.5.10"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Num.5.11" osisID="Num.5.11"/>The Eternal gave Moses this
       <milestone type="pb" n="154"/>
      <verse eID="Num.5.11"/>
      <verse sID="Num.5.12" osisID="Num.5.12"/>
       order for the Israelites. <q>If a man’s wife goes wrong and proves unfaithful to him, <verse eID="Num.5.12"/>
      <verse sID="Num.5.13" osisID="Num.5.13"/> if an­other man lies with her, un­known to her husband, if she remains
       undetected although she has defiled herself, if there is no witness against her since she was not caught in the
       act, <verse eID="Num.5.13"/>
      <verse sID="Num.5.14" osisID="Num.5.14"/> then, if he has a fit of suspicion, suspect­ing his wife, even although
       she may not have defiled herself, <verse eID="Num.5.14"/>
      <verse sID="Num.5.15" osisID="Num.5.15"/> he must take his wife before the priest, bringing the requisite
       offering of seven pints of barley meal (but pouring no oil over it and adding no frankincense to it, since it
       is a cereal-offering of suspicion, a cereal-offering meant to recall sin). <verse eID="Num.5.15"/>
      <verse sID="Num.5.16" osisID="Num.5.16"/> The priest shall place her in front of the Eternal; <verse eID="Num.5.16"/>
      <verse sID="Num.5.17" osisID="Num.5.17"/> he shall put some holy water in an earthen jar and drop into the water
       some dust from the floor of the Dwelling; <verse eID="Num.5.17"/>
      <verse sID="Num.5.18" osisID="Num.5.18"/> then the priest shall loosen the woman’s hair and make her hold the
       cereal-offering that is a memento of sin, the cereal­offering of suspicion, he himself holding the water that
       causes pain, that brings a curse with it. <verse eID="Num.5.18"/>
      <verse sID="Num.5.19" osisID="Num.5.19"/> The priest shall then say to the woman, <q>If no man has lain with
       you, if you have not turned to unclean courses as a married woman, then may no harm come to you from this water
       that causes pain, that brings a curse with it! <verse eID="Num.5.19"/>
      <verse sID="Num.5.20" osisID="Num.5.20"/> But if, as a married woman, you have gone wrong, if you have defiled
       yourself and let another man besides your husband lie with you, then--</q> <verse eID="Num.5.20"/>
      <verse sID="Num.5.21" osisID="Num.5.21"/> adjuring the woman with a sol­emn curse, the priest shall add--<q>May
       the Eternal make an example of you, may he make you accursed among your peo­ple, by causing your thighs to
       shrivel and your belly to swell! <verse eID="Num.5.21"/>
      <verse sID="Num.5.22" osisID="Num.5.22"/> May this water that brings a curse with it enter your womb, causing
       your thighs to shrivel and your belly to swell!</q> <q>So be it,</q> shall the woman say, <q>so be it.</q></q>
      <verse eID="Num.5.22"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Num.5.23" osisID="Num.5.23"/><q>Then the priest shall write the curses down and wash the writ­ingk
       into the water that causes pain; <verse eID="Num.5.23"/>
      <verse sID="Num.5.24" osisID="Num.5.24"/> he shall make the woman drink the water that causes pain, that brings
       a curse with it, so that the water which brings a curse with it may pass into her and cause pain. <verse eID="Num.5.24"/>
      <verse sID="Num.5.25" osisID="Num.5.25"/> Then shall the priest take the cereal-offering of suspicion from the
       woman and wave the cereal-offering in front of the Eternal, bringing it up to the altar
      <verse eID="Num.5.25"/>
      <verse sID="Num.5.26" osisID="Num.5.26"/> and burning a handful of it on the altar as a memento. Once he has
       made the woman drink the water, <verse eID="Num.5.26"/>
      <verse sID="Num.5.27" osisID="Num.5.27"/> if she has de­filed herself and been unfaithful to her husband, then
       the water that brings a curse with it shall pass into her and cause pain, till her belly swells and her thighs
       shrivel and she becomes accursed among her people. <verse eID="Num.5.27"/>
      <verse sID="Num.5.28" osisID="Num.5.28"/> But if she has not defiled herself, if she is a pure woman, then she
       shall re­main unharmed, and she can still bear children.</q><verse eID="Num.5.28"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Num.5.29" osisID="Num.5.29"/><q>Such is the law in cases of suspicion, when a married wom­an goes wrong
       and defiles her­self, <verse eID="Num.5.29"/>
      <verse sID="Num.5.30" osisID="Num.5.30"/> or when a fit of suspicion comes over a man, till he is sus­picious of
       his wife; he shall make her stand in front of the Eter­nal, and the priest shall deal with her in terms of this
       law. <verse eID="Num.5.30"/>
      <verse sID="Num.5.31" osisID="Num.5.31"/> The husband shall incur no guilt, but the woman must be punished for
       her sin.</q>
      <verse eID="Num.5.31"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eId="Num.5"/>
    <chapter osisId="Num.6" sId="Num.6"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Num.6.1" osisID="Num.6.1"/>The Eternal gave Moses this order <verse eID="Num.6.1"/>
      <verse sID="Num.6.2" osisID="Num.6.2"/> for the Israelites. <q>If a man or a woman makes a special vow, the vow
       of a Nazirite, setting himself apart for
       <milestone type="pb" n="155"/>
       the Eternal, <verse eID="Num.6.2"/>
      <verse sID="Num.6.3" osisID="Num.6.3"/> he must abstain from wine and liquor, drinking neither vinegar made from
       wine nor vinegar made from liquor nor any grape-juice, and eating neither fresh grapes nor raisins; <verse eID="Num.6.3"/>
      <verse sID="Num.6.4" osisID="Num.6.4"/>so long as he remains a Nazirite, he shall not eat any part of a grape,
       from pip to skin. <verse eID="Num.6.4"/>
      <verse sID="Num.6.5" osisID="Num.6.5"/> No razor shall trim his head while he remains set apart; till the days
       are over for which he set himself apart to the Eternal, he must count as one consecrated, and let his hair grow.
      <verse eID="Num.6.5"/>
      <verse sID="Num.6.6" osisID="Num.6.6"/>
       Nor shall he go near a corpse, during all the time he has set himself apart for the Eternal; <verse eID="Num.6.6"/>
      <verse sID="Num.6.7" osisID="Num.6.7"/> he must not in­cur such defilement over his father or mother, his brother
       or sister, should they die; for he is set apart for the Eternal, and bound by that. <verse eID="Num.6.7"/>
      <verse sID="Num.6.8" osisID="Num.6.8"/> He counts as one consecrated to the Eternal, all the time he is set
       apart. <verse eID="Num.6.8"/>
      <verse sID="Num.6.9" osisID="Num.6.9"/> If anyone suddenly dies beside him, so that his person is de­filed and
       desecrated, he must shave his head on the seventh day, when he regains his cleanness, <verse eID="Num.6.9"/>
      <verse sID="Num.6.10" osisID="Num.6.10"/> and on the eighth day he must take a pair of turtle-doves or young
       pigeons to the priest at the entrance of the Trysting tent; <verse eID="Num.6.10"/>
      <verse sID="Num.6.11" osisID="Num.6.11"/> one of these the priest shall offer as a sin-offering and the other
       as a burnt-offering by way of expiation for his sin incurred with regard to the corpse;
       that same day he must consecrate his head again <verse eID="Num.6.11"/>
      <verse sID="Num.6.12" osisID="Num.6.12"/> and renew the whole period of his consecration, offering a male
       yearling lamb for his guilt; his previous period of consecration does not count, since it has been defiled.</q> <verse eID="Num.6.12"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Num.6.13" osisID="Num.6.13"/><q>It is the law of the Nazirite that, on the day his period of
       consecration is over, he shall be taken to the entrance of the Trysting tent, <verse eID="Num.6.13"/>
      <verse sID="Num.6.14" osisID="Num.6.14"/> where he shall present to the Eternal one year­ling male lamb without a
       blem­ish as a burnt-offering, one yearling ewe lamb without a blemish as a sin-offering, one ram without a
       blemish as a recompense-offering, <verse eID="Num.6.14"/>
      <verse sID="Num.6.15" osisID="Num.6.15"/> and a basket of unleavened bread, of cakes made of fine flour mixed
       with oil, and unleavened pan­cakes smeared with oil, besides the ordinary cereals and liba­tions for sacrifice. <verse eID="Num.6.15"/>
      <verse sID="Num.6.16" osisID="Num.6.16"/> These the priest shall offer on his behalf, sacrificing the
       sin-offering and the burnt-offering, <verse eID="Num.6.16"/>
      <verse sID="Num.6.17" osisID="Num.6.17"/> and the ram as a recompense-offering to the Eternal, along with its
       cereals and libations, and the basket of unleavened bread. <verse eID="Num.6.17"/>
      <verse sID="Num.6.18" osisID="Num.6.18"/> Then the Nazirite shall shave his con­secrated head at the entrance
       of the Trysting tent, and lay the hair cut from his consecrated head upon the fire that is burn­ing under the
       sacrifice of the recompense-offering. <verse eID="Num.6.18"/>
      <verse sID="Num.6.19" osisID="Num.6.19"/> The priest shall take the cooked shoulder of the ram, along with one
       un­leavened cake and one pancake from the basket, placing them in the hands of the Nazirite after he has shaved;
      <verse eID="Num.6.19"/>
      <verse sID="Num.6.20" osisID="Num.6.20"/> then the priest shall wave them before the Eternal as a waved
       offering, and they shall form a hallowed gilt for the priest, in addition to the breast of the waved offering
       and the right thigh of the animal contributed. Thereafter the Nazirite may drink wine. </q> <verse eID="Num.6.20"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Num.6.21" osisID="Num.6.21"/><q>Such is the law for the Nazirite who takes a vow--such is the of­fering
       he makes as one set apart for the Eternal, besides any­thing else that he can afford.</q> <verse eID="Num.6.21"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Num.6.22" osisID="Num.6.22"/> The Eternal gave Moses <verse eID="Num.6.22"/>
      <verse sID="Num.6.23" osisID="Num.6.23"/> this order for Aaron and his sons, <q>You shall bless Israel in these
       words; <verse eID="Num.6.23"/>
      <milestone type="pb" n="156"/>
      <verse sID="Num.6.24" osisID="Num.6.24"/>
      <lg><q>
       <l>May the Eternal bless you and protect you!</l>
      <verse eID="Num.6.24"/>
      <verse sID="Num.6.25" osisID="Num.6.25"/>
       <l>May the Eternal smile on you and favour you!</l>
      <verse eID="Num.6.25"/>
      <verse sID="Num.6.26" osisID="Num.6.26"/>
       <l>May the Eternal befriend you and prosper you!</l>
      <verse eID="Num.6.26"/>
      </q></lg>
      <verse sID="Num.6.27" osisID="Num.6.27"/>So shall they ensure my pres­ence among Israel, that I may bless
       them.</q> <verse eID="Num.6.27"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eId="Num.6"/>
    <chapter osisId="Num.7" sId="Num.7"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Num.7.1" osisID="Num.7.1"/>Now on the day when Moses finished the erection of the Dwelling,
       anointing it and con­secrating it, and also anointing and consecrating all its belong­ings and the altar with all
       its belongings, <verse eID="Num.7.1"/>
      <verse sID="Num.7.2" osisID="Num.7.2"/> the chieftains of Israel who were heads of fam­ilies (that is, the
       leaders of the clans, at the head of the men who had been registered) <verse eID="Num.7.2"/>
      <verse sID="Num.7.3" osisID="Num.7.3"/> brought their offerings before the Eternal, six large waggons and
       twelve oxen, a waggon for every two chieftains and one ox for every chieftain; these they presented in front of
       the Dwelling, <verse eID="Num.7.3"/>
      <verse sID="Num.7.4" osisID="Num.7.4"/> and the Eternal told Moses <verse eID="Num.7.4"/>
      <verse sID="Num.7.5" osisID="Num.7.5"/> to accept the gift from them, that the waggons might serve for moving
       the Trysting tent; he was to hand them over to the Levites, as they required them for their special duties. <verse eID="Num.7.5"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Num.7.6" osisID="Num.7.6"/>So Moses accepted the wag­gons and the oxen and handed them over to the
       Levites: <verse eID="Num.7.6"/>
      <verse sID="Num.7.7" osisID="Num.7.7"/> two waggons and four oxen he handed over to the Gershonites for their
       work, <verse eID="Num.7.7"/>
      <verse sID="Num.7.8" osisID="Num.7.8"/> and four waggons with eight oxen he handed over to the Merarites for
       the work they had to do under the super­vision of Ithamar the son of Aaron the priest. <verse eID="Num.7.8"/>
      <verse sID="Num.7.9" osisID="Num.7.9"/> To the Kohathites he gave nothing, for they were in charge of sacred
       ob­jects which they had to carry on their shoulders. <verse eID="Num.7.9"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Num.7.10" osisID="Num.7.10"/>On the day that the altar was anointed the chieftains also brought
       their dedication gift, presenting their offerings before the altar; <verse eID="Num.7.10"/>
      <verse sID="Num.7.11" osisID="Num.7.11"/> whereupon the Eternal told Moses that the chief­tains were to present
       their offer­ings one after another, day by day, for the dedication of the altar. <verse eID="Num.7.11"/>
      <verse sID="Num.7.12" osisID="Num.7.12"/> He who offered on the first day was Nahshon the son of Amminadab,
       belonging to the clan of Judah, <verse eID="Num.7.12"/>
      <verse sID="Num.7.13" osisID="Num.7.13"/> and his offering was a silver dish weighing about five pounds, a
       silver bowl weighing nearly three pounds (on the sacred scale of weights), both of them full of fine flour
       mixed with oil as a cereal-offering, <verse eID="Num.7.13"/>
      <verse sID="Num.7.14" osisID="Num.7.14"/> a golden saucer weighing nearly five ounces, full of incense, <verse eID="Num.7.14"/>
      <verse sID="Num.7.15" osisID="Num.7.15"/> a young bullock, a ram, and a yearling male lamb as a burnt-offering, <verse eID="Num.7.15"/>
      <verse sID="Num.7.16" osisID="Num.7.16"/> a he-goat as a sin-offering, <verse eID="Num.7.16"/>
      <verse sID="Num.7.17" osisID="Num.7.17"/> and, by way of sacrifice for a recompense-offering, two oxen, five
       rams, five he-goats and five yearling male lambs. Such was what Nahshon the son of Amminadab offered. <verse eID="Num.7.17"/>
      <verse sID="Num.7.18" osisID="Num.7.18"/> On the second day Nathaniel the son of Zuar, chieftain of Issachar,
       made his offering. <verse eID="Num.7.18"/>
      <verse sID="Num.7.19" osisID="Num.7.19"/> He presented for his offering a silver dish weigh­ing about five
       pounds, a silver bowl weighing nearly three pounds (on the sacred scale of weights), both of them full of fine
       flour mixed with oil as a cereal-­offering, <verse eID="Num.7.19"/>
      <verse sID="Num.7.20" osisID="Num.7.20"/> a golden saucer weigh-ing nearly five ounces, full of incense, <verse eID="Num.7.20"/>
      <verse sID="Num.7.21" osisID="Num.7.21"/> a young bullock, a ram, and a yearling male lamb as a burnt-offering, <verse eID="Num.7.21"/>
      <verse sID="Num.7.22" osisID="Num.7.22"/> a he-goat as a sin-offering, <verse eID="Num.7.22"/>
      <verse sID="Num.7.23" osisID="Num.7.23"/> and, by way of sacrifice for a recompense-offer-ing, two oxen, five
       rams, five he-goats, and five yearling male lambs. Such was what Nathaniel the son of Zuar offered.<verse eID="Num.7.23"/>
      <verse sID="Num.7.24" osisID="Num.7.24"/> On the third day Eliab the son of Helon, chieftain of Zebulun, made
       his offering. <verse eID="Num.7.24"/>
      <verse sID="Num.7.25" osisID="Num.7.25"/>He presented
       <milestone type="pb" n="157"/>
       for his offering a silver dish weighing about five pounds, a silver bowl weighing nearly three pounds (on the
        sacred scale of weights), both of them full of fine flour mixed with oil as a cereal-offering, <verse eID="Num.7.25"/>
      <verse sID="Num.7.26" osisID="Num.7.26"/> a golden saucer weighing nearly five ounces, full of incense, <verse eID="Num.7.26"/>
      <verse sID="Num.7.27" osisID="Num.7.27"/> a young bullock, a ram, and a yearling male lamb as a burnt-offering, <verse eID="Num.7.27"/>
      <verse sID="Num.7.28" osisID="Num.7.28"/> a he-goat as a sin-offering, <verse eID="Num.7.28"/>
      <verse sID="Num.7.29" osisID="Num.7.29"/> and, by way of sacrifice for a recom­pense-offering, two oxen, five
       rams, five he-goats, and five yearling male lambs. Such was what Eliab the son of Helon offered. <verse eID="Num.7.29"/>
      <verse sID="Num.7.30" osisID="Num.7.30"/> On the fourth day Elizur the son of Shedeur, chief­tain of Reuben,
       made his offering. <verse eID="Num.7.30"/>
      <verse sID="Num.7.31" osisID="Num.7.31"/> He presented for his offering a silver dish weighing about five
       pounds, a silver bowl weighing nearly three pounds (on the sacred scale of weights), both of them full of fine
       flour mixed with oil as a cereal-offering, <verse eID="Num.7.31"/>
      <verse sID="Num.7.32" osisID="Num.7.32"/> a golden saucer weighing nearly five ounces, full of incense, <verse eID="Num.7.32"/>
      <verse sID="Num.7.33" osisID="Num.7.33"/> a young bullock, a ram, and a yearling male lamb as a burnt-offering, <verse eID="Num.7.33"/>
      <verse sID="Num.7.34" osisID="Num.7.34"/> a he-goat as a sin-offering, <verse eID="Num.7.34"/>
      <verse sID="Num.7.35" osisID="Num.7.35"/> and, by way of sac­rifice for a recompense-offering, two oxen, five
       rams, five he-goats, and five yearling male lambs. Such was what Elizur the son of Shedeur offered. <verse eID="Num.7.35"/>
      <verse sID="Num.7.36" osisID="Num.7.36"/>On the fifth day Shelumiel the son of Zurishaddai, chieftain of Simeon,
       made his offering. <verse eID="Num.7.36"/>
      <verse sID="Num.7.37" osisID="Num.7.37"/> He presented for his offering a silver dish weighing about five
       pounds, a silver bowl weighing nearly three pounds (on the sacred scale of weights), both of them full of fine
       flour mixed with oil as a cereal-offering, <verse eID="Num.7.37"/>
      <verse sID="Num.7.38" osisID="Num.7.38"/> a golden saucer weighing nearly five ounces, full of incense, <verse eID="Num.7.38"/>
      <verse sID="Num.7.39" osisID="Num.7.39"/> a young bullock, a ram, and a yearling male lamb as a burnt-offering, <verse eID="Num.7.39"/>
      <verse sID="Num.7.40" osisID="Num.7.40"/> a he-goat, as a sin-offering, <verse eID="Num.7.40"/>
      <verse sID="Num.7.41" osisID="Num.7.41"/> and, by way of sacrifice for a recompense-offering, two oxen, five
       rams, five he-goats, and five yearling male lambs. Such was what Shelumiel the son of Zurishaddai offered. <verse eID="Num.7.41"/>
      <verse sID="Num.7.42" osisID="Num.7.42"/> On the sixth day Eliasaph the son of Reuel, chieftain of Gad, made
       his offering. <verse eID="Num.7.42"/>
      <verse sID="Num.7.43" osisID="Num.7.43"/> He presented for his offering a silver dish weigh­ing about five
       pounds, a silver bowl weighing nearly three pounds (on the sacred scale of weights), both of them full of fine
       flour mixed with oil as a cereal-offering, <verse eID="Num.7.43"/>
      <verse sID="Num.7.44" osisID="Num.7.44"/> a golden saucer weighing nearly five ounces, full of incense, <verse eID="Num.7.44"/>
      <verse sID="Num.7.45" osisID="Num.7.45"/> a young bullock, a ram, and a yearling male lamb as a burnt-offering,
      <verse eID="Num.7.45"/>
      <verse sID="Num.7.46" osisID="Num.7.46"/> a he-goat as a sin-offering, <verse eID="Num.7.46"/>
      <verse sID="Num.7.47" osisID="Num.7.47"/> and, by way of sacrifice for a recompense-offer­ing, two oxen, five
       rams, five he-goats, and five yearling male lambs. Such was what Eliasaph the son of Reuel offered.<verse eID="Num.7.47"/>
      <verse sID="Num.7.48" osisID="Num.7.48"/> On the seventh day Elishama the son of Ammihud, chieftain of Ephraim,
       made his offering. <verse eID="Num.7.48"/>
      <verse sID="Num.7.49" osisID="Num.7.49"/> He presented for his offering a silver dish weighing about five
       pounds, a silver bowl weighing nearly three pounds (on the sacred scale of weights), both full of fine flour
       mixed with oil as a cereal-offering, <verse eID="Num.7.49"/>
      <verse sID="Num.7.50" osisID="Num.7.50"/> a golden saucer weighing nearly five ounces, full of incense, <verse eID="Num.7.50"/>
      <verse sID="Num.7.51" osisID="Num.7.51"/> a young bullock, a ram, and a yearling male lamb as a burnt-offering, <verse eID="Num.7.51"/>
      <verse sID="Num.7.52" osisID="Num.7.52"/> a he-goat as a sin-offering, <verse eID="Num.7.52"/>
      <verse sID="Num.7.53" osisID="Num.7.53"/> and, by way of sacrifice for a recom­pense-offering, two oxen, five
       rams, five he-goats, and five yearling male lambs. Such was what Elishama the son of Am­mihud offered. <verse eID="Num.7.53"/>
      <verse sID="Num.7.54" osisID="Num.7.54"/> On the eighth day Gamaliel the son of Pedahzur, chieftain of Manasseh,
       <milestone type="pb" n="158"/>
       made his offering. <verse eID="Num.7.54"/>
      <verse sID="Num.7.55" osisID="Num.7.55"/> He presented for his offering a silver dish weighing about five
       pounds, a silver bowl weighing nearly three pounds (on the sacred scale of weights), both of them full of fine
       flour mixed with oil as a cereal-offering,
      <verse eID="Num.7.55"/>
      <verse sID="Num.7.56" osisID="Num.7.56"/> a golden saucer weighing nearly five ounces, full of incense, <verse eID="Num.7.56"/>
      <verse sID="Num.7.57" osisID="Num.7.57"/> a young bullock, a ram, and a yearling male lamb as a burnt-offering,
      <verse eID="Num.7.57"/>
      <verse sID="Num.7.58" osisID="Num.7.58"/> a he-goat as a sin-offering, <verse eID="Num.7.58"/>
      <verse sID="Num.7.59" osisID="Num.7.59"/> and, by way of sacrifice for a recom­pense-offering, two oxen, five
       rams, five he-goats, and five yearling male lambs. Such was what Gamaliel the son of Pedahzur offered. <verse eID="Num.7.59"/>
      <verse sID="Num.7.60" osisID="Num.7.60"/> On the ninth day Abidan the son of Gideoni, chieftain of Benjamin,
       made his offering. <verse eID="Num.7.60"/>
      <verse sID="Num.7.61" osisID="Num.7.61"/> He presented for his offering a silver dish weighing about five
       pounds, a silver bowl weighing nearly three pounds (on the sacred scale of weights), both of them full of fine
       flour mixed with oil as a cereal-offering, <verse eID="Num.7.61"/>
      <verse sID="Num.7.62" osisID="Num.7.62"/> a golden saucer weighing nearly five ounces, full of incense, <verse eID="Num.7.62"/>
      <verse sID="Num.7.63" osisID="Num.7.63"/> a young bullock, a ram, and a yearling male lamb as a burnt-offering,
      <verse eID="Num.7.63"/>
      <verse sID="Num.7.64" osisID="Num.7.64"/> a he-goat as a sin-offering, <verse eID="Num.7.64"/>
      <verse sID="Num.7.65" osisID="Num.7.65"/> and, by way of sacrifice for a recompense-offer­ing, two oxen, five
       rams, five he-goats, and five yearling male lambs. Such was what Abidan the son of Gideoni offered. <verse eID="Num.7.65"/>
      <verse sID="Num.7.66" osisID="Num.7.66"/> On the tenth day Ahiezer the son of Ammishaddai, chieftain of Dan,
       made his offering. <verse eID="Num.7.66"/>
      <verse sID="Num.7.67" osisID="Num.7.67"/> He presented for his offering a sil­ver dish weighing about five
       pounds, a silver bowl weighing nearly three pounds (on the sa­cred scale of weights), both of them full of fine
       flour mixed with oil as a cereal-offering, <verse eID="Num.7.67"/>
      <verse sID="Num.7.68" osisID="Num.7.68"/> a golden saucer weighing nearly five ounces, full of incense, <verse eID="Num.7.68"/>
      <verse sID="Num.7.69" osisID="Num.7.69"/> a young bullock, a ram, and a yearling male lamb as a burnt-offering, <verse eID="Num.7.69"/>
      <verse sID="Num.7.70" osisID="Num.7.70"/> a he-goat as a sin-offering, <verse eID="Num.7.70"/>
      <verse sID="Num.7.71" osisID="Num.7.71"/> and, by way of sacrifice for a recom­pense-offering, two oxen, five
       rams, five he-goats, and five yearling male lambs. Such was what Ahiezer the son of Ammi­shaddai offered. <verse eID="Num.7.71"/>
      <verse sID="Num.7.72" osisID="Num.7.72"/> On the eleventh day Pagiel the son of Ochran, chieftain of Asher, made
       his offering. <verse eID="Num.7.72"/>
      <verse sID="Num.7.73" osisID="Num.7.73"/> He presented for his offering a silver dish weigh­ing about five
       pounds, a silver bowl weighing nearly three pounds (on the sacred scale of weights), both of them full of fine
       flour mixed with oil as a cereal-­offering, <verse eID="Num.7.73"/>
      <verse sID="Num.7.74" osisID="Num.7.74"/> a golden saucer weighing nearly five ounces, full of in­cense, <verse eID="Num.7.74"/>
      <verse sID="Num.7.75" osisID="Num.7.75"/> a young bullock, a ram, and a yearling male lamb as a burnt-offering,
      <verse eID="Num.7.75"/>
      <verse sID="Num.7.76" osisID="Num.7.76"/> a he-goat as a sin-offering, <verse eID="Num.7.76"/>
      <verse sID="Num.7.77" osisID="Num.7.77"/> and, by way of sacrifice for a recompense-offer­ing, two oxen, five
       rams, five he-goats, and five yearling male lambs. Such was what Pagiel the son of Ochran offered. <verse eID="Num.7.77"/>
      <verse sID="Num.7.78" osisID="Num.7.78"/> On the twelfth day Ahira the son of Enan, chieftain of Naphtali, made
       his offering. <verse eID="Num.7.78"/>
      <verse sID="Num.7.79" osisID="Num.7.79"/> He presented for his offering a silver dish weighing about five
       pounds, a silver bowl weighing nearly three pounds (on the sacred scale of weights), both of them full of fine
       flour mixed with oil as a cereal-offering, <verse eID="Num.7.79"/>
      <verse sID="Num.7.80" osisID="Num.7.80"/> a golden saucer weighing nearly five ounces, full of incense, <verse eID="Num.7.80"/>
      <verse sID="Num.7.81" osisID="Num.7.81"/> a young bullock, a ram, and a yearling male lamb as a burnt-offering,
      <verse eID="Num.7.81"/>
      <verse sID="Num.7.82" osisID="Num.7.82"/> a he-goat as a sin-offering, <verse eID="Num.7.82"/>
      <verse sID="Num.7.83" osisID="Num.7.83"/> and, by way of sacrifice for a recompense-offering, two oxen, five
       rams, five he-goats, and five yearling male lambs. Such was what Ahira the son of Enan offered.
      <verse eID="Num.7.83"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Num.7.84" osisID="Num.7.84"/> Such were the gifts presented by the chieftains of Israel at the
       <milestone type="pb" n="159"/>
       dedication of the altar, on the day it was anointed; twelve sil­ver dishes, twelve silver bowls, and twelve
       golden saucers, <verse eID="Num.7.84"/>
      <verse sID="Num.7.85" osisID="Num.7.85"/> each dish weighing about five pounds, each bowl nearly three pounds,
       the total weight of silver (on the sacred scale) being close upon a hundred pounds, <verse eID="Num.7.85"/>
      <verse sID="Num.7.86" osisID="Num.7.86"/> and the weight of gold in the twelve saucers full of incense being
       about five pounds: <verse eID="Num.7.86"/>
      <verse sID="Num.7.87" osisID="Num.7.87"/> the animals for the burnt-offering amounted to twelve bullocks,
       twelve rams, twelve yearling male lambs with the ordinary cereal-offerings, and twelve he-goats for a
       sin-offering, <verse eID="Num.7.87"/>
      <verse sID="Num.7.88" osisID="Num.7.88"/> the total number of animals for the recompense-offering be­ing
       twenty-four bullocks, sixty rams, sixty he-goats, and sixty yearling male lambs. Such were the gifts presented
       at the dedica­tion of the altar, on the day it was anointed. <verse eID="Num.7.88"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Num.7.89" osisID="Num.7.89"/>... And when Moses en­tered the Trysting tent to talk with Him, he heard
       the Voice speaking to him from above the cover on the ark of the Presence, between the two kherubs; and the
       Eternal said to him . . . <verse eID="Num.7.89"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eId="Num.7"/>
    <chapter osisId="Num.8" sId="Num.8"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Num.8.1" osisID="Num.8.1"/>The Eternal gave Moses this order <verse eID="Num.8.1"/>
      <verse sID="Num.8.2" osisID="Num.8.2"/> for Aaron, that when he hung up the lamps, the seven lamps were to
       light up the wall opposite the lampstand. <verse eID="Num.8.2"/>
      <verse sID="Num.8.3" osisID="Num.8.3"/> Aaron saw to this: he hung up the lamps in front of the lampstand, as
       the Eternal had told Moses. <verse eID="Num.8.3"/>
      <verse sID="Num.8.4" osisID="Num.8.4"/> (The lampstand was wrought in beaten gold, from base to branches--beaten
       gold entirely; Moses made the lampstand after the pattern which the Eternal had shown him.)
      <verse eID="Num.8.4"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Num.8.5" osisID="Num.8.5"/>The Eternal said to Moses, <verse eID="Num.8.5"/>
      <verse sID="Num.8.6" osisID="Num.8.6"/> <q>Set aside the Levites in Israel and cleanse them; <verse eID="Num.8.6"/>
      <verse sID="Num.8.7" osisID="Num.8.7"/> cleanse them thus. Sprinkle them with water, to purify them; have all
       their bodies shaved, and make them wash their clothes and be clean. <verse eID="Num.8.7"/>
      <verse sID="Num.8.8" osisID="Num.8.8"/> Then let them take a young bullock and the usual cereal-­offering, some
       fine flour mixed with oil, while you take another young bullock as a sin-offering; <verse eID="Num.8.8"/>
      <verse sID="Num.8.9" osisID="Num.8.9"/> bring the Levites in front of the Trysting tent, where you must
       convene the whole community of Israel, <verse eID="Num.8.9"/>
      <verse sID="Num.8.10" osisID="Num.8.10"/> presenting the Levites before the Eternal; whereupon the Israelites
       shall lay their hands upon the Levites, <verse eID="Num.8.10"/>
      <verse sID="Num.8.11" osisID="Num.8.11"/> and Aaron shall formally make them over to the Eternal as Israelites
       who are to do the Eternal’s work. <verse eID="Num.8.11"/>
      <verse sID="Num.8.12" osisID="Num.8.12"/> The Levites shall lay their hands on the bullocks, and you must
       sacrifice them to the Eternal as expiation for the Le­vites, one as a sin-offering, the other as a
       burnt-offering. <verse eID="Num.8.12"/>
      <verse sID="Num.8.13" osisID="Num.8.13"/> You shall place the Levites before Aaron and his sons, making them
       over formally to the Eter­nal, <verse eID="Num.8.13"/>
      <verse sID="Num.8.14" osisID="Num.8.14"/> and singling out the Levites from Israel to belong to me.</q><verse eID="Num.8.14"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Num.8.15" osisID="Num.8.15"/><q>Then the Levites can enter upon their duties in the Trysting tent,
       cleansed and made over to me, as Israelites who belong to me. <verse eID="Num.8.15"/>
      <verse sID="Num.8.16" osisID="Num.8.16"/> I have taken them instead of all the first-born, the eld­est children
       of the Israelites--<verse eID="Num.8.16"/>
      <verse sID="Num.8.17" osisID="Num.8.17"/> for all the eldest children of the Israelites, the first-born of men
       as well as of cattle, belong to me; when I killed the eldest born in the land of Egypt, I conse­crated them to
       me. <verse eID="Num.8.17"/>
      <verse sID="Num.8.18" osisID="Num.8.18"/> And now I take the Levites instead of them, <verse eID="Num.8.18"/>
      <verse sID="Num.8.19" osisID="Num.8.19"/> assigning the Levites to Aaron and his sons as Israelites who shall
       perform Israel’s service in the Trysting tent and avert any plague of my anger from break­ing out upon the
       Israelites in
       <milestone type="pb" n="160"/>
       their approach to the sacred place.</q>
      <verse eID="Num.8.19"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Num.8.20" osisID="Num.8.20"/>So Moses and Aaron and all the community of Israel did exactly as the
       Eternal had or­dered them to do to the Levites; <verse eID="Num.8.20"/>
      <verse sID="Num.8.21" osisID="Num.8.21"/> the Levites purged themselves from sin and washed their clothes,
       Aaron formally made them over to the Eternal, sacrificing on behalf of their cleansing, <verse eID="Num.8.21"/>
      <verse sID="Num.8.22" osisID="Num.8.22"/> and then the Levites entered upon their duties in the Trysting tent
       in presence of Aaron and his sons. The Is­raelites did with them exactly as the Eternal had ordered Moses. <verse eID="Num.8.22"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Num.8.23" osisID="Num.8.23"/>The Eternal also said to Moses, <verse eID="Num.8.23"/>
      <verse sID="Num.8.24" osisID="Num.8.24"/> <q>The rule for the Le­vites is, that after twenty-five they must
       enter on their attendance in the Trysting tent, <verse eID="Num.8.24"/>
      <verse sID="Num.8.25" osisID="Num.8.25"/> but after fifty everyone must with­draw from active service and give
       up his position; <verse eID="Num.8.25"/>
      <verse sID="Num.8.26" osisID="Num.8.26"/> he may help his fellows to look after things within the Trysting tent,
       but he is not to have any work of his own. This is how you must arrange the Levites' du­ties.</q> <verse eID="Num.8.26"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eId="Num.8"/>
    <chapter osisId="Num.9" sId="Num.9"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Num.9.1" osisID="Num.9.1"/>In the first month of the sec­ond year after leaving Egypt, the Eternal
       said to Moses in the desert of Sinai, <verse eID="Num.9.1"/>
      <verse sID="Num.9.2" osisID="Num.9.2"/> <q>The Israelites must keep the passover at its proper time; <verse eID="Num.9.2"/>
      <verse sID="Num.9.3" osisID="Num.9.3"/> you must keep it at the proper time, on the four­teenth day of the month,
       to­wards evening, and keep it ac­cording to the due rules and all the ritual.</q> <verse eID="Num.9.3"/>
      <verse sID="Num.9.4" osisID="Num.9.4"/> So Moses told the Israelites that they were to keep the passover, <verse eID="Num.9.4"/>
      <verse sID="Num.9.5" osisID="Num.9.5"/> and they kept the passover on the fourteenth day of the first month,
       towards evening, in the desert of Sinai; the Israelites did exactly as the Eternal had ordered Moses. <verse eID="Num.9.5"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Num.9.6" osisID="Num.9.6"/>Some, however, could not keep the passover on that day, as they had been
       defiled by con­tact with a corpse. So they came to Moses [[and Aaron]] that day saying, <verse eID="Num.9.6"/>
      <verse sID="Num.9.7" osisID="Num.9.7"/> <q>We are defiled by contact with a corpse; but why should we be
       prevented from offering sacrifice to the Eternal at the proper time in Israel?</q> <verse eID="Num.9.7"/>
      <verse sID="Num.9.8" osisID="Num.9.8"/> Moses answered, <q>Wait till I hear what the Eter­nal has to say about
       you.</q> <verse eID="Num.9.8"/>
      <verse sID="Num.9.9" osisID="Num.9.9"/> And the Eternal gave Moses <verse eID="Num.9.9"/>
      <verse sID="Num.9.10" osisID="Num.9.10"/> this injunction for the Israelites. <q>If any one of you or of your
       descendants is either defiled by contact with a corpse or absent on a journey, he can still keep a passover in
       honour of the Eternal. <verse eID="Num.9.10"/>
      <verse sID="Num.9.11" osisID="Num.9.11"/> Such persons shall keep it on the fourteenth day of the second month,
       towards evening, using unleavened bread and bitter herbs, <verse eID="Num.9.11"/>
      <verse sID="Num.9.12" osisID="Num.9.12"/> leaving not a morsel of it over till next morn­ing, and breaking not
       one bone of the lamb; they must follow all the rules of the passover. <verse eID="Num.9.12"/>
      <verse sID="Num.9.13" osisID="Num.9.13"/> But if any man, who is neither un­clean nor absent on a journey, fails
       to keep the passover, that person shall be outlawed from his kinsfolk, because he has not offered to the
       Eternal at the proper time: that man must take the consequences of his sin. <verse eID="Num.9.13"/>
      <verse sID="Num.9.14" osisID="Num.9.14"/> If an alien settles among you and keeps the passover in honour of the
       Eternal, he must follow the rule and ritual of the passover; you must have only one rule for the alien and for
       the native.</q> <verse eID="Num.9.14"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Num.9.15" osisID="Num.9.15"/> Now on the day when the Dwelling was erected, the cloud covered the
       Dwelling, that is, the tent of the Presence, while in the evening something like shin­ing fire hung over the
       Dwelling until the morning. <verse eID="Num.9.15"/>
      <verse sID="Num.9.16" osisID="Num.9.16"/> It was always so; the cloud used to cover it by day and the shining
       fire by
       <milestone type="pb" n="161"/>
       night.
      <verse eID="Num.9.16"/>
      <verse sID="Num.9.17" osisID="Num.9.17"/> Whenever the cloud rose above the Dwelling, then the Israelites moved
       forward, and when the cloud stopped the Israelites encamped; <verse eID="Num.9.17"/>
      <verse sID="Num.9.18" osisID="Num.9.18"/> at the bid­ding of the Eternal the Israelites moved forward, and at the
       bid­ding of the Eternal they encamped.  Any day that the cloud remained over the Dwell­ing, they remained in
       camp;<verse eID="Num.9.18"/>
      <verse sID="Num.9.19" osisID="Num.9.19"/> even when the cloud stayed over the Dwelling for a number of days, the
       Israelites obeyed the behest of the Eternal and did not move forward. <verse eID="Num.9.19"/>
      <verse sID="Num.9.20" osisID="Num.9.20"/> Sometimes the cloud remained over the Dwelling only for a few days;
       then, as the Eternal ordered, they remained in camp; <verse eID="Num.9.20"/>
      <verse sID="Num.9.21" osisID="Num.9.21"/> some­times the cloud was there from evening to morning and rose in the
       morning, so that they moved forward; <verse eID="Num.9.21"/>
      <verse sID="Num.9.22" osisID="Num.9.22"/> sometimes the cloud would remain for a day and a night, sometimes for
       two days or for a month or longer. <verse eID="Num.9.22"/>
      <verse sID="Num.9.23" osisID="Num.9.23"/>But the Israelites always en­camped at the bidding of the Eternal and
       moved forward at the bidding of the Eternal; they obeyed the behest of the Eter­nal, as he conveyed it through
       Moses. <verse eID="Num.9.23"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eId="Num.9"/>
    <chapter osisId="Num.10" sId="Num.10"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Num.10.1-Num.10.2" osisID="Num.10.1 Num.10.2"/><q>Make two silver bugles,</q> said the Eternal to
       Moses, <q>make them of beaten silver, and use them to summon the community and to start the march. <verse eID="Num.10.1-Num.10.2"/>
      <verse sID="Num.10.3" osisID="Num.10.3"/> When both are sounded, all the community shall gather round you at
       the entrance of the Trysting tent; <verse eID="Num.10.3"/>
      <verse sID="Num.10.4" osisID="Num.10.4"/> when only one is sounded, the chieftains at the head of the septs of
       Israel shall gather round you. <verse eID="Num.10.4"/>
      <verse sID="Num.10.5" osisID="Num.10.5"/> When a full blast is blown, those encamped on the eastern side shall
       move on; <verse eID="Num.10.5"/>
      <verse sID="Num.10.6" osisID="Num.10.6"/>at a second blast, those en­camped on the south side shall move on; and
       so with the others, a blast is to be blown whenever they are to move on. <verse eID="Num.10.6"/>
      <verse sID="Num.10.7" osisID="Num.10.7"/> But when you convoke the assembly you must sound the bugles without
       blowing a blast. <verse eID="Num.10.7"/>
      <verse sID="Num.10.8" osisID="Num.10.8"/> (The sons of Aaron, the priests, shall sound the bugles, and the use
       of them shall hold good for ever among you, generation after genera­tion.) <verse eID="Num.10.8"/>
      <verse sID="Num.10.9" osisID="Num.10.9"/> When you engage in war against any invader of your country, you must
       blow a blast on the bugles, to remind the Eternal your God of your plight, and so be saved from the foe. <verse eID="Num.10.9"/>
      <verse sID="Num.10.10" osisID="Num.10.10"/> Also at your festivals, on your days of celebration, and on the
       first day of the month, you must sound the bugles over what you sacrifice as burnt-offerings and
       recompense-offerings; that will serve as a reminder of you for your God: I am the Eternal your God.</q> <verse eID="Num.10.10"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Num.10.11" osisID="Num.10.11"/> On the twentieth day of the second month of the second year, the
       cloud rose from above the Dwelling of the Presence, <verse eID="Num.10.11"/>
      <verse sID="Num.10.12" osisID="Num.10.12"/> and the Israelites set out from the desert of Sinai, marching stage
       by stage, till the cloud set­tled down in the desert of Paran. <verse eID="Num.10.12"/>
      <verse sID="Num.10.13" osisID="Num.10.13"/> This was the first time they started a march at the bidding of the
       Eternal through Moses. <verse eID="Num.10.13"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Num.10.14" osisID="Num.10.14"/> The company of the Judahites marched in front, division after
       division, headed by Nahshon the son of Amminadab; <verse eID="Num.10.14"/>
      <verse sID="Num.10.15" osisID="Num.10.15"/> the battalions of the clan of Issachar were led by Nathaniel the
       son of Zuar, <verse eID="Num.10.15"/>
      <verse sID="Num.10.16" osisID="Num.10.16"/> and the battalions of the clan of Zebulun by Eliab the son of
       Helon. <verse eID="Num.10.16"/>
      <verse sID="Num.10.17" osisID="Num.10.17"/> Then, after the Dwelling had been taken down, the Gershonites and
       the Merarites moved forward, carrying the tent. <verse eID="Num.10.17"/>
      <verse sID="Num.10.18" osisID="Num.10.18"/> The company of the Reubenites followed, division after division,
       led by Elizur the son of Shedeur; <verse eID="Num.10.18"/>
      <verse sID="Num.10.19" osisID="Num.10.19"/> the battalions of
       <milestone type="pb" n="162"/>
       the clan of Simeon were headed by Shelumiel the son of Zurishaddai, <verse eID="Num.10.19"/>
      <verse sID="Num.10.20" osisID="Num.10.20"/> and the battalions of the clan of Gad by Eliasaph the son of Reuel. <verse eID="Num.10.20"/>
      <verse sID="Num.10.21" osisID="Num.10.21"/> Then came the Kohathites, carrying the sacred objects (the other
       Levites used to erect the Dwelling for them). <verse eID="Num.10.21"/>
      <verse sID="Num.10.22" osisID="Num.10.22"/> The company of the Ephraimites came next, division after division,
       headed by Elishama the son of Ammihud; <verse eID="Num.10.22"/>
      <verse sID="Num.10.23" osisID="Num.10.23"/> the bat­talions of the clan of Manasseh were led by Gamaliel the
       son of Pedahzur, <verse eID="Num.10.23"/>
      <verse sID="Num.10.24" osisID="Num.10.24"/> and the battalions of the clan of Benjamin by Abidan the son of
       Gideoni. <verse eID="Num.10.24"/>
      <verse sID="Num.10.25" osisID="Num.10.25"/> The rear was brought up by the company of the Danites, marching in
       their divisions, and led by Ahiezer the son of Ammishaddai; <verse eID="Num.10.25"/>
      <verse sID="Num.10.26" osisID="Num.10.26"/> the battal­ions of the clan of Asher were led by Pagiel the son of
       Ochran, <verse eID="Num.10.26"/>
      <verse sID="Num.10.27" osisID="Num.10.27"/> and the battalions of the clan of Naphtali by Ahira the son of
       Enan. <verse eID="Num.10.27"/>
      <verse sID="Num.10.28" osisID="Num.10.28"/> Such was the order of march for the divisions of Israel. <verse eID="Num.10.28"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Num.10.29" osisID="Num.10.29"/> Moses said to his father-in-law Hobab, the son of Reuel the
       Midianite, <q>We are starting for the country which the Eternal has promised to give us; come along with us to
       share in our prosperity, for the Eternal has promised to prosper Israel.</q> <verse eID="Num.10.29"/>
      <verse sID="Num.10.30" osisID="Num.10.30"/> <q>I will not go,</q> he answered, <q> will depart to my native
       country and my kinsfolk.</q> <verse eID="Num.10.30"/>
      <verse sID="Num.10.31" osisID="Num.10.31"/> But Moses said, <q>Pray do not leave us, for you know where we can
       camp in the desert; come and be a pair of eyes for us, <verse eID="Num.10.31"/>
      <verse sID="Num.10.32" osisID="Num.10.32"/> and as the Eternal prospers us, so will we prosper you.</q> <verse eID="Num.10.32"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Num.10.33" osisID="Num.10.33"/>They marched from the moun­tain of the Eternal for three days, and
       the ark with the Eter­nal’s compact went in front of them all the time, to find out where they were to camp; <verse eID="Num.10.33"/>
      <verse sID="Num.10.34" osisID="Num.10.34"/> whenever they started from camp, the cloud of the Eternal was over
       them all day. <verse eID="Num.10.34"/>
     <hi type="italic">
      <verse sID="Num.10.35" osisID="Num.10.35"/> When the ark started, Moses would say,
       <lg>
        <l>Up, O Eternal,</l>
        <l>for the scattering of thy foes,</l>
        <l>for the routing of those who thee oppose!</l>
       </lg> <verse eID="Num.10.35"/>
      <verse sID="Num.10.36" osisID="Num.10.36"/> When it halted, he would say,
       <lg>
        <l> Come back, O Eternal, </l>
        <l> to the myriad clans of Israel! </l>
       </lg>
      <verse eID="Num.10.36"/>
      </hi>
     </p>
    <chapter eId="Num.10"/>
    <chapter osisId="Num.11" sId="Num.11"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Num.11.1" osisID="Num.11.1"/>[Now the people were like folk bewailing misfortune, in the hearing
       of the Eternal; and when the Eternal heard it, his anger blazed up, his fire burned among them, raging on the
       outskirts of the camp. <verse eID="Num.11.1"/>
      <verse sID="Num.11.2" osisID="Num.11.2"/> So the people cried to Moses, who prayed to the Eternal, and the
       fire abated. <verse eID="Num.11.2"/>
      <verse sID="Num.11.3" osisID="Num.11.3"/> Hence the spot was called Taberah (Burning), be­cause the fire of the
       Eternal had burned among them.] <verse eID="Num.11.3"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <hi type="italic">
       <verse sID="Num.11.4" osisID="Num.11.4"/> The riff-raff among them craved flesh as food, and the very
        Israelites wailed again, <q>O for flesh to eat! <verse eID="Num.11.4"/>
       <verse sID="Num.11.5" osisID="Num.11.5"/> We remember the fish we ate free in Egypt, and the cucumbers and
        melons and leeks and onions and garlic. <verse eID="Num.11.5"/>
       <verse sID="Num.11.6" osisID="Num.11.6"/> But now our appetite is starved; there is no food to be seen at
        all, nothing but this manna!</q> <verse eID="Num.11.6"/>
       <verse sID="Num.11.7" osisID="Num.11.7"/> (The manna was like grains of cori­ander seed, resembling pearls; <verse eID="Num.11.7"/>
       <verse sID="Num.11.8" osisID="Num.11.8"/> the people used to wander about and gather it, grinding it be­tween
        millstones or pounding it in a mortar, boiling it in a pot and making it into cakes; it tasted like a cake
        baked with oil. <verse eID="Num.11.8"/>
       <verse sID="Num.11.9" osisID="Num.11.9"/> When the dew fell on the camp by night, the manna fell along with
        it.) <verse eID="Num.11.9"/>
      </hi>
     </p>
     <p>
      <hi type="italic">
       <verse sID="Num.11.10" osisID="Num.11.10"/> Moses heard every family of the people weeping, every man at the
        door of his tent. <verse eID="Num.11.10"/>
      </hi>
      <verse sID="Num.11.11" osisID="Num.11.11"/> [Then 11 said Moses to the Eternal, <q>Why hast thou been so hard
       upon thy
       <milestone type="pb" n="163"/>
       servant? Why have I not found favour in thine eyes? Thou art leaving me to bear the burden of all this
       people! <verse eID="Num.11.11"/>
      <verse sID="Num.11.12" osisID="Num.11.12"/> Did I conceive them, did I give birth to them, that thou shouldest
       order me to carry them in my arms as a nurse carries an infant, to the land which thou hast sworn to their
       fathers to give them? <verse eID="Num.11.12"/>
      <verse sID="Num.11.14" osisID="Num.11.14"/> I cannot carry this people single-handed; the burden is too heavy
       for me.</q> <verse eID="Num.11.14"/>
      <verse sID="Num.11.16" osisID="Num.11.16"/> So the Eternal said to Moses, <q>Gather seventy of the sheikhs of
       Israel, men whom you know to be sheikhs of the people and authorities; bring them to the Trysting tent, to
       stand beside you; <verse eID="Num.11.16"/>
      <verse sID="Num.11.17" osisID="Num.11.17"/> I will come down and talk to you there, and I will endue them with
       part of your spirit; they shall share the bur­den of the people with you, in­stead of you bearing it by
       yourself.</q> <verse eID="Num.11.17"/>
      <verse sID="Num.11.24" osisID="Num.11.24"/> So he gathered seventy of the sheikhs of the people, and placed
       them round the tent. <verse eID="Num.11.24"/>
      <verse sID="Num.11.25" osisID="Num.11.25"/> The Eternal came down in the cloud and talked to him, endu­ing the
       seventy sheikhs with his spirit; as the spirit caught them, they suddenly prophesied--then stopped. <verse eID="Num.11.25"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Num.11.26" osisID="Num.11.26"/>Two men had remained within the camp, however, one called Eldad and
       the other Medad. The spirit caught them also, and they prophesied inside the camp--for although they had been
       registered among the seventy, they had not gone outside to the tent. <verse eID="Num.11.26"/>
      <verse sID="Num.11.27" osisID="Num.11.27"/> Whereupon a young man ran to tell Moses, <q>Eldad and Medad are
       prophesying inside the camp!</q> <verse eID="Num.11.27"/>
      <verse sID="Num.11.28" osisID="Num.11.28"/> And Joshua the son of Nun, who had served Moses ever since he was
       a youth, broke out, <q>My lord Moses, put a stop to them!</q> <verse eID="Num.11.28"/>
      <verse sID="Num.11.29" osisID="Num.11.29"/> But Moses answered, <q>Are you jealous on my account? Would that
       the people of the Eternal were all prophets! Would that the Eternal would endue them all with his spirit!</q>
      <verse eID="Num.11.29"/>
      <verse sID="Num.11.30" osisID="Num.11.30"/> Then Moses and the sheikhs of Israel re­turned to the camp.] <verse eID="Num.11.30"/>
      <hi type="italic">
       <verse sID="Num.11.13" osisID="Num.11.13"/> He resented it. <q>How can I get flesh to feed all this people?</q>
        he asked the Eternal; <q>they oppress me by weeping and crying for flesh to eat. <verse eID="Num.11.13"/>
       <verse sID="Num.11.15" osisID="Num.11.15"/> If this is to be thy treatment of me, pray kill me and be done
        with it--do me that favour! Leave me not to face my trouble.</q> <verse eID="Num.11.15"/>
       <verse sID="Num.11.10" osisID="Num.11.10"/> The Eternal’s anger blazed out in fury; <verse eID="Num.11.10"/>
       <verse sID="Num.11.18" osisID="Num.11.18"/> he bade Moses to tell the people, <q>Hallow yourselves in
        readiness for to-morrow, and you shall eat flesh. You have let the Eternal hear you weeping and crying, <q>
        O for flesh to eat! we were all right in Egypt!</q> So the Eternal will give you flesh to eat;<verse eID="Num.11.18"/>
       <verse sID="Num.11.19" osisID="Num.11.19"/> you shall eat flesh not one day or two days or five days or ten
        days or twenty days, <verse eID="Num.11.19"/>
       <verse sID="Num.11.20" osisID="Num.11.20"/> but a whole month, till you cannot bear the smell of it, till
        you loathe it--since you have spurned the Eternal who is in your midst, weeping before Him and wailing that
        you ever left Egypt!</q> <verse eID="Num.11.20"/>
       <verse sID="Num.11.21" osisID="Num.11.21"/> <q>What!</q> said Moses, <q>the people with me are six hundred
        thousand, as they stand, and thou art promising them flesh as food for a whole month? <verse eID="Num.11.21"/>
       <verse sID="Num.11.22" osisID="Num.11.22"/> Can flocks and herds enough be slaughtered for them? Can all the
        fish of the sea be gathered to satisfy them?</q> <verse eID="Num.11.22"/>
       <verse sID="Num.11.23" osisID="Num.11.23"/> The Eternal answered, <q>Is the Eter­nal’s power too small? You
        shall see now whether my promise comes true or not.</q> <verse eID="Num.11.23"/>
       <verse sID="Num.11.24" osisID="Num.11.24"/> So Moses went outside and told the people what the Eternal said.
       <verse eID="Num.11.24"/>
       <verse sID="Num.11.31" osisID="Num.11.31"/> And a wind blowing from the Eternal brought up quails from the
        sea, dropping them near the camp,
        <milestone type="pb" n="164"/>
        about a day’s journey on each side of it, all round the camp, about three feet above the ground. <verse eID="Num.11.31"/>
       <verse sID="Num.11.32" osisID="Num.11.32"/> All that day and night and all the next day the people were
        gathering quails; he who gathered least gathered over a hundred bushels weight of them. They were spread out
        to be cured, all round the camp. <verse eID="Num.11.32"/>
       <verse sID="Num.11.33" osisID="Num.11.33"/> But as the people were munching this food, before the supply
        gave out, the anger of the Eternal blazed out in fury against them, and he slaughtered them with a terrible
        plague. <verse eID="Num.11.33"/>
       <verse sID="Num.11.34" osisID="Num.11.34"/> Hence they called the spot Kibroth-hattaavah
        (graves-of-the-greedy), since they buried there the peo­ple who had been greedy for flesh.
       <verse eID="Num.11.34"/>
       <verse sID="Num.11.35" osisID="Num.11.35"/> From Kibroth-hattaavah the people marched to Hazeroth, where
        they settled. <verse eID="Num.11.35"/>
      </hi>
     </p>
    <chapter eId="Num.11"/>
    <chapter osisId="Num.12" sId="Num.12"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Num.12.1" osisID="Num.12.1"/>[Miriam and Aaron at­tacked Moses [[for having married an Ethiopian
       woman--his wife was an Ethiopian]], <verse eID="Num.12.1"/>
      <verse sID="Num.12.2" osisID="Num.12.2"/> asking, <q>Has the Eternal spoken to Moses alone? Has he not spoken
       to us as well?</q> The Eternal heard what they said. <verse eID="Num.12.2"/>
      <verse sID="Num.12.3" osisID="Num.12.3"/> (Now the man Moses was a most devout creature, the most pious of all
       men upon earth.) <verse eID="Num.12.3"/>
      <verse sID="Num.12.4" osisID="Num.12.4"/> Suddenly the Eternal told Moses, Aaron, and Miriam, these three, to
       come outside the camp to the Trysting tent. The three went out, <verse eID="Num.12.4"/>
      <verse sID="Num.12.5" osisID="Num.12.5"/> and the Eternal came down in a column of cloud and stood at the
       entrance of the tent, calling Aaron and Miriam to come forward. <verse eID="Num.12.5"/>
      <verse sID="Num.12.6" osisID="Num.12.6"/> <q>Hear what I say,</q> he told them; <q>to any prophet among you I
       make my­self known by visions, I talk to him in dreams. <verse eID="Num.12.6"/>
      <verse sID="Num.12.7" osisID="Num.12.7"/> Not so with my servant Moses, so faithful in all my household; <verse eID="Num.12.7"/>
      <verse sID="Num.12.8" osisID="Num.12.8"/> I speak to him directly, openly, with no dark sayings, and he sees
       the very form of the Eternal. Why, then, were you not afraid to attack my servant Moses?</q> <verse eID="Num.12.8"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Num.12.9" osisID="Num.12.9"/> And the Eternal’s anger blazed against them; he departed, and as
       soon as the cloud had with­drawn from the tent, there was Miriam leprous, as white as snow! <verse eID="Num.12.9"/>
      <verse sID="Num.12.10" osisID="Num.12.10"/> When Aaron looked at Miriam, there she was, all lep­rous! <verse eID="Num.12.10"/>
      <verse sID="Num.12.11" osisID="Num.12.11"/> <q>O my lord!</q> Aaron cried to Moses, <q>let us not bear the
       penalty of this wicked folly we have committed. <verse eID="Num.12.11"/>
      <verse sID="Num.12.12" osisID="Num.12.12"/> Let her not turn like a corpse, like one born with a body half
       wasted.</q> <verse eID="Num.12.12"/>
      <verse sID="Num.12.13" osisID="Num.12.13"/> So Moses called to the Eternal, <q>Nay, heal her, pray heal her!</q>
      <verse eID="Num.12.13"/>
      <verse sID="Num.12.14" osisID="Num.12.14"/> The Eternal answered, <q>If her father had done no more than spit
       in her face, would she not hide for seven days in shame? Let her be isolated for seven days out­side the camp;
       then she can come back.</q> <verse eID="Num.12.14"/>
      <verse sID="Num.12.15" osisID="Num.12.15"/> So for seven days Miriam was isolated out­side the camp, and the
       people did not march till Miriam was recalled. <verse eID="Num.12.15"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <hi type="italic">
       <verse sID="Num.12.16" osisID="Num.12.16"/> Then the people marched from Hazeroth and encamped in the desert
        of Paran. <verse eID="Num.12.16"/>
      </hi>
     </p>
    <chapter eId="Num.12"/>
    <chapter osisId="Num.13" sId="Num.13"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Num.13.1" osisID="Num.13.1"/>The Eternal told Moses <verse eID="Num.13.1"/>
      <verse sID="Num.13.2" osisID="Num.13.2"/> to send some men to spy out the country of Canaan which he was
       handing over to the Is­raelites; he was to send a man for every clan, all of them lead­ing men. <verse eID="Num.13.2"/>
      <verse sID="Num.13.3" osisID="Num.13.3"/> So Moses despatched them from the desert of Paran, as the Eternal
       ordered, all of them men in authority over Is­rael. <verse eID="Num.13.3"/>
      <verse sID="Num.13.4" osisID="Num.13.4"/> Their names were Shammua the son of Zakkur from the clan of Reuben,
      <verse eID="Num.13.4"/>
      <verse sID="Num.13.5" osisID="Num.13.5"/> Shaphat, the son of Hori from the clan of Simeon, <verse eID="Num.13.5"/>
      <verse sID="Num.13.6" osisID="Num.13.6"/> Caleb the son of Jephunneh from the clan of Judah, <verse eID="Num.13.6"/>
      <verse sID="Num.13.7" osisID="Num.13.7"/> Igal the son of Joseph from the clan
       <milestone type="pb" n="165"/>
       of Issachar, <verse eID="Num.13.7"/>
      <verse sID="Num.13.8" osisID="Num.13.8"/> Hoshea the son of Nun from the clan of Ephraim, <verse eID="Num.13.8"/>
      <verse sID="Num.13.9" osisID="Num.13.9"/> Palti the son of Raphu from the clan of Benjamin, <verse eID="Num.13.9"/>
      <verse sID="Num.13.10" osisID="Num.13.10"/> Gaddiel the son of Sodi from the clan of Zebulun, <verse eID="Num.13.10"/>
      <verse sID="Num.13.11" osisID="Num.13.11"/> Gaddi the son of Susi from the clan of Joseph (that is, from the
       clan of Manasseh), <verse eID="Num.13.11"/>
      <verse sID="Num.13.12" osisID="Num.13.12"/> Ammiel the son of Gemalli from the clan of Dan, <verse eID="Num.13.12"/>
      <verse sID="Num.13.13" osisID="Num.13.13"/> Sethur the son of Michael from the clan of Asher, <verse eID="Num.13.13"/>
      <verse sID="Num.13.14" osisID="Num.13.14"/> Nahbi the son of Vophsi from the clan of Naphtali, <verse eID="Num.13.14"/>
      <verse sID="Num.13.15" osisID="Num.13.15"/> and Geuel the son of Machi from the clan of Gad. <verse eID="Num.13.15"/>
      <verse sID="Num.13.16" osisID="Num.13.16"/> These are the names of the men whom Moses des­patched to spy out
       the land. (Hoshea the son of Nun was called Joshua by Moses.) <verse eID="Num.13.16"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Num.13.17" osisID="Num.13.17"/>Moses despatched them to spy out the land of Canaan, <verse eID="Num.13.17"/>
      <verse sID="Num.13.21" osisID="Num.13.21"/> and from the desert of Zin to Rehob, in the direction of Hamath, <verse eID="Num.13.21"/>
      <verse sID="Num.13.25" osisID="Num.13.25"/> they spied it out, re­turning at the end of forty days. <verse eID="Num.13.25"/>
      <verse sID="Num.13.26" osisID="Num.13.26"/> When they reached Moses, Aaron, and all the community of the
       Israelites in the desert of Paran, <verse eID="Num.13.26"/>
      <verse sID="Num.13.32" osisID="Num.13.32"/> they gave the Israelites a bad report of the land they had spied
       out. <q>The land over which we have gone as spies,</q> they said, <q>is a land that starves its inhabitants
       to death.</q> <verse eID="Num.13.32"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eId="Num.13"/>
    <chapter osisId="Num.14" sId="Num.14"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Num.14.1" osisID="Num.14.1"/>At this, all the community wailed aloud,
      <verse eID="Num.14.1"/>
      <verse sID="Num.14.2" osisID="Num.14.2"/> and the Israelites all grumbled against Moses and Aaron; the
       commu­nity all said to them, <q>Would that we had died in Egypt! Or would that we had died here in the
       desert!</q> <verse eID="Num.14.2"/>
      <verse sID="Num.14.5" osisID="Num.14.5"/> Then Moses and Aaron fell on their faces before all the assembled
       gathering of the Israelites, <verse eID="Num.14.5"/>
      <verse sID="Num.14.6" osisID="Num.14.6"/> while Joshua the son of Nun and Caleb the son of Jephunneh, who had
       been among the spies, tore their clothes <verse eID="Num.14.6"/>
      <verse sID="Num.14.7" osisID="Num.14.7"/> and told all the assembly of the Israelites, <q>The land over which
       we have gone as spies is a right fertile country.</q> <verse eID="Num.14.7"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Num.14.10" osisID="Num.14.10"/> The community were all on the point of stoning them, when the
       majesty of the Eternal appeared at the Trysting tent to all the Israelites, <verse eID="Num.14.10"/>
      <verse sID="Num.14.26" osisID="Num.14.26"/> and the Eternal said to Moses and Aaron, <verse eID="Num.14.26"/>
      <verse sID="Num.14.27" osisID="Num.14.27"/> <q>How long will this wicked community dare to grumble against
       me? <verse eID="Num.14.27"/>
      <verse sID="Num.14.28" osisID="Num.14.28"/> Tell them that as surely as I live--the Eternal has said it--I
       will do with you as I have heard you desire: <verse eID="Num.14.28"/>
      <verse sID="Num.14.29" osisID="Num.14.29"/> your corpses shall fall in this desert, and not one of your
       number, not one over twenty on your register, who has grumbled against me, <verse eID="Num.14.29"/>
      <verse sID="Num.14.30" osisID="Num.14.30"/> not one shall enter the land where I solemnly swore to settle
       you--none except Caleb the son of Jephunneh and Joshua the son of Nun. <verse eID="Num.14.30"/>
      <verse sID="Num.14.31" osisID="Num.14.31"/> [[Your children, who would be seized, you thought, I will bring
       in, to let them hold the land you despise.]] <verse eID="Num.14.31"/>
      <verse sID="Num.14.32" osisID="Num.14.32"/> But as for the rest of you, your corpses shall fall in this
       desert, <verse eID="Num.14.32"/>
      <verse sID="Num.14.33" osisID="Num.14.33"/> and your children must be wandering shepherds in the desert for
       forty years, paying the penalty of your un­faithfulness, till the last of your corpses falls in the desert. <verse eID="Num.14.33"/>
      <verse sID="Num.14.34" osisID="Num.14.34"/> For every day spent in spying out the land, you shall spend a
       year being punished for your evil-doing, forty years for forty days; that will teach you what it is to have
       me against you. <verse eID="Num.14.34"/>
      <verse sID="Num.14.35" osisID="Num.14.35"/> I the Eternal have said it; this is what I will certainly do to
       all this wicked community who have conspired against me: in this desert to the last man they shall fall and
       die.</q>
      <verse eID="Num.14.35"/>
      <verse sID="Num.14.36" osisID="Num.14.36"/> The men despatched by Moses to spy out the land, who on their
       return made all the assembly
       <milestone type="pb" n="166"/>
       grumble against him by giving a bad report of the land, <verse eID="Num.14.36"/>
      <verse sID="Num.14.37" osisID="Num.14.37"/> these men died by a stroke before the Eternal; <verse eID="Num.14.37"/>
      <verse sID="Num.14.38" osisID="Num.14.38"/> but Joshua the son of Nun and Caleb the son of Jephunneh remained
       alive, out of the men who had gone to spy out the land. <verse eID="Num.14.38"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eId="Num.14"/>
    <chapter osisId="Num.13" sId="Num.13"/>
     <hi type="italic">
      <p>
       <verse sID="Num.13.17" osisID="Num.13.17"/>... And he told them to <q>Go up, then, into the Negeb, enter the
        highlands, <verse eID="Num.13.17"/>
       <verse sID="Num.13.18" osisID="Num.13.18"/> and see what the land is like, and whether the natives are
        strong or weak, few or many; <verse eID="Num.13.18"/>
       <verse sID="Num.13.19" osisID="Num.13.19"/> see whether the country is good or bad, and whether the
        inhabitants live in camps or in strongholds; <verse eID="Num.13.19"/>
       <verse sID="Num.13.20" osisID="Num.13.20"/> see whether the land is rich or poor, and whether it is wooded
        or not. Also do your best to bring back some fruit of the country.</q> <verse eID="Num.13.20"/>
      </p>
      <p>
       <verse sID="Num.13.22" osisID="Num.13.22"/>So they went up into the Ne­geb and reached Hebron (Hebron was
        built seven years before Zoan in Egypt), where the giant clans of Ahiman, Sheshai, and Talmai lived. <verse eID="Num.13.22"/>
       <verse sID="Num.13.23" osisID="Num.13.23"/> It was the season for early grapes, and when they came to the
        wady of Eshcol, they cut a branch with a single cluster of grapes, which two of them carried back on a
        stretcher, along with some pomegranates and figs. <verse eID="Num.13.23"/>
       <verse sID="Num.13.24" osisID="Num.13.24"/> The spot came to be called Eshcol (Cluster) from the cluster
        which the Israelites took there. <verse eID="Num.13.24"/>
       <verse sID="Num.13.26" osisID="Num.13.26"/> Then they brought back word to all the community of Israel at
        Kadesh, showing them the fruit of the country. <verse eID="Num.13.26"/>
       <verse sID="Num.13.27" osisID="Num.13.27"/> They reported: <q>We reached the land to which you sent us; it
        does abound in milk and honey; and here are its fruits. <verse eID="Num.13.27"/>
       <verse sID="Num.13.28" osisID="Num.13.28"/> Still, the natives are strong, the cities are fortified and
        powerful, and we saw giant clans there; <verse eID="Num.13.28"/>
       <verse sID="Num.13.29" osisID="Num.13.29"/> Amalekites lives in the Negeb, the high­lands are held by
        Hittites, Jebusites, and Amorites, and Canaanites dwell on the coast and by the banks of the Jordan. <verse eID="Num.13.29"/>
       <verse sID="Num.13.32" osisID="Num.13.32"/> All the people we saw there were men of huge size. <verse eID="Num.13.32"/>
       <verse sID="Num.13.33" osisID="Num.13.33"/> We saw the Nephtlim there (the giant clans belong to the
        Nephilim); they made us feel like grasshoppers, and grass­hoppers we were to them.</q> <verse eID="Num.13.33"/>
      </p>
     </hi>
    <chapter eId="Num.13"/>
    <chapter osisId="Num.14" sId="Num.14"/>
     <hi type="italic">
      <p>
       <verse sID="Num.14.1" osisID="Num.14.1"/>That night the people wept, <verse eID="Num.14.1"/>
       <verse sID="Num.14.3" osisID="Num.14.3"/> <q>Why is the Eternal taking us to this land, only to fall by the
        sword? Our wives and children will be seized. Should we not rather return to Egypt? <verse eID="Num.14.3"/>
       <verse sID="Num.14.4" osisID="Num.14.4"/>Better appoint some captain and return to Egypt!</q><verse eID="Num.14.4"/>
    <chapter eId="Num.14"/>
    <chapter osisId="Num.13" sId="Num.13"/>
       <verse sID="Num.13.30" osisID="Num.13.30"/>Caleb silenced this clamour of the people in presence of Moses,
        by saying, <q>We ought to march up at once and seize the land; for we are well able to master it.</q> <verse eID="Num.13.30"/>
       <verse sID="Num.13.31" osisID="Num.13.31"/> But the men who had accompanied him said, <q>We are not able to
        march against the natives; they are too strong for us.</q> <verse eID="Num.13.31"/>
    <chapter osisId="Num.14" sId="Num.14"/>
       <verse sID="Num.14.8" osisID="Num.14.8"/>Caleb answered, <q>If the Eternal be pleased with us, he will bring
        us to this land and give it to us, a land abounding in milk and honey. <verse eID="Num.14.8"/>
       <verse sID="Num.14.9" osisID="Num.14.9"/> Only, rebel not against the Eternal. And have no fear of the
        natives--we shall eat them up; their protection has failed, and the Eternal is with us; fear them not.</q>
       <verse eID="Num.14.9"/>
      </p>
      <p>
       <verse sID="Num.14.11" osisID="Num.14.11"/>Then said the Eternal to n Moses, <q>How long is this people to
        despise me? How long are they to distrust me, in spite of all the proofs I have shown them? <verse eID="Num.14.11"/>
       <verse sID="Num.14.12" osisID="Num.14.12"/> I will smite them with pestilence and destroy them, and out of
        you I will make a nation greater and mightier than they.</q> <verse eID="Num.14.12"/>
       <verse sID="Num.14.13" osisID="Num.14.13"/> <q>But,</q> said Moses to the Eternal, <q>the Egyptians will
        hear of it <verse eID="Num.14.13"/>
       <verse sID="Num.14.14" osisID="Num.14.14"/> and tell the natives of the land that thou didst bring this
        people out of Egypt by thy might. They have heard that thou the
        <milestone type="pb" n="167"/>
        Eternal art among this people, for thou the Eternal art seen clearly by them; thy cloud, stands over them,
        and thou goest before them in a column of cloud by day and in a column of fire by night. <verse eID="Num.14.14"/>
       <verse sID="Num.14.15" osisID="Num.14.15"/> Now, if thou killest off this people to a man, then the nations
        who have heard of thee will say that the Eternal destroyed this people in the desert <verse eID="Num.14.15"/>
       <verse sID="Num.14.16" osisID="Num.14.16"/> because he could not bring them to the land that he had sworn to
        give them. <verse eID="Num.14.16"/>
       <verse sID="Num.14.17" osisID="Num.14.17"/> Ah, let the power of my Lord be displayed in carrying out thy
        prom­ise <verse eID="Num.14.17"/>
       <verse sID="Num.14.18" osisID="Num.14.18"/> that the Eternal is slow to be angry, rich in love, forgiving
        iniquity and transgression, but one who will never acquit the guilty, one who avenges the sins of fathers
        on their children, down to the third and the fourth generation. <verse eID="Num.14.18"/>
       <verse sID="Num.14.19" osisID="Num.14.19"/> Pray pardon the sin of thy people, as thy love is rich, and as
        thou hast forgiven this people ever since they left Egypt.</q> <verse eID="Num.14.19"/>
       <verse sID="Num.14.20" osisID="Num.14.20"/> The Eternal an­swered, <q>I pardon them as you have asked; <verse eID="Num.14.20"/>
       <verse sID="Num.14.21" osisID="Num.14.21"/> but as surely as I live, and as surely as the whole earth shall
        one day be full of the glory of the Eternal, <verse eID="Num.14.21"/>
       <verse sID="Num.14.22" osisID="Num.14.22"/> not one of the men who have seen my glory and the proofs I
        wrought in Egypt and in the desert and who yet have put me to the proof over again, refusing to listen to 
        me, <verse eID="Num.14.22"/>
       <verse sID="Num.14.23" osisID="Num.14.23"/> not one of them shall live to see the land I swore to their
        fathers to give them; not one who has despised me shall see it. <verse eID="Num.14.23"/>
       <verse sID="Num.14.24" osisID="Num.14.24"/> But my servant Caleb is of an­other spirit; he has been devoted
        to me, and him will I bring to the land he once entered as a spy, and his descendants shall own it. <verse eID="Num.14.24"/>
       <verse sID="Num.14.25" osisID="Num.14.25"/> [[Meantime, as the Amalekites and Canaanites are living in the
        valleys, turn away to-morrow into the desert in the direction of the Gulf of Akabah]]</q> <verse eID="Num.14.25"/>
      </p>
      <p>
       <verse sID="Num.14.39" osisID="Num.14.39"/> Moses told this to all Israel, and the people lamented it
        bit­terly. <verse eID="Num.14.39"/>
       <verse sID="Num.14.40" osisID="Num.14.40"/> In the morning they started to make their way up, saying, <q>We
        have sinned, but here we are, ready now to march to the place of which the Eternal spoke.</q> <verse eID="Num.14.40"/>
       <verse sID="Num.14.41" osisID="Num.14.41"/> Moses replied, <q>Why will you break the Eternal's or­ders? Your
        plan will not prosper. <verse eID="Num.14.41"/>
       <verse sID="Num.14.42" osisID="Num.14.42"/> Do not start, only to be beaten by your enemies; for the Eternal
        is not with you. <verse eID="Num.14.42"/>
       <verse sID="Num.14.43" osisID="Num.14.43"/> Yonder lie the Amalekites and Canaan­ites in front of you; you
        will be cut to pieces, for you have given up following the Eternal, and therefore the Eternal will not be
        with you.</q> <verse eID="Num.14.43"/>
      </p>
      <p>
       <verse sID="Num.14.44" osisID="Num.14.44"/> Though neither the ark of the Eternal nor Moses left the camp,
        the people dared to start on the way up; <verse eID="Num.14.44"/>
       <verse sID="Num.14.45" osisID="Num.14.45"/> whereupon down came the Amalekites and the Canaan­ites who
        inhabited the high­lands, and drove them in defeat as far as Hormah.] <verse eID="Num.14.45"/>
      </p>
     </hi>
    <chapter eId="Num.14"/>
    <chapter osisId="Num.21" sId="Num.21"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Num.21.1" osisID="Num.21.1"/>[[When the Canaanites who lived in the Negeb heard that Israel
       were advanc­ing by the caravan route, they attacked the Israelites and took some prisoners. <verse eID="Num.21.1"/>
      <verse sID="Num.21.2" osisID="Num.21.2"/> But Israel vowed to the Eternal that if he would hand over this
       people to them, they would doom their towns. <verse eID="Num.21.2"/>
      <verse sID="Num.21.3" osisID="Num.21.3"/> The Eternal listened to them; he handed over the Canaanites to the
       Israelites, who doomed and destroyed both them and their towns. Hence the name of the place was called
       Hormah or Doom.]] <verse eID="Num.21.3"/>
      </p>
    <chapter eId="Num.21"/>
    <chapter osisId="Num.15" sId="Num.15"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Num.15.1" osisID="Num.15.1"/>The Eternal gave Moses these orders
      <verse eID="Num.15.1"/>
      <verse sID="Num.15.2" osisID="Num.15.2"/>
       for the Israelites. <q>When you enter the home­land which I assign you, and make an offering to the Eternal,
      <verse eID="Num.15.2"/>
      <verse sID="Num.15.3" osisID="Num.15.3"/>
      <milestone type="pb" n="168"/> whether a burnt-offering or a sacrifice in fulfilment of some vow or a
       freewill-offering or an offering at some stated festival, to send a soothing odour up to the Eternal from
       some sacrifice of the herd or of the flock, <verse eID="Num.15.3"/>
      <verse sID="Num.15.4" osisID="Num.15.4"/> then the man who makes his oblation to the Eternal must present as
       his cereal-offering seven pints of fine flour mixed with three pints of oil,
      <verse eID="Num.15.4"/>
      <verse sID="Num.15.5" osisID="Num.15.5"/> as well as a libation of three pints of wine, to go with every lamb
       that is sacrificed. <verse eID="Num.15.5"/>
      <verse sID="Num.15.6" osisID="Num.15.6"/> In the case of a ram, you must furnish as a cereal-offering
       four­teen pints of fine flour mixed with four pints of oil, <verse eID="Num.15.6"/>
      <verse sID="Num.15.7" osisID="Num.15.7"/> and a liba­tion of four pints of wine, for a soothing odour to the
       Eternal. <verse eID="Num.15.7"/>
      <verse sID="Num.15.8" osisID="Num.15.8"/> When you prepare a young bullock as a burnt-offering or as a
       sacrifice in fulfilment of some vow or as a recompense-offering to the Eternal, <verse eID="Num.15.8"/>
      <verse sID="Num.15.9" osisID="Num.15.9"/> along with the bullock one and a quarter pecks of fine flour mixed
       with three quarts of oil must be furnished as a cereal-offering, <verse eID="Num.15.9"/>
      <verse sID="Num.15.10" osisID="Num.15.10"/> together with a libation of three quarts of wine, in sacrifice, for
       a soothing odour to the Eternal. <verse eID="Num.15.10"/>
      <verse sID="Num.15.11" osisID="Num.15.11"/> This is what must be done in the case of a single ox or ram or male
       lamb or kid, <verse eID="Num.15.11"/>
      <verse sID="Num.15.12" osisID="Num.15.12"/> for each animal you sacrifice, however many. <verse eID="Num.15.12"/>
      <verse sID="Num.15.13" osisID="Num.15.13"/> Such is the rule for you natives, in burning any sacrifice to send
       up a soothing odour to the Eternal; <verse eID="Num.15.13"/>
      <verse sID="Num.15.14" osisID="Num.15.14"/> and any alien who has settled among you, anyone who may come to live
       with you, must do exactly as you do, in burning any sacrifice to send up a soothing odour to the Eternal. <verse eID="Num.15.14"/>
      <verse sID="Num.15.15" osisID="Num.15.15"/> All members of the community, both yourselves and your resident
       aliens, shall be under the same rule, a settled rule for all time; <verse eID="Num.15.15"/>
      <verse sID="Num.15.16" osisID="Num.15.16"/> both you and the resident aliens shall be alike before the Eternal;
       one and the same law, one set of regulations, for you and your resident aliens.</q> <verse eID="Num.15.16"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Num.15.17" osisID="Num.15.17"/> The Eternal also gave Moses <verse eID="Num.15.17"/>
      <verse sID="Num.15.18" osisID="Num.15.18"/> these orders for the Israelites. <q>When you enter the land to which
       I bring you, <verse eID="Num.15.18"/>
      <verse sID="Num.15.19" osisID="Num.15.19"/> you must reserve a contribution for the Eternal out of your food
       from the land. <verse eID="Num.15.19"/>
      <verse sID="Num.15.20" osisID="Num.15.20"/> You must reserve a cake as a contribution, out of your first batch
       of groats, and make it over to him as a contribution from your threshing-floors; <verse eID="Num.15.20"/>
      <verse sID="Num.15.21" osisID="Num.15.21"/> part of the first batch of your groats you must make over as a
       contribution to the Eternal, for all time.</q><verse eID="Num.15.21"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Num.15.22" osisID="Num.15.22"/><q>When by mistake you fail to carry out any of the orders given by
       the Eternal to Moses, <verse eID="Num.15.22"/>
      <verse sID="Num.15.23" osisID="Num.15.23"/> any command of the Eternal given by Moses ever since the Eternal has
       been giving orders to you, <verse eID="Num.15.23"/>
      <verse sID="Num.15.24" osisID="Num.15.24"/> then for this unintentional offence, of which the community has had
       no knowledge, the community shall all prepare to sacrifice a young bullock as a soothing odour for the Eternal,
       along with its usual cereal-offering and libation, and one he-goat as a sin-offering; <verse eID="Num.15.24"/>
      <verse sID="Num.15.25" osisID="Num.15.25"/> the priest shall make expiation for all the community of Israel, and
       they shall be forgiven, because it was an oversight and because they brought their oblation to the Eternal,
       burning it in sacrifice and presenting a sin-offering for their mistake. <verse eID="Num.15.25"/>
      <verse sID="Num.15.26" osisID="Num.15.26"/> All the assembly of Israel and their resident aliens shall be
       forgiven (for the oversight involved all the people). <verse eID="Num.15.26"/>
      <verse sID="Num.15.27" osisID="Num.15.27"/> If any individual sins by mistake, he shall bring a yearling
       she-goat as a sin-offering, <verse eID="Num.15.27"/>
      <verse sID="Num.15.28" osisID="Num.15.28"/> and the priest shall make expiation for him who has erred by
       <milestone type="pb" n="169"/>
       sinning unintentionally before the Eternal, making expiation for him that he may be forgiven, <verse eID="Num.15.28"/>
      <verse sID="Num.15.29" osisID="Num.15.29"/> whether he is a native born in Israel or an alien resident in Israel:
       you must have one and the same law for both in a case of oversight. <verse eID="Num.15.29"/>
      <verse sID="Num.15.30" osisID="Num.15.30"/> But anyone who sins wilfully, be he native or alien, has insulted
       the Eternal, and that person shall be killed out of this people <verse eID="Num.15.30"/>
      <verse sID="Num.15.31" osisID="Num.15.31"/> for having despised the word of the Eternal and broken his command;
       that person shall be outlawed from his kinsfolk, he must bear the guilt of his sin.</q>
      <verse eID="Num.15.31"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Num.15.32" osisID="Num.15.32"/>When the Israelites were in the desert, a man was caught gathering
       wood for fuel on the sabbath day. <verse eID="Num.15.32"/>
      <verse sID="Num.15.33" osisID="Num.15.33"/> Those who caught him gathering fuel brought him before Moses and
       Aaron and all the community, <verse eID="Num.15.33"/>
      <verse sID="Num.15.34" osisID="Num.15.34"/> who put him under arrest, as there was no clear law about how he was
       to be punished. <verse eID="Num.15.34"/>
      <verse sID="Num.15.35" osisID="Num.15.35"/> But the Eternal said to Moses, <q>The man must certainly be put to
       death; the community must all stone him to death outside the camp.</q> <verse eID="Num.15.35"/>
      <verse sID="Num.15.36" osisID="Num.15.36"/> So the community all took him outside the camp and stoned him till
       he died, as the Eternal had ordered Moses. <verse eID="Num.15.36"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Num.15.37" osisID="Num.15.37"/> The Eternal also gave Moses <verse eID="Num.15.37"/>
      <verse sID="Num.15.38" osisID="Num.15.38"/> these orders for the Israelites. <q>Tell them to put tassels at the
       corners of their robes, attached by a violet thread. <verse eID="Num.15.38"/>
      <verse sID="Num.15.39" osisID="Num.15.39"/> This shall be for all time. The tassel will serve to catch your eye
       and remind you to obey all the commands of the Eternal, not to follow your own wandering desires and fancies,
       <verse eID="Num.15.39"/>
      <verse sID="Num.15.40" osisID="Num.15.40"/> but to remember and obey all my commands, and be consecrated to your
       God. <verse eID="Num.15.40"/>
      <verse sID="Num.15.41" osisID="Num.15.41"/> I am the Eternal your God, who brought you from the land of Egypt in
       order to be your God; I am the Eternal your God.</q> <verse eID="Num.15.41"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eId="Num.15"/>
    <chapter osisId="Num.16" sId="Num.16"/>
     <hi type="italic">
      <p>
       <verse sID="Num.16.1" osisID="Num.16.1"/>[Now Dathan and Abiram the sons of Eliab (son of Pallu and grandson
        of Reuben), men of good standing, <verse eID="Num.16.1"/>
       <verse sID="Num.16.2" osisID="Num.16.2"/> rebelled against Moses. <verse eID="Num.16.2"/>
       <verse sID="Num.16.12" osisID="Num.16.12"/> Moses summoned Dathan and Abiram, the sons of Eliab, to appear
        be­fore him, but they said, <q>No, we are not coming; <verse eID="Num.16.12"/>
       <verse sID="Num.16.13" osisID="Num.16.13"/> are you not satisfied with having taken us away from a land
        abounding in milk and honey only to kill us in the desert? And you would make yourself a prince over us?
       <verse eID="Num.16.13"/>
       <verse sID="Num.16.14" osisID="Num.16.14"/> You have not brought us to a land abounding in milk and honey,
        nor have you put us in possession of fields and vineyards. Will you throw dust in the eyes of these men?
        No, we are not coming be­fore you!</q> <verse eID="Num.16.14"/>
       <verse sID="Num.16.15" osisID="Num.16.15"/> Moses was enraged; he said to the Eternal, <q>Disregard any
        offering they make; I have not robbed them of a single ass, I have not injured any of them!</q> <verse eID="Num.16.15"/>
      </p>
      <p>
       <verse sID="Num.16.25" osisID="Num.16.25"/> Then Moses went to Dathan and Abiram, followed by the sheikhs of
        Israel; <verse eID="Num.16.25"/>
       <verse sID="Num.16.27" osisID="Num.16.27"/> and when Dathan and Abiram, with their wives and little
        children, came out and stood at the entrance to their tents, <verse eID="Num.16.27"/>
       <verse sID="Num.16.26" osisID="Num.16.26"/> Moses told the people to withdraw from the tents of these evil
        men and to touch nothing that belonged to them; <q>lest,</q> he said, <q>you are swept to ruin along with
        their sins.</q> <verse eID="Num.16.26"/>
       <verse sID="Num.16.28" osisID="Num.16.28"/> Moses added, <q>This will convince you that the Eternal has sent
        me to act, and that I am not acting on my own impulse: <verse eID="Num.16.28"/>
       <verse sID="Num.16.29" osisID="Num.16.29"/> if these men die an ordinary death and suffer as all men suf­fer,
        then the Eternal has not sent me; <verse eID="Num.16.29"/>
       <verse sID="Num.16.30" osisID="Num.16.30"/> but if the Eternal does something new, if the ground yawns and
        swallows up them and theirs, and they go down
        <milestone type="pb" n="170"/>
        alive to the grave, then you may be sure that these men have despised the Eternal.</q> <verse eID="Num.16.30"/>
       <verse sID="Num.16.31" osisID="Num.16.31"/> He had just finished speaking when the ground split under their
        feet; <verse eID="Num.16.31"/>
       <verse sID="Num.16.32" osisID="Num.16.32"/> the earth did yawn and swal­low up them and their households. <verse eID="Num.16.32"/>
       <verse sID="Num.16.33" osisID="Num.16.33"/> So they and all theirs went down alive to the grave, the earth
        closed over them, and they vanished from the community. <verse eID="Num.16.33"/>
       <verse sID="Num.16.34" osisID="Num.16.34"/> Then all the Israelites around fled at their shrieks, thinking
        the earth might swallow them also] <verse eID="Num.16.34"/>
      </p>
     </hi>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Num.16.1" osisID="Num.16.1"/>Korah the son of Izhar (son of Kohath and grandson of Levi) <verse eID="Num.16.1"/>
      <verse sID="Num.16.2" osisID="Num.16.2"/> and some Israelites, two hundred and fifty chieftains of the
       community who were councillors, gathered to oppose Moses and Aaron, <verse eID="Num.16.2"/>
      <verse sID="Num.16.3" osisID="Num.16.3"/> saying to them, <q>Enough of you and your pretensions. The whole
       community are consecrated, every man of them, and the Eternal is among them; why do you raise yourselves
       higher than the assembly of the Eter­nal?</q> <verse eID="Num.16.3"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Num.16.4" osisID="Num.16.4"/> When Moses heard this, he fell on his face; <verse eID="Num.16.4"/>
      <verse sID="Num.16.5" osisID="Num.16.5"/> then he said to Korah and all his companions, <q>In the morning the
       Eternal will show who belong to him; he will allow those who are really consecrated to approach him, he will
       allow the men of his own choice to approach him. <verse eID="Num.16.5"/>
      <verse sID="Num.16.6" osisID="Num.16.6"/> Do this: take your fire-pans, <verse eID="Num.16.6"/>
      <verse sID="Num.16.7" osisID="Num.16.7"/> put burning coals on them and in­cense on the top, in presence of
       the Eternal to-morrow; and he whom the Eternal chooses, he shall be the consecrated man.</q> <verse eID="Num.16.7"/>
      <verse sID="Num.16.8" osisID="Num.16.8"/> Moses said to Korah, <q>Listen to me, you Levites. <verse eID="Num.16.8"/>
      <verse sID="Num.16.9" osisID="Num.16.9"/> Is it not enough for you that the God of Israel has singled you out
       from the community of Israel and allowed you near his presence to do the work of the Eternal’s Dwelling, and
       to be servants of the community, <verse eID="Num.16.9"/>
      <verse sID="Num.16.10" osisID="Num.16.10"/> allowing you and all your fellow-Levites to approach him? You
       want to be priests as well? <verse eID="Num.16.10"/>
      <verse sID="Num.16.11" osisID="Num.16.11"/> Such a gathering of you and all your com­panions is against the
       Eternal. For what has Aaron done that you should murmur against him? <verse eID="Num.16.11"/>
      <verse sID="Num.16.16" osisID="Num.16.16"/> To-morrow,</q> Moses added, <q>do you and all your company appear
       before the Eternal, you and they and Aaron together. <verse eID="Num.16.16"/>
      <verse sID="Num.16.17" osisID="Num.16.17"/> Let each of you take his fire-pan and put incense in it,
       bringing them up to the Eternal, all the two hun­dred and fifty fire-pans; you bring your fire-pans and Aaron
       his.</q> <verse eID="Num.16.17"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Num.16.18" osisID="Num.16.18"/> So each of them took his firepan, put burning coals on it and
       incense on the top; then they took their place at the en­trance of the Trysting tent, along with Moses and
       Aaron. <verse eID="Num.16.18"/>
      <verse sID="Num.16.19" osisID="Num.16.19"/> Korah had collected all the assembly to confront them at the
       entrance of the Trysting tent, and the majesty of the Eternal appeared to the whole community; <verse eID="Num.16.19"/>
      <verse sID="Num.16.20" osisID="Num.16.20"/> the Eternal said to Moses and Aaron, <verse eID="Num.16.20"/>
      <verse sID="Num.16.21" osisID="Num.16.21"/> <q>Separate yourselves from this community that I may destroy
       them in one instant.</q> <verse eID="Num.16.21"/>
      <verse sID="Num.16.22" osisID="Num.16.22"/> But they fell on their faces, crying, <q>O God, the God of all
       spirits of mankind, shall one man sin and wilt thou be angry with the whole commu­nity?</q> <verse eID="Num.16.22"/>
      <verse sID="Num.16.23" osisID="Num.16.23"/> So the Eternal bade Moses <verse eID="Num.16.23"/>
      <verse sID="Num.16.24" osisID="Num.16.24"/> tell the community to move away from the Dwelling. <verse eID="Num.16.24"/>
      <verse sID="Num.16.27" osisID="Num.16.27"/> They did withdraw from the Dwelling, all round, <verse eID="Num.16.27"/>
      <verse sID="Num.16.35" osisID="Num.16.35"/> and then fire issued from the Eternal, de­stroying the two hundred
       and fifty men who had offered the incense, even all the followers of
       <milestone type="pb" n="171"/>
       Korah and all their goods. <verse eID="Num.16.35"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Num.16.36" osisID="Num.16.36"/> Then the Eternal bade Moses <verse eID="Num.16.36"/>
      <verse sID="Num.16.37" osisID="Num.16.37"/> tell Eleazar the son of Aaron the priest to pick up the fire-pans
       out of the blaze--<q>and do you scatter the burning coals far and wide, for the fire-pans of these men whose
       sin has cost them their lives are forfeit to the sanctuary; <verse eID="Num.16.37"/>
      <verse sID="Num.16.38" osisID="Num.16.38"/> have them beaten into plates to cover the altar; they were
       presented before the Eternal, and therefore they are forfeit to the sanctuary. That will be an object-lesson
       to the Israelites.</q> <verse eID="Num.16.38"/>
      <verse sID="Num.16.39" osisID="Num.16.39"/> So Eleazar the priest picked up the bronze fire­pans presented by
       the men who had been burned, and they were beaten flat to form a covering for the altar, <verse eID="Num.16.39"/>
      <verse sID="Num.16.40" osisID="Num.16.40"/> to remind the Israelites that no layman who did not belong to
       Aaron’s fam­ily was to venture near to offer incense before the Eternal, else he would fare like Korah and
       his company. This Eleazar did, as the Eternal had told him by Moses. <verse eID="Num.16.40"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Num.16.41" osisID="Num.16.41"/>But next day the community of Israel all grumbled against Moses
       and Aaron, complaining that it was they who had slain some of the Eternal’s people. <verse eID="Num.16.41"/>
      <verse sID="Num.16.42" osisID="Num.16.42"/> As the community gathered against Moses and Aaron, they turned to
       face the Trysting tent, and there was the cloud cover­ing it!--the Eternal’s majesty appeared. <verse eID="Num.16.42"/>
      <verse sID="Num.16.43" osisID="Num.16.43"/> When Moses and Aaron stepped in front of the Trysting tent, <verse eID="Num.16.43"/>
      <verse sID="Num.16.44" osisID="Num.16.44"/> the Eternal said to Moses, <verse eID="Num.16.44"/>
      <verse sID="Num.16.45" osisID="Num.16.45"/> <q>Withdraw from this community, that I may destroy them in one
       instant.</q> They fell on their faces. <verse eID="Num.16.45"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Num.16.46" osisID="Num.16.46"/> Then said Moses to Aaron, <q>Take your fire-pan, put some burning
       coals on it from the altar and lay incense on the top, then carry it quickly into community and make
       expiation for them; for wrath has issued from the Eternal, the death-stroke has begun.</q> <verse eID="Num.16.46"/>
      <verse sID="Num.16.47" osisID="Num.16.47"/> So Aaron did as Moses told him, he took the fire-pan and ran
       among the people; the death-stroke had be­gun, but with his incense he made expiation for the people; <verse eID="Num.16.47"/>
      <verse sID="Num.16.48" osisID="Num.16.48"/> he stood between the living and the dead, and the attack was
       checked. <verse eID="Num.16.48"/>
      <verse sID="Num.16.49" osisID="Num.16.49"/> Those who died of it numbered fourteen thousand seven hundred, in
       addition to those who died in Korah’s rebel­lion. <verse eID="Num.16.49"/>
      <verse sID="Num.16.50" osisID="Num.16.50"/> Then, the death-stroke having been checked, Aaron went back to
       Moses at the en­trance of the Trysting tent. <verse eID="Num.16.50"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eId="Num.16"/>
    <chapter osisId="Num.17" sId="Num.17"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Num.17.1" osisID="Num.17.1"/>Then the Eternal gave Moses
      <verse eID="Num.17.1"/>
      <verse sID="Num.17.2" osisID="Num.17.2"/> these orders for the Israelites. <q>Take one stick for every clan,
       from all the chiefs of the clans, twelve sticks in all; write each man’s name on his stick, <verse eID="Num.17.2"/>
      <verse sID="Num.17.3" osisID="Num.17.3"/> and Aaron’s name on the stick of Levi (for one stick is to
       represent the families of Levi). <verse eID="Num.17.3"/>
      <verse sID="Num.17.4" osisID="Num.17.4"/> Lay them inside the Trysting tent, in front of the ark of the
       Presence, where I meet with you; <verse eID="Num.17.4"/>
      <verse sID="Num.17.5" osisID="Num.17.5"/> and the man whom I choose, his stick shall sprout. Thus will I stop
       and silence any grum­bling on the part of the Israel­ites.</q> <verse eID="Num.17.5"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Num.17.6" osisID="Num.17.6"/> So Moses spoke to the Israelites, and their chiefs gave him a stick
       each, as representing their clans, twelve sticks in all, with Aaron’s stick among them, <verse eID="Num.17.6"/>
      <verse sID="Num.17.7" osisID="Num.17.7"/> Moses put the sticks down before the Eternal inside the tent of the
       Presence, <verse eID="Num.17.7"/>
      <verse sID="Num.17.8" osisID="Num.17.8"/> and next morn­ing, when Moses entered the tent, lo and behold,
       Aaron’s stick, representing the clan of Levi, had sprouted, budding and flowering and bearing ripe al­monds!
      <verse eID="Num.17.8"/>
      <verse sID="Num.17.9" osisID="Num.17.9"/> Moses then brought all 9 the sticks out from the presence
       <milestone type="pb" n="172"/>
       of the Eternal, before all the Israelites; they looked at them, and each man took his stick. <verse eID="Num.17.9"/>
      <verse sID="Num.17.10" osisID="Num.17.10"/> And the Eternal said to Moses, <q>Put Aaron’s stick back in front
       of the ark of the Presence, to remain as an object-lesson for rebellious men, and to stop them from wearying
       me with their grumbling. Else they will die.</q> <verse eID="Num.17.10"/>
      <verse sID="Num.17.11" osisID="Num.17.11"/>Moses then did as the Eternal bade him. <verse eID="Num.17.11"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Num.17.12" osisID="Num.17.12"/>Once the Israelites cried to Moses, <q>We are undone! We are lost,
       all of us lost! <verse eID="Num.17.12"/>
      <verse sID="Num.17.13" osisID="Num.17.13"/> Anyone who ever approaches the tent of the Eternal will die. 
       Are we to perish one and all?</q> <verse eID="Num.17.13"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eId="Num.17"/>
    <chapter osisId="Num.18" sId="Num.18"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Num.18.1" osisID="Num.18.1"/>So the Eternal said to Aaron, <q>You and your sons and your family
       shall answer for any guilt in connexion with the sanctuary; you and your sons shall answer for any guilt in
       connexion with your priesthood. <verse eID="Num.18.1"/>
      <verse sID="Num.18.2" osisID="Num.18.2"/> But take your fellows in the clan of Levi to join you and wait upon
       you as you and your sons minister in front of the tent of the Presence;
      <verse eID="Num.18.2"/>
      <verse sID="Num.18.3" osisID="Num.18.3"/>they shall attend to you and all the tent, but they must not come
       near the sacred vessels or the altar; else they and you will perish. <verse eID="Num.18.3"/>
      <verse sID="Num.18.4" osisID="Num.18.4"/> Let them join you and attend to all the business of the Trysting
       tent, to every­thing connected with it; for no layman must come near you. <verse eID="Num.18.4"/>
      <verse sID="Num.18.5" osisID="Num.18.5"/> The charge of the sanctuary and the duties of the altar must be
       your care; else wrath di­vine shall fall again upon the Israelites. <verse eID="Num.18.5"/>
      <verse sID="Num.18.6" osisID="Num.18.6"/> Well, then, I have selected your fellow-Levites from Israel, as a
       gift for you and as men made over to the Eternal, to look after the Trysting tent: <verse eID="Num.18.6"/>
      <verse sID="Num.18.7" osisID="Num.18.7"/> but you and your sons shall discharge as priests all the duties
       connected with the altar and what lies inside the curtain. That is your task; I bestow this priest­hood on
       you, endowing you with the sacred service, and any layman who dares to interfere shall die.</q> <verse eID="Num.18.7"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Num.18.8" osisID="Num.18.8"/> The Eternal also said to Aaron, <q>I hereby assign you what is left
       over of the contribu­tions offered to me, that is, of all the sacred gifts made by the Israelites; to you and
       to your sons I assign them as your share, as your perpetual due. <verse eID="Num.18.8"/>
      <verse sID="Num.18.9" osisID="Num.18.9"/> Out of the most sacred offerings left over from the altar-fire, you
       shall have whatever people offer in the shape of cereals, all the animals they sacrifice as sin-offerings,
       and the guilt-offerings whereby they make restitution to me; all this shall be sacred to you and your sons;
      <verse eID="Num.18.9"/>
      <verse sID="Num.18.10" osisID="Num.18.10"/> in a sacred spot you shall eat it, every male among you; it
       belongs to you as a sacred gift. <verse eID="Num.18.10"/>
      <verse sID="Num.18.11" osisID="Num.18.11"/> Yours also shall be the reserved part of Israel’s contributions
       in all the recom­pense-offerings; to you and your sons and daughters I assign them as your share, as your
       perpetual due, to be eaten by everyone in your family who is undefiled; <verse eID="Num.18.11"/>
      <verse sID="Num.18.12" osisID="Num.18.12"/> the best oil and wine and corn, the choicest of their gifts to
       the Eternal, I assign to you; <verse eID="Num.18.12"/>
      <verse sID="Num.18.13" osisID="Num.18.13"/> the first ripe produce of all that grows in their land shall be
       yours, as they bring it to the Eternal, to be eaten by everyone in your family who is undefiled. <verse eID="Num.18.13"/>
      <verse sID="Num.18.14" osisID="Num.18.14"/> Then, everything throughout Israel that is dedicated to me shall
       be yours. <verse eID="Num.18.14"/>
      <verse sID="Num.18.15" osisID="Num.18.15"/> Also, the first-born of man or of beast, which they present to
       the Eternal, shall be yours,
      <verse eID="Num.18.15"/>
      <verse sID="Num.18.16" osisID="Num.18.16"/> though you must take care to have the first-born children of men
       redeemed, the price for each child of the age
       <milestone type="pb" n="173"/>
       of one month being fixed by you at twelve silver shillings (on the sacred scale). <verse eID="Num.18.16"/>
      <verse sID="Num.18.15" osisID="Num.18.15"/> You must have the first-born of unclean animals redeemed, <verse eID="Num.18.15"/>
      <verse sID="Num.18.17" osisID="Num.18.17"/> but not the first­born of oxen, sheep, or goats; they are sacred,
       and you must splash their blood upon the altar and burn their fat in sacrifice as a soothing odour for the
       Eternal, <verse eID="Num.18.17"/>
      <verse sID="Num.18.18" osisID="Num.18.18"/> though their flesh be­longs to you, like the breast and the thigh
      <verse eID="Num.18.18"/>
      <verse sID="Num.18.19" osisID="Num.18.19"/> of animals presented for the recompense-offering. Thus do I
       assign what is left of the sacred contributions offered by Israel to the Eternal, assigning them to you and
       your sons and your daughters as your share, as your perpetual due; it is a perpetual compact, valid before
       the Eternal for you and for your family.</q> <verse eID="Num.18.19"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Num.18.20" osisID="Num.18.20"/>The Eternal also said to Aaron, <q>You shall hold no property in
       this land, you shall have no share in it; I am your property, I am your share in life, among the Israelites.
      <verse eID="Num.18.20"/>
      <verse sID="Num.18.21" osisID="Num.18.21"/> To the Levites, however, I assign all the tithes in Israel as
       their property, in return for the work they have to do in the service of the Trysting tent. <verse eID="Num.18.21"/>
      <verse sID="Num.18.22" osisID="Num.18.22"/> Never again shall any Israelites ap­proach the Trysting tent and
       incur sin that would be the death of them; <verse eID="Num.18.22"/>
      <verse sID="Num.18.23" osisID="Num.18.23"/> the Levites shall do the work inside the Trysting tent, and it is
       the Levites who shall answer for any fault there. This shall be a perpetual rule, for all time. And they
       shall hold no property in Israel, <verse eID="Num.18.23"/>
      <verse sID="Num.18.24" osisID="Num.18.24"/> for I have assigned to the Levites, as their property, the tithes
       contributed by the Israelites as their offering to the Eternal; hence I have told them that they are to hold
       no property in Israel.</q> <verse eID="Num.18.24"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Num.18.25" osisID="Num.18.25"/> The Eternal also gave Moses <verse eID="Num.18.25"/>
      <verse sID="Num.18.26" osisID="Num.18.26"/> these orders for the Levites. <q>Tell them that in taking from
       the Israelites the tithes I have assigned them as their property, they must set aside a special part of the
       tithes for the Eternal, <verse eID="Num.18.26"/>
      <verse sID="Num.18.27" osisID="Num.18.27"/> and that this contribution of theirs will count as if it were
       corn taken from the threshing-floor or new wine from the vintage. <verse eID="Num.18.27"/>
      <verse sID="Num.18.28" osisID="Num.18.28"/> Thus shall they set aside a share for the Eternal from all the
       tithes they get, and assign the Eter­nal’s share to Aaron the priest; <verse eID="Num.18.28"/>
      <verse sID="Num.18.29" osisID="Num.18.29"/> the share for the Eternal is to be selected from all they
       receive, and they must consecrate the best of it all. <verse eID="Num.18.29"/>
      <verse sID="Num.18.30" osisID="Num.18.30"/> Also tell them that when they make this con­tribution to you, the
       rest of the tithes shall be reckoned to them as the tithed produce of the threshing-floor or the vintage; <verse eID="Num.18.30"/>
      <verse sID="Num.18.31" osisID="Num.18.31"/> it may be eaten anywhere by them or by their families, since it
       is their payment for the work they do in the Trysting tent. <verse eID="Num.18.31"/>
      <verse sID="Num.18.32" osisID="Num.18.32"/> Provided that they set aside the best part of it, they shall
       incur no sin; but they must not pro­fanely grasp the sacred gifts of Israel, else they die.</q> <verse eID="Num.18.32"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eId="Num.18"/>
    <chapter osisId="Num.19" sId="Num.19"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Num.19.1" osisID="Num.19.1"/>The Eternal gave Moses and Aaron <verse eID="Num.19.1"/>
      <verse sID="Num.19.2" osisID="Num.19.2"/> this ritual regulation, laid down by the Eternal himself. <q>Tell
       the Israelites to let you have a red cow, sound and whole, which has never been in harness, <verse eID="Num.19.2"/>
      <verse sID="Num.19.3" osisID="Num.19.3"/> and hand it over to Eleazar the priest, to be led outside the camp
       and slain there in his presence. <verse eID="Num.19.3"/>
      <verse sID="Num.19.4" osisID="Num.19.4"/> Then Eleazar the priest must dip his finger in its blood and splash
       some of the blood towards the front of the Trysting tent, seven times over. <verse eID="Num.19.4"/>
      <verse sID="Num.19.5" osisID="Num.19.5"/> After which the cow is to be burned in his presence, skin, flesh,
       blood, and even its
       <milestone type="pb" n="174"/>
       dung, all burned; <verse eID="Num.19.5"/>
      <verse sID="Num.19.6" osisID="Num.19.6"/> and the priest shall throw some cedar-wood and marjoram and scarlet
       thread into the burning body. <verse eID="Num.19.6"/>
      <verse sID="Num.19.7" osisID="Num.19.7"/>He shall then wash his robes and bathe his body before entering the
       camp, and till evening the priest shall remain unclean. <verse eID="Num.19.7"/>
      <verse sID="Num.19.8" osisID="Num.19.8"/> The man who burned the cow shall also wash his robes and bathe his
       body and remain unclean till evening. <verse eID="Num.19.8"/>
      <verse sID="Num.19.9" osisID="Num.19.9"/> A man who is clean shall gather the ashes of the cow and put them
       in some clean place outside the camp, to be kept for use by the community of Israel in water meant for
       removing pol­lution;  the cow thus serves to put sin away.<verse eID="Num.19.9"/>
      <verse sID="Num.19.10" osisID="Num.19.10"/> (The man who gathers the ashes of the cow shall wash his robes
       and remain unclean till evening.)</q>
     </p>
     <p>
       <q>Now the rule binding on the Israelites and their resident aliens for all time is this:<verse eID="Num.19.10"/>
      <verse sID="Num.19.11" osisID="Num.19.11"/> anyone who touches a dead body, that is, a human corpse, shall
       remain unclean for seven days. <verse eID="Num.19.11"/>
      <verse sID="Num.19.12" osisID="Num.19.12"/> On the third day and on the seventh day he must purify himself
       from the sin; if so, he shall be clean, but, if not, he shall not be clean. <verse eID="Num.19.12"/>
      <verse sID="Num.19.13" osisID="Num.19.13"/> Anyone who touches a dead body, that is, a human corpse, and does
       not cleanse himself from the sin, has polluted the Dwelling of the Eternal, and shall be out­lawed from
       Israel, since the water for removing pollution has not been splashed over him; he is unclean, his
       uncleanness clings to him. <verse eID="Num.19.13"/>
      <verse sID="Num.19.14" osisID="Num.19.14"/> When a man dies inside a tent, the law is that anyone entering
       the tent and all who are already in the tent shall remain unclean for seven days; <verse eID="Num.19.14"/>
      <verse sID="Num.19.15" osisID="Num.19.15"/> also, that every open vessel whose lid is not fastened down,
       shall be un­clean. <verse eID="Num.19.15"/>
      <verse sID="Num.19.16" osisID="Num.19.16"/> Again, anyone who in the open touches the dead body of a man
       fallen in battle or of one who has died a natural death, anyone who touches even a bone or a grave, shall
       remain unclean for seven days. <verse eID="Num.19.16"/>
      <verse sID="Num.19.17" osisID="Num.19.17"/> On behalf of the unclean man, some ashes of the sacrificed cow
       shall be taken, and fresh water poured over them in a vessel; <verse eID="Num.19.17"/>
      <verse sID="Num.19.18" osisID="Num.19.18"/> then some clean man shall dip a bundle of marjoram in the water
       and splash it over the tent and the furniture and all persons present, or on the man who has touched a bone
       or a corpse or a grave; <verse eID="Num.19.18"/>
      <verse sID="Num.19.19" osisID="Num.19.19"/> the clean man shall splash the water over the unclean man on the
       third day and on the seventh day, freeing him from sin on the seventh day, when he must wash his robes and
       bathe in water, and by evening he shall be clean again. <verse eID="Num.19.19"/>
      <verse sID="Num.19.20" osisID="Num.19.20"/> But as for anyone who becomes unclean and does not have himself
       cleansed from sin, that man shall be outlawed from the com­munity, since he has polluted the sanctuary of the
       Eternal and had no water for removing pollution splashed over him--the unclean creature! <verse eID="Num.19.20"/>
      <verse sID="Num.19.21" osisID="Num.19.21"/> This shall be a regulation for all time among you. (The man who
       splashes the water for removing pollution shall wash his robes, and any­one who touches the water shall
       remain unclean till evening. <verse eID="Num.19.21"/>
      <verse sID="Num.19.22" osisID="Num.19.22"/> Also, anything that the unclean man touches shall become un­clean,
       and anyone touching it or him shall remain unclean till evening.)</q> <verse eID="Num.19.22"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eId="Num.19"/>
    <chapter osisId="Num.20" sId="Num.20"/>
     <hi type="italic">
      <p>
       <verse sID="Num.20.1" osisID="Num.20.1"/>[While the people were staying at Kadesh, Miriam died there and
        was buried there. <verse eID="Num.20.1"/>
       <verse sID="Num.20.3" osisID="Num.20.3"/> And the people quarrelled with
        <milestone type="pb" n="175"/>
        Moses, complaining, <verse eID="Num.20.3"/>
       <verse sID="Num.20.4" osisID="Num.20.4"/> <q>Why have you brought the community of the Eternal into this
        desert, only to let us die, both us and our cattle? <verse eID="Num.20.4"/>
       <verse sID="Num.20.5" osisID="Num.20.5"/> Why did you make us leave Egypt for this evil place? It is no
        place for seed, for figs, or for vines, or for pomegranates; and there is no water to drink!</q>
       <verse eID="Num.20.5"/>
       <verse sID="Num.20.7" osisID="Num.20.7"/>Then said the Eternal to Moses, <verse eID="Num.20.7"/>
       <verse sID="Num.20.8" osisID="Num.20.8"/><q>Take your staff, and after con­vening the people bring water
        from the rock for them, to let them and their cattle drink.</q> <verse eID="Num.20.8"/>
       <verse sID="Num.20.10" osisID="Num.20.10"/> So Moses said to them, <q>Listen, you rebels, must I bring you
        water from this rock?</q> <verse eID="Num.20.10"/>
       <verse sID="Num.20.11" osisID="Num.20.11"/> And lifting his hand he struck the rock with his staff, till
        water gushed out, and the community and their cattle drank of it. <verse eID="Num.20.11"/>
       <verse sID="Num.20.13" osisID="Num.20.13"/> It is called the water of Meribah (Complaint), because there
        the Israelites complained of the Eternal, and there he vindi­cated himself.] <verse eID="Num.20.13"/>
      </p>
     </hi>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Num.20.1" osisID="Num.20.1"/>In the first month of . . . the Israelites, the whole commu­nity of
       them, entered the desert of Zin. <verse eID="Num.20.1"/>
      <verse sID="Num.20.2" osisID="Num.20.2"/> As there was no water for the community, they gath­ered against
       Moses and Aaron, <verse eID="Num.20.2"/>
      <verse sID="Num.20.3" osisID="Num.20.3"/> crying, <q>Would that we had died when our fellows died before the
       Eternal!</q> <verse eID="Num.20.3"/>
      <verse sID="Num.20.6" osisID="Num.20.6"/> Then Moses and Aaron withdrew to the entrance of the Trysting tent
       and fell on their faces; the Eternal’s majesty appeared to them, <verse eID="Num.20.6"/>
      <verse sID="Num.20.7" osisID="Num.20.7"/> and he said, <verse eID="Num.20.7"/>
      <verse sID="Num.20.8" osisID="Num.20.8"/> <q>Do you and Aaron order the rock to yield its water before the
       eyes of the people.</q> <verse eID="Num.20.8"/>
      <verse sID="Num.20.9" osisID="Num.20.9"/> Then, in obe­dience to the Eternal, Moses took the stick of Aaron
       from the presence of the Eternal, <verse eID="Num.20.9"/>
      <verse sID="Num.20.10" osisID="Num.20.10"/> and Moses and Aaron convened the community in front of the rock. <verse eID="Num.20.10"/>
      <verse sID="Num.20.12" osisID="Num.20.12"/> ...So the Eternal said to Moses and Aaron, <q>Because you would
       not trust me and vindi­cate my honour before the Israelites, you shall not lead this community into the
       land that I have given them.</q> <verse eID="Num.20.12"/>
     </p>
     <hi type="italic">
      <p>
       <verse sID="Num.20.14" osisID="Num.20.14"/>[From Kadesh Moses sent messengers to the king of Edom from his
        <q>kinsmen the Israel­ites.</q> The message was, <q>You know all the hardships that have befallen us, <verse eID="Num.20.14"/>
       <verse sID="Num.20.15" osisID="Num.20.15"/> how our fathers went down to Egypt, how we stayed long in Egypt
        and were badly treated, both we and our fathers, by the Egyptians; <verse eID="Num.20.15"/>
       <verse sID="Num.20.16" osisID="Num.20.16"/> and how, when we cried to the Eternal, he listened to us and
        sent an angel and brought us out of Egypt. Now here we are at Kadesh, a town on the edge of your terri­tory.
       <verse eID="Num.20.16"/>
       <verse sID="Num.20.17" osisID="Num.20.17"/> Pray let us cross your land. We will not march over any field
        or vineyard, nor will we drink the water of your wells, but march along the royal high road, turning
        neither to right nor to left, until we pass beyond your frontier.</q> <verse eID="Num.20.17"/>
       <verse sID="Num.20.18" osisID="Num.20.18"/> Edom answered Israel, <q>No, you shall not cross; if you do, I
        will attack you.</q> <verse eID="Num.20.18"/>
       <verse sID="Num.20.19" osisID="Num.20.19"/> The Israelites said to him, <q>We will keep to the high road,
        and we will pay you for any water that we or our cattle drink; pray let us walk quietly across--there is
        no harm in that!</q> <verse eID="Num.20.19"/>
       <verse sID="Num.20.20" osisID="Num.20.20"/> <q>No,</q> said Edom, and sallied out to stop them with a large
        army in strong force. <verse eID="Num.20.20"/>
       <verse sID="Num.20.21" osisID="Num.20.21"/> Thus Edom refused to let Israel cross his territory; Israel had
        to turn aside.] <verse eID="Num.20.21"/>
      </p>
     </hi>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Num.20.22" osisID="Num.20.22"/> From Kadesh the Israelites set out and came, the whole community
       of them, to mount Hor. <verse eID="Num.20.22"/>
      <verse sID="Num.20.23" osisID="Num.20.23"/> At mount Hor on the borders of Edom the Eternal said to Moses
       and Aaron, <verse eID="Num.20.23"/>
      <verse sID="Num.20.24" osisID="Num.20.24"/> <q>Aaron must now rejoin his kinsfolk, for he is not to enter
       the land I have given to the Israelites, because you and he were faithless to my orders at the water of
       Meribah. <verse eID="Num.20.24"/>
      <verse sID="Num.20.25" osisID="Num.20.25"/> Take
       <milestone type="pb" n="176"/>
       Aaron and his son Eleazar up mount Hor, <verse eID="Num.20.25"/>
      <verse sID="Num.20.26" osisID="Num.20.26"/> strip Aaron of his robes and put them on Eleazar; Aaron shall
       depart and die there.</q> <verse eID="Num.20.26"/>
      <verse sID="Num.20.27" osisID="Num.20.27"/> So Moses did as the Eternal told him; they went up mount Hor
       before the eyes of all the community, <verse eID="Num.20.27"/>
      <verse sID="Num.20.28" osisID="Num.20.28"/> and, after Moses had stripped Aaron of his robes and put them on
       his son Eleazar, Aaron died there on the mountain-top. <verse eID="Num.20.28"/>
      <verse sID="Num.20.29" osisID="Num.20.29"/> Then Moses and Eleazar came down the mountain and when all the
       assembly saw that Aaron was dead, all Israel mourned for Aaron thirty days. <verse eID="Num.20.29"/>
    <chapter eId="Num.20"/>
    <chapter osisId="Num.21" sId="Num.21"/>
      <verse sID="Num.21.4" osisID="Num.21.4"/> Then the Israelites set out from mount Hor <verse eID="Num.21.4"/>
      <verse sID="Num.21.10" osisID="Num.21.10"/> and passed forward to encamp at Oboth; <verse eID="Num.21.10"/>
      <verse sID="Num.21.11" osisID="Num.21.11"/> setting out from Oboth, they encamped at Ije-abarim. <verse eID="Num.21.11"/>
    <chapter eId="Num.21"/>
    <chapter osisId="Num.22" sId="Num.22"/>
      <verse sID="Num.22.1" osisID="Num.22.1"/>Then the Israelites set out and en­camped on the steppes of Moab
       east of the Jordan opposite Jericho. <verse eID="Num.22.1"/>
    <chapter eId="Num.22"/>
      </p>
    <chapter osisId="Num.21" sId="Num.21"/>
     <hi type="italic">
      <p>
       <verse sID="Num.21.4" osisID="Num.21.4"/>[They cast back to go round the land of Edom by the Gulf of Akdbah,
        and the peo­ple grew impatient over the route; <verse eID="Num.21.4"/>
       <verse sID="Num.21.5" osisID="Num.21.5"/> they attacked God and Moses, crying, <q>Why have you brought us
        from Egypt to die in the desert? There is neither bread nor water, and we loathe this wretched food.</q>
       <verse eID="Num.21.5"/>
       <verse sID="Num.21.6" osisID="Num.21.6"/> Then the Eternal sent stinging serpents among the people, that
        bit the people, till many an Israelite died. <verse eID="Num.21.6"/>
       <verse sID="Num.21.7" osisID="Num.21.7"/> So the people came and said to Moses, <q>We have sinned by
        attacking the Eternal and you; pray to the Eternal to take the serpents away from us.</q> Moses prayed for
        the people, <verse eID="Num.21.7"/>
       <verse sID="Num.21.8" osisID="Num.21.8"/> and the Eternal told Moses to make a bronze serpent and erect it
        on a pole, so that any person who was bitten might live by looking at it. <verse eID="Num.21.8"/>
       <verse sID="Num.21.9" osisID="Num.21.9"/> Moses made a bronze serpent and erected it on a pole; and when
        anyone who had been bitten by a serpent looked at the bronze serpent, he lived. <verse eID="Num.21.9"/>
      </p>
      <p>
       <verse sID="Num.21.12" osisID="Num.21.12"/> Marching forward through the desert to the east of Moab, they
        encamped in the wady of Zered; <verse eID="Num.21.12"/>
       <verse sID="Num.21.13" osisID="Num.21.13"/> then marching forward they encamped north of Arnon in the
        desert that stretches to the east of the Amorite territory, for the Arnon is the northern boundary of Moab,
        between them and the Amorites. <verse eID="Num.21.13"/>
       <verse sID="Num.21.14" osisID="Num.21.14"/> Hence the lines in the book of the <q>Battles of the
        Eternal</q>--
        <lg>
         <l>Through Waheb we swept,</l>
       <verse eID="Num.21.14"/>
       <verse sID="Num.21.15" osisID="Num.21.15"/>
         <l> through the valleys of Arnon, </l>
         <l> o’er the slope of the valleys </l>
         <l> that stretches where Ar lies, </l>
         <l> that leans over Moab’s edge. </l>
        </lg>
       <verse eID="Num.21.15"/>
      </p>
      <p>
       <verse sID="Num.21.16" osisID="Num.21.16"/> Then they pushed on to Beer, the Beer where the Eternal said to
        Moses, <q>Gather the people and I will give them water</q>; <verse eID="Num.21.16"/>
       <verse sID="Num.21.17" osisID="Num.21.17"/> and Israel sang this song,
        <lg>
         <l> Spring up, O well-- </l>
         <l> ah, sing to the well </l>
       <verse eID="Num.21.17"/>
       <verse sID="Num.21.18" osisID="Num.21.18"/>
         <l> that chieftains dug, </l>
         <l> that captains delved, </l>
         <l> wielding their wands, </l>
         <l> wielding their staves! </l>
        </lg>
        From Beer (Welltown) they pushed on to Mattanah, <verse eID="Num.21.18"/>
      </p>
      <p>
       <verse sID="Num.21.19" osisID="Num.21.19"/> from Mattanah to Nahaliel, from Nahaliel to Bamoth, <verse eID="Num.21.19"/>
       <verse sID="Num.21.20" osisID="Num.21.20"/> and from Bamoth to the wady in the re­gion of Moab at the head
        of the Pisgah plateau that looks down upon the Jeshimon. <verse eID="Num.21.20"/>
      </p>
      <p>
       <verse sID="Num.21.21" osisID="Num.21.21"/> Here Israel sent messengers to Sihon king of the Amorites,
        saying, <verse eID="Num.21.21"/>
       <verse sID="Num.21.22" osisID="Num.21.22"/> <q>Let us cross your land; we will not turn aside into any
        field or vineyard, we will not drink any water from your wells, but will march along the royal high road
        until we pass beyond your frontier.</q> <verse eID="Num.21.22"/>
       <verse sID="Num.21.23" osisID="Num.21.23"/> But Sihon would not allow Israel to pass across his territory.
        Sihon mustered all his forces and sallied out against Israel in the desert; he reached
        <milestone type="pb" n="177"/>
        Jahaz and there attacked Israel, <verse eID="Num.21.23"/>
       <verse sID="Num.21.24" osisID="Num.21.24"/>but Israel routed him, giving no quarter, and seized his country
        from Arnon to Jabbok on the north and the Ammonites on the east (Jazer marking the Ammonite frontier). <verse eID="Num.21.24"/>
       <verse sID="Num.21.25" osisID="Num.21.25"/> Israel captured all the local towns and lived in all the
        Amorite towns, in Heshbon and all its dependencies. <verse eID="Num.21.25"/>
       <verse sID="Num.21.26" osisID="Num.21.26"/> Heshbon was the capital of Sihon, king of the Amorites, who had
        fought against the former king of Moab and captured all his territory, from Jabbok to Arnon. <verse eID="Num.21.26"/>
       <verse sID="Num.21.27" osisID="Num.21.27"/> Hence the song and satire of the bards--
       <lg>
        <l> Come to Heshbon and rebuild it! </l>
        <l> Repair the capital of Sihon, if you can! </l>
       <verse eID="Num.21.27"/>
       <verse sID="Num.21.28" osisID="Num.21.28"/>
        <l> For the blaze began at Heshbon, </l>
        <l> at the capital of Sihon, </l>
        <l> till Ar of Moab was consumed, </l>
        <l> and Arnon’s heights devoured. </l>
       <verse eID="Num.21.28"/>
       <verse sID="Num.21.29" osisID="Num.21.29"/>
        <l> Poor Moabites! </l>
        <l> O forlorn folk of Kemdsh! </l>
        <l> The god has left his sons to flight, </l>
        <l> his daughters to a prisoner’s plight, </l>
       <verse eID="Num.21.29"/>
       <verse sID="Num.21.30" osisID="Num.21.30"/>
        <l> their children have perished </l>
        <l> from Heshbon to Dibon; </l>
        <l> and we ravaged till war’s fire </l>
        <l> was blown to Medeba. </l>
       </lg>
       <verse eID="Num.21.30"/>
       <verse sID="Num.21.31" osisID="Num.21.31"/>So Israel settled in the Amorite land. <verse eID="Num.21.31"/>
       <verse sID="Num.21.32" osisID="Num.21.32"/> Moses sent spies to Jazer, and Israel captured its depend­encies
        and evicted the local Amorites.] <verse eID="Num.21.32"/>
      </p>
     </hi>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Num.21.33" osisID="Num.21.33"/>They turned to march in the direction of Bashan. Og the king of
       Bashan sallied out against them, he and all his forces, to give battle at Edrei. <verse eID="Num.21.33"/>
      <verse sID="Num.21.34" osisID="Num.21.34"/> But the Eternal said to Moses, <q>Fear him not, I put him into
       your hands, with all his forces and his land; you shall handle him as you handled Sihon king of the
       Amorites at Heshbon.</q> <verse eID="Num.21.34"/>
      <verse sID="Num.21.35" osisID="Num.21.35"/> Whereupon they routed him and all his forces, till not a man was
       left him; then they seized his land. <verse eID="Num.21.35"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eId="Num.21"/>
    <chapter osisId="Num.22" sId="Num.22"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Num.22.2" osisID="Num.22.2"/>[Now Balak the son of Zippor watched all that Israel did to the
       Amorites; <verse eID="Num.22.2"/>
      <verse sID="Num.22.3" osisID="Num.22.3"/> Moab was in dread of the people, they were in such numbers.]
      <hi type="italic">
        Moab began to loathe the Israelites, <verse eID="Num.22.3"/>
       <verse sID="Num.22.4" osisID="Num.22.4"/> and Moab said to the sheikhs of Midian, <q>These hordes will lick
        up all the pasture round us, as an ox licks up the grass in the field.</q> Balak the son of Zippor was king
        of Moab at that time; <verse eID="Num.22.4"/>
       <verse sID="Num.22.5" osisID="Num.22.5"/> [he sent messengers to Balaam the son of Beor at Pethor on the
        Euphrates,] in the land of the Ammonites, with this summons: <q>Here is a people that has come from Egypt!
        They have been swarming over the face of the earth, and here they are now, settled opposite me! <verse eID="Num.22.5"/>
       <verse sID="Num.22.6" osisID="Num.22.6"/> Pray come and curse this people for me (for they are stronger than
        I am); then maybe I shall have power to defeat them and drive them out of the country. For I know that he
        whom you bless is blessed, and he whom you curse is cursed.</q> <verse eID="Num.22.6"/>
       <verse sID="Num.22.7" osisID="Num.22.7"/> So the sheikhs of Moab and the sheikhs of Midian started off,
        taking the usual fee for cursing, and, when they reached Balaam they gave him Balak’s message
      </hi>
       [.<verse eID="Num.22.7"/>
      <verse sID="Num.22.8" osisID="Num.22.8"/> He said to them, <q>Stay here overnight, and I will give you
       whatever answer the Eternal sends me.</q> So the chieftains of Moab remained be­side Balaam. <verse eID="Num.22.8"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Num.22.9" osisID="Num.22.9"/> God came and said to Balaam, <q>Who are these men with you?</q>
      <verse eID="Num.22.9"/>
      <verse sID="Num.22.10" osisID="Num.22.10"/> Balaam said to God, <q>Balak the son of Zippor, king of Moab,
       has sent for me],</q>
      <hi type="italic">
        saying, <verse eID="Num.22.10"/>
       <verse sID="Num.22.11" osisID="Num.22.11"/><q><q>Here is this people out of Egypt swarming over the face of
        the earth! Pray come and curse them for me; then maybe I can fight them and drive them out of the country</q></q>
       <verse eID="Num.22.11"/>
      </hi>
      <verse sID="Num.22.12" osisID="Num.22.12"/> God said to Balaam, <q>You must not go with
       <milestone type="pb" n="178"/> them? you must not curse that people, for they are blessed.</q> <verse eID="Num.22.12"/>
      <verse sID="Num.22.13" osisID="Num.22.13"/>So in the morning Balaam rose and told the chieftains of Balak to
       go back to their country, since the Eternal re­fused to let him go with them. <verse eID="Num.22.13"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Num.22.14" osisID="Num.22.14"/>The chieftains of Moab went back to Balak and told him that
       Balaam had refused to come. <verse eID="Num.22.14"/>
      <verse sID="Num.22.15" osisID="Num.22.15"/>Then Balak sent a larger num­ber of chieftains, more distinguished
       men, <verse eID="Num.22.15"/>
      <verse sID="Num.22.16" osisID="Num.22.16"/> who came to Balaam with this appeal from Balak the son of Zippor,
       <q>Pray allow nothing to keep you from coming to me].</q><verse eID="Num.22.16"/>
      <hi type="italic">
       <verse sID="Num.22.17" osisID="Num.22.17"/><q>I will pay you richly, and do whatever you tell me; pray come,
        then, and curse this people for me.</q> <verse eID="Num.22.17"/>
       <verse sID="Num.22.18" osisID="Num.22.18"/> Balaam re­plied to Balak’s courtiers, <q>Though Balak were to
        give me his very house full of silver and gold, I could not do a single thing beyond what the Eternal my
        God bids me.</q><verse eID="Num.22.18"/>
      </hi>
      <verse sID="Num.22.19" osisID="Num.22.19"/><q>[Do you re­main overnight with me also, till I find out what the
       Eternal has to say to me further.</q> <verse eID="Num.22.19"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Num.22.20" osisID="Num.22.20"/> In the night God came to Balaam and said to him, <q>As these men
       have come to call you away, go with them; only, you must do nothing except what I tell you.</q> <verse eID="Num.22.20"/>
      <verse sID="Num.22.21" osisID="Num.22.21"/> So Balaam rose in the morning, saddled his ass, and rode away
       with the chieftains of Moab.] <verse eID="Num.22.21"/>
      <hi type="italic">
       <verse sID="Num.22.22" osisID="Num.22.22"/> The anger of the Eter­nal blazed at him for going, and the
        Eternal’s angel placed him­self on the road to hinder him. <verse eID="Num.22.22"/>
      </hi>
     </p>
     <hi type="italic">
      <p>
       <verse sID="Num.22.23" osisID="Num.22.23"/> He was riding on an ass, accompanied by two servants, and when
        the ass saw the Eternal’s angel standing on the road with a drawn sword, she swerved aside to the open
        country. Balaam struck the ass, in order to turn her back into the road. <verse eID="Num.22.23"/>
       <verse sID="Num.22.24" osisID="Num.22.24"/> Where­upon the Eternal’s angel stood in a narrow lane between
        vine­yards, with a fence on one side and a fence on the other; <verse eID="Num.22.24"/>
       <verse sID="Num.22.25" osisID="Num.22.25"/> and when the ass saw the Eternal’s angel there, she pressed
        against the wall and crushed Balaam’s foot, till he struck her again. <verse eID="Num.22.25"/>
       <verse sID="Num.22.26" osisID="Num.22.26"/> Then the Eternal’s angel went farther ahead and stood in a place
        so narrow that there was no room to turn either to right or to left; <verse eID="Num.22.26"/>
       <verse sID="Num.22.27" osisID="Num.22.27"/> when the ass saw the Eternal’s angel there, she lay down under
        Balaam. Balaam’s anger blazed; he struck the ass with his stick. <verse eID="Num.22.27"/>
      </p>
      <p>
       <verse sID="Num.22.28" osisID="Num.22.28"/> But the Eternal opened the mouth of the ass, and she asked
        Balaam, <q>What have I done to you, that you have struck me these three times?</q> <verse eID="Num.22.28"/>
       <verse sID="Num.22.29" osisID="Num.22.29"/><q>You have played the fool with me,</q> said Balaam; <q>if only
        I had had a sword, I would have killed you.</q> <verse eID="Num.22.29"/>
       <verse sID="Num.22.30" osisID="Num.22.30"/> The ass answered, <q>Am I not your own ass, the ass you have
        always ridden? Have I ever been in the habit of playing the fool with you?</q> <q>No,</q> he said. <verse eID="Num.22.30"/>
       <verse sID="Num.22.31" osisID="Num.22.31"/> And then the Eternal opened his eyes; he saw the Eternal’s angel
        standing on the road with a drawn sword. Bowing his head, he fell upon his face. <verse eID="Num.22.31"/>
      </p>
     </hi>
     <p>
      <hi type="italic">
       <verse sID="Num.22.32" osisID="Num.22.32"/> The Eternal’s angel said to him, <q>Why have you struck your ass
        these three times? Here am I, sent to hinder you, at the sight of your headlong ways. <verse eID="Num.22.32"/>
       <verse sID="Num.22.33" osisID="Num.22.33"/> The ass saw me and swerved from me these three times; had she
        not swerved, I would certainly have slain you and spared her.</q> <verse eID="Num.22.33"/>
       <verse sID="Num.22.34" osisID="Num.22.34"/> Balaam answered the angel of the Eternal, <q>I have sinned; I
        did not know you were standing on the road to stop me. So now, if my going displeases you, I will turn
        back.</q> <verse eID="Num.22.34"/>
      </hi>
       <verse sID="Num.22.35" osisID="Num.22.35"/> [<q>Go with the men,</q> said the angel of the Eternal, 
        <q>but you shall say only
        <milestone type="pb" n="179"/>
        what I tell you.</q> So Balaam went with the chieftains of Balak. <verse eID="Num.22.35"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Num.22.36" osisID="Num.22.36"/>When Balak heard of Balaam’s arrival, he went out to meet him at
       Ir of Moab on the Arnon frontier, at its eastern end. <verse eID="Num.22.36"/>
      <verse sID="Num.22.37" osisID="Num.22.37"/> Balak said to Balaam, <q>Did I not send to summon you? Why did
       you not come? Am I not able to reward you?</q> <verse eID="Num.22.37"/>
      <verse sID="Num.22.38" osisID="Num.22.38"/>And Balaam said to Balak, <q>Well, I have come to you now. But
       have I the power to say a single word? Whatever word God gives me, that word I must speak.</q> <verse eID="Num.22.38"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Num.22.39" osisID="Num.22.39"/>Then Balaam went along with Balak as far as Kiriath-huzzoth,
      <verse eID="Num.22.39"/>
      <verse sID="Num.22.40" osisID="Num.22.40"/>where Balak sacrificed oxen and sheep, sending portions of their
       flesh to Balaam and the chieftains with him. <verse eID="Num.22.40"/>
      <verse sID="Num.22.41" osisID="Num.22.41"/> Next morning Balak took Balaam up to the heights of Baal, where
       he could catch sight of the fringe of Israel. <verse eID="Num.22.41"/>
    <chapter eId="Num.22"/>
    <chapter osisId="Num.23" sId="Num.23"/>
      <verse sID="Num.23.1" osisID="Num.23.1"/><q>Build seven altars for me here,</q> said Balaam to Balak, <q>and
       prepare seven bullocks and seven rams.</q> <verse eID="Num.23.1"/>
      <verse sID="Num.23.2" osisID="Num.23.2"/> Ba­lak did so, sacrificing on every altar one bullock and one ram.
      <verse eID="Num.23.2"/>
      <verse sID="Num.23.4" osisID="Num.23.4"/><q>Now,</q> he said, <q>I have pre­pared the seven altars and
       sacri­ficed on every altar one bullock and one ram.</q><verse eID="Num.23.4"/>
      <verse sID="Num.23.3" osisID="Num.23.3"/> Balaam then said to Balak, <q>Remain here beside your sacrifice,
       and I will go apart; perhaps God will come to meet me, and then I can tell you whatever he tells me.</q>
       So he went his way. <verse eID="Num.23.3"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Num.23.4" osisID="Num.23.4"/>God met Balaam, <verse eID="Num.23.4"/>
      <verse sID="Num.23.5" osisID="Num.23.5"/> and gave him a message, bidding him go back to Balak and telling
       him what to say. <verse eID="Num.23.5"/>
      <verse sID="Num.23.6" osisID="Num.23.6"/> When he got back, he found Balak beside his sacri­fice, Balak and
       all the chieftains of Moab. <verse eID="Num.23.6"/>
      <verse sID="Num.23.7" osisID="Num.23.7"/> Then he uttered these lines:
       <lg>
        <l> From Aram I am brought by Balak, </l>
        <l> from eastern hills by Moab’s king, </l>
        <l> to lay a curse on Jacob, </l>
        <l> and to denounce Israel. </l>
      <verse eID="Num.23.7"/>
      <verse sID="Num.23.8" osisID="Num.23.8"/>
        <l> But how can I curse whom God has not cursed, </l>
        <l> or denounce whom the Eternal has not denounced? </l>
      <verse eID="Num.23.8"/>
      <verse sID="Num.23.9" osisID="Num.23.9"/>
        <l> From these cliffs I scan them, </l>
        <l> from the mount I mark them, </l>
        <l> a folk who live secure, </l>
        <l> who reckon themselves above all races. </l>
      <verse eID="Num.23.9"/>
      <verse sID="Num.23.10" osisID="Num.23.10"/>
        <l> Who can count up Jacob’s numbers, </l>
        <l> who can reckon Israel’s myriads? </l>
        <l> Be it mine to die as these just men shall die, </l>
        <l> be my last end like theirs! </l>
      <verse eID="Num.23.10"/>
       </lg>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Num.23.11" osisID="Num.23.11"/><q>What is this you have done?</q> said Balak. <q>I brought you
       to curse my foes, and here you have done nothing but bless them!</q> <verse eID="Num.23.11"/>
      <verse sID="Num.23.12" osisID="Num.23.12"/> Balaam answered, <q>Must I not be careful to say whatever the
       Eternal gives me to say?</q> <verse eID="Num.23.12"/>
      <verse sID="Num.23.13" osisID="Num.23.13"/> Balak cried, <q>Pray come along to another place to view them,
       and curse them for me there!</q> <verse eID="Num.23.13"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Num.23.14" osisID="Num.23.14"/> So he took him to Gazerfield on the Pisgah plateau, where he
       built seven altars, sacrificing a bullock and a ram on each. <verse eID="Num.23.14"/>
      <verse sID="Num.23.15" osisID="Num.23.15"/> Balaam said, <q>Remain here beside your sacrifice, while I meet
       God yonder.</q> <verse eID="Num.23.15"/>
      <verse sID="Num.23.16" osisID="Num.23.16"/> God met Balaam and gave him a message, bidding him go back to
       Balak and telling him what to say. <verse eID="Num.23.16"/>
      <verse sID="Num.23.17" osisID="Num.23.17"/> When he got back he found Balak beside his sacrifice, Balak and
       the chief­tains of Moab. Balak asked him what the Eternal had said, <verse eID="Num.23.17"/>
      <verse sID="Num.23.18" osisID="Num.23.18"/> and he uttered these lines:
       <lg>
        <l> Balak, listen and attend, </l>
        <l> hear me, son of Zippor! </l>
      <verse eID="Num.23.18"/>
      <verse sID="Num.23.19" osisID="Num.23.19"/>
        <l> God is no man to break his word, </l>
        <l> no mortal to change his mind; </l>
        <l> he promises, and does he not per­form? </l>
        <l> Does he not carry out his word? </l>
      <verse eID="Num.23.19"/>
      <verse sID="Num.23.20" osisID="Num.23.20"/>
        <l> He bids me bless, </l>
        <milestone type="pb" n="180"/>
        <l> and bless I must--I cannot take it back. </l>
      <verse eID="Num.23.20"/>
      <verse sID="Num.23.21" osisID="Num.23.21"/>
        <l> I see no scathe for Jacob, </l>
        <l> I mark no misery for Israel; </l>
        <l> the Eternal their God is with them, </l>
        <l> they shout in honour of their King; </l>
      <verse eID="Num.23.21"/>
      <verse sID="Num.23.22" osisID="Num.23.22"/>
        <l> God, who brought them out of Egypt, </l>
        <l> bears all down before them. </l>
      <verse eID="Num.23.22"/>
      <verse sID="Num.23.23" osisID="Num.23.23"/>
        <l> Jacob needs no omens, </l>
        <l> Israel tries no magic arts; </l>
        <l> it is revealed to Jacob and to Israel </l>
        <l> what God will do. </l>
      <verse eID="Num.23.23"/>
      <verse sID="Num.23.24" osisID="Num.23.24"/>
        <l> The nation rises like a lioness, </l>
        <l> rearing like any lion; </l>
        <l> it never rests till it has crunched its prey, </l>
        <l> and drunk the victim’s blood. </l>
       </lg>
      <verse eID="Num.23.24"/>
      <verse sID="Num.23.25" osisID="Num.23.25"/> Balak then said to Balaam, <q>Neither curse them nor bless them
       at all!</q> <verse eID="Num.23.25"/>
      <verse sID="Num.23.26" osisID="Num.23.26"/> But Balaam re­plied, <q>Did I not tell you that I must do exactly
       as God told me?</q> <verse eID="Num.23.26"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eId="Num.23"/>
    <chapter osisId="Num.24" sId="Num.24"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Num.24.25" osisID="Num.24.25"/>So Balaam started for his home, and Balak also went away.] <verse eID="Num.24.25"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eId="Num.24"/>
    <chapter osisId="Num.23" sId="Num.23"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Num.23.27" osisID="Num.23.27"/> [[Then Balak said to Balaam, <q>Come and I will take you to
       another place; per­haps God will be pleased to let you curse them for me there.</q>]] <verse eID="Num.23.27"/>
      <hi type="italic">
       <verse sID="Num.23.28" osisID="Num.23.28"/> Balak took Balaam to the top of the Peor, looking down upon
        the Jeshimon. <verse eID="Num.23.28"/>
       <verse sID="Num.23.29" osisID="Num.23.29"/> <q>Build seven al­tars for me here,</q> said Balaam to Balak,
        <q>and prepare seven bullocks and seven rams.</q> <verse eID="Num.23.29"/>
       <verse sID="Num.23.30" osisID="Num.23.30"/> Balak did so, sacrificing on every altar one bullock and one
        ram. <verse eID="Num.23.30"/>
    <chapter eId="Num.23"/>
    <chapter osisId="Num.24" sId="Num.24"/>
       <verse sID="Num.24.1" osisID="Num.24.1"/>But when Balaam saw that the Eternal was pleased to bless Israel,
        he had no recourse to omens as usual, he gazed out on the desert; <verse eID="Num.24.1"/>
       <verse sID="Num.24.2" osisID="Num.24.2"/> as he looked, he saw Israel lying encamped, clan by clan, and the
        spirit of God came over him, <verse eID="Num.24.2"/>
       <verse sID="Num.24.3" osisID="Num.24.3"/> till he uttered these lines:
        <lq>
         <l> The oracle of Balaam son of Beor, </l>
         <l> the oracle of the seer, </l>
       <verse eID="Num.24.3"/>
       <verse sID="Num.24.4" osisID="Num.24.4"/>
         <l> the oracle of him who hears God speak, </l>
         <l> who sees a vision of the Almighty, </l>
         <l> sleeping, but awake in soul. </l>
       <verse eID="Num.24.4"/>
       <verse sID="Num.24.5" osisID="Num.24.5"/>
         <l> How fair, O Jacob, are your tents! </l>
         <l> how fair your homes, O Israel! </l>
       <verse eID="Num.24.5"/>
       <verse sID="Num.24.6" osisID="Num.24.6"/>
         <l> like glens that stretch afar, </l>
         <l> like gardens by a river, </l>
         <l> like oaks planted by the Eternal, </l>
         <l> like cedars by a stream. </l>
       <verse eID="Num.24.6"/>
       <verse sID="Num.24.7" osisID="Num.24.7"/>
         <l> Let nations tremble at their might, </l>
         <l> let many a people feel their power! </l>
         <l> Let their king be greater than Gog, </l>
         <l> let their kingdom triumph! </l>
       <verse eID="Num.24.7"/>
       <verse sID="Num.24.8" osisID="Num.24.8"/>
         <l> God, who brought them out of Egypt, </l>
         <l> bears all down before them. </l>
       <verse eID="Num.24.8"/>
       <verse sID="Num.24.9" osisID="Num.24.9"/>
         <l> They crouch, they lurk like a lion, </l>
         <l> like a lioness--who dare rouse them? </l>
       <verse eID="Num.24.9"/>
       <verse sID="Num.24.8" osisID="Num.24.8"/>
         <l> They eat up the opposing nations, </l>
         <l> and they crush their conquerors. </l>
       <verse eID="Num.24.8"/>
       <verse sID="Num.24.9" osisID="Num.24.9"/>
         <l> Blessed be all who bless you, </l>
         <l> and cursed all who curse you! </l>
       <verse eID="Num.24.9"/>
        </lq>
      </hi>
     </p>
     <hi type="italic">
      <p>
       <verse sID="Num.24.10" osisID="Num.24.10"/> This made Balak’s anger blaze against Balaam; he struck his
        hands together in contempt and told him, <q>I summoned you to curse my foes, and here you have blessed
        them these three times. <verse eID="Num.24.10"/>
       <verse sID="Num.24.11" osisID="Num.24.11"/> Be off with you; away home! In meant to pay you richly, and the
        Eternal has prevented you from receiving a reward!</q> <verse eID="Num.24.11"/>
       <verse sID="Num.24.12" osisID="Num.24.12"/><q>But,</q> said Balaam to Balak, <q>did not I tell your
        messengers <verse eID="Num.24.12"/>
       <verse sID="Num.24.13" osisID="Num.24.13"/> that even if Balak were to give me his very house full of
        silver and gold, I could not go beyond the word of the Eternal to do anything of my own accord, good or
        bad? Whatever the Eternal says, I say. <verse eID="Num.24.13"/>
       <verse sID="Num.24.14" osisID="Num.24.14"/> I go back indeed to my own people, but let me tell you what
        this people will do to your peo­ple in after days.</q> <verse eID="Num.24.14"/>
       <verse sID="Num.24.15" osisID="Num.24.15"/> Then he uttered these lines:
        <milestone type="pb" n="181"/>
        <lg>
         <l> The oracle of Balaam son of Beor, </l>
         <l> the oracle of the seer, </l>
       <verse eID="Num.24.15"/>
       <verse sID="Num.24.16" osisID="Num.24.16"/>
         <l> the oracle of him who hears God speak, </l>
         <l> who knows what the most High knows, </l>
         <l> who sees a vision of the Almighty, </l>
         <l> sleeping, but awake in soul! </l>
       <verse eID="Num.24.16"/>
       <verse sID="Num.24.17" osisID="Num.24.17"/>
         <l> I see them in the future far, </l>
         <l> I mark them in the days to come; </l>
         <l> a star of a king has come from Jacob, </l>
         <l> a mace has risen from Israel </l>
         <l> crashing in Moab’s head, </l>
         <l> the skull of these proud crea­tures! </l>
       <verse eID="Num.24.17"/>
       <verse sID="Num.24.18" osisID="Num.24.18"/>
         <l> Edom falls a prey to him, </l>
         <l> and Seir is dispossessed, </l>
         <l> as Israel wins the day, </l>
       <verse eID="Num.24.18"/>
       <verse sID="Num.24.19" osisID="Num.24.19"/>
         <l> and Jacob tramples on his foes. </l>
        </lg>
       <verse eID="Num.24.19"/>
      </p>
     </hi>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Num.24.20" osisID="Num.24.20"/>[[When he looked at Amalek he uttered these lines:
       <lg>
        <l> Amalek headed the nations; </l>
        <l> its end is to be destroyed. </l>
       </lg>
      <verse eID="Num.24.20"/>
      <verse sID="Num.24.21" osisID="Num.24.21"/> When he looked at the Kenites he uttered these lines:
       <lg>
        <l> Strong your seat is, Kenites, </l>
        <l> your eyry in the rocks! </l>
      <verse eID="Num.24.21"/>
      <verse sID="Num.24.22" osisID="Num.24.22"/>
        <l> Yet one day shall it be rifled. </l>
        <l> For how long? . . . </l>
      <verse eID="Num.24.22"/>
      <verse sID="Num.24.23" osisID="Num.24.23"/>
        <l> Sea-folk shall issue from the north, </l>
        <l> and ships swarm out of Cyprus, </l>
      <verse eID="Num.24.23"/>
      <verse sID="Num.24.24" osisID="Num.24.24"/>
        <l> for the ruin of Assyria over the Euphrates, </l>
        <l> till it in turn is overwhelmed.]] </l>
      <verse eID="Num.24.24"/>
       </lg>
     </p>
    <chapter eId="Num.24"/>
    <chapter osisId="Num.25" sId="Num.25"/>
     <hi type="italic">
      <p>
       <verse sID="Num.25.1" osisID="Num.25.1"/>When Israel was at Shittim, the people began to wanton with the
        women of Moab, <verse eID="Num.25.1"/>
       <verse sID="Num.25.2" osisID="Num.25.2"/> who invited them to the sacrifices of their gods; the peo­ple
        partook of their feasts and paid homage to their gods <verse eID="Num.25.2"/>
       <verse sID="Num.25.3" osisID="Num.25.3"/>[Israel attached themselves to the Baal of Peor,] till the
        Eter­nal's anger blazed against Israel, <verse eID="Num.25.3"/>
       <verse sID="Num.25.4" osisID="Num.25.4"/>and the Eternal bade Moses seize all the leaders of the people and
        execute them in broad day­light before the Eternal, in order to avert the Eternal’s hot anger from Israel.
       <verse eID="Num.25.4"/>
       <verse sID="Num.25.5" osisID="Num.25.5"/> [So Moses told all the sheriffs to put to death throughout their
        jurisdictions the men who had attached themselves to the Baal of Peor.] <verse eID="Num.25.5"/>
      </p>
     </hi>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Num.25.6" osisID="Num.25.6"/> Now one of the Israelites introduced into his family a Midianite
       woman, in face of Moses and all the community of Israel who were wailing at the entrance of the Trysting
       tent. <verse eID="Num.25.6"/>
      <verse sID="Num.25.7" osisID="Num.25.7"/> When Phinehas the son of Eleazar, a grandson of Aaron the priest,
       saw this, he left the assembly, seized a spear, <verse eID="Num.25.7"/>
      <verse sID="Num.25.8" osisID="Num.25.8"/> and following the Israelite into the tent stabbed the pair of
       them, the Israelite and the woman right through her belly. This stopped the death-stroke in Israel, <verse eID="Num.25.8"/>
      <verse sID="Num.25.9" osisID="Num.25.9"/> the death-stroke by which twenty-four thousand had died. <verse eID="Num.25.9"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Num.25.10" osisID="Num.25.10"/> Then said the Eternal to Moses, <verse eID="Num.25.10"/>
      <verse sID="Num.25.11" osisID="Num.25.11"/> <q>Phinehas the son of Eleazar, a grandson of Aaron the priest,
       has averted my wrath from the Israelites by resenting the sin among you even as I re­sent it;  hence I have
       not put an end to Israel in my resentment.<verse eID="Num.25.11"/>
      <verse sID="Num.25.12" osisID="Num.25.12"/> So proclaim that I pledge him my favour, <verse eID="Num.25.12"/>
      <verse sID="Num.25.13" osisID="Num.25.13"/> pledging him and his descendants a perpetual priest­hood, for
       having resented sin on behalf of his God and having made expiation for the Israel­ites.</q> <verse eID="Num.25.13"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Num.25.14" osisID="Num.25.14"/> The Israelite who was killed with the Midianite woman was called
       Zimri the son of Salu, a chieftain belonging to one of the families of Simeon. <verse eID="Num.25.14"/>
      <verse sID="Num.25.15" osisID="Num.25.15"/> The Midianite woman who was killed was called Cozbi, the
       daughter of Zur, head of a clan or family in Midian. <verse eID="Num.25.15"/>
      <verse sID="Num.25.16" osisID="Num.25.16"/> [[The Eternal said to Moses, <verse eID="Num.25.16"/>
      <verse sID="Num.25.17" osisID="Num.25.17"/> <q>Attack the Midianites and crush them, <verse eID="Num.25.17"/>
      <verse sID="Num.25.18" osisID="Num.25.18"/> for they made an attack on you with their subtle intrigues over
       Peor and over their country­woman Cozbi, the daughter of a Midianite chief, who was
       <milestone type="pb" n="182"/>
       killed when the death-stroke fell on account of Peor.</q>]] <verse eID="Num.25.18"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eId="Num.25"/>
    <chapter osisId="Num.26" sId="Num.26"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Num.26.1" osisID="Num.26.1"/>After the death-stroke, the Eternal bade Moses and Eleazar the son
       of Aaron the priest <verse eID="Num.26.1"/>
      <verse sID="Num.26.2" osisID="Num.26.2"/> count the entire commu­nity of the Israelites over twenty years of
       age, clan by clan, all Is­raelites who were able for active service. <verse eID="Num.26.2"/>
      <verse sID="Num.26.3" osisID="Num.26.3"/> So Moses and Eleazar the priest numbered them on the steppes of
       Moab beside the Jordan at Jericho, <verse eID="Num.26.3"/>
      <verse sID="Num.26.4" osisID="Num.26.4"/> counting all over twenty, as the Eternal had commanded Moses.
     </p>
     <p>
       The Israelites who left Egypt were as follows: <verse eID="Num.26.4"/>
      <verse sID="Num.26.5" osisID="Num.26.5"/>There was Reu­ben the first-born of Israel; his sons were Hanok head
       of the Hanokite sept, Pallu head of the Palluite sept, <verse eID="Num.26.5"/>
      <verse sID="Num.26.6" osisID="Num.26.6"/> Hezron head of the Hezronite sept, and Karmi head of the Karmite
       sept; <verse eID="Num.26.6"/>
      <verse sID="Num.26.7" osisID="Num.26.7"/> these were the septs of Reuben, numbering forty-three thousand
       seven hundred and thirty men. <verse eID="Num.26.7"/>
      <verse sID="Num.26.8" osisID="Num.26.8"/> (The son of Pallu was Eliab, <verse eID="Num.26.8"/>
      <verse sID="Num.26.9" osisID="Num.26.9"/> and Eliab’s sons were Nemuel, Dathan, and Abiram, the Dathan and
       Abiram, selected from the community, who opposed Moses and Aaron along with Korah’s company of rebels
       against the Eternal. <verse eID="Num.26.9"/>
      <verse sID="Num.26.10" osisID="Num.26.10"/> But the earth yawned and swallowed them up along with Korah,
       when that company perished, when fire burned up two hun­dred and fifty men, as a warning. <verse eID="Num.26.10"/>
      <verse sID="Num.26.11" osisID="Num.26.11"/> However, the sons of Korah did not die out.) <verse eID="Num.26.11"/>
      <verse sID="Num.26.12" osisID="Num.26.12"/> The sons of Simeon, sept by sept, were Nemuel head of the
       Nemuelite sept, Jamin head of the Jaminite sept, Jachin head of the Jachinite sept, <verse eID="Num.26.12"/>
      <verse sID="Num.26.13" osisID="Num.26.13"/> Zerah head of the Zerahite sept, and Shaul head of the Shaulite
       sept; <verse eID="Num.26.13"/>
      <verse sID="Num.26.14" osisID="Num.26.14"/> these were the septs of Simeon, twenty-two thousand two hun­dred
       men. <verse eID="Num.26.14"/>
      <verse sID="Num.26.15" osisID="Num.26.15"/> The sons of Gad, sept by sept, were Zephon head of the
       Zephonite sept, Haggi head of the Haggite sept, Shuni head of the Shunite sept, <verse eID="Num.26.15"/>
      <verse sID="Num.26.16" osisID="Num.26.16"/> Ozni head of the Oznite sept, Eri head of the Erite sept, <verse eID="Num.26.16"/>
      <verse sID="Num.26.17" osisID="Num.26.17"/> Arod head of the Arodite sept, and Areli head of the Arelite
       sept; <verse eID="Num.26.17"/>
      <verse sID="Num.26.18" osisID="Num.26.18"/> these were the septs of Gad, numbering forty thousand five
       hundred men. <verse eID="Num.26.18"/>
      <verse sID="Num.26.19" osisID="Num.26.19"/> The sons of Judah were Er and Onan (but they died in Canaan), <verse eID="Num.26.19"/>
      <verse sID="Num.26.20" osisID="Num.26.20"/> then Shelah the head of the Shelahite sept, Perez the head of
       the Perezite sept, and Zerah the head of the Zerahite sept, <verse eID="Num.26.20"/>
      <verse sID="Num.26.21" osisID="Num.26.21"/> with the sons of Perez, Hezron the head of the Hezronite sept
       and Hamul the head of the Hamulite sept; <verse eID="Num.26.21"/>
      <verse sID="Num.26.22" osisID="Num.26.22"/> these were the septs of Judah, numbering seventy-six thousand
       five hundred men. <verse eID="Num.26.22"/>
      <verse sID="Num.26.23" osisID="Num.26.23"/> The sons of Issachar, sept by sept, were Tola the head of the
       Tolaite sept, Puvah the head of the Puvite sept, <verse eID="Num.26.23"/>
      <verse sID="Num.26.24" osisID="Num.26.24"/> Jashub the head of the Jashubite sept, and Shimron the head of
       the Shimronite sept; <verse eID="Num.26.24"/>
      <verse sID="Num.26.25" osisID="Num.26.25"/> these were the septs of Issachar, numbering sixty-four thousand
       three hun­dred men. <verse eID="Num.26.25"/>
      <verse sID="Num.26.26" osisID="Num.26.26"/> The sons of Zebulun, sept by sept, were Sered the head of the
       Seredite sept, Elon the head of the Elonite sept, and Jahleel the head of the Jahleelite sept; <verse eID="Num.26.26"/>
      <verse sID="Num.26.27" osisID="Num.26.27"/> these were the septs of Zebulun, num­bering sixty thousand five
       hundred men. <verse eID="Num.26.27"/>
      <verse sID="Num.26.28" osisID="Num.26.28"/> The sons of Joseph, sept by sept, were Manasseh and Ephraim;
      <verse eID="Num.26.28"/>
      <verse sID="Num.26.29" osisID="Num.26.29"/> Manasseh’s son Machir, the head of the Machirite sept, was the
       father of Gilead the head of the Gileadite sept, <verse eID="Num.26.29"/>
      <verse sID="Num.26.30" osisID="Num.26.30"/> and the sons of Gilead were Jezer the head of the Jezerite sept,
       Helek the head of the Helekite sept, <verse eID="Num.26.30"/>
      <verse sID="Num.26.31" osisID="Num.26.31"/> Asriel the head of the Asrielite sept,
       <milestone type="pb" n="183"/>
       Shechem the head of the Shechemite sept,
      <verse eID="Num.26.31"/>
      <verse sID="Num.26.32" osisID="Num.26.32"/> Shemeda the head of the Shemedaite sept, and Hepher the head of
       the Hepherite sept <verse eID="Num.26.32"/>
      <verse sID="Num.26.33" osisID="Num.26.33"/> (Zelophehad the son of Hepher had no sons, only daughters, and
       his daugh­ters were called Mahlah, Noah, Hoglah, Milkah, and Tirzah); <verse eID="Num.26.33"/>
      <verse sID="Num.26.34" osisID="Num.26.34"/> these were the septs of Manasseh, numbering fifty-two thousand
       seven hundred men. <verse eID="Num.26.34"/>
      <verse sID="Num.26.35" osisID="Num.26.35"/> The sons of Ephraim, sept by sept, were Shuthelah--the head of
       the Shuthelaite sept, Becher the head of the Becherite sept, and Tahan the head of the Tahanite sept, <verse eID="Num.26.35"/>
      <verse sID="Num.26.36" osisID="Num.26.36"/> Shuthelah’s son being Eran the head of the Eranite sept; <verse eID="Num.26.36"/>
      <verse sID="Num.26.37" osisID="Num.26.37"/> these were the septs of Ephraim, numbering thirty-two thousand
       five hun­dred men. Such were the sons of Joseph, sept by sept. <verse eID="Num.26.37"/>
      <verse sID="Num.26.38" osisID="Num.26.38"/> The sons of Benjamin, sept by sept, were Bela the head of the
       Belaite sept, Ashbel the head of the Ashbelite sept, Ahiram the head of the Ahiramite sept, <verse eID="Num.26.38"/>
      <verse sID="Num.26.39" osisID="Num.26.39"/> Shephupham the head of the Shephupham sept, and Hupham the head
       of the Huphamite sept, <verse eID="Num.26.39"/>
      <verse sID="Num.26.40" osisID="Num.26.40"/>Bela being the father of Ard, the head of the Ardite sept, and of
       Naaman the head of the Naamite sept; <verse eID="Num.26.40"/>
      <verse sID="Num.26.41" osisID="Num.26.41"/> these were the septs of Benjamin, numbering forty-five thousand
       six hundred men. <verse eID="Num.26.41"/>
      <verse sID="Num.26.42" osisID="Num.26.42"/> The son of Dan was Shuham, head of the Shuhamite sept; <verse eID="Num.26.42"/>
      <verse sID="Num.26.43" osisID="Num.26.43"/> the Shuhamite sept numbered sixty-four thousand four hundred
       men. <verse eID="Num.26.43"/>
      <verse sID="Num.26.44" osisID="Num.26.44"/> The sons of Asher were, sept by sept, Imnah the head of the
       Imnite sept, Ishvi the head of the Ishvite sept, and Beriah the head of the Beriite sept, <verse eID="Num.26.44"/>
      <verse sID="Num.26.45" osisID="Num.26.45"/> Beriah being the father of Heber head of the Heberite sept, and
       of Malchiel head of the Malchielite sept. <verse eID="Num.26.45"/>
      <verse sID="Num.26.46" osisID="Num.26.46"/> (Asher had a daughter called Sarah.) <verse eID="Num.26.46"/>
      <verse sID="Num.26.47" osisID="Num.26.47"/> These were the sons of Asher, sept by sept, numbering
       fifty-three thousand four hundred men. <verse eID="Num.26.47"/>
      <verse sID="Num.26.48" osisID="Num.26.48"/> The sons of Naphtali, sept by sept, were Jahzeel head of the
       Jahzeelite sept, Guni head of the Gunite sept, <verse eID="Num.26.48"/>
      <verse sID="Num.26.49" osisID="Num.26.49"/> Jezer head of the Jezerite sept, and Shillem head of the
       Shillemite sept; <verse eID="Num.26.49"/>
      <verse sID="Num.26.50" osisID="Num.26.50"/> these were the septs of Naphtali, numbering forty-five thousand
       four hun­dred men. <verse eID="Num.26.50"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Num.26.51" osisID="Num.26.51"/> The total number of the Israelites was six hundred and one
       thousand seven hundred and thirty. <verse eID="Num.26.51"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Num.26.52" osisID="Num.26.52"/>The Eternal ordered Moses <verse eID="Num.26.52"/>
      <verse sID="Num.26.53" osisID="Num.26.53"/> to have the country divided up among them according to their
       respective numbers; <verse eID="Num.26.53"/>
      <verse sID="Num.26.54" osisID="Num.26.54"/> a large clan was to receive a large property, and a small clan
       a small property, each being assigned a holding according to the number of its members. <verse eID="Num.26.54"/>
      <verse sID="Num.26.55" osisID="Num.26.55"/> The country was to be divided up by lot, and individuals were to
       hold property as members of their septs; <verse eID="Num.26.55"/>
      <verse sID="Num.26.56" osisID="Num.26.56"/> the common possession of Israel was to be divided by lot between
       the larger and the smaller clans. <verse eID="Num.26.56"/>
      <verse sID="Num.26.57" osisID="Num.26.57"/> In the census the Levites, sept by sept, included the
       Gershonite sept of Gershon, the Kohathite sept of Kohath, and the Merarite sept of Merari; <verse eID="Num.26.57"/>
      <verse sID="Num.26.58" osisID="Num.26.58"/> the Levite septs were the Libnites, the Hebronites, the
       Mahlites, the Mushites, and the Korahites. Kohath was the father of Amram, <verse eID="Num.26.58"/>
      <verse sID="Num.26.59" osisID="Num.26.59"/> who married Jochebed a daughter of Levi, born in Egypt, and she
       bore Aaron, Moses, and Miriam their sister. <verse eID="Num.26.59"/>
      <verse sID="Num.26.60" osisID="Num.26.60"/> Aaron was the father of Nadab, Abihu, Eleazar, and Ithamar <verse eID="Num.26.60"/>
      <verse sID="Num.26.61" osisID="Num.26.61"/> (Nadab and Abihu
       <milestone type="pb" n="184"/>
       died for having offered irregular fire before the Eternal). <verse eID="Num.26.61"/>
      <verse sID="Num.26.62" osisID="Num.26.62"/> Their total number was twenty-three thousand, counting every
       male over a month old. Their num­ber was not included in that of Israel, as they received no property in
       Israel. <verse eID="Num.26.62"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Num.26.63" osisID="Num.26.63"/> [[Such were the men counted by Moses and Eleazar the priest as
       they took the census of the Israelites on the steppes of Moab beside the Jordan opposite Jericho. <verse eID="Num.26.63"/>
      <verse sID="Num.26.64" osisID="Num.26.64"/> There was not a man among them who had been in the census taken
       by Moses and Aaron the priest, when they counted the Israelites in the desert of Sinai; <verse eID="Num.26.64"/>
      <verse sID="Num.26.65" osisID="Num.26.65"/> the Eternal had declared that they would cer­tainly perish in the
       desert, and not a man of them was left, except Caleb the son of Je phunneh and Joshua the son of Nun.]] <verse eID="Num.26.65"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eId="Num.26"/>
   </div>