   <div type="book" osisID="Num">
    <milestone type="pb" n="147"/>
    <chapter osisId="Num.1" sId="Num.1"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Num.1.1" osisID="Num.1.1"/>On the first day of the second month in the second year after they had
       left the land of Egypt, the Eternal spoke to Moses in the desert of Sinai, within the Trysting tent, bidding him
       and Aaron <verse eID="Num.1.1"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.2" osisID="Num.1.2"/> count up the total mem­bers of the community of Israel, clan by clan,
       family by family, and also number all the male individuals, head by head; <verse eID="Num.1.2"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.3" osisID="Num.1.3"/> all Israelites over twenty years who were able for active service were to
       be numbered, company by company. <verse eID="Num.1.3"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.4" osisID="Num.1.4"/> They were to take a representative of every clan, in each case the head
       of the family, <verse eID="Num.1.4"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.5" osisID="Num.1.5"/> the names of the representa­tives were to be as follows. From Reuben,
       Elizur the son of Shedeur; <verse eID="Num.1.5"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.6" osisID="Num.1.6"/> from Simeon, Shelumiel the son of Zurishaddai; <verse eID="Num.1.6"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.7" osisID="Num.1.7"/> from Judah, Nahshon the son of Amminadab; <verse eID="Num.1.7"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.8" osisID="Num.1.8"/> from Issachar, Nathaniel the son of Zuar; <verse eID="Num.1.8"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.9" osisID="Num.1.9"/> from Zebulun, Eliab the son of Helon; <verse eID="Num.1.9"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.10" osisID="Num.1.10"/> from the Josephites -- Ephraim, Elishama the son of Ammihud, and from
       Manasseh, Gamaliel the son of Pedahzur; <verse eID="Num.1.10"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.11" osisID="Num.1.11"/> from Benjamin, Abidan the son of Gideoni; <verse eID="Num.1.11"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.12" osisID="Num.1.12"/> from Dan, Ahiezer the son of Ammishaddai; <verse eID="Num.1.12"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.13" osisID="Num.1.13"/> from Asher, Pagiel the son of Ochran; <verse eID="Num.1.13"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.14" osisID="Num.1.14"/> from Gad, Eliasaph the son of Reuel; <verse eID="Num.1.14"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.15" osisID="Num.1.15"/> from Naphtali, Ahira the son of Enan. <verse eID="Num.1.15"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.16" osisID="Num.1.16"/> Such were the men selected from the com­munity, the leaders of their
       an­cestral clans, who were at the head of the septs in Israel. <verse eID="Num.1.16"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.17" osisID="Num.1.17"/> Moses and Aaron took these men who have been named, <verse eID="Num.1.17"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.18" osisID="Num.1.18"/> and mustered all the community on the first day of the second month,
       when they registered themselves, clan by clan, family by family, and had every indi­vidual over twenty numbered, <verse eID="Num.1.18"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.19" osisID="Num.1.19"/> head by head, as the Eternal had ordered.  Moses numbered them in the
       desert thus.<verse eID="Num.1.19"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Num.1.20" osisID="Num.1.20"/> The descendants of Reuben, Israel’s eldest son, reckoned clan by clan,
       family by family, with every male indi­vidual over twenty years, head by head, <verse eID="Num.1.20"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.21" osisID="Num.1.21"/> all the Reubenites who were able for active service amounted to
       forty-six thousand five hundred. <verse eID="Num.1.21"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.22" osisID="Num.1.22"/> The descendants of Simeon, reckoned clan by clan, family by family,
       with every male individual over twenty years, <verse eID="Num.1.22"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.23" osisID="Num.1.23"/> all the Simeonites who were able for active service amounted to
       fifty-nine thousand three hundred. <verse eID="Num.1.23"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.24" osisID="Num.1.24"/> The descendants of Gad, reckoned clan by clan, family by family, with
       every male individual over twenty years numbered, head by head, <verse eID="Num.1.24"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.25" osisID="Num.1.25"/> all the Gadites who were able for active service amounted to
       forty-five thousand six hundred and fifty. <verse eID="Num.1.25"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.26" osisID="Num.1.26"/> The descendants of Judah, reckoned clan by clan, family by family, with
       every male individual over twenty years, head by head, <verse eID="Num.1.26"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.27" osisID="Num.1.27"/> all the Judahites who were able for active service amounted to
       seventy-four thousand six hun­dred. <verse eID="Num.1.27"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.28" osisID="Num.1.28"/> The descendants of Issachar, reckoned clan by clan, family by family,
       with every male individual over twenty years, head by head, <verse eID="Num.1.28"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.29" osisID="Num.1.29"/> all the Issacharites who were able for active service amounted to
       fifty-four thousand four hun­dred. <verse eID="Num.1.29"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.30" osisID="Num.1.30"/> The descendants of Zebulun, reckoned clan by clan, family by family,
       with every male individual over twenty years, head by head,
      <verse eID="Num.1.30"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.31" osisID="Num.1.31"/> all the 
       <milestone type="pb" n="148"/>
       Zebulunites who were able for ac­tive service amounted to fifty-seven thousand four hundred. <verse eID="Num.1.31"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.32" osisID="Num.1.32"/> As for the Josephites--the de­scendants of Ephraim, reckoned clan by
       clan, family by family, with every male individual over twenty, head by head, <verse eID="Num.1.32"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.33" osisID="Num.1.33"/> all the Ephraimites who were able for active service amounted to forty
       thousand five hundred; <verse eID="Num.1.33"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.34" osisID="Num.1.34"/> the de­scendants of Manasseh, reck­oned clan by clan, family by family,
       with every male indi­vidual over twenty years, head by head, <verse eID="Num.1.34"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.35" osisID="Num.1.35"/> all the Manassites who were able for active service amounted to
       thirty-two thousand two hundred. <verse eID="Num.1.35"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.36" osisID="Num.1.36"/> The de­scendants of Benjamin, reck­oned clan by clan, family by family,
       with every male indi­vidual over twenty years, head by head, <verse eID="Num.1.36"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.37" osisID="Num.1.37"/> all the Benjamites who were able for active service amount to
       thirty-five thousand four hundred. <verse eID="Num.1.37"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.38" osisID="Num.1.38"/> The de­scendants of Dan, reckoned clan by clan, family by family, with
       every male descendant over twenty years, head by head, <verse eID="Num.1.38"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.39" osisID="Num.1.39"/> all the Danites who were able for active service amounted to sixty-two
       thousand seven hundred. <verse eID="Num.1.39"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.40" osisID="Num.1.40"/> The descendants of Asher, reckoned clan by clan, family by family, with
       every male individual over twenty years, head by head, <verse eID="Num.1.40"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.41" osisID="Num.1.41"/> all the Asherites who were able for active service amounted to
       forty-one thousand five hundred. <verse eID="Num.1.41"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.42" osisID="Num.1.42"/> The descendants of Naphtali, reck­oned clan by clan, family by family,
       with every male individual over twenty years, head by head, <verse eID="Num.1.42"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.43" osisID="Num.1.43"/> all the Naphtalites who were able for active service amounted to
       fifty-three thou­sand four hundred. <verse eID="Num.1.43"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Num.1.44" osisID="Num.1.44"/>Such were those whom Moses and Aaron counted up, along with the leaders
       of Israel, twelve men, each of whom represented his ancestral house. <verse eID="Num.1.44"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.45" osisID="Num.1.45"/> The number of the Israelites, family by family, over twenty years, who
       were able for active service, <verse eID="Num.1.45"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.46" osisID="Num.1.46"/> the total number was six hundred and three thousand five hun­dred and
       fifty. <verse eID="Num.1.46"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Num.1.47" osisID="Num.1.47"/> The ancestral clan of the Levites was not included, how­ever; <verse eID="Num.1.47"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.48" osisID="Num.1.48"/> the Eternal told Moses <verse eID="Num.1.48"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.49" osisID="Num.1.49"/> that he was to leave out the clan of Levi, and not to count its total
       among the Israelites, <verse eID="Num.1.49"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.50" osisID="Num.1.50"/> but to put the Levites in charge of the Dwelling of the Presence, with
       all its equipment and all its belongings; they were to carry the Dwelling and its equipment, to attend to it,
       and to encamp round it; <verse eID="Num.1.50"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.51" osisID="Num.1.51"/> whenever the Dwelling had to be moved, the Levites were to take it down,
       and when­ever it had to be pitched, the Levites were to erect it; any outsider who dared to interfere was to be
       put to death. <verse eID="Num.1.51"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.52" osisID="Num.1.52"/> The Israelites were to pitch their tents according to their respec­tive
       camps and companies, in military order, <verse eID="Num.1.52"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.53" osisID="Num.1.53"/> but the Levites were to pitch their tents round the Dwelling of the
       Presence, in order to avert any outburst of divine anger against the com­munity of Israel; they were to take
       charge of the Dwelling. <verse eID="Num.1.53"/>
      <verse sID="Num.1.54" osisID="Num.1.54"/> The Israelites carried this out; they obeyed every order given by the
       Eternal to Moses. <verse eID="Num.1.54"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eId="Num.1"/>
    <chapter osisId="Num.2" sId="Num.2"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Num.2.1" osisID="Num.2.1"/>The Eternal told Moses and Aaron <verse eID="Num.2.1"/>
      <verse sID="Num.2.2" osisID="Num.2.2"/> that the Israelites were to pitch their tents according to their
       respective companies and the pennons of their clans, fac­ing the Trysting tent on every side.
      <verse eID="Num.2.2"/>
      <verse sID="Num.2.3" osisID="Num.2.3"/> Those who encamped on the eastern side, towards the dawn, were to be
       the companies
       <milestone type="pb" n="149"/>
       belonging to Judah, led by Nahshon the son of Amminadab;
      <verse eID="Num.2.3"/>
      <verse sID="Num.2.4" osisID="Num.2.4"/> his host numbered in all seventy-four thousand six hundred. <verse eID="Num.2.4"/>
      <verse sID="Num.2.5" osisID="Num.2.5"/>Next to him the clan of Issachar was to encamp, led by Nathaniel the son
       of Zuar; <verse eID="Num.2.5"/>
      <verse sID="Num.2.6" osisID="Num.2.6"/> his host numbered in all fifty-four thousand four hundred. <verse eID="Num.2.6"/>
      <verse sID="Num.2.7" osisID="Num.2.7"/> Then the clan of Zebulun, led by Eliab the son of Helon;
      <verse eID="Num.2.7"/>
      <verse sID="Num.2.8" osisID="Num.2.8"/>
       his host numbered in all fifty-seven thousand four hundred.
      <verse eID="Num.2.8"/>
      <verse sID="Num.2.9" osisID="Num.2.9"/> These battalions of Judah, numbering a hundred and eighty-six thou­sand
       four hundred, were to start on the march first. <verse eID="Num.2.9"/>
      <verse sID="Num.2.10" osisID="Num.2.10"/> On the south side the companies be­longing to Reuben were to en­camp,
       led by Elizur the son of Shedeur; <verse eID="Num.2.10"/>
      <verse sID="Num.2.11" osisID="Num.2.11"/> his host numbered in all forty-six thousand five hundred. <verse eID="Num.2.11"/>
      <verse sID="Num.2.12" osisID="Num.2.12"/> Next to him the clan of Simeon was to encamp, led by Shelumiel the son
       of Zurishaddai; <verse eID="Num.2.12"/>
      <verse sID="Num.2.13" osisID="Num.2.13"/> his host numbered in all fifty-nine thousand three hundred. <verse eID="Num.2.13"/>
      <verse sID="Num.2.14" osisID="Num.2.14"/> Then the clan of Gad, led by Eliasaph the son of Reuel; <verse eID="Num.2.14"/>
      <verse sID="Num.2.15" osisID="Num.2.15"/> his host numbered forty-five thousand six hundred and fifty. <verse eID="Num.2.15"/>
      <verse sID="Num.2.16" osisID="Num.2.16"/>These battalions of Reuben, numbering a hundred and fifty-one thousand
       four hundred and fifty, were to start second on the march. <verse eID="Num.2.16"/>
      <verse sID="Num.2.17" osisID="Num.2.17"/> Then the Trysting tent was to advance, along with the host of Levites,
       in the centre of the other hosts; they were to march, as they encamped, in their respective companies. <verse eID="Num.2.17"/>
      <verse sID="Num.2.18" osisID="Num.2.18"/> On the western side the com­panies belonging to Ephraim were to encamp,
       led by Elishama the son of Arnmihud; <verse eID="Num.2.18"/>
      <verse sID="Num.2.19" osisID="Num.2.19"/> his host numbered in all forty thousand five hundred. <verse eID="Num.2.19"/>
      <verse sID="Num.2.20" osisID="Num.2.20"/> Next to him the clan of Manasseh was to encamp, led by Gamaliel the
       son of Pedahzur; <verse eID="Num.2.20"/>
      <verse sID="Num.2.21" osisID="Num.2.21"/> his host numbered in all thirty-two thousand two hun­dred. <verse eID="Num.2.21"/>
      <verse sID="Num.2.22" osisID="Num.2.22"/> Then the clan of Benjamin, led by Abidan the son of Gideoni; <verse eID="Num.2.22"/>
      <verse sID="Num.2.23" osisID="Num.2.23"/> his host numbered in all thirty-five thousand four hun­dred. <verse eID="Num.2.23"/>
      <verse sID="Num.2.24" osisID="Num.2.24"/> These battalions of Ephraim, numbering a hundred and eight thousand
       one hundred, were to start third on the march. <verse eID="Num.2.24"/>
      <verse sID="Num.2.25" osisID="Num.2.25"/> On the northern side the companies belonging to Dan were to encamp,
       led by Ahiezer the son of Ammishaddai; <verse eID="Num.2.25"/>
      <verse sID="Num.2.26" osisID="Num.2.26"/> his host numbered in all sixty-two thousand seven hundred. <verse eID="Num.2.26"/>
      <verse sID="Num.2.27" osisID="Num.2.27"/> Next to him the clan of Asher was to encamp, led by Pagiel the son of
       Ochran; <verse eID="Num.2.27"/>
      <verse sID="Num.2.28" osisID="Num.2.28"/> his host numbered in all forty-one thousand five hundred. <verse eID="Num.2.28"/>
      <verse sID="Num.2.29" osisID="Num.2.29"/> Then the clan of Naphtali, led by Ahira the son of Enan; <verse eID="Num.2.29"/>
      <verse sID="Num.2.30" osisID="Num.2.30"/> his host numbered fifty-three thou­sand four hundred. <verse eID="Num.2.30"/>
      <verse sID="Num.2.31" osisID="Num.2.31"/> These battalions of Dan, numbering a hundred and fifty-seven thou­sand
       six hundred, were to march company by company in the rear. <verse eID="Num.2.31"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Num.2.32" osisID="Num.2.32"/> Such were the Israelites counted by their families; those who were
       numbered by com­panies in their respective camps amounted to six hundred and three thousand five hundred and
       fifty. <verse eID="Num.2.32"/>
      <verse sID="Num.2.33" osisID="Num.2.33"/> But, by order of the Eternal to Moses, the Levites were not included
       in the reckon­ing of the Israelites. <verse eID="Num.2.33"/>
      <verse sID="Num.2.34" osisID="Num.2.34"/> The Israelites carried this out; exactly as the Eternal had ordered
       Moses, so they encamped in their respective companies and marched, clan by clan, family by family. <verse eID="Num.2.34"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eId="Num.2"/>
   </div>