   <div type="book" osisID="Ruth">
    <milestone type="pb" n="301"/>
    <chapter osisID="Ruth.1" sID="Ruth.1"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Ruth.1.1" osisID="Ruth.1.1"/>In the days when the heroes governed, there was a fam­ine in the land, and a
       man of Bethlehem in Judah went to re­side in the country of Moab, along with his wife and his two sons; <verse eID="Ruth.1.1"/>
      <verse sID="Ruth.1.2" osisID="Ruth.1.2"/> the man’s name was Elimelek, his wife’s name was Naomi, and his two sons were
       called Mahlon and Kilion, all Ephrathites belonging to Beth­lehem in Judah. They went to the country of Moab and
       re­mained there. <verse eID="Ruth.1.2"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Ruth.1.3" osisID="Ruth.1.3"/> Elimelek the husband of Naomi died, leaving her with her two sons, <verse eID="Ruth.1.3"/>
      <verse sID="Ruth.1.4" osisID="Ruth.1.4"/> who married women of Moab, the one called Orpah and the other Ruth. After they
       had stayed there for about ten years <verse eID="Ruth.1.4"/>
      <verse sID="Ruth.1.5" osisID="Ruth.1.5"/> both Mahlon and Kilion died, so that Naomi was bereft of her two children and
       her husband. <verse eID="Ruth.1.5"/>
      <verse sID="Ruth.1.6" osisID="Ruth.1.6"/> Then, as she heard in the country of Moab that the Eternal had remem­bered
       kindly to give his people food, she started home with her daughters-in-law from the country of Moab. <verse eID="Ruth.1.6"/>
      <verse sID="Ruth.1.7" osisID="Ruth.1.7"/> She went from the place where she was, along with her two daughters-in-law;
       but, as they were setting out to go back to the land of Judah, <verse eID="Ruth.1.7"/>
      <verse sID="Ruth.1.8" osisID="Ruth.1.8"/> Naomi said to her two daugh­ters-in-law, <q>You go back, each of you, to her
       mother’s house. May the Eternal treat you kindly, as you have treated the dead and myself! <verse eID="Ruth.1.8"/>
      <verse sID="Ruth.1.9" osisID="Ruth.1.9"/> May the Eternal let each of you find a settlement in the house of a husband!</q>
       Then she kissed them. But they wept loudly <verse eID="Ruth.1.9"/>
      <verse sID="Ruth.1.10" osisID="Ruth.1.10"/> and said to her, <q>No, we will go back with you to your people.</q>
      <verse eID="Ruth.1.10"/>
      <verse sID="Ruth.1.11" osisID="Ruth.1.11"/> Naomi said, <q>Turn back, my daughters, why will you come with me? Have I
       any more sons in my womb to be husbands for you? <verse eID="Ruth.1.11"/>
      <verse sID="Ruth.1.12" osisID="Ruth.1.12"/> Turn back, my daughters, go your way; I am too old to have a husband. Were
       I to say that I had hopes of marrying, if I even had a husband this night and bore sons, <verse eID="Ruth.1.12"/>
      <verse sID="Ruth.1.13" osisID="Ruth.1.13"/> would you wait on till they had grown up? Would you let that debar you
       from marrying? No, my daughters, my plight is worse than yours, for the Eternal is against me.</q> <verse eID="Ruth.1.13"/>
      <verse sID="Ruth.1.14" osisID="Ruth.1.14"/> Again they wept aloud; Orpah kissed her mother-in-law, but Ruth clung to
       her. <verse eID="Ruth.1.14"/>
      <verse sID="Ruth.1.15" osisID="Ruth.1.15"/> Naomi said, <q>Look, your sister-in-law is going back to her people and to
       her gods; turn back after her.</q> <verse eID="Ruth.1.15"/>
      <verse sID="Ruth.1.16" osisID="Ruth.1.16"/> But Ruth said, <q>Entreat me not to leave you and to turn back from
       following you; wher­ever you go, there will I go; wherever you stay, there will I stay; your people shall be my people,
       and your God shall be my God; <verse eID="Ruth.1.16"/>
      <verse sID="Ruth.1.17" osisID="Ruth.1.17"/> wherever you die, there will I die, and beside you will I be buried. May
       the Eternal kill me and worse, if anything but death part you and me.</q> <verse eID="Ruth.1.17"/>
      <verse sID="Ruth.1.18" osisID="Ruth.1.18"/> So when Naomi saw that she was determined to ac­company her, she said no
       more. <verse eID="Ruth.1.18"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Ruth.1.19" osisID="Ruth.1.19"/> The two went on till they reached Bethlehem. And the whole town was
       stirred by their arrival. The women said, <q>Is this Naomi?</q> <verse eID="Ruth.1.19"/>
      <verse sID="Ruth.1.20" osisID="Ruth.1.20"/> <q>Call me not Naomi,</q> she said, <q>call me Mara, for the Almighty has
       cruelly marred me; <verse eID="Ruth.1.20"/>
      <verse sID="Ruth.1.21" osisID="Ruth.1.21"/> I left this place full, and the Eternal has brought me back empty-handed.
       Why call me Naomi, when the Eternal has turned against me, and the Almighty has afflicted
       <milestone type="pb" n="302"/>
       me?</q> <verse eID="Ruth.1.21"/>
      <verse sID="Ruth.1.22" osisID="Ruth.1.22"/> This was how Naomi came back, with Ruth the Moabitess her daughter-in-law,
       from the country of Moab; the barley harvest was beginning when they reached Bethlehem. <verse eID="Ruth.1.22"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eID="Ruth.1"/>
    <chapter osisID="Ruth.2" sID="Ruth.2"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Ruth.2.1" osisID="Ruth.2.1"/>Naomi had a kinsman of her husband's, a man of large property, who belonged
       to the family of Elimelek; his name was Boaz. <verse eID="Ruth.2.1"/>
      <verse sID="Ruth.2.2" osisID="Ruth.2.2"/> Now Ruth the Moabitess said to Naomi, <q>Let me go to the field and glean
       among the grain after some man with whom I may find favour.</q> So she said, <q>Go, my daughter.</q> <verse eID="Ruth.2.2"/>
      <verse sID="Ruth.2.3" osisID="Ruth.2.3"/> And when she went and gleaned in the field behind the reapers, it was her
       fortune to come upon that part of the field which belonged to Boaz, who was connected with the family of Elimelek.
      <verse eID="Ruth.2.3"/>
      <verse sID="Ruth.2.4" osisID="Ruth.2.4"/> Just then Boaz came out from Bethle­hem, and said to the reapers,
       <q>May the Eternal be with you!</q> They replied, <q>May the Eternal bless you!</q> <verse eID="Ruth.2.4"/>
      <verse sID="Ruth.2.5" osisID="Ruth.2.5"/> Then he asked the foreman of the reapers in his service, <q>Whose girl is
       this?</q> <verse eID="Ruth.2.5"/>
      <verse sID="Ruth.2.6" osisID="Ruth.2.6"/> The foreman replied, <q>It is the Moabitish girl who came back with Naomi
       from the country of Moab; <verse eID="Ruth.2.6"/>
      <verse sID="Ruth.2.7" osisID="Ruth.2.7"/> she asked to be al­lowed to glean and gather be­hind the reapers among the
       sheaves, and she has been working ever since morning, without stopping for a moment.</q> <verse eID="Ruth.2.7"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Ruth.2.8" osisID="Ruth.2.8"/> Boaz said to Ruth, <q>Now listen, my daughter. Glean in no other field,
       never leave this one, but stay here close to my girls. <verse eID="Ruth.2.8"/>
      <verse sID="Ruth.2.9" osisID="Ruth.2.9"/> Keep your eyes on the field they are reaping and follow them up; I have
       strictly forbidden the young men to molest you. Whenever you are thirsty, go to the cans and drink what the young
       men have drawn.</q> <verse eID="Ruth.2.9"/>
      <verse sID="Ruth.2.10" osisID="Ruth.2.10"/> Then she fell upon her face, bowing to the ground; she said to him,
       <q>Why have I found favour with you, that you should take notice of me? I am a foreigner.</q> <verse eID="Ruth.2.10"/>
      <verse sID="Ruth.2.11" osisID="Ruth.2.11"/> But Boaz replied, <q>I have been well informed of all you have done for
       your mother-in-law since your husband died, of how you left your father and mother and your native land and came to
       a people who were strange to you. <verse eID="Ruth.2.11"/>
      <verse sID="Ruth.2.12" osisID="Ruth.2.12"/> May the Eternal reward your services! May you receive a rich recompense
       from the Eter­nal, the God of Israel, under whose wings you have sought shelter!</q> <verse eID="Ruth.2.12"/>
      <verse sID="Ruth.2.13" osisID="Ruth.2.13"/> She answered, <q>I am finding favour with you, my lord, for you have
       comforted me and spoken kindly to your maid­servant, even though I do not belong to your own maid­servants.</q> <verse eID="Ruth.2.13"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Ruth.2.14" osisID="Ruth.2.14"/> When the time came for the meal, Boaz said to her, <q>Come here, eat some
       of our bread, and dip your slice in the vinegar.</q> So she sat beside the reapers, and he handed her roasted grain;
       she ate till she was satis­fied, and had some left over. <verse eID="Ruth.2.14"/>
      <verse sID="Ruth.2.15" osisID="Ruth.2.15"/> When she got up to glean, Boaz ordered his young men, <q>Let her glean
       even among the sheaves, and never hinder her. <verse eID="Ruth.2.15"/>
      <verse sID="Ruth.2.16" osisID="Ruth.2.16"/> Pull out some stalks for her from the bundles and leave them for her to
       glean; do not check her.</q> <verse eID="Ruth.2.16"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Ruth.2.17" osisID="Ruth.2.17"/> So she gleaned in the field till evening. Then she beat out what she had
       gleaned (it was about a bushel of barley), <verse eID="Ruth.2.17"/>
      <verse sID="Ruth.2.18" osisID="Ruth.2.18"/> and took it away with her to the town. She showed her mother-in-law what
       she had gleaned, and she also produced for her the food she had left over, after her hunger had been satisfied. <verse eID="Ruth.2.18"/>
      <verse sID="Ruth.2.19" osisID="Ruth.2.19"/> Her mother-in-law asked her,
       <milestone type="pb" n="303"/>
       <q>Where did you glean to-day? Where were you working? A blessing on the man who took some notice of you!</q> So she
        explained to her mother-in-law whom she had been working with. <q>The name of the man with whom I worked to-day,</q>
        she said, <q>was Boaz.</q> <verse eID="Ruth.2.19"/>
      <verse sID="Ruth.2.20" osisID="Ruth.2.20"/> And Naomi said to her, <q>May the Eternal bless him, the Eter­nal who has
       not ceased to be kind to the living and to the dead! The man is a relative of our own,</q> added Naomi; <q>he is one
       of our near kinsmen.</q> <verse eID="Ruth.2.20"/>
      <verse sID="Ruth.2.21" osisID="Ruth.2.21"/> <q>Yes,</q> said Ruth the Moabitess, <q>and he told me to keep close to
       his young men till they had finished his harvesting.</q> <verse eID="Ruth.2.21"/>
      <verse sID="Ruth.2.22" osisID="Ruth.2.22"/> But Naomi said to Ruth her daughter-in-law, <q>My daugh­ter, you had
       better accompany his girls, so that the reapers may not attack you in some other field.</q> <verse eID="Ruth.2.22"/>
      <verse sID="Ruth.2.23" osisID="Ruth.2.23"/> So she kept close to the girls of Boaz as she gleaned, till the barley
       and the wheat were all harvested. She stayed with her mother-in-law. <verse eID="Ruth.2.23"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eID="Ruth.2"/>
    <chapter osisID="Ruth.3" sID="Ruth.3"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Ruth.3.1" osisID="Ruth.3.1"/>Then Naomi her mother-in-law said to her, <q>My daugh­ter, I must see you
       settled in life, that you may fare well. <verse eID="Ruth.3.1"/>
      <verse sID="Ruth.3.2" osisID="Ruth.3.2"/> Now here is our kinsman Boaz, with whose girls you have been work­ing.
       To-night he is winnowing barley in the threshing-floor. <verse eID="Ruth.3.2"/>
      <verse sID="Ruth.3.3" osisID="Ruth.3.3"/> Come, wash and anoint your­self, dress yourself, and go down to the
       threshing-floor, but do not disclose yourself to the man before he has done eating and drinking. <verse eID="Ruth.3.3"/>
      <verse sID="Ruth.3.4" osisID="Ruth.3.4"/> When he lies down, you must note the place; you must slip in, uncover his
       waist, and lie down there; and then he will tell you what is to be done next.</q> <verse eID="Ruth.3.4"/>
      <verse sID="Ruth.3.5" osisID="Ruth.3.5"/> She said, <q>I will do whatever you say.</q> <verse eID="Ruth.3.5"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Ruth.3.6" osisID="Ruth.3.6"/> She went down to the threshing-floor and did exactly as her mother-in-law
       had told her. <verse eID="Ruth.3.6"/>
      <verse sID="Ruth.3.7" osisID="Ruth.3.7"/> When Boaz had eaten and drunk, and had a merry time, he went to lie down at
       the end of the grain-heap. Then she crept in noiselessly, uncovered his waist, and lay down there. <verse eID="Ruth.3.7"/>
      <verse sID="Ruth.3.8" osisID="Ruth.3.8"/> At midnight the man started up and bent forward; there was a woman lying at
       his feet! <verse eID="Ruth.3.8"/>
      <verse sID="Ruth.3.9" osisID="Ruth.3.9"/> <q>Who are you?</q> he asked. She replied, <q>I am Ruth your maid­servant;
       now spread your robe over your maidservant, for you are a near kinsman.</q> <verse eID="Ruth.3.9"/>
      <verse sID="Ruth.3.10" osisID="Ruth.3.10"/> And he said, <q>May the Eternal bless you, my daughter! This last
       kindness of yours is more than all you ever did before, for you have not run after the young men, poor or rich. <verse eID="Ruth.3.10"/>
      <verse sID="Ruth.3.11" osisID="Ruth.3.11"/> Have no fear, my daughter! I will do all you ask; the folk of my town
       know you are a woman of worth. <verse eID="Ruth.3.11"/>
      <verse sID="Ruth.3.12" osisID="Ruth.3.12"/> It is true I am a near kinsman, but there is a nearer kinsman than
       myself. <verse eID="Ruth.3.12"/>
      <verse sID="Ruth.3.13" osisID="Ruth.3.13"/> Wait over this night, and in the morning, if he does his duty to you as a
       kins­man, good and well; let him do a kinsman's duty. But if he will not do his duty to you as a kinsman, as surely
       as the Eter­nal fives, I will do a kinsman's duty to you. Lie down till morning.</q> <verse eID="Ruth.3.13"/>
      <verse sID="Ruth.3.14" osisID="Ruth.3.14"/> So she lay at his feet till morning, and got up before anyone’s face
       could be seen--for Boaz had said, <q>No one must know that a woman came to the threshing-floor.</q> <verse eID="Ruth.3.14"/>
      <verse sID="Ruth.3.15" osisID="Ruth.3.15"/> He told her to bring her mantle and hold it open. So she held it open,
       and he measured out six pecks of barley for her to carry. <verse eID="Ruth.3.15"/>
      <verse sID="Ruth.3.16" osisID="Ruth.3.16"/> Then she went to the town;
     </p>
     <p>
       and when she arrived, her mother-in-law said, <q>How have you fared, my daughter?</q> She
       <milestone type="pb" n="304"/>
       told her all that Boaz had done about her; <verse eID="Ruth.3.16"/>
      <verse sID="Ruth.3.17" osisID="Ruth.3.17"/> <q>and he gave me these six pecks of barley,</q> she said, <q>for he said
       that I must not go empty-handed to my mother-in-law.</q> <verse eID="Ruth.3.17"/>
      <verse sID="Ruth.3.18" osisID="Ruth.3.18"/> Then said Naomi, <q>My daughter, wait until you see how things go, for
       the man will not rest till he settles the matter this very day.</q> <verse eID="Ruth.3.18"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eID="Ruth.3"/>
    <chapter osisID="Ruth.4" sID="Ruth.4"/>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Ruth.4.1" osisID="Ruth.4.1"/>Boaz had gone up to the town Gate and sat down. And there was the near
       kinsman of whom Boaz had spoken, pass­ing by! So Boaz cried to him, <q>Ho, you! step aside and sit down here!</q>
      <verse eID="Ruth.4.1"/>
      <verse sID="Ruth.4.2" osisID="Ruth.4.2"/> The man stepped aside and sat down. Then Boaz got ten of the sheikhs of the
       town and bade them sit down also. They sat down,<verse eID="Ruth.4.2"/>
      <verse sID="Ruth.4.3" osisID="Ruth.4.3"/>and then he said to the near kinsman, <q>Naomi, who has come back from the
       country of Moab, is selling the plot of land which belonged to our kinsman Elimelek, <verse eID="Ruth.4.3"/>
      <verse sID="Ruth.4.4" osisID="Ruth.4.4"/> and I thought I would lay the matter before you. Buy it in presence of
       those who are sitting here and in presence of the sheikhs of my people. If you will take up the property, take it up;
       but if you will not take it up, tell me, that I may know how things stand; for there is no one to take it up except
       yourself, and I come after you.</q> The man said, <q>I will take it up.</q> <verse eID="Ruth.4.4"/>
      <verse sID="Ruth.4.5" osisID="Ruth.4.5"/> Then Boaz said, <q>When you buy the field from Naomi, you are also buy­ing
       Ruth the Moabitess, the widow of a dead man, so as to carry on the name of the dead along with his inheritance</q>
      <verse eID="Ruth.4.5"/>
      <verse sID="Ruth.4.6" osisID="Ruth.4.6"/>But the near kinsman said, <q>I cannot take it up, for fear of injuring my
       own inheritance. Take over my rights yourself. I cannot take up the property.</q> <verse eID="Ruth.4.6"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Ruth.4.7" osisID="Ruth.4.7"/>Now to make any transaction valid, in the matter of taking up property and
       exchanging rights, the ancient custom in Israel was that a man drew off his shoe and handed it to the other party;
       this was how ex­changes were attested in Israel. <verse eID="Ruth.4.7"/>
      <verse sID="Ruth.4.8" osisID="Ruth.4.8"/> So when the near kinsman said to Boaz, <q>Buy it for yourself,</q> he drew
       off his shoe. <verse eID="Ruth.4.8"/>
      <verse sID="Ruth.4.9" osisID="Ruth.4.9"/> Then said Boaz to the sheikhs and all the people, <q>You are witnesses
       to­day that I have bought from Naomi all that belonged to Elimelek and Kilion and Mahlon. <verse eID="Ruth.4.9"/>
      <verse sID="Ruth.4.10" osisID="Ruth.4.10"/> Also I have purchased Mahlon's wife, Ruth the Moab­itess, to be my wife,
       that the name of the dead may be car­ried on along with his inherit­ance, lest the name of the dead perish from among
       his kinsmen and from the Gate of his native place: you are witnesses of this to-day!</q> <verse eID="Ruth.4.10"/>
      <verse sID="Ruth.4.11" osisID="Ruth.4.11"/> And all the people in the Gate and the sheikhs an­swered, <q>We are
       witnesses! May the Eternal make the woman who is coming into your house like Rachel and Leah, who together built up
       the house of Israel! Prosperity be yours in Ephrathah, and re­nown in Bethlehem! <verse eID="Ruth.4.11"/>
      <verse sID="Ruth.4.12" osisID="Ruth.4.12"/> May your house flourish like the house of Perez, whom Tamar bore to Judah,
       with the offspring which the Eternal shall give you from this young woman!</q> <verse eID="Ruth.4.12"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Ruth.4.13" osisID="Ruth.4.13"/> So Boaz took Ruth, and she became his wife; when he went in to her, the
       Eternal gave her conception, and she bore a son. <verse eID="Ruth.4.13"/>
      <verse sID="Ruth.4.14" osisID="Ruth.4.14"/> Then said the women to Naomi, <q>Blessed be the Eternal! He has this day
       provided you with a near kinsman. May his name be renowned in Israel! <verse eID="Ruth.4.14"/>
      <verse sID="Ruth.4.15" osisID="Ruth.4.15"/> He will revive your life and nourish your old age, for he is born of
       <milestone type="pb" n="305"/>
       your daughter-in-law, who loves you, who is better than seven sons to you.</q> <verse eID="Ruth.4.15"/>
      <verse sID="Ruth.4.16" osisID="Ruth.4.16"/> Naomi took the baby and laying it in her bosom nursed it; <verse eID="Ruth.4.16"/>
      <verse sID="Ruth.4.17" osisID="Ruth.4.17"/> and the women, her neighbours, gave it a name. <q>A son is born for Naomi,</q>
      they said, and they called its name Obed. He was the father of Jesse, the father of David. <verse eID="Ruth.4.17"/>
     </p>
     <p>
      <verse sID="Ruth.4.18" osisID="Ruth.4.18"/> These are the descendants of Perez: Perez was the father of Hezron, <verse eID="Ruth.4.18"/>
      <verse sID="Ruth.4.19" osisID="Ruth.4.19"/> Hezron of Ram, Ram of Amminadab, <verse eID="Ruth.4.19"/>
      <verse sID="Ruth.4.20" osisID="Ruth.4.20"/> Amminadab of Nahshon, Nahshon of Salmon, <verse eID="Ruth.4.20"/>
      <verse sID="Ruth.4.21" osisID="Ruth.4.21"/> Salmon of Boaz, Boaz of Obed,<verse eID="Ruth.4.21"/>
      <verse sID="Ruth.4.22" osisID="Ruth.4.22"/> Obed of Jesse, and Jesse of David. <verse eID="Ruth.4.22"/>
     </p>
    <chapter eID="Ruth.4"/>
   </div>